<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Zvi Mark – The Religious Thought of Rabbi Nachman of Bratslav  Part 1 of 3 updated	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/18/zvi-mark-%e2%80%93-the-religious-thought-of-rabbi-nachman-of-bratslav-part-1-of-2/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/18/zvi-mark-%e2%80%93-the-religious-thought-of-rabbi-nachman-of-bratslav-part-1-of-2/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Aug 2010 17:02:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: avraham rosenblum		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/18/zvi-mark-%e2%80%93-the-religious-thought-of-rabbi-nachman-of-bratslav-part-1-of-2/#comment-1536</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[avraham rosenblum]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 29 Aug 2010 17:02:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1809#comment-1536</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It is not just in halacha ritual that Rebbi Nachman was not post modern. It is in inner essence. He lived in the conceptual world of classical torah (Talmud Rambam Arizal etc.) His conception of the spiritual reality is that of the Arizal. The difference between Rebbi Nachman and the Arizal is that Rebbi Nachman found human problems interesting. In fact he found human problems so interesting that that is all that he deals with in his books and tries to show which mitzvah can solve which problem. But to Rebbi Nachman human problems and desires are larger and greater in significance than all the world of the Kabalah. He is the most profound thinker in the torah world since the Arizal and the Rambam. He is not just making commentaries to the Zohar and Arizal or fixing up the system of the Arizal or deepening it. He discovered a vast human world--the infinite attic of the human soul and the bottomless basement also.
The problem with understanding Rebbi Nachman is that people do it with no deep understanding of the connection between Rebbi Nachman and the Talmud and the Zohar. This applies in Breslov and out of it where interpretation of Rebbi Nachman shows an amazing lack of knowledge of the basis for Rebbi Nachman’s thought.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It is not just in halacha ritual that Rebbi Nachman was not post modern. It is in inner essence. He lived in the conceptual world of classical torah (Talmud Rambam Arizal etc.) His conception of the spiritual reality is that of the Arizal. The difference between Rebbi Nachman and the Arizal is that Rebbi Nachman found human problems interesting. In fact he found human problems so interesting that that is all that he deals with in his books and tries to show which mitzvah can solve which problem. But to Rebbi Nachman human problems and desires are larger and greater in significance than all the world of the Kabalah. He is the most profound thinker in the torah world since the Arizal and the Rambam. He is not just making commentaries to the Zohar and Arizal or fixing up the system of the Arizal or deepening it. He discovered a vast human world&#8211;the infinite attic of the human soul and the bottomless basement also.<br />
The problem with understanding Rebbi Nachman is that people do it with no deep understanding of the connection between Rebbi Nachman and the Talmud and the Zohar. This applies in Breslov and out of it where interpretation of Rebbi Nachman shows an amazing lack of knowledge of the basis for Rebbi Nachman’s thought.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Hillel B		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/18/zvi-mark-%e2%80%93-the-religious-thought-of-rabbi-nachman-of-bratslav-part-1-of-2/#comment-1484</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Hillel B]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 19 Aug 2010 13:28:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1809#comment-1484</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Greetings Dr. Brill! 

I&#039;d be very interested in reviewing Kamenetz&#039;s new book--it (I believe and sincerely hope) seems to address the profound spiritual affinity between these two great and radically modernist Jewish thinkers.

I just pre-ordered it on amazon! Very excited.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Greetings Dr. Brill! </p>
<p>I&#8217;d be very interested in reviewing Kamenetz&#8217;s new book&#8211;it (I believe and sincerely hope) seems to address the profound spiritual affinity between these two great and radically modernist Jewish thinkers.</p>
<p>I just pre-ordered it on amazon! Very excited.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: soloveitchikfan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/18/zvi-mark-%e2%80%93-the-religious-thought-of-rabbi-nachman-of-bratslav-part-1-of-2/#comment-1482</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[soloveitchikfan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 19 Aug 2010 11:45:42 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1809#comment-1482</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Nice article on the book about Rav Nachman. The book seems to to represent a real paradigm shift in interpretation of Rav Nachman.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Nice article on the book about Rav Nachman. The book seems to to represent a real paradigm shift in interpretation of Rav Nachman.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
