<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: NYT ending Peter Steinfel&#8217;s weekly relgion column	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/23/nyt-ending-peter-steinfels-weekly-relgion-column/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/23/nyt-ending-peter-steinfels-weekly-relgion-column/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2009 12:10:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Arie Folger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/23/nyt-ending-peter-steinfels-weekly-relgion-column/#comment-308</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arie Folger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2009 12:10:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=403#comment-308</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&lt;em&gt;Sixth, a major concern threading its way through these columns is protection of conscience. From its Protestant and Enlightenment origins, American society has tended to honor the personal conscience of the dissenting individual — at least in principle, although, as any atheist running for public office can testify, not necessarily in practice.&lt;/em&gt;

Freedom of conscience encompasses two concepts (actually three), which are not dependent on one another.

First, there is the freedom of conscience as in the above quote, which is a kind of societal creed that, however, really is a pragmatic way to organize society. So much violence has been committed by those who demand that all citizens adhere to a certain train of thought, that the Europeans who settled the United States argued for freedom from state imposed conscience. Over time, this has merged together with a third kind of freedom of conscience (which is not relevant here, hence I only spoke of two concepts of freedom of conscience), namely a political freedom to question and disagree with our political leadership.

Political freedom of conscience is important for a democracy to function, and the stability of political system it engenders argues for democratic society, but that is not our topic. However, in a similar fashion, multicultural society needs religious freedom of conscience, or we will quickly be at each others&#039; throats. Depending on the way society is structured, this may also argue for freedom of conscience within communities. I.e., when, as is common nowadays, we belong to religious communities through voluntary association, then, it may be beneficial to provide members with a larger amount of freedom of conscience, and thus of disagreement with officially sanctioned creed, because otherwise some or many members will react with their feet. This phenomenon - and the concomitant desirability of a measure of freedom of conscience - may have existed since oldest antiquity, but that is immaterial to my argument.

All of the above is pragmatic in kind, and unless we subscribe to some new agey kind of belief system where the supreme value is finding oneself and linking up with the pantheistic Force from Star Wars (is it pantheistic? We could argue about that), I would guess that it has very limited (limited does not mean none) application within established religions. In Judaism, there are a number of famous works that concentrate on required beliefs, most notably the then trail blazing &#039;Hovot haLevavot (Duties of the Heart, by Rabbenu Ba&#039;hya Ibn Pequda). If beliefs are required, then, conscience is not truly free.

There is another kind of freedom of conscience, however, which is at the core of Judaism, and indeed embedded within the very first human story in the Torah: the fact that we are free to choose, within ourselves, even to do what is wrong. Whether or not the religious community allows it, people have let their minds wander wherever their minds would take them, and have even at times acted upon those beliefs. Jewish jurisprudence, notably even in moral and cultic matters (in civic matters it is more obvious and more widely held), is entirely based upon the notion that we are responsible for our actions, and that we are free to make other decisions than those we made.

The latter concept is indispensable in religion, the former concept is a pragmatic matter.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Sixth, a major concern threading its way through these columns is protection of conscience. From its Protestant and Enlightenment origins, American society has tended to honor the personal conscience of the dissenting individual — at least in principle, although, as any atheist running for public office can testify, not necessarily in practice.</em></p>
<p>Freedom of conscience encompasses two concepts (actually three), which are not dependent on one another.</p>
<p>First, there is the freedom of conscience as in the above quote, which is a kind of societal creed that, however, really is a pragmatic way to organize society. So much violence has been committed by those who demand that all citizens adhere to a certain train of thought, that the Europeans who settled the United States argued for freedom from state imposed conscience. Over time, this has merged together with a third kind of freedom of conscience (which is not relevant here, hence I only spoke of two concepts of freedom of conscience), namely a political freedom to question and disagree with our political leadership.</p>
<p>Political freedom of conscience is important for a democracy to function, and the stability of political system it engenders argues for democratic society, but that is not our topic. However, in a similar fashion, multicultural society needs religious freedom of conscience, or we will quickly be at each others&#8217; throats. Depending on the way society is structured, this may also argue for freedom of conscience within communities. I.e., when, as is common nowadays, we belong to religious communities through voluntary association, then, it may be beneficial to provide members with a larger amount of freedom of conscience, and thus of disagreement with officially sanctioned creed, because otherwise some or many members will react with their feet. This phenomenon &#8211; and the concomitant desirability of a measure of freedom of conscience &#8211; may have existed since oldest antiquity, but that is immaterial to my argument.</p>
<p>All of the above is pragmatic in kind, and unless we subscribe to some new agey kind of belief system where the supreme value is finding oneself and linking up with the pantheistic Force from Star Wars (is it pantheistic? We could argue about that), I would guess that it has very limited (limited does not mean none) application within established religions. In Judaism, there are a number of famous works that concentrate on required beliefs, most notably the then trail blazing &#8216;Hovot haLevavot (Duties of the Heart, by Rabbenu Ba&#8217;hya Ibn Pequda). If beliefs are required, then, conscience is not truly free.</p>
<p>There is another kind of freedom of conscience, however, which is at the core of Judaism, and indeed embedded within the very first human story in the Torah: the fact that we are free to choose, within ourselves, even to do what is wrong. Whether or not the religious community allows it, people have let their minds wander wherever their minds would take them, and have even at times acted upon those beliefs. Jewish jurisprudence, notably even in moral and cultic matters (in civic matters it is more obvious and more widely held), is entirely based upon the notion that we are responsible for our actions, and that we are free to make other decisions than those we made.</p>
<p>The latter concept is indispensable in religion, the former concept is a pragmatic matter.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
