<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Rabbi Yitzchak Ginsburgh on Chanukah and Israelis in India	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/27/rabbi-yitzchak-ginsburgh-on-chanukah-and-israelis-in-india/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/27/rabbi-yitzchak-ginsburgh-on-chanukah-and-israelis-in-india/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2014 14:30:58 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/27/rabbi-yitzchak-ginsburgh-on-chanukah-and-israelis-in-india/#comment-9694</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2014 14:30:58 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6396#comment-9694</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/27/rabbi-yitzchak-ginsburgh-on-chanukah-and-israelis-in-india/#comment-9693&quot;&gt;alon goshen-gottstein&lt;/a&gt;.

good point, thank you. But some of the the pandits who became university professors and some of my Bengali friends have offered other explanations.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/27/rabbi-yitzchak-ginsburgh-on-chanukah-and-israelis-in-india/#comment-9693">alon goshen-gottstein</a>.</p>
<p>good point, thank you. But some of the the pandits who became university professors and some of my Bengali friends have offered other explanations.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: alon goshen-gottstein		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/27/rabbi-yitzchak-ginsburgh-on-chanukah-and-israelis-in-india/#comment-9693</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[alon goshen-gottstein]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2014 14:16:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6396#comment-9693</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[on question of worshiping Ganges - Alan, I have to agree with Ginbsburg. The underpinning of the &quot;worshipability&quot; of all things is the advaitic recognition that God is in all. Your attempt to draw a distinction between worshiping God who manifests as everything and who is all pervading, between that and &quot;drawing light&quot; or benediction or whatever, does not correspond to all that i have heard advaitins explain about their own practice. What one has to consider, then, is how &quot;wrong&quot; it is theologically to worship based on that premise. Ginbsurg simply says &quot;God forbid&quot;. that is not a theological argument.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>on question of worshiping Ganges &#8211; Alan, I have to agree with Ginbsburg. The underpinning of the &#8220;worshipability&#8221; of all things is the advaitic recognition that God is in all. Your attempt to draw a distinction between worshiping God who manifests as everything and who is all pervading, between that and &#8220;drawing light&#8221; or benediction or whatever, does not correspond to all that i have heard advaitins explain about their own practice. What one has to consider, then, is how &#8220;wrong&#8221; it is theologically to worship based on that premise. Ginbsurg simply says &#8220;God forbid&#8221;. that is not a theological argument.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Jeff Eyges		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/27/rabbi-yitzchak-ginsburgh-on-chanukah-and-israelis-in-india/#comment-9194</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jeff Eyges]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2013 15:54:50 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6396#comment-9194</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This appears to have become the frum party line in recent years: &quot;For the most part, the other nations are spiritually bankrupt, and when they do have something worthwhile - they got it from us!&quot; Akiva Tatz pulled the same nonsense in &quot;Letters to a Buddhist Jew&quot;.

You may feel he gives some sound advice on meditation, but everything else - his explanation of the differences between the methods, the soul, what&#039;s appropriate for a Jew, etc. - is pure Chabad propaganda &#038; triumphalism. 

Honestly, Alan, every time I read this sort of thing, it convinces me that if I had the capacity to meditate, I&#039;d stay far away from guys like this, and if I had any talent at all for &quot;spirituality&quot; (and as you know, I finally had to come to terms with the fact that I haven&#039;t) - again, I&#039;d stay far away from guys like this.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This appears to have become the frum party line in recent years: &#8220;For the most part, the other nations are spiritually bankrupt, and when they do have something worthwhile &#8211; they got it from us!&#8221; Akiva Tatz pulled the same nonsense in &#8220;Letters to a Buddhist Jew&#8221;.</p>
<p>You may feel he gives some sound advice on meditation, but everything else &#8211; his explanation of the differences between the methods, the soul, what&#8217;s appropriate for a Jew, etc. &#8211; is pure Chabad propaganda &amp; triumphalism. </p>
<p>Honestly, Alan, every time I read this sort of thing, it convinces me that if I had the capacity to meditate, I&#8217;d stay far away from guys like this, and if I had any talent at all for &#8220;spirituality&#8221; (and as you know, I finally had to come to terms with the fact that I haven&#8217;t) &#8211; again, I&#8217;d stay far away from guys like this.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
