<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: An Interview with Dr. Shai Secunda about The Iranian Talmud	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/03/an-interview-with-dr-shai-secunda-about-the-iranian-talmud/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/03/an-interview-with-dr-shai-secunda-about-the-iranian-talmud/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2013 03:38:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: The Iranian Talmud &#171; Menachem Mendel		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/03/an-interview-with-dr-shai-secunda-about-the-iranian-talmud/#comment-8990</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[The Iranian Talmud &#171; Menachem Mendel]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2013 03:38:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6276#comment-8990</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[[&#8230;] weeks away and there is a definite Persian aspect to the holiday, be sure to pick up your copy of Shai Secunda&#8217;s The Iranian Talmud: Reading the Bavli in Its Sasanian [&#8230;]]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] weeks away and there is a definite Persian aspect to the holiday, be sure to pick up your copy of Shai Secunda&#8217;s The Iranian Talmud: Reading the Bavli in Its Sasanian [&#8230;]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: LXXI &#124; Biblioblog Carnival—October 2013		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/03/an-interview-with-dr-shai-secunda-about-the-iranian-talmud/#comment-8951</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[LXXI &#124; Biblioblog Carnival—October 2013]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2013 04:05:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6276#comment-8951</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[[&#8230;] Alan Brill interviews Shai Secunda about his new book The Iranian Talmud: Reading the Bavli in Its Sasanian Context [&#8230;]]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] Alan Brill interviews Shai Secunda about his new book The Iranian Talmud: Reading the Bavli in Its Sasanian Context [&#8230;]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: The Iranian Talmud &#124; BLT		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/03/an-interview-with-dr-shai-secunda-about-the-iranian-talmud/#comment-8826</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[The Iranian Talmud &#124; BLT]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2013 15:01:50 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6276#comment-8826</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[[&#8230;] Book of Doctrines and Opinions recently posted An Interview with Dr. Shai Secunda about The Iranian Talmud  that I thought might be of interest to BLT readers, particularly including the historical review at [&#8230;]]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] Book of Doctrines and Opinions recently posted An Interview with Dr. Shai Secunda about The Iranian Talmud  that I thought might be of interest to BLT readers, particularly including the historical review at [&#8230;]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: David Z		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/03/an-interview-with-dr-shai-secunda-about-the-iranian-talmud/#comment-8796</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[David Z]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2013 19:26:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6276#comment-8796</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/03/an-interview-with-dr-shai-secunda-about-the-iranian-talmud/#comment-8720&quot;&gt;yisrael dubitsky&lt;/a&gt;.

To add to the author, and I can&#039;t wait to read his book, some of what i have already read in this field also highlights the differences (e.g. in how we treat menstruant women, which of course is also expressly dealt with in the Pentateuch).  So there&#039;s plenty of room for &quot;eternity.&quot;

To the limited extent that there was direct influence, and its cool to see where it was, there&#039;s nothing wrong with khaza&quot;l taking to heart ezehu khakham or yesh khokhma b&#039;yavan (i.e. goyim).  We are bound to rabbinic law because we lost s&#039;mikha but it is ridiculous to think that if we had s&#039;mikha things wouldn&#039;t change (or that every posek since then absorbs ideas from all the earlier poskim as well as surrounding legal norms when making p&#039;sak).  ]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/03/an-interview-with-dr-shai-secunda-about-the-iranian-talmud/#comment-8720">yisrael dubitsky</a>.</p>
<p>To add to the author, and I can&#8217;t wait to read his book, some of what i have already read in this field also highlights the differences (e.g. in how we treat menstruant women, which of course is also expressly dealt with in the Pentateuch).  So there&#8217;s plenty of room for &#8220;eternity.&#8221;</p>
<p>To the limited extent that there was direct influence, and its cool to see where it was, there&#8217;s nothing wrong with khaza&#8221;l taking to heart ezehu khakham or yesh khokhma b&#8217;yavan (i.e. goyim).  We are bound to rabbinic law because we lost s&#8217;mikha but it is ridiculous to think that if we had s&#8217;mikha things wouldn&#8217;t change (or that every posek since then absorbs ideas from all the earlier poskim as well as surrounding legal norms when making p&#8217;sak).  </p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Menachem Lipkin		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/03/an-interview-with-dr-shai-secunda-about-the-iranian-talmud/#comment-8794</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Menachem Lipkin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2013 11:44:57 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6276#comment-8794</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Can we get your book in Israel at an Israeli salary price? :)]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Can we get your book in Israel at an Israeli salary price? 🙂</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/03/an-interview-with-dr-shai-secunda-about-the-iranian-talmud/#comment-8756</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2013 13:26:58 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6276#comment-8756</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/03/an-interview-with-dr-shai-secunda-about-the-iranian-talmud/#comment-8754&quot;&gt;i. jebreel&lt;/a&gt;.

U of Penn. I will add it. 
click on the Amazon link]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/03/an-interview-with-dr-shai-secunda-about-the-iranian-talmud/#comment-8754">i. jebreel</a>.</p>
<p>U of Penn. I will add it.<br />
click on the Amazon link</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: i. jebreel		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/03/an-interview-with-dr-shai-secunda-about-the-iranian-talmud/#comment-8754</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[i. jebreel]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2013 10:41:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6276#comment-8754</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[who is the publisher of your book?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>who is the publisher of your book?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Shai Secunda		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/03/an-interview-with-dr-shai-secunda-about-the-iranian-talmud/#comment-8748</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shai Secunda]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2013 19:18:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6276#comment-8748</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/03/an-interview-with-dr-shai-secunda-about-the-iranian-talmud/#comment-8740&quot;&gt;ruvie&lt;/a&gt;.

Ruvie, I relate directly to these specific questions (and expectations) in the book. I would say it&#039;s a little of both. The Bavli itself (and its Middle Persian equivalent) makes it difficult to point to direct Persian influence. But also more generally, as I responded above, there is rarely anything that you can point to in the world that is entirely a result of direct influence, and direct influence alone. These things are &quot;negotiated&quot; and the process of negotiation can drag on longer than even the negotiation between the Israelis and the Palestinians.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/03/an-interview-with-dr-shai-secunda-about-the-iranian-talmud/#comment-8740">ruvie</a>.</p>
<p>Ruvie, I relate directly to these specific questions (and expectations) in the book. I would say it&#8217;s a little of both. The Bavli itself (and its Middle Persian equivalent) makes it difficult to point to direct Persian influence. But also more generally, as I responded above, there is rarely anything that you can point to in the world that is entirely a result of direct influence, and direct influence alone. These things are &#8220;negotiated&#8221; and the process of negotiation can drag on longer than even the negotiation between the Israelis and the Palestinians.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Shai Secunda		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/03/an-interview-with-dr-shai-secunda-about-the-iranian-talmud/#comment-8747</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shai Secunda]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2013 19:13:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6276#comment-8747</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/03/an-interview-with-dr-shai-secunda-about-the-iranian-talmud/#comment-8720&quot;&gt;yisrael dubitsky&lt;/a&gt;.

Hi Yisrael.  First, I perhaps did not express it so well in the interview, but the book makes it clear that the project of the Iranian Talmud cannot be one that just looks for obvious &quot;Persian looking&quot; things and then gets all excited when these are discovered. The last chapter of the book shows how the Bavli just doesn&#039;t work that way. First of all, it is a second-order text in the sense that it is built on the Mishna and, to a certain extent, Palestinian material. As a result, the method of reading I ultimately suggest is one that tries to appreciate the way older rabbinic texts and statements (&quot;Eternity&quot; in your question) resonated differently (and sometimes changed along the way) in the Bavli, given its context.

I of course don&#039;t deal with theology in the book, and that too brief comment in the interview was originally directed mainly at the yeshiva world. But some of what I discuss in that same final chapter can be formulated into a theological response. Basically, if the twentieth century taught us anything about how language works, it is that meaning is not inherent in language (Benjamin&#039;s &quot;language as such&quot;), rather it is achieved through a complex process in which one particular option is articulated as opposed to infinite others. Put crudely, if the other options didn&#039;t exist then the particular utterance that was made would be meaningless. I think the same is true about Judaism. I guess you could say that I believe, at least from the human perspective, that there is not pure &quot;eternity&quot; to be found. But the eternity of halakha and Judaism, if you subscribe to it, -is-achieved in the course of its transmission, articulation, and being lived in the world. This is hard to put down clearly in a blog post, but when you read the final chapter of the book, my thoughts on the matter should be clearer.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/03/an-interview-with-dr-shai-secunda-about-the-iranian-talmud/#comment-8720">yisrael dubitsky</a>.</p>
<p>Hi Yisrael.  First, I perhaps did not express it so well in the interview, but the book makes it clear that the project of the Iranian Talmud cannot be one that just looks for obvious &#8220;Persian looking&#8221; things and then gets all excited when these are discovered. The last chapter of the book shows how the Bavli just doesn&#8217;t work that way. First of all, it is a second-order text in the sense that it is built on the Mishna and, to a certain extent, Palestinian material. As a result, the method of reading I ultimately suggest is one that tries to appreciate the way older rabbinic texts and statements (&#8220;Eternity&#8221; in your question) resonated differently (and sometimes changed along the way) in the Bavli, given its context.</p>
<p>I of course don&#8217;t deal with theology in the book, and that too brief comment in the interview was originally directed mainly at the yeshiva world. But some of what I discuss in that same final chapter can be formulated into a theological response. Basically, if the twentieth century taught us anything about how language works, it is that meaning is not inherent in language (Benjamin&#8217;s &#8220;language as such&#8221;), rather it is achieved through a complex process in which one particular option is articulated as opposed to infinite others. Put crudely, if the other options didn&#8217;t exist then the particular utterance that was made would be meaningless. I think the same is true about Judaism. I guess you could say that I believe, at least from the human perspective, that there is not pure &#8220;eternity&#8221; to be found. But the eternity of halakha and Judaism, if you subscribe to it, -is-achieved in the course of its transmission, articulation, and being lived in the world. This is hard to put down clearly in a blog post, but when you read the final chapter of the book, my thoughts on the matter should be clearer.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ruvie		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/03/an-interview-with-dr-shai-secunda-about-the-iranian-talmud/#comment-8740</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ruvie]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2013 17:39:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6276#comment-8740</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Alan - thank you for your great intro into the subject matter (as usual on these subjects). its helpful for lay folks like myself who may not know all the background research in the area (on that note can you expand on the difference of approaches/methodologies (if there is any) between geoffry herman and shai?)
Shai - does whatever you see in the bavli tied to persian influences have to be contrasted to how different it is from the yerushalmi (or mishnah) for contrasting what maybe general worldwide influences as oppose to particular ones? have you conclusively shown cause and effect of influences - or casting of middle persian - that shed new light on rabbinic law (more than it &quot;feels like&quot; or &quot;looks like&quot;)? if so, how many instances? if one can show it via greek or roman influences (or its opposite reaction) why shouldn&#039;t persian direct influence not be easily shown?
btw, nice work on du-partzufim.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Alan &#8211; thank you for your great intro into the subject matter (as usual on these subjects). its helpful for lay folks like myself who may not know all the background research in the area (on that note can you expand on the difference of approaches/methodologies (if there is any) between geoffry herman and shai?)<br />
Shai &#8211; does whatever you see in the bavli tied to persian influences have to be contrasted to how different it is from the yerushalmi (or mishnah) for contrasting what maybe general worldwide influences as oppose to particular ones? have you conclusively shown cause and effect of influences &#8211; or casting of middle persian &#8211; that shed new light on rabbinic law (more than it &#8220;feels like&#8221; or &#8220;looks like&#8221;)? if so, how many instances? if one can show it via greek or roman influences (or its opposite reaction) why shouldn&#8217;t persian direct influence not be easily shown?<br />
btw, nice work on du-partzufim.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/03/an-interview-with-dr-shai-secunda-about-the-iranian-talmud/#comment-8726</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2013 22:57:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6276#comment-8726</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/03/an-interview-with-dr-shai-secunda-about-the-iranian-talmud/#comment-8720&quot;&gt;yisrael dubitsky&lt;/a&gt;.

I think what is truly reductive is asking every academic about the effects of their research on practical halakhah and/or Rabbinic devotion.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/03/an-interview-with-dr-shai-secunda-about-the-iranian-talmud/#comment-8720">yisrael dubitsky</a>.</p>
<p>I think what is truly reductive is asking every academic about the effects of their research on practical halakhah and/or Rabbinic devotion.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: yisrael dubitsky		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/03/an-interview-with-dr-shai-secunda-about-the-iranian-talmud/#comment-8720</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[yisrael dubitsky]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2013 21:16:42 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6276#comment-8720</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Sorry to sound so provincal, but will there be any scrap of &quot;Eternity&quot; left after every word, phrase, story, concept and law is reduced to borrowings, influence, cultural context etc.? I am afraid Shai glosses too easily over the theological challenges (and yes, i am aware others have tackled them before) around which such academic reductionism inevitably devolves. I am a fan of detail, and historical discovery, but can a paragraph be added about the effects of his research on practical halakhah and/or Rabbinic devotion? Question 3 glosses over too much]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sorry to sound so provincal, but will there be any scrap of &#8220;Eternity&#8221; left after every word, phrase, story, concept and law is reduced to borrowings, influence, cultural context etc.? I am afraid Shai glosses too easily over the theological challenges (and yes, i am aware others have tackled them before) around which such academic reductionism inevitably devolves. I am a fan of detail, and historical discovery, but can a paragraph be added about the effects of his research on practical halakhah and/or Rabbinic devotion? Question 3 glosses over too much</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
