<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Rabbi Shmuly Yanklowitz replies	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/15/rabbi-shmuly-yanklowitz-replies/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/15/rabbi-shmuly-yanklowitz-replies/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2010 15:49:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/15/rabbi-shmuly-yanklowitz-replies/#comment-1190</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2010 15:49:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1535#comment-1190</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Now I&#039;m even more disturbed. First you take a doctrine that proposes an essential soul that operates and transmigrates via particular mechanisms. This is clearly not Aristotelian conception of the soul, but you seem to think that the two can be effortlessly joined. Why? Because you want it to work. Does coherence not factor into the way you think about these things? Does the actual text not matter, only its distillation into cliffs notes? 

My earlier point is that particularly when we cannot state hard truths (although the majority of your orthodox coreligionists do not have this problem) we need to delineate why we attach ourselves, nay, hang our collective spiritual identities, on particular theological pegs such as a divine Torah and &quot;soul&quot; that in some way is not dependent on a body.

We are at a our peril when we multiply necessities simply out of convenience or the desire for a theology with a particular functional orientation instead of the burden of history and the weight of compelling texts.

It does not even look like you are trying to seriously read the texts. Perhaps if you were you could move from critical distance to reclamation - that is a hermeneutic, but you cannot begin by projecting your idols into the texts and make them dance around like marionettes.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Now I&#8217;m even more disturbed. First you take a doctrine that proposes an essential soul that operates and transmigrates via particular mechanisms. This is clearly not Aristotelian conception of the soul, but you seem to think that the two can be effortlessly joined. Why? Because you want it to work. Does coherence not factor into the way you think about these things? Does the actual text not matter, only its distillation into cliffs notes? </p>
<p>My earlier point is that particularly when we cannot state hard truths (although the majority of your orthodox coreligionists do not have this problem) we need to delineate why we attach ourselves, nay, hang our collective spiritual identities, on particular theological pegs such as a divine Torah and &#8220;soul&#8221; that in some way is not dependent on a body.</p>
<p>We are at a our peril when we multiply necessities simply out of convenience or the desire for a theology with a particular functional orientation instead of the burden of history and the weight of compelling texts.</p>
<p>It does not even look like you are trying to seriously read the texts. Perhaps if you were you could move from critical distance to reclamation &#8211; that is a hermeneutic, but you cannot begin by projecting your idols into the texts and make them dance around like marionettes.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: chakira		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/15/rabbi-shmuly-yanklowitz-replies/#comment-1184</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[chakira]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2010 05:39:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1535#comment-1184</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[If we have to look relatively far afield to the obscure gilgul doctrine to find some social justice, does this imply that mainstream Jewish texts are unconcerned with social justice? Why is there no social justice in Taanis or even Uktzin? Why do we need esotericism to get there?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If we have to look relatively far afield to the obscure gilgul doctrine to find some social justice, does this imply that mainstream Jewish texts are unconcerned with social justice? Why is there no social justice in Taanis or even Uktzin? Why do we need esotericism to get there?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: tomerpersico		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/15/rabbi-shmuly-yanklowitz-replies/#comment-1180</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tomerpersico]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2010 19:23:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1535#comment-1180</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thank you, that made things more clear, and more compelling!]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thank you, that made things more clear, and more compelling!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
