<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Cordovero on the nature of Prayer	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 May 2010 19:40:58 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Yonatan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/#comment-967</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Yonatan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 06 May 2010 19:40:58 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1230#comment-967</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I was asking how one would describe this spiritual practice in the most &quot;mundane&quot; prosaic detail. What would one do first, second, etc.

&lt;i&gt;What would you take them to mean based on your basic knowledge.&lt;/i&gt;


As to the answer your question, I just re-read them before davening Mincha. The first of the second set of texts would advocate the learning of Sod/Nistar &#038; say that the way to connect to God would be through studying Nistar.

Second texts says to just connect to Malchus/Shechinah when praying. What this means practically is to just focus on Malchus throughout Tefillah.

The first Meditation that you posted was much more difficult and it had as a prelude a Yichud during Shema that was not included. But once one is in a state of this Yichud, you draw down whatever you have gained in the Yichud, while constantly thinking of Malchus, but going down the chain/ladder of the Sefirot.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I was asking how one would describe this spiritual practice in the most &#8220;mundane&#8221; prosaic detail. What would one do first, second, etc.</p>
<p><i>What would you take them to mean based on your basic knowledge.</i></p>
<p>As to the answer your question, I just re-read them before davening Mincha. The first of the second set of texts would advocate the learning of Sod/Nistar &amp; say that the way to connect to God would be through studying Nistar.</p>
<p>Second texts says to just connect to Malchus/Shechinah when praying. What this means practically is to just focus on Malchus throughout Tefillah.</p>
<p>The first Meditation that you posted was much more difficult and it had as a prelude a Yichud during Shema that was not included. But once one is in a state of this Yichud, you draw down whatever you have gained in the Yichud, while constantly thinking of Malchus, but going down the chain/ladder of the Sefirot.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/#comment-965</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 06 May 2010 18:03:42 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1230#comment-965</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The answer the last question first. The publisher of the Ramak did not assume the reader read everything.  the kavvanot first came out in a pamphlet in Italy published by his son to take to shul on Rosh Hashanah. They assume that this is the basic Jewish worldview for 17th century Italy, in which people know the basics. The Mehaber manages to summarize kavvanot hatefilah of the Ramak in a paragraph and says do it. So, they were not looking for long expositions first. The cutting of the passages into a single unit was done in several other works most notably the Shelah. The Ramak writes that there are several kavvanot for the shema- quotes from a variety - and then says pick one. He does not give a context for each one. In a similar manner, when the Shelah doubles the number of possible shema kavvanot and says pick one, the reader wold not have access the contexts of each one.

Prayer seems to be driven by praxis, as do his chapters on shemot, Abulafia, the soul, and ritual. The type of question changes. 

What exactly do they mean is the question. Thank you for actually reading the passage and not showing up with other thinkers. What would you take them to mean based on your basic knowledge.

&lt;em&gt;But how does this play out in practice? &lt;/em&gt;
What are you asking in specific?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The answer the last question first. The publisher of the Ramak did not assume the reader read everything.  the kavvanot first came out in a pamphlet in Italy published by his son to take to shul on Rosh Hashanah. They assume that this is the basic Jewish worldview for 17th century Italy, in which people know the basics. The Mehaber manages to summarize kavvanot hatefilah of the Ramak in a paragraph and says do it. So, they were not looking for long expositions first. The cutting of the passages into a single unit was done in several other works most notably the Shelah. The Ramak writes that there are several kavvanot for the shema- quotes from a variety &#8211; and then says pick one. He does not give a context for each one. In a similar manner, when the Shelah doubles the number of possible shema kavvanot and says pick one, the reader wold not have access the contexts of each one.</p>
<p>Prayer seems to be driven by praxis, as do his chapters on shemot, Abulafia, the soul, and ritual. The type of question changes. </p>
<p>What exactly do they mean is the question. Thank you for actually reading the passage and not showing up with other thinkers. What would you take them to mean based on your basic knowledge.</p>
<p><em>But how does this play out in practice? </em><br />
What are you asking in specific?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Len Moskowitz		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/#comment-964</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Len Moskowitz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 06 May 2010 17:18:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1230#comment-964</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/#comment-950&quot;&gt;Alan Brill&lt;/a&gt;.

In the chapters between shaar 3 and 4, Rav Khayyim talks about how physically saying the words of the Amida is the important thing, even without any mental intention about or understanding of the words.

I don&#039;t see where he addresses individual informal prayer outside of the context of the formal Shmoneh Esrei (the Amida).

Am I missing something?

And if the RM&quot;K only addresses the process of meditation in the context of the formal form of the Amida (never addressing modifications to the form for individual petition), does that mean he completely dismisses individual informal prayer outside of the Amida?

I guess what I&#039;m suggesting is: if the RM&quot;K restricts his meditation process to the formal Amida process, then perhaps he is not saying anything at all about informal unstructured individual prayer.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/#comment-950">Alan Brill</a>.</p>
<p>In the chapters between shaar 3 and 4, Rav Khayyim talks about how physically saying the words of the Amida is the important thing, even without any mental intention about or understanding of the words.</p>
<p>I don&#8217;t see where he addresses individual informal prayer outside of the context of the formal Shmoneh Esrei (the Amida).</p>
<p>Am I missing something?</p>
<p>And if the RM&#8221;K only addresses the process of meditation in the context of the formal form of the Amida (never addressing modifications to the form for individual petition), does that mean he completely dismisses individual informal prayer outside of the Amida?</p>
<p>I guess what I&#8217;m suggesting is: if the RM&#8221;K restricts his meditation process to the formal Amida process, then perhaps he is not saying anything at all about informal unstructured individual prayer.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Yonatan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/#comment-958</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Yonatan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 06 May 2010 16:15:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1230#comment-958</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I am curious about all of these texts about where they originally said and in what context.

Also, how jarring is to for you to be splicing the Ramak zt&quot;l together?

I had a similar question about your previous Ramak post. The discussion of Sefirot during Tefillah sounded  to me(our of context) as a self-referencial symbolic system. 

It was not clear to me what the content that one is meditating on when they are thinking about Sefirot. There is a mapping of specific sefirot onto specific words in Tefillah. But how does this play out in practice?

In the texts quoted above, there is a reference to specific practices (ascent, calling to the gatekeeper, directing the heart). What exactly do they mean, specifically?

Lastly, what is the relationship between the Ramak zt&quot;l texts on prayer and the rest of his corpus. Is the Sefirot discussed in these texts elaborated at length in Pardes Rimonim or in Tomer Devorah.

Does the Rama&quot;k assume that anyone doing these practices have read his entire corpus and know what they should have in their mind?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I am curious about all of these texts about where they originally said and in what context.</p>
<p>Also, how jarring is to for you to be splicing the Ramak zt&#8221;l together?</p>
<p>I had a similar question about your previous Ramak post. The discussion of Sefirot during Tefillah sounded  to me(our of context) as a self-referencial symbolic system. </p>
<p>It was not clear to me what the content that one is meditating on when they are thinking about Sefirot. There is a mapping of specific sefirot onto specific words in Tefillah. But how does this play out in practice?</p>
<p>In the texts quoted above, there is a reference to specific practices (ascent, calling to the gatekeeper, directing the heart). What exactly do they mean, specifically?</p>
<p>Lastly, what is the relationship between the Ramak zt&#8221;l texts on prayer and the rest of his corpus. Is the Sefirot discussed in these texts elaborated at length in Pardes Rimonim or in Tomer Devorah.</p>
<p>Does the Rama&#8221;k assume that anyone doing these practices have read his entire corpus and know what they should have in their mind?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Len Moskowitz		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/#comment-955</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Len Moskowitz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 06 May 2010 00:27:40 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1230#comment-955</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/#comment-929&quot;&gt;Alan Brill&lt;/a&gt;.

For the Ariza&quot;l, Ahtzeeloot is Ehlokoot Gamoor (absolute Godliness), so presumably there&#039;s no gap in his system either.

He just doesn&#039;t explain how it is that Ahtziloot manifests the Ein Sofe after propagation through the myriad worlds that are between Ein Sofe and Ahtziloot.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/#comment-929">Alan Brill</a>.</p>
<p>For the Ariza&#8221;l, Ahtzeeloot is Ehlokoot Gamoor (absolute Godliness), so presumably there&#8217;s no gap in his system either.</p>
<p>He just doesn&#8217;t explain how it is that Ahtziloot manifests the Ein Sofe after propagation through the myriad worlds that are between Ein Sofe and Ahtziloot.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: natan21		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/#comment-952</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[natan21]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2010 07:05:26 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1230#comment-952</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Dear Len,
The author of the Shulkhan Arukh in siman 98 is copying the Tur who I believe is influenced by the Gerona Kabbalistic interpretation of the meditative techniques of the early pietists, Hasidim Rishonim. To understand the development of early Jewish meditative techniques, I think that it might be interesting to explore the connections of Hasidim rishonim to the Jewish ascetic sect of Therapeutae (therapists (healers) of the spirit) of the 1st century. The Therapeutae (male, pl.) and Therapeutrides (female, pl.) who were described by Philo as contemplative ascetics, engaged in prayer, fasting and scriptural study. It has been speculated that the Therapeutae were influenced by Buddhist monasticism due to Buddhist missionary activity to the Mediterranean (e.g. 250 BCE in the Edicts of Ashoka) and that &quot;Therapeutae&quot; is a Hellenization of the Indian Pali word for Theravada. If so, the Buddhist tradition has now come full circle with the revival of Jewish Meditation techniques that integrate Theravada meditative practices.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dear Len,<br />
The author of the Shulkhan Arukh in siman 98 is copying the Tur who I believe is influenced by the Gerona Kabbalistic interpretation of the meditative techniques of the early pietists, Hasidim Rishonim. To understand the development of early Jewish meditative techniques, I think that it might be interesting to explore the connections of Hasidim rishonim to the Jewish ascetic sect of Therapeutae (therapists (healers) of the spirit) of the 1st century. The Therapeutae (male, pl.) and Therapeutrides (female, pl.) who were described by Philo as contemplative ascetics, engaged in prayer, fasting and scriptural study. It has been speculated that the Therapeutae were influenced by Buddhist monasticism due to Buddhist missionary activity to the Mediterranean (e.g. 250 BCE in the Edicts of Ashoka) and that &#8220;Therapeutae&#8221; is a Hellenization of the Indian Pali word for Theravada. If so, the Buddhist tradition has now come full circle with the revival of Jewish Meditation techniques that integrate Theravada meditative practices.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Dr. Natan Ophir		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/#comment-951</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dr. Natan Ophir]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2010 06:42:12 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1230#comment-951</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Dear Alan,

I can send you several articles related to your topic - please email 

1. A study unit on RaMaK&#039;s meditative techniques. On a related topic, I recently posted a YouTube video introduction to R. Hayyim Vital&#039;s meditative techniques - http://www.youtube.com/user/JewishMeditation21

2. An article describing R. Moshe Cordovero&#039;s meditative technique in love to be published by Massechet. I just received the editorial corrections and the journal is expected to be published by Sukkot.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dear Alan,</p>
<p>I can send you several articles related to your topic &#8211; please email </p>
<p>1. A study unit on RaMaK&#8217;s meditative techniques. On a related topic, I recently posted a YouTube video introduction to R. Hayyim Vital&#8217;s meditative techniques &#8211; <a href="http://www.youtube.com/user/JewishMeditation21" rel="nofollow ugc">http://www.youtube.com/user/JewishMeditation21</a></p>
<p>2. An article describing R. Moshe Cordovero&#8217;s meditative technique in love to be published by Massechet. I just received the editorial corrections and the journal is expected to be published by Sukkot.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/#comment-950</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2010 22:23:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1230#comment-950</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Where does the RM”K say one should insert individual requests and petitions into the Amida?

He does not.

I don’t readily recall him discussing extra-liturgical individual prayer.

in the unnumbered shaar]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Where does the RM”K say one should insert individual requests and petitions into the Amida?</p>
<p>He does not.</p>
<p>I don’t readily recall him discussing extra-liturgical individual prayer.</p>
<p>in the unnumbered shaar</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Len Moskowitz		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/#comment-948</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Len Moskowitz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2010 20:40:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1230#comment-948</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Amida (which is what we&#039;re referring to when we say &quot;prayer&quot;) is framed in the plural, and all requests are for the benefit of the Jewish nation .

Rav Khayyim Volozhiner goes so far as to say that the entire t&#039;fila is oriented to the collective, and personal requests are misplaced in that context.  I don&#039;t readily recall him discussing extra-liturgical individual prayer.

Where does the RM&quot;K say one should insert individual requests and petitions into the Amida?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Amida (which is what we&#8217;re referring to when we say &#8220;prayer&#8221;) is framed in the plural, and all requests are for the benefit of the Jewish nation .</p>
<p>Rav Khayyim Volozhiner goes so far as to say that the entire t&#8217;fila is oriented to the collective, and personal requests are misplaced in that context.  I don&#8217;t readily recall him discussing extra-liturgical individual prayer.</p>
<p>Where does the RM&#8221;K say one should insert individual requests and petitions into the Amida?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/#comment-942</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2010 12:52:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1230#comment-942</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/#comment-940&quot;&gt;Len Moskowitz&lt;/a&gt;.

The Ramak would disagree with Rav Nahman. Already the Kuzari III has many statements about tefilah that would critique a Rav Nahman position. For your perspective, Nefesh Hahayim certainly disagrees with outpouring of the heart without liturgy. You can read Rav Kenig for a response to Reb Hayyim but they are considered as conflicting positions.
The Ramak would also disagree with the power of the word by themselves as described in Nefesh HaHayyim Shaar 2. Neither of the two position you oscillate between are similar to Ramak.  It is not words or free-form outpouring, but meditation through the levels.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/#comment-940">Len Moskowitz</a>.</p>
<p>The Ramak would disagree with Rav Nahman. Already the Kuzari III has many statements about tefilah that would critique a Rav Nahman position. For your perspective, Nefesh Hahayim certainly disagrees with outpouring of the heart without liturgy. You can read Rav Kenig for a response to Reb Hayyim but they are considered as conflicting positions.<br />
The Ramak would also disagree with the power of the word by themselves as described in Nefesh HaHayyim Shaar 2. Neither of the two position you oscillate between are similar to Ramak.  It is not words or free-form outpouring, but meditation through the levels.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Len Moskowitz		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/#comment-941</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Len Moskowitz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2010 10:03:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1230#comment-941</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Brill wrote: &quot;What does it say? The page does not match in my edition.&quot;

Sorry -- it&#039;s in his&quot; Meditation and the Bible&quot;.  It begins &quot;It is taught that there is a single Light, in the form of a Man, which radiates through all the four Universes... .&quot;

If you can&#039;t find it, let me know.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Brill wrote: &#8220;What does it say? The page does not match in my edition.&#8221;</p>
<p>Sorry &#8212; it&#8217;s in his&#8221; Meditation and the Bible&#8221;.  It begins &#8220;It is taught that there is a single Light, in the form of a Man, which radiates through all the four Universes&#8230; .&#8221;</p>
<p>If you can&#8217;t find it, let me know.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Len Moskowitz		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/#comment-940</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Len Moskowitz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2010 09:57:57 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1230#comment-940</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[There are at least two types of prayer.  One is in the form that Anshei Knesset Ha-G&#039;dolah formulated.  The other is like what Rebbee Nakhman described.

One is formal.

The other is not.

Both are effective, each in their own way.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There are at least two types of prayer.  One is in the form that Anshei Knesset Ha-G&#8217;dolah formulated.  The other is like what Rebbee Nakhman described.</p>
<p>One is formal.</p>
<p>The other is not.</p>
<p>Both are effective, each in their own way.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/#comment-937</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2010 05:22:03 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1230#comment-937</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/#comment-933&quot;&gt;jd&lt;/a&gt;.

Moral preparation via Tomer Devorah.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/#comment-933">jd</a>.</p>
<p>Moral preparation via Tomer Devorah.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
