<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Holy Ignorance part II	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/12/04/holy-ignorance-part-ii/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/12/04/holy-ignorance-part-ii/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2011 01:09:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Isaac Shalev (@rejewvenator)		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/12/04/holy-ignorance-part-ii/#comment-3838</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Isaac Shalev (@rejewvenator)]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2011 21:55:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4386#comment-3838</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I was intrigued by that last bit about translation. There&#039;s no doubt that Artscroll play a hugely important role in the fundamentalist move in Orthodoxy. And Roy is right on - Orthodoxy has used English translations to &quot;dodge the historical and cultural resonances of the text.&quot; 

At the risk of overgeneralizing, the tone and tenor of Artscroll translations is to smooth out the text, reduce or remove ambiguities, and to make the translated text correspond closely with only one of the many existing traditional interpretations for these texts (or even harmonizing/synthesizing multiple traditional interpretations into one). By de-problematizing the text, they limit the space and need for interpretation. The text means only one thing, notwithstanding that our own tradition shows incredible diversity of possible meanings living in tension with one another.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I was intrigued by that last bit about translation. There&#8217;s no doubt that Artscroll play a hugely important role in the fundamentalist move in Orthodoxy. And Roy is right on &#8211; Orthodoxy has used English translations to &#8220;dodge the historical and cultural resonances of the text.&#8221; </p>
<p>At the risk of overgeneralizing, the tone and tenor of Artscroll translations is to smooth out the text, reduce or remove ambiguities, and to make the translated text correspond closely with only one of the many existing traditional interpretations for these texts (or even harmonizing/synthesizing multiple traditional interpretations into one). By de-problematizing the text, they limit the space and need for interpretation. The text means only one thing, notwithstanding that our own tradition shows incredible diversity of possible meanings living in tension with one another.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: L		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/12/04/holy-ignorance-part-ii/#comment-3836</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[L]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2011 13:18:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4386#comment-3836</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Aside from the issue of modest dress, there is no mention of the role of women, generally considered a watershed issue and key differentiator between the various degrees of religious adherence. Is the regulation of the behavior of half the population simply a &quot;religious marker&quot;?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Aside from the issue of modest dress, there is no mention of the role of women, generally considered a watershed issue and key differentiator between the various degrees of religious adherence. Is the regulation of the behavior of half the population simply a &#8220;religious marker&#8221;?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: IH		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/12/04/holy-ignorance-part-ii/#comment-3834</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[IH]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2011 00:40:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4386#comment-3834</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[“For Roy, most of the flashpoints and controversial issues discussed are not in the theology/halakhah group but in the religious marker group.”

The RW Orthodoxies, regardless of  whether they are Muslim or Jewish, are unwilling to make this distinction.  Head covering and &quot;modest&quot; attire for women are the classic examples of religious markers that have been so fetishized.   Their sociological context have been subsumed into revisionist readings of source texts that are then promulgated as the (explicit and exclusive) word of God, thus, upping the ante for sociological moderation.

Where, it seems to me, this becomes more complex is when State power becomes complicit in the sociology.  This is certainly true for Islam, in which the unfolding events in Egypt will be an interesting reality check on many political theories discussed over the past few decades.  But, it is also critical in our more parochial discussions of Judaism.

On your final point, it seems to me that the issue within Orthodoxy is not translation per se.  As an unlikely source for cutting to the crux, R. Meiselman just wrote in Mishpacha:  “When I deal with most products of today’s yeshivos, I have to assume they’re not proficient in independently learning a Mishnah Berurah, so I have to teach them how to read a Mishnah Berurah. I have to assume the only seforim they’ve seen in mussar and machshava are ArtScroll books, and so I have to get them exposed to primary sources. Many of them are not equipped to go through things inside.”]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>“For Roy, most of the flashpoints and controversial issues discussed are not in the theology/halakhah group but in the religious marker group.”</p>
<p>The RW Orthodoxies, regardless of  whether they are Muslim or Jewish, are unwilling to make this distinction.  Head covering and &#8220;modest&#8221; attire for women are the classic examples of religious markers that have been so fetishized.   Their sociological context have been subsumed into revisionist readings of source texts that are then promulgated as the (explicit and exclusive) word of God, thus, upping the ante for sociological moderation.</p>
<p>Where, it seems to me, this becomes more complex is when State power becomes complicit in the sociology.  This is certainly true for Islam, in which the unfolding events in Egypt will be an interesting reality check on many political theories discussed over the past few decades.  But, it is also critical in our more parochial discussions of Judaism.</p>
<p>On your final point, it seems to me that the issue within Orthodoxy is not translation per se.  As an unlikely source for cutting to the crux, R. Meiselman just wrote in Mishpacha:  “When I deal with most products of today’s yeshivos, I have to assume they’re not proficient in independently learning a Mishnah Berurah, so I have to teach them how to read a Mishnah Berurah. I have to assume the only seforim they’ve seen in mussar and machshava are ArtScroll books, and so I have to get them exposed to primary sources. Many of them are not equipped to go through things inside.”</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/12/04/holy-ignorance-part-ii/#comment-3833</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2011 00:18:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4386#comment-3833</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[My experience of the growth of Orthodoxy was like this. For the most part the generation that came of age around 1970 were not baal teshuvas, they came
from Orthodox families, but in a large measure the parents were sociological Jews, to use your term or moderate shteibel Jews, who were still connected to European Orthodoxy. Because the parents were to different degrees heimish, they sent their kids to charedi yeshivas, a move that both gave them nachis,and was horrifying at the same time. Newly minted charedi young people, mechutzafim, confronted frum parents on many fronts, dress, college, style and place of davening. There was a failure of nerve on the part of the parents and a successful Oedipal revolution by these young people, who while depreciated their parents over- idealized their teachers. paralleling in many respects the generation of ’68 and the hippies. This outdoing of parents is becoming more difficult. This last Agudah convention highlighted by the hysterical, fanatic speeches of Rabbis Avraham Schorr and Shimshon Sherrer are examples of children justifying their place in the world by being even more frum than their charedi parents.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My experience of the growth of Orthodoxy was like this. For the most part the generation that came of age around 1970 were not baal teshuvas, they came<br />
from Orthodox families, but in a large measure the parents were sociological Jews, to use your term or moderate shteibel Jews, who were still connected to European Orthodoxy. Because the parents were to different degrees heimish, they sent their kids to charedi yeshivas, a move that both gave them nachis,and was horrifying at the same time. Newly minted charedi young people, mechutzafim, confronted frum parents on many fronts, dress, college, style and place of davening. There was a failure of nerve on the part of the parents and a successful Oedipal revolution by these young people, who while depreciated their parents over- idealized their teachers. paralleling in many respects the generation of ’68 and the hippies. This outdoing of parents is becoming more difficult. This last Agudah convention highlighted by the hysterical, fanatic speeches of Rabbis Avraham Schorr and Shimshon Sherrer are examples of children justifying their place in the world by being even more frum than their charedi parents.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
