<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>kabbalah &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/category/kabbalah/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2012 03:26:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='kavvanah.wordpress.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/c9f111237f93750b6b994fc5185d49c3?s=96&#038;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>kabbalah &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>David Shasha on Kellner, Idel, and Nationalism</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/08/david-shasha-on-kellner-idel-and-nationalism/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/08/david-shasha-on-kellner-idel-and-nationalism/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2010 21:16:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[israel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[david shasha]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[menachem Kellner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Moshe idel]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1643</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[David Shasha is a proponent of all things Sefardi and a radical follower of Jose Faur who envisions a Levantine synthesis of Jewish and Arabic humanism. Shasha offers a critique of Kellner, Idel and others as destroying the humanistic foundations &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/08/david-shasha-on-kellner-idel-and-nationalism/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>David Shasha is a proponent of  all things Sefardi and a radical follower of Jose Faur who envisions a Levantine synthesis of Jewish and Arabic humanism. Shasha offers a critique of Kellner, Idel and others as destroying the humanistic foundations of Judaism. He claims that they destroy the foundation of Maimonidean humanism even if they accept Maimonides. Kellner advocates for the rationalism of Maimonides but back-handedly considers the Maimonideans as too demanding for the common person, as rejecting folk religion, and as not the Jewish tradition. Shasha demands that Maimonides be considered the tradition or else Maimonideans would always be in a defensive position. If one does not live in a rational world then all the power is in the magical hand of the rabbis. </p>
<p>Shasha places blame at the feet of Moshe Idel who explores the magical, irrational, and mythic forces in Judaism but who also maintains that this theurgic world is the world of the Talmudic Rabbis. For Idel, the Rabbinic tradition is magical. Kabbalah is not a Gnostic intruder into Judaism but the very meaning of the commandments for the Rabbis. Once Jews studied Saadyah, Ibn Ezra, Maimonides, Gersonides as the traditon, now they read Abulafia and Zohar. For Shasha, this is tantamount to a return to idolatry and the source of militant nationalism. <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/david-shasha/dangerous-mystic-motifs-i_b_637535.html">Full Version here.</a></p>
<p>Shasha writes:<br />
<em>At the center of this controversy is the vexing question of Jewish authenticity.<br />
In his 2006 study &#8220;Maimonides&#8217; Confrontation with Mysticism,&#8221; Menachem Kellner adopts an approach that has become standard in most Jewish circles, writing:</p>
<blockquote><p>&#8220;The Jewish world in which Maimonides lived was uncongenial to the austere, abstract, demanding vision of Torah which he preached. Evidence from a wide variety of sources shows that Jews in Maimonides&#8217; day &#8211; common folk and scholars alike &#8211; accepted astrology, the magical use of divine names, appeals to angels, etc.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p></em><em> In a noble attempt to elevate the thinking of Maimonides, Kellner&#8217;s arguments bizarrely lend credence to the positions of the anti-Maimonideans.</em><br />
<em>In the book&#8217;s conclusion he states:</em></p>
<blockquote><p>The world favored by Maimonides&#8217; opponents, on the other hand, is an &#8220;enchanted&#8221; world. Many of Maimonides&#8217; opponents, in his day and ours, do indeed accept the efficacy of charms and amulets, and fear the harm of demons and the evil eye. But it is not in that sense that I maintain that they live in an enchanted world. Theirs is not a world which can be explained in terms of the unvarying workings of divinely ordered laws of nature; it is not a world which can be rationally understood. It is a world in which the notion of miracle loses all meaning, since everything that happens is a miracle. In such a world instructions from God, and contact with the divine in general, must be mediated by a religious elite who alone can see the true reality masked by nature. This is the opposite of an empowering religion, since it takes their fate out of the hands of Jews, and, in effect, puts it into the hands of the rabbis.</p></blockquote>
<p><em>We can see the tension at the heart of Kellner&#8217;s argument, a tension that forces his hand in accepting the absolute authenticity of the mystical-occult tradition of the Kabbalah and rejecting the Jewish validity of Maimonidean rationalism.</p>
<p>Kellner&#8217;s book contains a forward by Hebrew University professor Moshe Idel, perhaps the single most influential academic in the world of Judaica, a winner of the prestigious Israel Prize and a ubiquitous presence in the world of Jewish studies. Idel has relentlessly promoted the pro-magic, neo-pagan, anti-rational strain of Jewish tradition also called Kabbalah. </p>
<p>Idel&#8217;s scholarly project has been designed to affirm the authenticity of the mystical-occult Kabbalah and undermine the validity of the rational standards of Religious Humanism. As we see in a representative passage in his seminal 1988 work &#8220;Kabbalah: New Perspectives&#8221;:</em></p>
<blockquote><p>Kabbalah can be viewed as part of a restructuring of those aspects of rabbinic thought that were denied authenticity by Maimonides&#8217; system. Far from being a total innovation, historical Kabbalah represented an ongoing effort to systematize existing elements of Jewish theurgy, myth, and mysticism into a full-fledged response to the rationalistic challenge.<br />
It is, however, possible to assume that, if the motifs transmitted in those unknown [Kabbalistic] circles formed part of an ancient weltanschauung, their affinities to the rabbinic mentality would be more organic and easily absorbed into the mystic cast of Judaism.<br />
According to this hypothesis, we do not need to account for why ancient Jews took over Gnostic doctrines, why they transmitted them, and, finally, how this &#8216;Gnostic&#8217; Judaism was revived in the Middle Ages by conservative Jewish authorities. </p></blockquote>
<p>Shasha concludes:</p>
<p><em>This has led to the rejection of Sephardic Jewish Humanism as formulated by Maimonides and an affirmation of an ethnocentric Jewish chauvinism based on the magical mysticism of Kabbalistic theurgy. It is a Judaism that rejects the tenets of a critical reading of the Jewish past and has led us to the sort of ideological purity and militant nationalism that has become characteristic of the intractable impasse in the Middle East. Though this occult process has been secularized by Zionism, it is apparent that the ideological values of the mystical continue to animate the Jewish self-perception in a nationalistic sense.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/08/david-shasha-on-kellner-idel-and-nationalism/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>10</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Isaiah Tishby.  Messianic Mysticism: Moses Hayim Luzzatto and the Padua School.</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/02/isaiah-tishby-messianic-mysticism-moses-hayim-luzzatto-and-the-padua-school/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/02/isaiah-tishby-messianic-mysticism-moses-hayim-luzzatto-and-the-padua-school/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Jun 2010 05:08:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mysticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[isaiah tishby]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[moshe valle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ramhal]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1444</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Isaiah Tishby. Messianic Mysticism: Moses Hayim Luzzatto and the Padua School. Littman Library of Jewish Civilization, 2008. $69.50 These studies were written by Tishby in the 1970&#8217;s and 1980&#8217;s and they are only now available English. They portray the clean-shaven &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/02/isaiah-tishby-messianic-mysticism-moses-hayim-luzzatto-and-the-padua-school/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Isaiah Tishby.  <strong>Messianic Mysticism: Moses Hayim Luzzatto and the Padua School.</strong> Littman Library of Jewish Civilization, 2008.  $69.50 </p>
<p>These studies were written by Tishby in the 1970&#8217;s and 1980&#8217;s and they are only now available English. They portray the clean-shaven unmarried Luzzatto who wrote plays in Italian and Latin, and who gathered a group of University of Padua medical students around him for the purposes of creating a mystical circle. Tishby explores the messianism, the Sabbatianism, Luzzatto&#8217;s angelic maggid, his messiah ketubah, and the heresy accusations. These are studies on recently discovered manuscripts not final thoughts, many of these topics can use further elucidation after the thirty years.We now have many more works by Luzzatto. For example he shows us the reader that Luzzatto used his ruah hakodesh to write a new Zohar but Tishby does not explore the content of the work nor its relationship to the extensive writings of Valle.  An intellectual biography of Luzzatto remains a desideratum.  </p>
<blockquote><p>Isaiah Tishby.  Messianic Mysticism: Moses Hayim Luzzatto and the<br />
Padua School.<a href="http:///www.h-net.org/reviews/showrev.php?id=3D23866"> Reviewed by Hartley Lachter</a> (Muhlenberg College)</p>
<p>Moses Hayim Luzzatto (1707-46) was undoubtedly one of the most important thinkers and fascinating personalities of<br />
eighteenth-century Italian Jewry. The scion of an influential Jewish family in Padua, Luzzatto&#8217;s life and literary legacy project a<br />
distinctly contradictory set of images. At once a poet, playwright, moralist, kabbalist, self-fashioned leader of a messianic group,<br />
radical prophet, and exiled accused heretic, Luzzatto nonetheless came to be celebrated by Orthodox and Hasidic Jews, as well as<br />
secular Jews of later generations</p>
<p>Many of the compositions by Luzzatto that Tishby addresses in this volume would be quite surprising to one familiar with Luzzatto&#8217;s more popular writing. Included here are a number of previously unknown works that Tishby discovered in MS<br />
Oxford 2593, as well as poetry (reproduced in both Hebrew and English), and several prayers that Luzzatto composed for a variety of<br />
occasions, including a confessional prayer that he wrote for his group of kabbalists in Padua. Tishby also gives attention to the<br />
works of Moses David Valle (a significant member of Luzzato&#8217;s kabbalistic group), reproducing his mystical diary, rife with<br />
messianic overtones, and he explores the question of the spread of Luzzatto&#8217;s works in Eastern Europe, and their influence on Hasidic<br />
schools of thought.</p>
<p>One of the most striking compositions discussed in this collection of studies is the kabbalistic commentary that Luzzatto wrote to his own marriage contract when he married Zipporah, the daughter of Rabbi David Finzi of Mantua, in 1731. This remarkable text, as noted in Dan&#8217;s introduction, sheds important light on Luzzatto&#8217;s messianic posture. Luzzatto came to be regarded with suspicion when he began claiming as early as 1727 that he was receiving revelations of a maggid or heavenly voice, enabling him to compose prophetic pronouncements, and even a &#8220;new Zohar,&#8221; which it seems he shared with the group of kabbalists that he led in Padua. Added to this was the  accusation leveled by Moses Hagiz before the rabbis of Venice that he intercepted a letter by a member of Luzzatto&#8217;s group containing evidence that Luzzatto was a follower of Shabbtai Zvi. </p>
<p>Luzzatto&#8217;s teacher and champion, Isaiah Bassan, convinced him that he could quell at least some of the controversy if he would agree to marry, since remaining single into one&#8217;s mid-twenties was itself understood to be unseemly. The discovery of Luzzatto&#8217;s kabbalistic commentary to his own marriage contract reveals that while his decision to marry was in part a concession intended to placate his critics, the marriage was also understood by Luzzatto as a union of divine dimensions, literally heralding the messianic era. Situating this document within the broader context of Luzzatto&#8217;s messianic doctrine, Tishby concludes that Luzzatto regarded himself as serving the role of Moses, whose task is to guide the actions of the Messiah son of Joseph and the Messiah son of David. Evidence indicates, according to Tishby, that Luzzatto understood Valle to be the Messiah son of David, while none other than Zvi was regarded as the Messiah son of Joseph.  Another of Luzzatto&#8217;s group, Jekutiel of Vilna, was believed to serve as Seraiah of the tribe of Dan, the general of the forces of the messianic army. Luzzatto&#8217;s commentary to his marriage contract is reproduced in full English translation in the volume, along with Tishby&#8217;s illuminating notes. Taken together with Valle&#8217;s diary, these texts provide important source material for an under appreciated moment of messianic ferment.</p>
<p>We know that Luzzatto received an education in non-Jewish areas of knowledge, and he even defended his colleague Jekutiel from detractors who took issue with his study of &#8220;Gentile wisdom,&#8221; since he came to Padua originally to study medicine. How are we to understand these otherwise &#8220;worldly&#8221; men in their turn toward Jewish esoteric discourse as the source for all true knowledge? </p>
<p>As Luzzatto remarks in a text addressing Jeremiah 9:22, &#8220;Let not the wise man glory in his wisdom,&#8221; found in MS Oxford 2593, &#8220;the whole science of truth [kabbalah] rests solely on this question, the question of the holiness of Israel: how the Holy One, blessed be He, adheres to them in His holiness and how Israel must adhere, through their desire and their worship, to His holiness, blessed be He; and how all the affairs of the world and of the all creation have rested upon this basis ever since they came into existence and [will do so] to all eternity&#8221; (p. 47). </p>
<p>There remains work to be done in better situating Luzzatto and his colleagues within the eighteenth-century Italian intellectual context. </p></blockquote>
<p>As a companion, I recommend Rivka Schatz-Uffenheimer, “Moshe Hayim Luzzatto&#8217;s thought against the background of theodicy literature,” in Justice and Righteousness (1992) 173-199 where she contextualizes Ramhal in the post Lisbon eathquake concerns of Leibnitz and King.</p>
<p>This baroque world of science and kabbalah intertwined ended abruptly with the Enlightenment. From Rav Yosef Karo to Ramhal and from there to the Vilna Gaon, a proper Gadol could ascend to heaven, perform kavvanot, receive angelic visitors, and attempt to bring the messiah. Forty years after these writings Ramhal&#8217;s own cousin Shadal would not suffer to perform any of these kabbalistic rites or utter kabbalistic prayers. Enlightenment concern with sense data and manuscript work on texts had brought the baroque edifice down. </p>
<p>Ramhal played almost no part in Gershom Scholem&#8217;s writings since Luzzatto treated kabbalah as either scientific or as theological providence,not as symbolism</p>
<p>In the 21st century, these remain as vestiges for the psychologist to decipher what to tell the client. There is a local psychiatrist that wants to work with me on some schema for understanding the Orthodox kids who come in with angelic visitors, when are they potential gadolim (or at least mathematicians and chess masters) and when do they need medication? But the real question is can we accept the epistemic rupture that the early modern period represents and the fact that we exists in a alternate formulation of Judaism. The Vilna Gaon with his angelic visitors belonged to Luzzatto&#8217;s world, the world of tikkunim.  </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/02/isaiah-tishby-messianic-mysticism-moses-hayim-luzzatto-and-the-padua-school/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>20</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Cordovero on the nature of Prayer</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2010 02:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[devekut]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[moshe cordovero]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[prayer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1230</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[For those following the more pietistic discussion on Ramak’s prayer, here is some more for discussion. The first text is on devekut. The second text is on the inability of prayer to rise without ascending level by level through the &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For those following the more pietistic discussion on Ramak’s prayer, here is some more for discussion. The first text is on devekut. The second text is on the inability of prayer to rise without ascending level by level through the known levels. One cannot prayer directly to the Eyn Sof. Any reactions or insights? I am delivering a conference paper next week on the topic, so all observations are helpful. Any insights to the meditation process?</p>
<p><strong>Devekut</strong></p>
<p>“Through these mysteries, a man is able to cleave to his master with will…”<br />
A person can cleave to Him through directing his will to the mystery of the sefirot, the Tetragrammaton, and the [other] Divine names. One who does not know the mystery of how to cleave to Him will not have the ability to grasp (beit ahizah),  because His place of grasping is through His sefirot, His precious names and holy Tetragrammaton.<br />
“In directing the heart to know the wisdom of His dominance in the highest mystery.” The dominance of hokhmah is a wondrous mystery. The first way to reach a state of cleaving to the Divine (devekut) is through the study of the mysteries of the Torah and the understanding of the hidden secrets in the Torah.<br />
The second is “when he worships his Master in prayer,” that is, the mystery of prayer and the way of cleaving to Him.<br />
“He will cleave like a flame in a coal&#8221;—for man’s will and soul that ascend from the walls of his heart will certainly be bound to the supernal palaces. Thus, man should first meditate on repairing malkhut, Her repairs are the mystery of the palaces, which bind and cleave together with malkhut like a flame bound in a coal, while his soul and meditation are a flame from the coal that is malkhut. Similarly, the palaces that spread out from and cleave to Her are like a flame spreading out from amidst the coal, yet cleaving to it. Because of this, the [palaces] return to their source and are swallowed up in Her through his soul that returns and is swallowed in its source. With the soul’s ascent, the [palaces] are raised as well, since only through the soul can they spread out below. Now this is the mystery of man’s intention and breath of his mouth created from the vapor of his mouth and the soul (neshamah) arising through breath (neshimah), that they cleave and return to their source. If it happens that the palaces, and further, the hizonim, spread out from there, he should meditate on binding and unifying her specifically from the palace of paved sapphire (livnat hasappir) and higher. There is the beginning of holy cleaving, binding themselves in unification.<br />
 <br />
<strong>Ascent of prayers</strong></p>
<p>When the Shekhinah is completely filled with prayers, then the prayers rise and ascend to a place where there is no pain and no lack.<br />
The purpose of ascent into worship of God is so the prayer should reach this place. Some people meditate in times of need, as it is written, &#8220;Israel are wise in that they know how to pray in times of need.&#8221; However, better and more meritorious is he who raises all of his prayers there [even not in a time of need].<br />
This form of worship is more desirable because it does not come out of pain or need, but rather from cleaving through worship to the true Object of worship.<br />
The masses think that the intention reaches there by itself; they are completely outside the palace, so that when they call the king from afar, the king does not answer them.<br />
Rather, it is necessary to call to the gatekeeper. The gatekeeper takes them in his hand and brings them into the control of the princes, from prince to prince of each palace, until they are brought to the king in his chamber, where they will find Him and bring their needs before Him.<br />
For those who pray or cleave to Ein Sof by itself, their goal remains far from them. He is only close to the one who knows His palaces and gatekeepers.<br />
Indeed,  for those who speak to the gatekeeper which is the attribute of malkhut, the attribute will bring them to the higher attributes higher, level after level through all the levels.<br />
These people will certainly enter to the King, Ein Sof, the Root of all roots, in His room, a wondrous place, and speak with Him, in the mystery of the ascent of prayer. Immediately, it will be powerful.  </p>
<p>Copyright © 2010 Alan Brill • All Rights Reserved</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>20</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>R. Moshe Cordovero on the Amidah.</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/26/r-moshe-cordovero-on-the-amidah/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/26/r-moshe-cordovero-on-the-amidah/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Apr 2010 04:17:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[liturgy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kavvanot hatefilah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[moshe cordovero]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ramak]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1180</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[R. Yosef Karo writes that he followed the kavvanot of the Ramak. In contrast, to Provençal method where there is an ascent to tiferet or binah. In Cordovero&#8217;s method, as mentioned above, the shekhinah itself is raised and the entire &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/26/r-moshe-cordovero-on-the-amidah/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>R. Yosef Karo writes that he followed the kavvanot of the Ramak.</strong></p>
<p>In contrast, to Provençal method where there is an ascent to <em>tiferet</em> or <em>binah</em>. In Cordovero&#8217;s method, as mentioned above, the <em>shekhinah</em> itself is raised and the entire system collapses up like <strong><em>the folding up of a telescope</em>.</strong> One folds <em>shekhinah</em> up beyond <em>nezah</em> and <em>hod </em>which makes her the same as <em>tiferet</em>, not that there is only <em>tiferet </em>or that she merged into <em>tiferet</em>, but that she has been raised to the point of <em>tiferet</em>.  From <em>tiferet</em>, the shekhinah together with <em>tiferet</em> receive from an influx from <em>binah</em>. There is  loss of differentiation and integration within <em>binah</em>. This ascent during the silent prayer allows the entrance and then the merging of the soul into the supernal realms.</p>
<p>The passage contains the division of <strong>ADNY</strong> into <strong>AY</strong>, the Infinite oneness found within ten sefirot showing unity of keter, tiferet, and malkhut, and <strong>DN</strong> the forces of judgment and materiality showing the emanation process as privation from the Divine goodness.</p>
<p>Here we have words of the amidah especially the name <strong>A-donai (A-d-n-y)</strong> divided into <em>Aleph</em> for the top three sefirot, and <em>daled-nun</em> as judgment of the world, and <em>yod</em> as the ten sefirot. The infinite light (<em>aleph</em>) above descends to the earthy world of judgment (<em>daled-nun</em>) through the means of the ten sefirot (<em>yod</em>). The infinite light cascades down in emanation as the discrete units of the three Divine names, E-hyah, Y-H-V-H, and A-donai.</p>
<p><strong><em>ADNY, </em></strong>this name is <em>malkhut</em>.</p>
<p>Meditate that She is now higher than <em>nezah</em> and <em>hod</em>, as She is silently rising between the two shepherds during the unification of the recitation of the <em>Shema</em>. The mystery of prayer is their literal union, that they completely unite. The individual is silent because the union is in silence. Voice (<em>kol</em>), <em>tiferet</em>, is not heard outside at all,. The mystery of this verse is to open the door of the palace for the worshiper to enter inside. Thus, he knocks on the opening of the palace gate, holy of holies, in order to enter inside, to unify and bind. As it is known, inside the palace is <em>malkhut</em>, bound with the three fathers whose mystery is love (<em>ahavah</em>).</p>
<p>One knocks and says, “<strong>my Lord” (<em>ADNY</em>)</strong>, who is <em>malkhut</em>, as she is the aspect bound in the mystery of <em>daled nun</em> that she is the mystery of <em>alef</em>, which is the name <em>eh-yeh</em> in <em>binah</em> and the mystery of <em>yud</em>, which is <em>Y-H-V-H</em> in <em>tiferet</em>. This is why she is called <em>Ado-nai</em>, tied to three names, <em>Eh-yeh</em>, <em>Y-H-V-H</em>, <em>Ado-nai</em> on <em>nezah</em> and <em>hod</em>.</p>
<p><strong>“My lips”</strong> are <em>nezah</em> and <em>hod</em>;</p>
<p><strong>“open” (<em>tiftah</em>)</strong> from inside the palace. These are the openings of palace of the gates of righteousness so that I may enter them and praise Y-H (Psalms 118:19).</p>
<p><strong>“and my mouth” (<em>u’fi</em>) </strong>for through the opening of the lips the mouth is formed, which is <em>malkhut</em>. Since She does not have a mouth without open lips, immediately you will see <em>malkhut</em>.</p>
<p>Immediately, <strong>“will express” (<em>yaggid</em>), </strong>from the side of <em>hokhmah</em>, which is the mystery of <em>gimmel</em> <em>daled</em>, seven <em>sefirot</em> <em>GYD</em>, a drop from the brains that are drawn down in the mystery of semen that shoots like an arrow.</p>
<p><span style="text-decoration:underline;">First Blessing</span></p>
<p>The goal of the first blessing of the silent amidah is to draw down from <em>binah</em> into the lower sefirot of <em>yesod and malkhut</em>.</p>
<p>The following paragraph is a note written above the liturgy, so that the reader does not misunderstand the process and think that one is still just connecting the lower to the higher sefirot, The entire first <em>berakhah </em>is not only in <em>binah</em>, but in the depths of <em>binah</em>; while the other mentioned sefirot are all within <em>binah</em>. The imagery is of the infinite king, a cosmic deity, who is so great, that there are many aspects (<em>bekhinot</em>) , called inner limbs. This passage is not included in the first Rosh Hashanah commentary  and may be by another hand, but it does express the characteristics of the practice of the Cordovero intentions.</p>
<p>This entire blessing is in the depths of <em>binah</em> until <strong>“shield of Abraham</strong>” that She descends into <em>hesed</em>. Whenever it says that [the pray-er] goes down into <em>malkhut</em> and the <em>avot</em>, it is all hidden in <em>binah</em>. For the first blessing is the first principle of the king, and all the higher inner limbs are included in it. Thus, she will have many aspects.</p>
<p>Cordovero wrote notes above the words <strong>Bless</strong> and <strong>You</strong> explaining how the blessings within the amidah work.  He reiterates that his method is to go from top to bottom during blessings drawing down from the eyn sof to malkhut.</p>
<p><strong> “Bless”</strong> During the <em>amidah</em>, one should direct “<strong>bless</strong>” down from the <em>Ein Sof</em> to <em>yesod</em> including all ten <em>sefirot</em> from the Source of everything. The power to bring down influence from on high until <em>malkhut</em> below depends on thought.</p>
<p>This is why the <em>Zohar</em> says that one should not start at the level of “Your face,” so that you do not admonished, God forbid. Should he start “<strong>bless</strong>” from bottom-up, standing in <em>din</em>, then the going bottom-up is <em>din</em>. Rather, start from the top and go before His face below; this is the mystery of “blessed” from top-down to repair it beforehand with influx and sweetening its judgments.</p>
<p>Energy is drawn down from the top three sefirot to the middle six, first as <em>keter</em>, <em>hokhmah</em>, and <em>binah</em> into <em>tiferet,</em> then in the middle blessings one draws <em>daat</em> the animating vitality of the world into the twelve-sided version of <em>tiferet,</em> and in the concluding blessings of the amidah one brings the spiritual energy into <em>malkhut</em>.</p>
<p><em>Yesod</em> includes <em>yesod malkhut</em> (<em>YM</em>) from <em>keter</em> until <em>yesod</em> seals this world of <em>yesod</em> <em>malkhut</em> from the world of the male, spreading top-down.</p>
<p><strong>Blessed (<em>Barukh</em>)</strong></p>
<p><em>Malkhut</em> is the world of the female. <em>Alef</em> (<em>A</em>) is <em>keter</em>; <em>tav</em> (<em>T</em>) is <em>hesed</em>, <em>binah</em>, <em>gedulah</em>, <em>gevurah</em>; <em>hei</em> (<em>H</em>) is <em>tiferet</em> until <em>malkhut</em>.</p>
<p><strong>Are You (<em>Atah</em>; <em>ATH</em>)</strong></p>
<p><em>Tiferet</em>, which binds together male and female from the bottom up.</p>
<p><strong>Lord (<em>Y-H-V-H</em>)</strong></p>
<p><em>Ein Sof keter</em> of <em>keter</em>:</p>
<p><em>yud hei vav hei</em> (<em>YUD HY VYV HY</em>); [72]</p>
<p><em>alef hei yud hei</em> (<em>ALF HA</em> <em>YUD HA</em>); [143]</p>
<p><em>yud hei vav hei</em> (<em>YUD HA VAV HA</em>); [45]</p>
<p><em>alef dalet nun yud</em> (<em>ALF DLT NUN YUD</em>). [#zzz]</p>
<p>Bind head to head <em>YAHH-VYHH</em>—<em>hokhmah</em> and <em>binah</em>.</p>
<p>Bind body to body <em>YAHD-UNHY</em>—<em>tiferet</em> and <em>malkhut</em>.<em> </em></p>
<p><em>Binah</em></p>
<p><strong>Our God (e-lo-heinu)</strong></p>
<p><em> </em></p>
<p><em>Hokhmah</em> that lights up <em>binah</em></p>
<p><strong>And God of (<em>vei-lo-hei</em>)</strong></p>
<p>In the mystery of her three roots, <em>gedulah</em>, <em>gevurah</em> and <em>tiferet</em> inside her.</p>
<p><strong>Our fathers (<em>avoteinu</em>)</strong></p>
<p><em>Hesed</em> of <em>hokhmah</em> bound in <em>hesed</em> of <em>binah</em>.</p>
<p><strong>God of (<em>e-lo-hei</em>) Abraham (<em>avraham</em>)</strong></p>
<p><em>Gevurah</em> of <em>hokhmah</em> bound in <em>gevurah</em> of <em>binah</em>.</p>
<p><strong>God of (<em>elo-hei</em>) Isaac (yizhak)</strong></p>
<p><em>Tiferet</em> of <em>hokhmah</em> bound in <em>tiferet</em> of <em>binah</em>.</p>
<p><strong>And God of (<em>vei-lo-hei</em>)  Jacob (<em>ya’akov</em>). </strong></p>
<p>Mystery of three fathers revealed in the great <em>binah</em> of <em>gedulah</em></p>
<p><strong>The God  (<em>ha-e-l</em>) The great (<em>ha-gadol</em>)</strong></p>
<p>Gevurah</p>
<p><strong>The mighty (<em>ha-gibbor</em>)</strong></p>
<p>Tiferet</p>
<p><strong>And the awesome (<em>ve-ha-nora</em>)</strong></p>
<p>To bring them influence and blessing from the source of the right of <em>keter</em>, called <em>or zah</em>, the mystery of <em>yud</em> in the name <em>yud hei vav hei</em> (<em>YUD HY VYV HY</em>) [72]</p>
<p><strong>God on high (<em>e-l elyon</em>)</strong></p>
<p>Who brings influence from <em>hokhmah</em> to <em>binah</em></p>
<p><strong>Benefactor of (<em>gomeil</em>)</strong></p>
<p><em> </em></p>
<p><em>Hasadim</em> that are great and give light, that her aspect is from the right, <em>hesed</em>; and all the aspects from her side are kind</p>
<p><strong>Great kindness (<em>hasadim tovim</em>)</strong></p>
<p>From the source of <em>binah</em> of <em>keter</em>, which is the name <em>alef hei yud hei</em> (<em>ALF HA YUD</em> <em>HA</em>) [143]</p>
<p><strong>And possesses all (<em>vekoneih ha-kol</em>)</strong></p>
<p>The sprouting of three fathers, all <em>hasadim</em> from the highest white light.</p>
<p><strong>And remembers the kindness of the fathers (<em>vezokheir hasdei avot</em>)</strong></p>
<p>Mystery of the name <em>yud hei vav hei</em> (<em>YUD HA VAV HA</em>) [45] of <em>keter</em>, <em>vav</em> of the name of <em>arikh anpin</em> and <em>keter</em> revealed</p>
<p><strong>And brings redemption (<em>u’meivi go’eil</em>)</strong></p>
<p>Nezah and <em>hod</em>, children of the three fathers</p>
<p><strong>To the sons (<em>livnei</em>) of their sons (<em>veneihem</em>)</strong></p>
<p>Meditate on spreading the last letter <em>hei</em> in the name <em>Y-H-V-H</em> of <em>keter</em></p>
<p><strong>For the sake of His name (<em>lema’an shemo</em>)</strong></p>
<p>From there, spreading out the exiled <em>malkhut</em> who will be bound between two arms.</p>
<p><strong>In love (<em>be’ahavah</em>).</strong></p>
<p>Now return to unify from bottom to top through <em>hokhmah</em> and <em>binah</em> as one. <em>Malkhut</em> bound with <em>malkhut</em> of <em>keter</em>.</p>
<p><strong>King (<em>melekh</em>)</strong></p>
<p><em>Tiferet</em> bound to <em>tiferet</em> of <em>keter</em> <em>yud</em> <em>hei</em> <em>vav</em> <em>hei</em> (<em>YUD HA VAV HA</em>) [45]</p>
<p><strong>Helper (<em>ozeir</em>)</strong></p>
<p><em>Gevurah</em> bound in the name <em>Eh-yeh</em> of <em>keter</em></p>
<p><strong>And savior (<em>u-moshia</em>)</strong></p>
<p><em>Hesed</em> bound in the mystery of the highest <em>hesed</em> of <em>keter</em>, <em>yud hei vav hei</em> (<em>YUD HY</em> <em>VYV</em> <em>HY</em>).[72]</p>
<p><strong>And Shield (<em>u-magein</em>).</strong></p>
<p><em>Yesod</em> including all ten <em>sefirot</em> from the world of the male</p>
<p><strong>Blessed (<em>barukh</em>)</strong></p>
<p><em>Malkhut</em> including all ten <em>sefirot</em> from the world of the female</p>
<p><strong>Are You (<em>atah</em>)</strong></p>
<p>Going up to unite in <em>keter</em> until <em>Ein Sof</em></p>
<p><strong>Lord (<em>Y-H-V-H</em>)</strong></p>
<p><em>YAHD-UNHY</em>; <em>YAHA-VYHH</em>;</p>
<p><em>alef dalet nun yud</em> (<em>ALF DLT NUN YUD</em>); [#zz]</p>
<p><em>yud hei vav hei</em> (<em>YUD HA VAV HA</em>);[45]</p>
<p><em>alef hei yud hei yud hei vav hei</em> (<em>ALF HA YUD HA YUD HY VYV</em> <em>HY</em>).[#]</p>
<p>Bind three fathers of <em>malkhut</em> in <em>hesed</em> to bring everything out from <em>binah</em> and bring them to <em>hesed</em>.</p>
<p><strong>Shield of Abraham (<em>magein avraham</em>).</strong></p>
<p><strong><br />
</strong></p>
<p>Copyright © 2010 Alan Brill • All Rights Reserved</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/26/r-moshe-cordovero-on-the-amidah/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>12</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Arthur Green- Radical Judaism #2 of 5 parts</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/26/arthur-green-radical-judaism-2/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/26/arthur-green-radical-judaism-2/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Apr 2010 03:43:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neo-Hasidism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rabbis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[spirituality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[arthur Green]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[radical judaism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1176</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The first chapter is on Green’s quest for God. Continued from part 1- here. Continue to part 3 &#8211; here. Continue to part 4 here. part 5 here Green writes that he is a Jewish seeker looking for a lone &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/26/arthur-green-radical-judaism-2/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The first chapter is on Green’s quest for God.</p>
<p><a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/06/arthur-green-radical-judaism-1/">Continued from part 1- here. </a>     </p>
<p> <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/01/arthur-green-–-radical-judaism-3/">Continue to part 3 &#8211; here.</a> <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/08/green-radical-judaism-4/">Continue to part 4 here. </a><br />
<a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/22/arthur-green-–-radical-judaism-5/">part 5 here</a></p>
<p>Green writes that he is a Jewish seeker looking for a lone path. He discusses his atheist upbringing and that he is seeking a middle path between atheism and theism, which he finds in his poetic pantheistic reading of Hasidism.</p>
<p>Green wants to be both a seeker and the spiritual leader of our age. His calling himself a seeker is a bit much at this point when Green sets himself up  as an exemplar and leader of our age.  Someone who is seeking does not write an article called “On Being Arthur Green” implying that one should learn from his wisdom &#8211; it was published when he first got to Hebrew College. One can only write an article like that at a pinnacle to share your wisdom. In addition, Green has been in the public eye and noted in the newspapers his whole life.</p>
<p>As a spiritual autobiography of someone who was in all the important places, there was little on his teachers at JTS or Brandeis. Nor on his classmates David Novak, Reuven Kimmelman, and  Byron Sherwin. Nothing as doctoral adviser at Penn or his being President of RRC. Nor a mention of being invited as a young academic to Peter Berger’s &#8220;other side of God&#8221; retreats or being one of the youngest involved in the Classics of Spirituality and World Spirituality series. Nothing on founding Shefa quarterly with Jonathan Omar-Man and Adin Steinsatz. And most surprisingly nothing on the founding of the first havurah while in grad school Havurat Shalom in Somerville, where along with his buddies Danny Matt, Michael Fishbane, James Kugel and Michael Strassfeld they set out to create a new Judaism for a new age. As a seeker he can claim to “still haven’t found what I am looking for” and not need to survey the past. But if he is offering wisdom that he holds as truth then the disestablishmentarianism is a bit jarring.</p>
<p>Green himself attributes his title <em>Radical Judaism</em> to the radical &#8220;God is dead&#8221; theology of the 1960’s. He claims that the holocaust and historical criticism ruptured his faith. He found his way back through the non-personal pantheistic hiding God of Hasidism and Kabbalah. He attributes his salvation in the writings of  Hilell Zeitlin (H”YD) who went from freethinking journalist to fervent Hasid and was uniquely able to interpret Hasidism through the eyes of Nietzsche, Schopenhauer, and Tolstoy. Zeitlin created an urbane Hasidism for his urban newspaper readers.</p>
<p>As a side point, Green’s <em>Tormented Master</em> followed the interpretive lines of Zeitlin and portrayed Rav Nahman as struggling with doubt and freethinking.  When Mendel Pierkaz gave a negative review of Green as “Hasidism for a new world” since it was based on Zeitlin, everyone was furious and even more furious when Piekarz reprinted his review.  The sacrilege was that Green was considered in America as the true university interpretation of Rav Nahman. Now Zvi Mark is the regnant academic work on Rav Nahman and has a different reading of Rav Nahman than Greens, and more people follow the interpretation of Rav Nahman by Rabbis Kenig, Schick, Arush and Schechter et al than academic works.</p>
<p>Green accepts his involvement in the psychedelic age and quaintly defines post-modernism as the rejection of modernity by the counter culture of the 1960’s  They sought to transcend the rational into the realm of myth, drugs, pantheism, and poetry. (Go read Art Green&#8217;s early psychedelic works under the pseudonym Itzhak Lodzer.) </p>
<p>Green accepts as another side to his thought that of religious humanism- Kafka, Buber, and Hebrew literature.</p>
<p>After almost 40 years, Green is not claiming identity of his thought with Heschel anymore. He does claim affinity to Tom Berry (d 2009) visionary advocate of evolutionary ecological development of human consciousness, human lifestyle, and our life on the planet. Berry is the near forgotten theologian of the Age of Aquarius and moon landing, who barely got obituaries last summer when he died. Green reminds people of Berry’s positions on our sitting on the edge of a new evolutionary moment where religion will no longer be literal. Like in 2001 Space Odyssey, the world is being thrust into the future and mankind needs to evolve with it.  Religion will now be a mystical pantheism of energy flow that God providentially directs. Yes, he believes this but just not literal the way fundamentalists or orthodox believe. This God is not the theistic God of the Protestant era but “God” – the force of the astro, geo, bio, psych, realms.</p>
<p>Many years ago, Green wrote an article in<em> Shefa Quarterly </em>on the need for a new Jewish theology deserves reprinting for its quest for remytholization over rationalism. Not shattered myths but learning to make the myths of Pesikta, Zohar, and Rav Nahman come live again. For a sense of what this new volume lacks in its discussion of myth compared to older Green writings, here are some excerpts from a <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/1989/02/19/us/reconstructionist-jews-turn-to-the-supernatural.html">NYT interview from 1989 </a>about the new RRC prayer book. They give a sense of the kernel of the birth his rejection of rational for myth and learning to see religion as a progressive force.</p>
<blockquote><p>While the notion of a &#8221;chosen people&#8221; is still excluded from the new liturgy, the mention of miracles, like the splitting of the Red Sea, have been restored. Dr. Arthur Green, president of the Reconstructionist Rabbinical College and one of the editors of the new volume, said the &#8221;language of myth&#8221; speaks powerfully to many people, even if they do not believe in the literal details. &#8221;As myth, the ancient tale of wonder underscores the sense of daily miracle in our lives,&#8221; he said.</p>
<p>Dr. Green, the president of the college, said the prayer book was molded by events that began unfolding in the 1960&#8217;s, and &#8221;our view of religion and its place in society have drastically changed&#8221; since then. The nation, he said, went from debates over &#8221;Is God Dead?&#8221; to seeing the power of religion in the civil rights movement and in the movement to end the Vietnam War. &#8221;We learned from the 60&#8217;s that religion can be a progressive social force for change,&#8221; he added.</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/01/arthur-green-–-radical-judaism-3/">Continue to part 3 &#8211; here.</a><br />
<a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/08/green-radical-judaism-4/">Continue to part Four here </a><br />
<a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/22/arthur-green-–-radical-judaism-5/">Continue to part 5 here.</a></p>
<p>Copyright © 2010 Alan Brill • All Rights Reserved </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/26/arthur-green-radical-judaism-2/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>6</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Teaching Meditation</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/16/teaching-meditation/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/16/teaching-meditation/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2010 00:06:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kavvanah]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=964</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The cartoon seeks to make fun, but I find it quite serious. Is there any other way to teach meditation than in the language of those you are teaching. If one teaches a kavvanah from Rabbi Isaac the blind or &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/16/teaching-meditation/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/computer-yoga.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="929" data-permalink="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/computer-yoga/" data-orig-file="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/computer-yoga.jpg" data-orig-size="400,350" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;}" data-image-title="computer yoga" data-image-description="" data-medium-file="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/computer-yoga.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/computer-yoga.jpg?w=400" src="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/computer-yoga.jpg?w=500" alt="" title="computer yoga"   class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-929" srcset="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/computer-yoga.jpg 400w, https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/computer-yoga.jpg?w=150 150w, https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/computer-yoga.jpg?w=300 300w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></a></p>
<p>The cartoon seeks to make fun, but I find it quite serious. Is there any other way to teach meditation than in the language of those you are teaching. If one teaches a kavvanah from Rabbi Isaac the blind or Rabbi Moses Cordovero does one teach medieval cosmology and medieval science to explain it? What if it is a once a week meditation class and one wants to get down to practice. Should one use the language of bittul or of &#8220;clear your cache and history? Should one imagine light at the bottom of emanation or a blank web page? Is this modernizing into new age like neo-hasidism or the only way to do things?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/16/teaching-meditation/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/computer-yoga.jpg" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">computer yoga</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Further Adventures in new Zohar scholarship</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/06/further-adventures-in-new-zohar-scholarship/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/06/further-adventures-in-new-zohar-scholarship/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2010 01:40:20 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gerald Blidstein]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[honoring parents]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[oded yisraeli]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sefirot]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[yehudah liebes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[zohar]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=903</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[We have previously looked at the Zohar scholarship of Daniel Abrams, and Melila Hellner-Eshed, Now we look at Oded Yisraeli in a new article “Honoring Father and Mother in Early Kabbalah: From Ethos to Mythos” JQR 99/3 Summer 2009 396-415 &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/06/further-adventures-in-new-zohar-scholarship/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We have previously looked at the Zohar scholarship of <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/22/was-the-zohar-ever-a-book/">Daniel Abrams,</a> and <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/13/why-read-the-zohar/">Melila Hellner-Eshed,</a> Now we look at Oded Yisraeli in a new article “Honoring Father and Mother in Early Kabbalah: From Ethos to Mythos” JQR 99/3 Summer 2009 396-415</p>
<p>Yisraeli looks at a piece of Zohar where R. Hiyya identifies the father with binah, R. Abba identifies it with hokhmah, but R. Yossi identifies it with tiferet. Why does R. Yossi lower the identity of Father? Ans: to be more like Rabbinic texts.</p>
<p>Others have noted (Fishbane, Liebes, Heller-Eshed) that the names in the Zohar each portray different sources. Usually the names reflect a procession from Midrash to Gerona Kabbalah to Castillian Kabblah. But this case offer insight into the relationship of Zohar with Rabbinics. </p>
<p>Mother and Father are portrayed as the higher sefirot is everywhere before the Zohar, including Bahir and Gerona. The source is a variety of Logos theories and personification of the Nous and the highest levels.But starting with the Zohar Mother and Father are lowered to Tiferet and Malkhut.  Yisraeli claims that the shift in this case reflects a return to Rabbinics, especially the Mekhilta also cited in the Talmud, and Philo.<br />
The Talmud states that one honors one’s parents because it is honoring the Holy One, Blessed be He. Alternately in Philo, “parents are the created Gods”</p>
<p>Gerald Blidstein in his classic work <em>Honor Thy Father and Mother</em>, shows the prevalence of this idea in Stoic sources. But Blidstein sharply differentiates the rabbis from the Hellenistic sources because the Rabbis do not essentialize, and in fact treat God using a parent metaphor. In contrast, Yisraeli claims, that even without denying some difference between the Hellenistic sources and the Rabbinic, the later readers of the rabbinic tradition in later midrash and then in Kabbalah, in fact did essentialize. Kabblah presents an essentialist reading of Hazal.<br />
The Kabblaists were drawing the connection between the earthly father and the divine father of HKBH, creating a tight parallel.</p>
<p>Yehudah Liebes (1994) already noted the reading of the live images of rabbinics into a “stiff” kabbalistic framework.<br />
Yisraeli claims that nevertheless many of these live images were repressed and not used in the later rabbinic texts and they return afresh in kabbalah. He also claims that the new sefirot symbol makes a stronger case for the ethical imperative.</p>
<p>He finds a similar process in how “the land of Israel” is identified with malkhut. A repressed live myth of the land of Israel as divine realm returns as a need to cleave to malkhut. Before the 13th century when the goal was a restored Divine name, it did not have the same ethical import.<br />
He has studies on the process of moving from midrash to Zohar of the images of Eliyahu, Avrham, Esau, the land of Israel, and has forthcoming book on Tree of Life by Magnes Press. I look forward to reading it.</p>
<p>His forthcoming book will deal with the theme of the Tree of Life and show that the tree as essentialized in certain [Biblical and ] rabbinic passages, then the entire Divine realm is a tree (Bahir) and finally only Tiferet is a tree, but one can join to it, creating a stronger symbol.</p>
<p>Are you essential? Well, Hazal are essential according to the early kabbalah.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/06/further-adventures-in-new-zohar-scholarship/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rabbi Morgenstern and Meditation</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/09/rabbi-morgenstern-and-meditation/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/09/rabbi-morgenstern-and-meditation/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2010 04:28:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Hasidism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neo-Hasidism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[popular religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rabbis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[spirituality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ashlag]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Derech yihud]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[derekh yihud]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rav Itchie Mayer Morgenstern]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sheva Eynayim]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tu beshevat]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yitzhak Meir Moregenstern]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[YM Erlanger]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=751</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When someone mentions Jewish meditation to me the first thing I think of are the Haredi Kabbalitic mediators. I think of Y.M Erlanger who in his Sheva Eynayim and in classes in Heimishe Yeshivos is teaching Hasidut combined with Abulafia &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/09/rabbi-morgenstern-and-meditation/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When someone mentions Jewish meditation to me the first thing I think of are the Haredi Kabbalitic mediators. I think of Y.M Erlanger who in his <em>Sheva Eynayim</em> and in classes in Heimishe Yeshivos is teaching Hasidut combined with Abulafia and I think of Yitzhak Meir Moregenstern who is reorganizing early Kabbalah, Ramak, Ari, and Abulafia as Hasidut.  Erlanger’s starts with the statements in <em>Sefer Habesht al Hatorah </em>and introduces ever more esoteric material and at the end of the last volume, he introduces Abulafia with a warning that the material that he is about to teach is not for everyone, and not everyone should enter the Pardes, and even if you do enter this may not be for you. In contrast, Rabbi  Morgenstern called Rav Itchie Mayer Morgenstern starts everyone on the real stuff.</p>
<p>R. Morgenstern is a Haredi descendant of the Kotzker and lived most of his life in England and has moved to Jerusalem and set up a Beit Midrash. You can find videos of him teaching and singing with Anglos on the web.  See<a href="http://dixieyid.blogspot.com/2007/11/rav-itchie-mayer-shalosh-sheudos.html"> here,</a> <a href="http://dixieyid.blogspot.com/2007/05/chochma-vs-bina-practical_30.html">here </a>and <a href="http://dixieyid.blogspot.com/2007/05/chochma-vs-bina-practical.html">here.</a><br />
He has attached a real following. He gives weekly public shiurim in kavvanot, in Komarno, and Ramhal. He has an email list serve for his Torah, his kabbalah, and for assorted teachings (Hebrew, English, and Yiddish).  Send an email here to subscribe tc7@neto.bezeqint.net </p>
<p>He seems to have read some generic books on “How to Meditate” or “Meditation for Everyone” and in his work <em>Derekh Yihud</em> he reorganizes traditional  kabbalistic practices into an order that reflects the general mediation world. The topics are sitting, breathing, visualizing, creating an avir in front of one, colors, and  a unified vision.  He freely takes pieces of Abulafia, Ramak,  and early kabbalah to create a Jewish meditation manual in line with the non-Jewish ones. The work <em>Derekh Yihud</em> opens up a new path of reorganizing the older materials based on modern principles.</p>
<p>I see him as potentially the future.  Rav Ashlag wrote in the 1930’s and took the meditation, medieval worldview and fantasy out of the Kabbalah and replaced it was science, communism, Schopenhauer, and a closed system. Now everything from the Kabbalah Centre to Bnai Baruch to Michael Leitman are his spiritual descendents. Rabbi Morgensten is teaching the young grandchildren of the Rebbes and many  in Kolel and he also accepts the varied pneumatics of Jerusalem as his students.  When all those students take their positions as Rebbes, Ramim, and teachers then the meditation format of breathing and visualization will be the tradition.  If the trend continues,  in 2050 this will be mainstream Kabbalah. </p>
<p>I had originally planned this post before my computer crash when I received the following two weeks ago. It offers a concise taste of <em>Derekh Yihud.</em> Morgenstern advises to close the eyes and see the hidden lights  in order to achieve bliss. One turns from this world to the airspace and achieves a vision of the Throne. Lights, then hidden mind, and finally the source of the soul and the Throne.</p>
<blockquote><p>
When a Jew spends time in hisbodedus before his Creator, he closes his eyes so as not to be enticed by the illusory pleasures of this world because he doesn’t want to be connected to them.<br />
When he closes his eyes in this way, he is able to see the brilliant hues that are rooted in the “hidden mind” of Mocha Sesima’ah, and he begins to derive pleasure from spiritual reality, from the fact that Hashem is revealed through a myriad of shades and hues of dveikus. He starts to feel Hashem’s light and glory within himself, and how all of the pleasures of this world are null and void, are like a mere sliver of light, compared with the delight of dveikus that is a composite of all possible forms of bliss.</p>
<p>So when a person seals his vision against the illusory nature of this world, he rises to the place of the “airspace” and its “membrane,” which is really the source of the human soul and its throne of glory. In that place it can be said, “From my flesh, I see G-d.” One begins to enjoy a vision of the ultimate Kisei HaKavod upon which the “form of a person sat.”<br />
The final three plagues parallel these three states of dveikus:<br />
First, a person must meditate and be misboded on the expansive Binah light of Hashem.<br />
Then he must ascend to the place of the “hidden mind” which is the counterpart of the holy darkness of turning aside from this-worldly concerns to receive “light in all his dwellings.” With this, he destroys the klippah of the impure firstborn and rises further to the place of the “membrane of the airspace” and the “airspace” itself which correlates to the level of the Da’as of Atik and which reveals to him the source of his neshamah that “sits upon the throne.”<br />
 “It is revealed and known before Your Kisei HaKavod&#8230;” Meaning, through coming to the level of the Kisei HaKavod, we are able to subdue all of the klippos and utterly “smite Egypt through their firstborns.”</p></blockquote>
<p>This past week he sent out a special Tu beShevat essay. He opens the essay stating that was asked why Hayyim Vital did not mention TuBeshevat and answers in the name of R. Haayim Cohen that it is a hidden quality. And when pressed why does everyone do it today? He turns to R. Aharon Halevi of Strashelye explaining that since we are lesser today everyone learns Kabbalah since they do not grasp the real depth anyway.  The essay is a running account of his Torah and the questions he received Tu Beshevat-Shabbat Shrah. There are many interesting points in it including -We are told of the joy from the recent publishing  of Vital’s alchemy and magic.</p>
<p>Copyright © 2010 Alan Brill • All Rights Reserved</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/09/rabbi-morgenstern-and-meditation/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>31</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Jewish Meditation 1995-2005</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/26/meditation-1995-2005/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/26/meditation-1995-2005/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2010 14:21:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Buddhism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[populations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[spirituality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[chochmat halev]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish meditation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=644</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Here is an account from The Forward that parallels what I have seen in the field. In the early and mid nineties there was a great desire for the technical aspects of meditation and Jewish meditation. Then, after only 5 &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/26/meditation-1995-2005/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here is an account from The Forward that parallels what I have seen in the field. In the early and mid nineties there was a great desire for the technical aspects of meditation and Jewish meditation. Then, after only 5 years it started broadening into all forms of spirituality especially musical forms and emotional healing. And finally right before our eyes, it all stops around 2005. People started coming to a class listed as Jewish meditation and assumed that it has something to do with guitars, bongos and chanting. In 1995, people wanted meditation and came with Zen or Vipasssana backgrounds and then flash it was gone by 2005, leaving revivalism in its wake.</p>
<p>Even the local Buddhist center here in NJ, gave daily and weekly meditation classes in 2000 and now only offers a once a month introduction to Happiness, saving any serious meditation instruction for biannual retreats.</p>
<blockquote><p>Chochmat HaLev came to life in the 1990s… One of these teachers, Rabbi Avram Davis, proposed creating a Jewish meditation center that could be a community resource…. Chochmat HaLev was launched, first as a series of classes in 1992 to 1993, and then as a nonprofit organization in 1995&#8230; In focusing on Jewish meditation, Gefen and Davis were at the forefront of a wave of interest in training a generation of Jewish “spiritual leaders,” who could bring meditation to their own congregations and lead meditation retreats and workshops for nonaffiliated Jews. So in addition to holding its own retreats and workshops, Chochmat pioneered a year-long leadership program with an initial cohort of 40 students.</p>
<p>Something happened on the communal meditation cushion, however. Joined by their interest in Jewish spirituality, the initial group felt a desire to pray together — a development that took Gefen by surprise. Davis, however, had thought of offering services from the beginning, because for him, Jewish meditation could exist only as part of a larger practice.</p>
<p>From the start, Davis led Chochmat’s services, distinguished by the constant thrum of a six-piece band composed of guitar, bass, drum set, keyboards and vocalists, its musical direction owed in equal parts to Rabbi Shlomo Carlebach, American rock and Moroccan beats. During a typical service, continuing today, participants dance in the aisles, clap, stomp their feet and sway with hands in the air, in an atmosphere most reminiscent of evangelical rapture</p>
<p>From 2000 to 2005, Chochmat HaLev functioned much like a cross between an institute for Jewish spirituality and an independent minyan.  Holding these two very different organizations together was a tight-knit, supportive community.</p>
<p>The year 2005 marked a crisis for Chochmat. The meditation school had essentially vanished. Aside from one year-long distance-learning program, the school was not offering more classes than an active synagogue. And because of its regular religious services, Chochmat was no longer seen as a non-denominational resource center: Its original mission was gone.</p>
<p>In 2005, the Chochmat board decided to become a functioning synagogue, and Avram Davis chose to leave.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.forward.com/articles/123815/">Full version</a></p></blockquote>
<p>Now Jewish meditation is once again for the few.People still do visualizations &#8211; part motivational part Neo-hasidic as a way to get psyched or as a means of bringing a moment of silence or a visualization into a regular service.  People are very sympathetic, &#8220;lets do it for a few minutes or a mini-course&#8221; and then let&#8217;s move on.</p>
<p>More on the year 2000 from<a href="http://zeek.forward.com/articles/116253/"> the same author</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>The year 2000 would see the establishment of the New York-based Institute of Jewish Spirituality, a Jewish meditation center run by Rabbi Sheila Pelz Weinberg; Makor Or, a San Francisco-based center founded by Rabbi Alan Lew (z’’l) and Norman Fischer; as well as a new emphasis on meditation at Elat Chayyim under Rabbi Jeff Roth and a burst of books on the topic (among them books by Gefen and Davis).</p></blockquote>
<p>Ten years ago there was a meditation moment.</p>
<p><strong>UPDATE &#8211; see the detailed rundown by Len Moskowitz in the Comments section. The comment shows that there is no diminution. </strong><br />
Copyright © 2010 Alan Brill • All Rights Reserved</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/26/meditation-1995-2005/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tu bShevat Seder -with Text</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/25/tu-bshevat-seder-with-text/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/25/tu-bshevat-seder-with-text/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2010 15:03:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[holidays]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[popular religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[DZ Hoffman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hemdat yamim]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[moshe fogel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[peri etz hadar]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pri etz hadar]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rav Kook]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tu be shevat]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tu bishevat]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tu bshevat]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=636</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[One year on tu b&#8217;shevat someone (a second career retiree) brought Rav Soloveitchik some bokser before shiur. After chuckling, Rav Soloveitchik told a story about how Rabbi DZ Hoffman would ask on his oral semikha exams – where is Tu &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/25/tu-bshevat-seder-with-text/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One year on tu b&#8217;shevat someone (a second career retiree) brought Rav Soloveitchik some bokser before shiur. After chuckling, Rav Soloveitchik told a story about how Rabbi DZ Hoffman would ask on his oral semikha exams – where is Tu bshevat in the shulkan arukh? (ANS-tahanun). Then someone (I don&#8217;t remember who) mentioned that Rav Kook on is exams would ask: what to do when you fnd a mistake in the Torah during Torah-reading?</p>
<p>Tu bshevat generated a piyyut for the amidah – found in the Cairo Genizah and is mentioned already by the Maharil in the 15<sup>th</sup> century. But by the end of the 17<sup>th</sup> century, in grand baroque age, the holiday generated a detailed seder of collecting 30 fruits. (There is a ton of painfully incorrect history about Tu bShevat on the web)</p>
<p>Twenty years ago, it was still hard to collect 30 fruits. But with the revolution in eating habits and the opening of new markets (Fairway, Whole Foods) one can now collect 30 fruits with ease. In 19<sup>th</sup> century Russia, even mid-summer one could with great difficulty only collect half the number.</p>
<p>It has made a come-back in certain circles. The seder will probably remain limited in its practitioners for a variety of reasons.</p>
<p>1] To collect 30 fruits based a set typology is a very tactile, crunchy, foody, techie activity. Most American Orthodox Jews don&#8217;t regularly shop for papaya, fresh lychees, gooseberries, dragon fruit, &nbsp;guavas, tamarind fruit, hickory nuts, and kumquats.</p>
<p>2] The seder assumes that one is comfortable with Zohar as one’s table talk. In America, this limits it to academics, Renewal Jews, Neo-Hasidim, and Moroccans.</p>
<p>3] The seder is a performance ritual. Most modern orthodox Jews have a difficult time with ritual. performance. Watch them struggle to get into hoshanot.</p>
<p>4] One has to have a visionary and narrative religion.</p>
<p>5] One has to have a meaningful understanding, beyond rationalism and irrationalism, of tikkunim, theurgy, magic, and religious cause and effect.</p>
<p>6] When you are told that Rav Kook avoided onions because they are all kelipot – it must resonate with you. .</p>
<p>Once, when Rav Abraham Kook was walking in the fields, lost deep in thought, the young student with him inadvertently plucked a leaf off a branch. Rav Kook was visibly shaken by this act, and turning to his companion he said gently, “Believe me when I tell you I never simply pluck a leaf or a blade of grass or any living thing, unless I have to.” He explained further, “Every part of the vegetable world is singing a song and breathing forth a secret of the divine mystery of the Creation.” For the first time the young student understood what it means to show compassion to all creatures. (Wisdom of the Mystics)</p>
<p>For those emailing me requesting sources:</p>
<p><strong>Here is the <a href="http://ellenbernstein.org/shomrei-periezhadar.htm">traditional Pri Etz Hadar in English.</a> This is the entire Seder- go for this.</strong></p>
<p><a href="http://www.hillel.org/NR/rdonlyres/A5339C76-6B07-4EC1-A970-D8FAFBA5E1CC/0/tu_bshevat_seder.pdf">Hillel Collegiate shortened version</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.chabad.org/kabbalah/article_cdo/aid/379846/jewish/Tu-BShevat-Basics.htm">A Chabad crib sheet</a></p>
<p>A nice article- with footnotes<em> <a href="http://www.biu.ac.il/JH/Parasha/eng/beshalah/arend.html">Tu Bishvat in Contemporary Rabbinical Literature</a></em></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><a href="http://rebshlomo.org/torahs/tu-bshvat-the-prayers-of-the-trees"><strong>Reb Shlomo on Tu Bshevat</strong></a></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>Excursus on Hemdat Yamim.</strong>The printed edition of the seder comes from the beautiful work <em>Hemdat Yamim,</em> which teaches the “customs of Safed” in a first person narrative, pretending to be a 16<sup>th</sup> century person from Safed. .According to current research, the work includes quotes of various Kabbalist customs from 1550 to 1715 from a variety of kabbalistic groups in Jerusalem, Safed, Italy, Turkey, Greece, and Amsterdam. Much of this material was attributed to the Ari, since anything based on Safed must be Ari. In this 150 period, there are over 300 little minhag books of Safed custom. Hemdat Yamin has many of them and collates them for us. To do any serious work on these customs one has to really be prepared to look at a large number of these books.</p>
<p>Isaiah Tishby places the editor in the circle of Kabbalists from Smyrna, and Benayahu attributed it to one member of the group,<a href="http://www.daat.ac.il/encyclopedia/value.asp?id1=1751"> Israel Yaakov Al Ghazi, Chief Rabbi of Jerusalem. </a></p>
<p>The book mixes customs based on Cordovero, Luria, Azikiri, ibn Makir, the Peri Hadash of Amsterdam, Nathan of Gaza and others. A recent article by Moshe Fogel in JSJT, shows that even if it has Sabbatian hymns written by Nathan of Gaza (such as the Atkinah Seudata for Yom Tov), it has no explicit Sabbatian theology or belief in Shabbati Zevi. And for those following Lithuanian tradition, &nbsp;both the Gra and Haayim of Volozhin accepted Hemdat Yamim.</p>
<p>(Think of using a potential Sabbatian custom as similar to the tune to Birkat Hamazon sung today in every Day School, which was commissioned by Mordechai Kaplan. It does not make those schools into Reconstructionist ideologically. It only shows that there are cultural overlaps and that one is part of a larger set of concerns called American Jewry. )</p>
<p>Copyright © 2010 Alan Brill • All Rights Reserved</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/25/tu-bshevat-seder-with-text/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>8</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why Read The Zohar?</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/13/why-read-the-zohar/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/13/why-read-the-zohar/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Jan 2010 22:21:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[aggadah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Daniel Matt]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[heller-eshed]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Melila Heller-Eshed.]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pritzker zohar]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rabbi Shimon bar Yochai]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[zohar]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=546</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[From this week&#8217;s issue of The Forward Why Read the Zohar? By Alan Brill (The Forward made a few rearrangements at the 11th hr, this was the version as of 2 days ago. Read this one) For an alternate view &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/13/why-read-the-zohar/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>From <a href="http://www.forward.com/articles/123344/">this week&#8217;s issue of The Forward<br />
<strong>Why Read the Zohar? By Alan Brill  </strong></a></p>
<p>(The Forward made a few rearrangements at the 11th hr, this was the version as of 2 days ago. Read this one)</p>
<p>For an alternate view to that of Melila Heller-Eshed, see the view of <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/22/was-the-zohar-ever-a-book/">Daniel Abrams discussed 2 months ago here..</a> </p>
<p><strong>Demystifying Kabbalah For English Readers</strong><br />
By Alan Brill Published January 13, 2010, issue of January 22, 2010</p>
<p>The Zohar 5: Pritzker Edition, Volume Five (With Translation and Commentary)<br />
Translated by Daniel C. Matt, Stanford University Press (Pritzker edition), 656 pages</p>
<p>A River Flows From Eden: The Language of Mystical Experience in the Zohar<br />
By Melila Hellner-Eshed Stanford University Press, 488 pages, $60.00.  </p>
<p>The Pritzker translation of the Zohar into English by Daniel Matt — the fifth volume of which has just appeared — should be greeted as a major cultural event. Yet, the publication of each volume has typically produced tiresome book reviews on the ownership of the word Kabbalah, comparing the academic approach of Gershom Scholem to Madonna’s New Age approach. The reviews do not answer the basic question: Why read the Zohar? Nor do they explain why the Zohar speaks to our age more than the myriad other kabbalistic works. </p>
<p>Melila Hellner-Eshed, in her book, “A River Flows From Eden: The Language of Mystical Experience in the Zohar,” provides an indispensible work that, finally, explains why the Zohar is an important and alluring work for our time. Susan Sontag taught readers to ask not what the art means, but rather “how it is what it is.” Hellner-Eshed follows Sontag and seeks to offer an experiential aesthetic of the Zohar.</p>
<p>Hellner-Eshed’s book is comparatively easy to read, despite being a scholarly work that assumes the reader has already read the terse prose of Scholem. Her work offers the nonacademic a chance to see the current state of Kabbalah study at Hebrew University among the students of Yehuda Liebes and Moshe Idel.</p>
<p>Liebes, who was Hellner-Eshed’s dissertation supervisor, claims that the Zohar was produced by a group similar to the group of mystics described in it. Accepting this approach, she muses “Who is this Rabbi Shimon who emerges from the quill of the Zohar’s composers?” Is he fictitious, or a legendary embellishment of a real historical person? Or maybe he represents the authors’ ideal figure? To these questions, she concludes: “There are of course no easy answers to these questions and perhaps this is as it ought to be.”</p>
<p>Hellner-Eshed’s book seeks to capture the life of the group of companions around Shimon, the stories of their wanderings and journeys, their study of Torah as a mystical quest and, finally, a description of their mystical experience. The book needs to be read cover to cover and then reread to integrate the concluding descriptions of mysticism back into the stories. This is because stories, experience and wisdom are not separate commodities for the kabbalists. </p>
<p>In Hellner-Eshed’s presentation, the companions around Shimon spend their time revealing the secrets of the Torah to each other as a collective form of mysticism. Instead of the usual reductionist discussion of sefirot (emanations of God), we are shown how the Holy Spirit pulsates within the companions of Rabbi Shimon bar Yohai. We also meet wondrous characters — old man, young child, donkey driver — who reveal ancient secrets to the companions.</p>
<p>The Zohar’s name originates in the biblical verse: “The enlightened will shine like the brilliance (zohar) of the sky&#8230;” (Daniel 12:3). Hellner-Eshed shows how the image of light is used to indicate the presence of a God in the Bible and in rabbinic literature. The Zohar, in turn, expands the metaphor to include variegated colors and mixings of shades, and combines light metaphors with those of fragrance and fluidity. Her own book draws its title from another of the Zohar’s central images, the superabundant divine plenty portrayed as “a river [that] flows from Eden.” Hellner-Eshed does not treat this imagery as mere metaphor, rather as a description of the mystic life of the companions engaged in nocturnal entrance into the Garden of Eden. When there is an awakening by the mystics below, then there is a parallel awakening from above, shown as a river of divine plenty.  </p>
<p>The Zohar portrays the experience of God as ecstatic delight through kissing, embracing and even intercourse. Hellner-Eshed’s original conclusion is that the mysticism of the Zohar describes the experience to be like a wave of water or A scent, where one enters into a period of heightened consciousness, sensuous pleasure, altered time frame and intuition of the secrets. According to Hellner-Eshed, there are three mystical states in the Zohar: when one drifts in and out; when one is “in the zone,” like a dancer or sprinter, and white light — a deep mythic level in which one enters into being itself. One can — using the terminology of less poetic scholars — call them shekhinah, tiferet and keter, but after Hellner-Eshed’s evocative exposition, that would show a tin ear for the drama. </p>
<p>Hellner-Eshed claims that the Zohar’s style is deliberately exaggerated and rhythmic to capture the experiential mood through trails of sensations and emotions. The rhythm of the Zohar offers many voices in which each sage continues and further develops the thought of the prior speaker. Hellner-Eshed compares the Zohar narrative to a jazz jam session, where a common melodic theme performed by the ensemble branches into solo improvisations that build to greater surprise, complexity and crescendo — the more virtuosity, the more wonderful and surprising the innovations. </p>
<p>One of her conclusions is, “The genius of the Zohar as a book lies precisely in its ability to capture the life of the experiences in Rabbi Shimon’s circle.” And thereby, according to Hellner-Eshed, it draws the reader into the mystical journey. She boldly claims that an academic attempt to understand the text should coincide properly with the attempt to induce a mystical experience. </p>
<p>What percentage of the Zohar fits Hellner-Eshed’s description? For that, we have to turn to the actual text of the Zohar. The Zohar corpus as published in the 16th century contains many reworked texts of ancient and medieval materials; there is certainly a large chunk of the Zohar that portrays the grand epic story of Shimon and his companions, but there are many segments that do not.</p>
<p>The fourth volume of the Pritzker edition of the Zohar (2007) was a diverse volume containing many texts that do not fit the model. It included a paraphrase of Philo of Alexandria’s ban on abortion, a Shiite style apocalypse of a messiah who is hidden in heaven, citations of 12th-century Ashkenazic theology, and selections from the rewritten biblical narrative of late antiquity.  </p>
<p>The newly published fifth volume of the Pritzker Zohar exemplifies Hellner-Eshed’s thesis in the delightful story of the Old Man of Mishpatim, who teaches though riddles and paradox and then explains them with a chivalrous story of a damsel in the castle who reveals herself only to the worthy kabbalist. But is also contains the terse and bombastic Book of Concealment, which describes the primordial world before emanation. Hellner-Eshed does not explain how the latter gnomic work fits with her selections. In addition, Hellner-Eshed’s biggest lack is that her work does not discuss the huge number of Zohar passages about mitzvahs, Halacha, rituals or pietistic life, all of which are admirably represented in Matt’s new volume.</p>
<p>Armed with these books, one can now begin to appreciate a cultural and religious treasure of Judaism. No journalist or book reviewer should write about Kabbalah again without first reading Hellner-Eshed. Her work steers the English reader between the Scylla of Kabbalah as technical sefirot and the Charybdis of Kabbalah as the personalized New Age spirituality. Hellner-Eshed’s work treats the Zohar as a mystical fantasy in which the Knights of the Round Table are rabbis living in an eroticized Middle Earth and spurred to great deeds by their love of the damsel Shechinah. Then, the beautifully edited Pritzker translation allows the interested reader to travel on these mystical journeys, yet still return home safely. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/13/why-read-the-zohar/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Authorship and the Individual</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/04/authorship-and-the-individual/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/04/authorship-and-the-individual/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2010 21:50:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[literary studies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[midrash]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[authorship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cosmology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[dante]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=480</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Interesting book review on questions of authorship as applied to Dante. The critical theorists have already shown that medievals treated Aristotelian philosophy the way we treat the rules of physics, not something that needs an author. And they showed how &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/04/authorship-and-the-individual/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Interesting book review on questions of authorship as applied to Dante.  The critical theorists have already shown that medievals treated Aristotelian philosophy the way we treat the rules of physics, not something that needs an author. And they showed how some medieval texts were written with the reader in mind- either as images on the side of the page or only giving allusions and letting the reader apply them on his own. Medievals also wrote as a form of revelation, and treated cosmologies as revelatory and they considered the bearers of the scholarly tradition as possessing an immanent truth. Not everyone who wrote was considered an <em>auctores</em>.</p>
<p>This opens up the question of what rabbinic Jewish author were doing? The Geonim and Nahmanides were writing with the a Divine spirit, or at least legal decisions were guided by the Divine. Some Kabbalistic works are seen as transmitting ancient knowledge or ascribed to older figures. And the Guide for the Perplexed is just that, a guide for the reader. But what were the “authors” of Pirkei deRebbe Eliezer  thinking? </p>
<p>To consider the modern issues: Judaism never bought into the idea of the individual author and still has trouble with intellectual property of an author. In many texts, Torah is seen as possessed by the collective or as eternally given. So when a posek writes a teshuvah: Is it his own authorship? Does he write as bearer of a mesorah, like a medieval kabbalist? Is there a revelation granted to the community? We tend to frame these questions using the anachronistic modern contrast of autonomy and authority. We need to ask: what is involved in an act of religious writing? Does one write ex cathedra, with immanent truth, with revelation, or for the reader?</p>
<p>But then it becomes more difficult- what happens when the written opinions of a rabbi are involved in petty squabbles or personal interests or manipulated by politics? Ascoli’s book on Dante  asks that question directly – If Dante claimed to write with revelation then how can he till be involved in his petty squabbles?  What happens when someone writes with immanent divine truth and also acts as an independent agent? </p>
<blockquote><p>
<a href="http://www.h-net.org/reviews/showrev.php?id=25533">Albert Russell Ascoli.  Dante and the Making of a Modern Author. Cambridge  Cambridge University Press, 2008. Reviewed by Jan G. Soffner (Zentrum Cr Literatur- und Kulturforschung) Published on H-Italy </a>(December, 2009)<br />
<strong><br />
By Which Authority Did Dante Write?</strong></p>
<p>If one happens to talk by chance about Dante&#8217;s fourteenth-century masterpiece _Divine Comedy_, one can observe a strange phenomenon.</p>
<p>Dante seems to misuse God for his political opinions, by letting the divine justice condemn his enemies, and for his personal<br />
pride or arrogance, by having all the best dead poets honor him (see, for instance, Inferno IV, 100-102). Moreover, isn&#8217;t it already quite<br />
presumptuous to &#8220;know&#8221; the divine verdict about everybody who has ever died? All this seems to be even stranger, since this work is<br />
evidently a literary text, not an inspired prophecy like the Revelation. So how could Dante attribute this authority to himself?<br />
And did he attribute this authority to himself after all, or did he &#8220;just&#8221; write fiction?</p>
<p>This suspicion arose as soon as the _poema sacro&#8211;_the &#8220;holy poem,&#8221; as Dante himself calls it (Paradiso XXV, 1)&#8211;was written. Nearly<br />
seven hundred years of &#8220;Dantology&#8221; (to use Robert Harrison&#8217;s brilliantly provocative term)[1] have not convincingly resolved this<br />
doubt. In the fourteenth century cosmological representations in the _Cosmographia_ of BernardusSilvestris (ca. 1084-1178), the _Anticlaudianus_ of Alanus ab Insulis (1120-1202) and the _Tesoretto_ of Brunetto Latini (ca. 1220-94). They read the text either as a spiritual revelation and a dream, despite its literary construction and despite the claim to report a physical journey, or they interpreted it in a &#8220;modern&#8221; way, that is, as a fictional construction, despite the explicit claims of the _Commedia_to be a revelatory work.</p>
<p>Ascoli also has an excellent knowledge notonly of the works of modern theoretical thinkers such as Hannah<br />
Arendt, Roland Barthes, Michel Foucault, and Mary Carruthers about literary authorship and authority, but also of the discursive<br />
figurations of _auctores_ available at Dante&#8217;s time. Ascoli starts with an extensive analysis of contemporary concepts of<br />
authorship, and of the manner in which Dante seems to be relating to them as a whole. Ascoli argues that the image of an author stemmed<br />
from the trustworthy _auctoritates_ of the ancient and/or philosophical and theological tradition granting for an immanent<br />
truth to biblical scribes and the true author, who is God. These traditional concepts refer to _auctoritas_ as both an individual and<br />
impersonal power and knowledge. The _auctor_ thereby was not so much a creative agent, but rather a mediating power of knowledge. He was<br />
one worthy of faith and obedience.</p>
<p>Hence Dante, modeled as an individual traveler in the _Divine Comedy_, &#8220;comes, paradoxically, to embody the canons of<br />
impersonal authority&#8221; (p. 20). On the one hand Dante is thereby traditionalist and conservative, on the other, he is also provided<br />
with the &#8220;transgressive desire to appropriate that attribute for himself, for the vernacular, and for &#8216;modernity'&#8221; (p. 20f).</p>
<p>How can a fictional work gain a revelatory truth? Ascoli shows convincingly how Dante assumes the traditional role of an<br />
authoritative author without thereby relating to the pre-existing models of knowledge implied by these kinds of authorship.<br />
The unease of us moderns when confronted with Dante cannot just be about the relation to an ineffable divine Being. Representationalist<br />
modern authors work with a more or less Aristotelian concept of fiction, that is, with a concept of a poetic truth relying on<br />
modeling possibilities and an emotionality that can be addressed playfully and without consequences. However, Dante tells us a<br />
different story </p></blockquote>
<p>Here is a sample of chapter one of <a href="http://www.cambridge.org/catalogue/catalogue.asp?isbn=9780511380464&amp;ss=exc">Albert Russell Ascoli.  Dante and the Making of a Modern Author.</a><br />
Can we move beyond the dichotomies of authority/autonomy or submission/freedom and explain the act of religious writing or studying Torah or acting as a rabbi in terms of how they define authorship or role of the self in the process? </p>
<p>Copyright © 2010 · All Rights Reserved </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/04/authorship-and-the-individual/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>6</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Islam as the relgion of Hesed</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/11/islam-as-the-relgion-of-hesed/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/11/islam-as-the-relgion-of-hesed/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 11 Dec 2009 07:57:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[israel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Abraham maimuni]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avraham elqayam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[clash of civilizations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[deot]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Judeo-Islamic synthesis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Shabbatai Zevi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yishmael]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=349</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Dr Avraham Elqayam is head of the Shlomo Moussaieff Center for Kabbalah Research and professor of Kabbalah at Bar Ilan University. A number of years ago he wrote an article in the journal of the Torah veAvodah movement called “The &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/11/islam-as-the-relgion-of-hesed/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dr Avraham Elqayam is head of the Shlomo Moussaieff Center for Kabbalah Research and professor of Kabbalah at Bar Ilan University. A number of years ago he wrote an article in the journal of the Torah veAvodah movement called “The Religion of Mercy: Encounters with Islam” <em>Deot </em>19, (2004) 6-8 (It is a late night freehand translation). I am not sure of his current opinion but it is a very interesting three page article. He does not draw broader implications than those presented here.</p>
<p>In the article, he discusses the clash of civilization that puts Jews on the side of Western civilization. He demurs:</p>
<blockquote><p>But are Jews part of the flesh of the flesh of Western Civilization? I am astonished! My family lived under the Muslim world in Spain and afterward in a small community in Gaza City. They lived submersed in the midst the Arabic Muslim civilization.</p></blockquote>
<p>On the identification of Judaism and the West:</p>
<blockquote><p>The question is – do we have to continue in this direction until we reach opposition or do we need to go in another direction? The Torah recounts how Isaac and Ishmael went together to bury Abraham. It is valid to ask on the role of Yishmael in the Jewish spiritual tradition. Our modern philosophers, especially [Franz] Rosenzweig betrayed us. I will turn, therefore, from the world of philosophy to the world of mysticism and Kabbalah. Perhaps there we will find a path and a direction.</p></blockquote>
<p>Elqayam finds three approaches in Jewish mysticism to Islam. Kabbalah, Jewish Sufism, and Sabbatianism.</p>
<p>In Kabbalah- the world is all symbolic of the divine realm, therefore</p>
<blockquote><p>When you contemplate about Islam, think about Ishmael in the parashah [Hayai Sarah] Ask what is being symbolized, what is the allusion in the world of divinity. It is surprising to reveal that the Spanish kabbalists saw the essence of Islam as connected to the power of the sefirah hesed. Abraham our patriarch represented hesed and Ishmael comes from Abraham, therefore Islam represents hesed.</p>
<p>In its inwardness, Islam is a religion of hesed  This is the self-consciousness of the Muslims themselves. Muslims are called in Arabic a religion of tolerance. This opinion appears in the writings of Yosef Gikitilla….The destiny of the Islamic nation amidst the humanity is to represent Divine hesed.”</p></blockquote>
<p>Rabbi Abraham Maimoni was influenced by the Sufi mystical schools. He quoted the learning of Sufis, and praised their use of music, body posture, and prostrations.</p>
<blockquote><p>Rabbi Abraham Maimuni saw Sufism as a form of meta-religion that bridged between Islamic spirituality and prophetic spirituality. His intention was understandably to imitate the prophets and not the Muslims, except according to his opinion, only the Muslims preserved the path of prophecy. We have seen in him the spiritual possibility within Judaism that preserves the Jewish identity but which expresses the spiritual world of Islam- the Jew lived in the culture of Islam, drawing leaven from the Muslim world yet making a synthesis between the worlds as a Jew.</p></blockquote>
<p>Shabbatai Zevi converted to Islam and his followers created a synthesis that mixed both religions, they were Muslims who also kept Jewish practices including the Jewish holidays. [He gives several examples of the syncretism]</p>
<p>He conlcudes:</p>
<blockquote><p>We need to reconnect the fine threads and the gleanings– that bring us to our brothers Ishmael, that are almost lost to us. It is possible that the time has already passed but we are required at least to try. It is incumbent upon us to begin afresh to build a spiritual bridge between Judaism and Islam, to this I desire.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/11/islam-as-the-relgion-of-hesed/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
