<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Prof Tamar Ross on Revelation and Biblical Criticism	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/12/prof-tamar-ross-on-revelation-and-biblical-criticism/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/12/prof-tamar-ross-on-revelation-and-biblical-criticism/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2013 20:47:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Jon Baker		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/12/prof-tamar-ross-on-revelation-and-biblical-criticism/#comment-7884</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jon Baker]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2013 20:47:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6030#comment-7884</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Sorry to be coming late to the game, but I wanted to digest it a bit, and reread it a few more times.  Mrs. B. took a class with Prof. Ross at Drisha many years ago, and found her quite confusing then.

She has long believed in continuing revelation.  Chasidim clearly have a  progressive revelation - Rashbi, then RMdL who reshaped the Zohar into contemporary idiom, then the Ari, then the Besht, then each group&#039;s rebbes.

Her assumptions about revelation seem to be: a) it is continous, b) it is non-verbal and comes through  rabbinic interpretation of texts, c) it cannot contradict (it must be filtered through) the &quot;original Sinaitic revelation&quot;.  The last says that she believes there *was* an original Sinaitic revelation. &quot;A Torah that is both wholly human and wholly divine&quot; 

After all that, it seems she has danced around the question of biblical criticism (which is about the text received at Sinai), and formulated a theory of Torah sheb&#039;al peh.

Question 5 starts to get at acosmism - there is no separate universe, even if we perceive one, which would imply that our rabbinic interpretations are revelation in that they are still part of Godliness in the timeless infinity.  We are not separate intellects, so what we perceive *is* part of  revelation.

The &quot;language game&quot; material and religion as a language with imbedded assumptions seems to echo R&#039; Brill&#039;s answer to my question some years ago, as to why the Chasidim who believe that humans are part of God don&#039;t succumb to antinomianism? because they are Yidden, who live a Jewish life, and wouldn&#039;t think of it.

While she talks about the text emerging out of the illocutionary encounter with man, that would seem to simply express the principle that God dictate the Torah to Moshe in some unknown fashion.  Meanwhile, she seems to speak about studying &quot;the text&quot;, which implies a unitary divine-originated text.  So I don&#039;t see her succumbing to higher criticism.

Rather, combining that with the acosmism, I see her saying something like:

if God is timeless and infinite,  and we are part of God, but can&#039;t perceive that because of the tzimtzum, then the revelation of the Torah is similarly timeless, not fixed at a  moment at Sinai.  How so, to incorporate both TSBK and TSBP? Our chidushim and interpretations, since we are part of God, originate in God every bit as much as the singular Sinaitic text.  So we too are part of the continuing  revelation as we perceive ourselves in time, even though it&#039;s all part of the singular revelation at Sinai and everywhere and everywhen.  

So biblical criticism falls by the wayside, it doesn&#039;t matter if there were four texts, or three, or one - it&#039;s all part of the same revelation.  We just see it as partial, and revealing itself continously over time, because of the tzimtzum, our limited perception.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sorry to be coming late to the game, but I wanted to digest it a bit, and reread it a few more times.  Mrs. B. took a class with Prof. Ross at Drisha many years ago, and found her quite confusing then.</p>
<p>She has long believed in continuing revelation.  Chasidim clearly have a  progressive revelation &#8211; Rashbi, then RMdL who reshaped the Zohar into contemporary idiom, then the Ari, then the Besht, then each group&#8217;s rebbes.</p>
<p>Her assumptions about revelation seem to be: a) it is continous, b) it is non-verbal and comes through  rabbinic interpretation of texts, c) it cannot contradict (it must be filtered through) the &#8220;original Sinaitic revelation&#8221;.  The last says that she believes there *was* an original Sinaitic revelation. &#8220;A Torah that is both wholly human and wholly divine&#8221; </p>
<p>After all that, it seems she has danced around the question of biblical criticism (which is about the text received at Sinai), and formulated a theory of Torah sheb&#8217;al peh.</p>
<p>Question 5 starts to get at acosmism &#8211; there is no separate universe, even if we perceive one, which would imply that our rabbinic interpretations are revelation in that they are still part of Godliness in the timeless infinity.  We are not separate intellects, so what we perceive *is* part of  revelation.</p>
<p>The &#8220;language game&#8221; material and religion as a language with imbedded assumptions seems to echo R&#8217; Brill&#8217;s answer to my question some years ago, as to why the Chasidim who believe that humans are part of God don&#8217;t succumb to antinomianism? because they are Yidden, who live a Jewish life, and wouldn&#8217;t think of it.</p>
<p>While she talks about the text emerging out of the illocutionary encounter with man, that would seem to simply express the principle that God dictate the Torah to Moshe in some unknown fashion.  Meanwhile, she seems to speak about studying &#8220;the text&#8221;, which implies a unitary divine-originated text.  So I don&#8217;t see her succumbing to higher criticism.</p>
<p>Rather, combining that with the acosmism, I see her saying something like:</p>
<p>if God is timeless and infinite,  and we are part of God, but can&#8217;t perceive that because of the tzimtzum, then the revelation of the Torah is similarly timeless, not fixed at a  moment at Sinai.  How so, to incorporate both TSBK and TSBP? Our chidushim and interpretations, since we are part of God, originate in God every bit as much as the singular Sinaitic text.  So we too are part of the continuing  revelation as we perceive ourselves in time, even though it&#8217;s all part of the singular revelation at Sinai and everywhere and everywhen.  </p>
<p>So biblical criticism falls by the wayside, it doesn&#8217;t matter if there were four texts, or three, or one &#8211; it&#8217;s all part of the same revelation.  We just see it as partial, and revealing itself continously over time, because of the tzimtzum, our limited perception.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/12/prof-tamar-ross-on-revelation-and-biblical-criticism/#comment-7861</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2013 13:52:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6030#comment-7861</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I believe Prof Ross is flying home today, so allow her a few days to post a reply to all the thoughtful comments.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I believe Prof Ross is flying home today, so allow her a few days to post a reply to all the thoughtful comments.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Isaac Shalev		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/12/prof-tamar-ross-on-revelation-and-biblical-criticism/#comment-7860</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Isaac Shalev]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2013 05:09:22 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6030#comment-7860</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Dr Ross forwards the position that revelation is neither the act of God speaking, nor the act of Man hearing, but rather, the act of Man speaking - retelling his experience of hearing a God who did not actually speak. This approach allows us to blame man for the shortcomings of revelation, from the lack of historical evidence for theophany at Sinai to lack of certainty over the content of revelation. God simply is. How we emerge from our encounter with God is our own problem.

Still, I&#039;m left with a problem over authority. Dr Ross finds God in everything, and all that we experience as humans is itself a kind of revelation - the evidence of Creation, at the very least. Yet Dr Ross limits her formal definition of revelation to the process of interpretation of that revelation by the rabbis. Seems like she&#039;s actually sketching out two ideas about revelation: first, as a matter of physics and metaphysics, all is God in an unbroken and indivisble unity that Man is incapable of grasping except in fragments (which must themselves be incapable of representing the indivisible whole). Second, there is also revelation as a matter of source and authority for moral behavior, which is the result of rabbinical interpretation of the former.

As a practical matter then, Dr Ross is faced with a different dilemma than the &quot;as if&quot; approach leaves us with, but it&#039;s a difficult one nonetheless. Dr Ross leaves us with the problem that individuals may well experience insightful revelation that resonates more closely with the infinited Divine, but those individuals may not have the institutional authority to define rules and norms. In esssence, Ross is falling back on the prophet vs priest dichotomy, and acknowledging that God may sometimes leak into the world through prophets, but it is the interpretive tradition of the rabbis that we priviledge. The irony then is that Ross, in doing so, may find herself best described as a prophet, not a priest - an unauthorized interpreter, a Cassandra whose accuracy doesn&#039;t impact her validity.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dr Ross forwards the position that revelation is neither the act of God speaking, nor the act of Man hearing, but rather, the act of Man speaking &#8211; retelling his experience of hearing a God who did not actually speak. This approach allows us to blame man for the shortcomings of revelation, from the lack of historical evidence for theophany at Sinai to lack of certainty over the content of revelation. God simply is. How we emerge from our encounter with God is our own problem.</p>
<p>Still, I&#8217;m left with a problem over authority. Dr Ross finds God in everything, and all that we experience as humans is itself a kind of revelation &#8211; the evidence of Creation, at the very least. Yet Dr Ross limits her formal definition of revelation to the process of interpretation of that revelation by the rabbis. Seems like she&#8217;s actually sketching out two ideas about revelation: first, as a matter of physics and metaphysics, all is God in an unbroken and indivisble unity that Man is incapable of grasping except in fragments (which must themselves be incapable of representing the indivisible whole). Second, there is also revelation as a matter of source and authority for moral behavior, which is the result of rabbinical interpretation of the former.</p>
<p>As a practical matter then, Dr Ross is faced with a different dilemma than the &#8220;as if&#8221; approach leaves us with, but it&#8217;s a difficult one nonetheless. Dr Ross leaves us with the problem that individuals may well experience insightful revelation that resonates more closely with the infinited Divine, but those individuals may not have the institutional authority to define rules and norms. In esssence, Ross is falling back on the prophet vs priest dichotomy, and acknowledging that God may sometimes leak into the world through prophets, but it is the interpretive tradition of the rabbis that we priviledge. The irony then is that Ross, in doing so, may find herself best described as a prophet, not a priest &#8211; an unauthorized interpreter, a Cassandra whose accuracy doesn&#8217;t impact her validity.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Amitai Blickstein		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/12/prof-tamar-ross-on-revelation-and-biblical-criticism/#comment-7859</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Amitai Blickstein]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2013 19:03:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6030#comment-7859</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I am invested in the attempt to reconcile the different spheres, and of late I have felt the inadequacy of Ricoeur’s contention that we moderns have irremediably lost the immediacy of belief, and that only “by interpreting that we can hear again,” but at the same time, living “as if” without even a second naiveté is (a) false, and (b) doesn’t work as advertised anyway. I read this post with great interest.

I was not optimistic about Ross’s conception of ‘blurring’ [as presented in summary], until I read to point 11, which I largely agree with, except for the conception of the &#039;game&#039; in question as a sub-world within a larger one (unless that world is a pre-linguistic one entirely, but then, that world is barely social, if you&#039;re only grunting at one another) {I hear resonances with Moshe Koppel’s lively essay “Judaism as a First Language” in Azure 2011}. You see, I share AS&#039;s concerns, and especially evanstonjew&#039;s expression of the matter - I appreciate Prof. Ross’s articulation of the problem, and her distinguishing herself from other options (I found the interview questions put to her were very well chosen, evoking informative responses), but at the critical moment, it felt like modern Kabbalah was a form of HandWavium (see tvtropes.org or wikipedia). למעשה, are we in NYC or Jerusalem? Speaking Hebrew or English? And how can you just say &quot;Oh, trust me, it sounds like Gibberish, but it really is Aramaic?&quot; That doesn&#039;t help in any way, it&#039;s a functionally neutral statement. There seems to be this magical bridge between the two worlds, painted over (or papered over) with quotes from RAIK and The Rebbe. How does Ross’s mitzido avoid “inadequate and wholly supernatural metaphysics”?

I personally gravitate towards pragmatism for that very reason, the clearing up of metaphysical statements in terms of how it plays out in the world. {This would also mean that a religion’s theory of revelation is not necessarily its metatheory, which would be too clean and top-down an account; the theophany at Sinai certainly is not necessarily so, [Perry Dane has an insightful essay on the topic]; I prefer Robert Cover’s pair nomos and narrative} However, pragmatism cannot be chauvinistic, claiming that its interpretations are what these metaphysical statements &quot;really&quot; mean. Alongside language games, we need translation games. The transcendent cannot be dismissed, if we are to avoid the problems of relativism and subjectivism that pragmatism falls prey to (e.g., since the pragmatic test of a statement is &quot;what works,&quot; well, who judges what has indeed worked? And by what criteria?). So we need a transcendent pragmatism. Ethics are that transcendence, but ethics are also a different language for the same pragmatic consequences of, say, certain kinds of psaq halakha. {I suppose I am implicitly adopting the standard communitarian position against classical liberalism. To put it differently, I am maintaining that one cannot “get rid of the funny ethics and stick with ethics,” because there is no such thing as ‘ethics’ (except as a heuristic device), there is *only* ‘funny ethics’ to work with}

This means that there are, not really, different &quot;logics&quot; that are epistemologically distinct. As it stands, I utterly reject those offerings in the comments. To my mind, that leads to the worst kind of insularity and ethical immunity, relativism, and circular logic. To belong to the global community of what we call &quot;ethical&quot; (or what Jewish tradition refers to in the verse [to name one source] כי ביתי בית תפילה יקרא לכל העמים, or עם חכם ונבון הגוי הגדול הזה! OK, two sources), implicitly requires what Hanan Alexander calls &quot;the requirements of ethical discourse,&quot; which include (1) intelligence, (2) freedom, and (3) fallibility. Any tradition which recognizes the importance of these qualities, and understands its members to be agents possessing them in turn, is &quot;ethical&quot; in that in can participate in moral critique (giving and receiving) from other traditions (language games) that are also intelligent, free, and fallible.

So there is no magical bridge, no need for Kabbalah {though, if you’re modern, I agree that there is a need for *something*}, and it is a bit close to Kaplan or Kadushin, as well as Spinoza, but existentially shares more with (as far as I know) with Soloveitchik. There is a logic, but it is *human* (which is the only face of God we really are arguing and care about anyway). And as anyone who has held a newborn can tell you, you can surely see the Divine within humanity.

{However, as I reread the post, it seems that on every pragmatic point, I am sympathetic to Ross’s position as presented. My only objection, in retrospect, is minor: I do not think that modern Kabbalah will help; that does not mean that it is inappropriate as a perfectly good ‘translation’ of native religious “simple belief,” practices, etc.

I do not think it will help (as much as one might like) because if the problem of contemporary modernity is the widespread loss of native ‘cultural-linguistic’ competence in halakha (that is, its substance, rather than its formalism), then replacing that requirement with one for a kabbalistic competence does not confront the issues of compartmentalization, nor provide direction towards a non-subjective methodology that might be the basis of a conversation between committed adherents who would like to constitute a unified community of more and/or less diverse elements.

So either the question of new data including Biblical Criticism does not really bother you, it’s a קשיא but not a תיובתא, a small detail to be filled in, but not a deal-breaker – filling in the brackets in Mordechai Breuer’s template with Kabbalistic terminology… OR the question really bothers you, and/because there are implications for differences in practice and discourse; and if Ross is addressing the question from this latter mindset, then, well Aren’t non-discursive practices inextricably linked to discourse (a point made by AS, I believe)? How can one set, say, the Tanya’s kabbalah as the *keystone* of one’s theory without in the same movement setting ShA HaRav as the keystone of one’s practice? As Prof. Brill said, “If one accepts the kabbalah as a solution, then one is Haredi, and if one treats it as naturalistic metaphor, then one is quite liberal.”

]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I am invested in the attempt to reconcile the different spheres, and of late I have felt the inadequacy of Ricoeur’s contention that we moderns have irremediably lost the immediacy of belief, and that only “by interpreting that we can hear again,” but at the same time, living “as if” without even a second naiveté is (a) false, and (b) doesn’t work as advertised anyway. I read this post with great interest.</p>
<p>I was not optimistic about Ross’s conception of ‘blurring’ [as presented in summary], until I read to point 11, which I largely agree with, except for the conception of the &#8216;game&#8217; in question as a sub-world within a larger one (unless that world is a pre-linguistic one entirely, but then, that world is barely social, if you&#8217;re only grunting at one another) {I hear resonances with Moshe Koppel’s lively essay “Judaism as a First Language” in Azure 2011}. You see, I share AS&#8217;s concerns, and especially evanstonjew&#8217;s expression of the matter &#8211; I appreciate Prof. Ross’s articulation of the problem, and her distinguishing herself from other options (I found the interview questions put to her were very well chosen, evoking informative responses), but at the critical moment, it felt like modern Kabbalah was a form of HandWavium (see tvtropes.org or wikipedia). למעשה, are we in NYC or Jerusalem? Speaking Hebrew or English? And how can you just say &#8220;Oh, trust me, it sounds like Gibberish, but it really is Aramaic?&#8221; That doesn&#8217;t help in any way, it&#8217;s a functionally neutral statement. There seems to be this magical bridge between the two worlds, painted over (or papered over) with quotes from RAIK and The Rebbe. How does Ross’s mitzido avoid “inadequate and wholly supernatural metaphysics”?</p>
<p>I personally gravitate towards pragmatism for that very reason, the clearing up of metaphysical statements in terms of how it plays out in the world. {This would also mean that a religion’s theory of revelation is not necessarily its metatheory, which would be too clean and top-down an account; the theophany at Sinai certainly is not necessarily so, [Perry Dane has an insightful essay on the topic]; I prefer Robert Cover’s pair nomos and narrative} However, pragmatism cannot be chauvinistic, claiming that its interpretations are what these metaphysical statements &#8220;really&#8221; mean. Alongside language games, we need translation games. The transcendent cannot be dismissed, if we are to avoid the problems of relativism and subjectivism that pragmatism falls prey to (e.g., since the pragmatic test of a statement is &#8220;what works,&#8221; well, who judges what has indeed worked? And by what criteria?). So we need a transcendent pragmatism. Ethics are that transcendence, but ethics are also a different language for the same pragmatic consequences of, say, certain kinds of psaq halakha. {I suppose I am implicitly adopting the standard communitarian position against classical liberalism. To put it differently, I am maintaining that one cannot “get rid of the funny ethics and stick with ethics,” because there is no such thing as ‘ethics’ (except as a heuristic device), there is *only* ‘funny ethics’ to work with}</p>
<p>This means that there are, not really, different &#8220;logics&#8221; that are epistemologically distinct. As it stands, I utterly reject those offerings in the comments. To my mind, that leads to the worst kind of insularity and ethical immunity, relativism, and circular logic. To belong to the global community of what we call &#8220;ethical&#8221; (or what Jewish tradition refers to in the verse [to name one source] כי ביתי בית תפילה יקרא לכל העמים, or עם חכם ונבון הגוי הגדול הזה! OK, two sources), implicitly requires what Hanan Alexander calls &#8220;the requirements of ethical discourse,&#8221; which include (1) intelligence, (2) freedom, and (3) fallibility. Any tradition which recognizes the importance of these qualities, and understands its members to be agents possessing them in turn, is &#8220;ethical&#8221; in that in can participate in moral critique (giving and receiving) from other traditions (language games) that are also intelligent, free, and fallible.</p>
<p>So there is no magical bridge, no need for Kabbalah {though, if you’re modern, I agree that there is a need for *something*}, and it is a bit close to Kaplan or Kadushin, as well as Spinoza, but existentially shares more with (as far as I know) with Soloveitchik. There is a logic, but it is *human* (which is the only face of God we really are arguing and care about anyway). And as anyone who has held a newborn can tell you, you can surely see the Divine within humanity.</p>
<p>{However, as I reread the post, it seems that on every pragmatic point, I am sympathetic to Ross’s position as presented. My only objection, in retrospect, is minor: I do not think that modern Kabbalah will help; that does not mean that it is inappropriate as a perfectly good ‘translation’ of native religious “simple belief,” practices, etc.</p>
<p>I do not think it will help (as much as one might like) because if the problem of contemporary modernity is the widespread loss of native ‘cultural-linguistic’ competence in halakha (that is, its substance, rather than its formalism), then replacing that requirement with one for a kabbalistic competence does not confront the issues of compartmentalization, nor provide direction towards a non-subjective methodology that might be the basis of a conversation between committed adherents who would like to constitute a unified community of more and/or less diverse elements.</p>
<p>So either the question of new data including Biblical Criticism does not really bother you, it’s a קשיא but not a תיובתא, a small detail to be filled in, but not a deal-breaker – filling in the brackets in Mordechai Breuer’s template with Kabbalistic terminology… OR the question really bothers you, and/because there are implications for differences in practice and discourse; and if Ross is addressing the question from this latter mindset, then, well Aren’t non-discursive practices inextricably linked to discourse (a point made by AS, I believe)? How can one set, say, the Tanya’s kabbalah as the *keystone* of one’s theory without in the same movement setting ShA HaRav as the keystone of one’s practice? As Prof. Brill said, “If one accepts the kabbalah as a solution, then one is Haredi, and if one treats it as naturalistic metaphor, then one is quite liberal.”</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Joebug		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/12/prof-tamar-ross-on-revelation-and-biblical-criticism/#comment-7857</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joebug]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2013 15:52:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6030#comment-7857</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I am still not quite clear which metaphysical assumptions Prof Ross finds untenable in normative Judaism - that God can speak to man - that miracles could happen - they are of course untenable to metaphysical materialists - but otherwise untenable? There is a strong argument that historical and sociological analysis show aspects of the particular traditional narrative in OJ to be untenable, but that&#039;s not quite the same as suggesting God&#039;s communication or miracles cannot happen. It would still be interesting to know where Prof Ross stands.

Current secular discourse not only severely critiques religion on materialist grounds, but just as much on ethical grounds. Prof Ross states:

&quot;Even passages in the Torah which appear problematic to us today, and the historical context which triggers our discontent and moves us to seek new interpretations, are part of that process.&quot; So your language game can change...but surely it does so based on external factors.

And in her constructivist Wittgensteinian theory - I choose the language game I like because I was born in to it or acculturated in to it. Fine, if we can alll agree on ethics roughly as motherhood and apple pie.
However, the secular discourse says religion is. for example, anti-gay, a huge ethics violation. If we change our language game based on external factors, such as the gay right movement, or the word is not flat movement, or slavery for black people is wrong movement, or feminist movement, then why think that the original game was ethical or worth something? Put it another way, why would God structure a world with ongoing revelation like that? Why not just start with the good ethics to begin with? Well you might say that Rambam suggests we need time to acculturate to good ethics...but you would have a hard time convincing anyone I fear...The problem is that Prof Ross&#039;s position leads back to Prof Marc Shapiro characterization of the unreconstructed traditional OJ worldview re history, evolution etc as not fundamentalist but obscurantist.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I am still not quite clear which metaphysical assumptions Prof Ross finds untenable in normative Judaism &#8211; that God can speak to man &#8211; that miracles could happen &#8211; they are of course untenable to metaphysical materialists &#8211; but otherwise untenable? There is a strong argument that historical and sociological analysis show aspects of the particular traditional narrative in OJ to be untenable, but that&#8217;s not quite the same as suggesting God&#8217;s communication or miracles cannot happen. It would still be interesting to know where Prof Ross stands.</p>
<p>Current secular discourse not only severely critiques religion on materialist grounds, but just as much on ethical grounds. Prof Ross states:</p>
<p>&#8220;Even passages in the Torah which appear problematic to us today, and the historical context which triggers our discontent and moves us to seek new interpretations, are part of that process.&#8221; So your language game can change&#8230;but surely it does so based on external factors.</p>
<p>And in her constructivist Wittgensteinian theory &#8211; I choose the language game I like because I was born in to it or acculturated in to it. Fine, if we can alll agree on ethics roughly as motherhood and apple pie.<br />
However, the secular discourse says religion is. for example, anti-gay, a huge ethics violation. If we change our language game based on external factors, such as the gay right movement, or the word is not flat movement, or slavery for black people is wrong movement, or feminist movement, then why think that the original game was ethical or worth something? Put it another way, why would God structure a world with ongoing revelation like that? Why not just start with the good ethics to begin with? Well you might say that Rambam suggests we need time to acculturate to good ethics&#8230;but you would have a hard time convincing anyone I fear&#8230;The problem is that Prof Ross&#8217;s position leads back to Prof Marc Shapiro characterization of the unreconstructed traditional OJ worldview re history, evolution etc as not fundamentalist but obscurantist.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/12/prof-tamar-ross-on-revelation-and-biblical-criticism/#comment-7854</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2013 13:02:40 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6030#comment-7854</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This comment was written by a local attorney very active in the Orthodox community. He sent it to me by email.

What caught my eye, though, and solidified my understanding of what Dr. Ross was truly saying mitzido/mitzideinu, was relatively late in the interview: Question 16 (emphasis, my own).
My view of God’s “speech” is rather as illocutionary acts that trigger humans to “hear” a message, and identify this as divine revelation.  The Torah surely records accounts of people believing that they had revelatory experiences, but its ultimate authority is grounded on the form of life that developed in the wake of such experiences and the strength of its grip upon us. 
This line of thought seems to be very closely aligned to the key thesis of T.M. Lurhmann’s “When God Talks Back”, describing the relationship experienced by Fundamentalist Christians (David recommended it to me).  Lurhmann observes that Fundamentalist Christians seek to train themselves to suppress the inherent “privacy” of one’s own brain function and thoughts in a manner that can permits one share his or her thoughts with the voice of the Divine.  (Asking God what I should wear this morning seems vulgar to me, but this is the result of the intimacy that they believe they create.)   

Like Lurhmann, Ross seems to be saying (i) revelation is a human experience, and (ii) she’s remaining neutral/positive as to whether it is a true experience or mere delusion.  (Sensing the attack from the hard secular left, Lurhmann devotes a full chapter defending fundamentalists as not mentally ill).

That, by the way, is what troubles me by what I believe is a muddled thesis – seeking to keep her feet in too many yards at the same time, expending too much effort in claiming that she does not attack the prime value of Torah, while undermining its divinity (even inspirational divinity) too much.
You had it right on the Shakespeare question:  She may deny it strongly, but there is simply no way to argue her thesis and defend Torah as anything other than one of many sources of wisdom that are claimed to be divinely inspired.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This comment was written by a local attorney very active in the Orthodox community. He sent it to me by email.</p>
<p>What caught my eye, though, and solidified my understanding of what Dr. Ross was truly saying mitzido/mitzideinu, was relatively late in the interview: Question 16 (emphasis, my own).<br />
My view of God’s “speech” is rather as illocutionary acts that trigger humans to “hear” a message, and identify this as divine revelation.  The Torah surely records accounts of people believing that they had revelatory experiences, but its ultimate authority is grounded on the form of life that developed in the wake of such experiences and the strength of its grip upon us.<br />
This line of thought seems to be very closely aligned to the key thesis of T.M. Lurhmann’s “When God Talks Back”, describing the relationship experienced by Fundamentalist Christians (David recommended it to me).  Lurhmann observes that Fundamentalist Christians seek to train themselves to suppress the inherent “privacy” of one’s own brain function and thoughts in a manner that can permits one share his or her thoughts with the voice of the Divine.  (Asking God what I should wear this morning seems vulgar to me, but this is the result of the intimacy that they believe they create.)   </p>
<p>Like Lurhmann, Ross seems to be saying (i) revelation is a human experience, and (ii) she’s remaining neutral/positive as to whether it is a true experience or mere delusion.  (Sensing the attack from the hard secular left, Lurhmann devotes a full chapter defending fundamentalists as not mentally ill).</p>
<p>That, by the way, is what troubles me by what I believe is a muddled thesis – seeking to keep her feet in too many yards at the same time, expending too much effort in claiming that she does not attack the prime value of Torah, while undermining its divinity (even inspirational divinity) too much.<br />
You had it right on the Shakespeare question:  She may deny it strongly, but there is simply no way to argue her thesis and defend Torah as anything other than one of many sources of wisdom that are claimed to be divinely inspired.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Dan Friedman		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/12/prof-tamar-ross-on-revelation-and-biblical-criticism/#comment-7850</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dan Friedman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2013 14:44:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6030#comment-7850</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I got lost in the pseudo-academic argot Tamar Ross employs. It&#039;s just a way  to make straight answers seem obscure. Hiding behind it all, I&#039;m afraid, is a women who has much more to contribute to plain-vanilla Jewish liberalism than to Torah-true Judaism. Much more.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I got lost in the pseudo-academic argot Tamar Ross employs. It&#8217;s just a way  to make straight answers seem obscure. Hiding behind it all, I&#8217;m afraid, is a women who has much more to contribute to plain-vanilla Jewish liberalism than to Torah-true Judaism. Much more.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: evanstonjew		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/12/prof-tamar-ross-on-revelation-and-biblical-criticism/#comment-7848</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[evanstonjew]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2013 02:32:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6030#comment-7848</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[There is a conflict between the way the world is and the way we need  it to be to live an Orthodox life without feeling any conflict. What to do? I would say live in two worlds, the modern world and the pre- enlightenment rabbinic world, but don’t mix them up or try to integrate them. Torah u madah, hold the u. It’s something like having  a relationship with a significant other in a different city. We travel back and forth…emails, Skype, airplanes. Or maybe it’s like having a house in Evanston  and a pied a’ terre in Jerusalem. No, no says Dr. Ross, it’s too as iffy, you still experience the conflict of living inside and outside a world, the transportation costs are too high so to speak. But no problem, because tzimtzum is a metaphor and ain od milvado sub specie aeternitatis, it’s not really true we are moving from one world to the other. We literally live in both Evanston and Jerusalem at the same time. Both Northwestern and the Hebrew U. are one and the same…And if reality appears a bit recalcitrant, if the natives speak English or Hebrew but not both, do not fret. Knowing the secret that what exists in front of your eyes is not, and what is hidden is apparent, we can adopt a more ironic approach to reinterpreting everything, and if we fail maybe the next generation will help us see that all is one. Elliot Wolfson pushes this line in his reading of the last Lubavitcher Rebbe’s ouvere. 
Prof. Ross is running a series of different philosophical ideas simultaneously, the kabbalah’s perspectivism is married to language game jargon and then given an evolutionary spin in the event we are stuck in a particularly recalcitrant form of life. But behind all this is I think a rather simple idea, something like reflective equilibrium. We have intuitions about particular cases, and we try to patch together an overriding picture that will enable us to have these convictions. Hopefully as these ideas are developed there will be a convincing picture that will clarify our frequently conflicting intuitions. As of now I think Josh Stadlan’s approach of different rules of inference etc for religious and secular worlds is more promising.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There is a conflict between the way the world is and the way we need  it to be to live an Orthodox life without feeling any conflict. What to do? I would say live in two worlds, the modern world and the pre- enlightenment rabbinic world, but don’t mix them up or try to integrate them. Torah u madah, hold the u. It’s something like having  a relationship with a significant other in a different city. We travel back and forth…emails, Skype, airplanes. Or maybe it’s like having a house in Evanston  and a pied a’ terre in Jerusalem. No, no says Dr. Ross, it’s too as iffy, you still experience the conflict of living inside and outside a world, the transportation costs are too high so to speak. But no problem, because tzimtzum is a metaphor and ain od milvado sub specie aeternitatis, it’s not really true we are moving from one world to the other. We literally live in both Evanston and Jerusalem at the same time. Both Northwestern and the Hebrew U. are one and the same…And if reality appears a bit recalcitrant, if the natives speak English or Hebrew but not both, do not fret. Knowing the secret that what exists in front of your eyes is not, and what is hidden is apparent, we can adopt a more ironic approach to reinterpreting everything, and if we fail maybe the next generation will help us see that all is one. Elliot Wolfson pushes this line in his reading of the last Lubavitcher Rebbe’s ouvere.<br />
Prof. Ross is running a series of different philosophical ideas simultaneously, the kabbalah’s perspectivism is married to language game jargon and then given an evolutionary spin in the event we are stuck in a particularly recalcitrant form of life. But behind all this is I think a rather simple idea, something like reflective equilibrium. We have intuitions about particular cases, and we try to patch together an overriding picture that will enable us to have these convictions. Hopefully as these ideas are developed there will be a convincing picture that will clarify our frequently conflicting intuitions. As of now I think Josh Stadlan’s approach of different rules of inference etc for religious and secular worlds is more promising.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: SK		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/12/prof-tamar-ross-on-revelation-and-biblical-criticism/#comment-7845</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[SK]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2013 22:31:51 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6030#comment-7845</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As someone trying to be a baal teshuva, AS&#039;s above criticism of Ross rings incredibly true, specifically the last paragraph.  Someone not raised in full immersion in an observant Jewish atmosphere could never succeed in applying Ross&#039; theory.  It relies on too delicate a foundation for a baal teshuva to change his pre-Orthodox personal convictions regarding ethical behavior.  A question: are there any seriously Orthopractic Jews who were not raised in a rich Jewish environment to serve as the foundation of their lifestyle, given the absence of a metaphysical foundation?  My guess is there are very, very few.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As someone trying to be a baal teshuva, AS&#8217;s above criticism of Ross rings incredibly true, specifically the last paragraph.  Someone not raised in full immersion in an observant Jewish atmosphere could never succeed in applying Ross&#8217; theory.  It relies on too delicate a foundation for a baal teshuva to change his pre-Orthodox personal convictions regarding ethical behavior.  A question: are there any seriously Orthopractic Jews who were not raised in a rich Jewish environment to serve as the foundation of their lifestyle, given the absence of a metaphysical foundation?  My guess is there are very, very few.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: alexanderjtsykin		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/12/prof-tamar-ross-on-revelation-and-biblical-criticism/#comment-7844</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[alexanderjtsykin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2013 19:47:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6030#comment-7844</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Ross claims her approach is based on &quot;tradiional sources.&quot; I think that it is fact not so. For a start, everybody quoted was a very later thinker. This is likely because she couldn&#039;t find anything to source among more classic sources of Jewish thought. Secondly, she doesn&#039;t seem to acknowledge that an aweful lot of the thought of the thinkers she claims to base her own theories on is itself based on the idea of Sinnaitic revelation. I don&#039;t think that you can eliminate this element from the thinking of people like Rav Kook and have the rest stand on its own, because for them the authority of Torah is dependent on its status as direct divine revelaiton and communication. Without that, their broader philosophical systems would collapse. This is especially true because they are kabbalistic thinkers and kabbalists are far more revelation focused than rationalist thinkers. My feeling is that in her theory the given was tradition and biblical criticism. Because Sinnaitic revelation is not a given for her it falls away. However, one could just as easily point out that Sinnaitic revelation is central to tradition (it&#039;s one of the few points in Jewish theology including divine omniscience which before the twentieth century was really never the subject of debate) and therefore her two givens are inherently contradictory.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ross claims her approach is based on &#8220;tradiional sources.&#8221; I think that it is fact not so. For a start, everybody quoted was a very later thinker. This is likely because she couldn&#8217;t find anything to source among more classic sources of Jewish thought. Secondly, she doesn&#8217;t seem to acknowledge that an aweful lot of the thought of the thinkers she claims to base her own theories on is itself based on the idea of Sinnaitic revelation. I don&#8217;t think that you can eliminate this element from the thinking of people like Rav Kook and have the rest stand on its own, because for them the authority of Torah is dependent on its status as direct divine revelaiton and communication. Without that, their broader philosophical systems would collapse. This is especially true because they are kabbalistic thinkers and kabbalists are far more revelation focused than rationalist thinkers. My feeling is that in her theory the given was tradition and biblical criticism. Because Sinnaitic revelation is not a given for her it falls away. However, one could just as easily point out that Sinnaitic revelation is central to tradition (it&#8217;s one of the few points in Jewish theology including divine omniscience which before the twentieth century was really never the subject of debate) and therefore her two givens are inherently contradictory.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/12/prof-tamar-ross-on-revelation-and-biblical-criticism/#comment-7841</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2013 10:52:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6030#comment-7841</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Prof. Ross&#039;s approach treads along the same fault line that either does or does not isolate ethics from metaethics. If we approach a religion&#039;s theory of revelation as its metatheory, then the question is whether the metatheroy is normatively neutral. In adopting a constructivist metatheory Ross is very much lined up with Habermas and others, in which case religious claims cannot be truth functional just like descriptive claims. Although I haven&#039;t done so, I think you plug in a constructivist metatheory of religion into virtually any metaethical theory that attempts to understand the function of moral claims absent any metaphysical apparatus. Then, like Habermas, you can claim that saying &quot;X is the halakhicly sanctioned thing to do&quot; is a species of validity claim, not a claim to truth because the sentence &quot;it is true that X is the halakhicly sanctioned thing to do&quot; has not added anything to the first statement.

This raises a fair number of questions such as religion has apparently become a funny kind of ethics in which the test of validity is not universality, but in a (practical) religious claim standing in some particular--nearly impossible to specify--inferential relationship to other practical statements. In which case, why not get rid of the funny ethics and stick with ethics. To which the answer is something along the lines of the ineligibility of the form of life into which we were born. Ok, but now you still want to specify how ethical claims could ever stand in a sufficient inferential relation to religious claims such that ethics-the universal has any type of influence on religion, the particular or visa-versa.

Or, in other words, you may have solved the problem that naturalist descriptions of religion do not have to result in a reflexive anti-realsim, and can remain cognitive, but you have created a practical problem because an agent (who, unlike the ideal presented is not simply someone emerging wholly from a religious tradition, but the product of a modern discourse in which religion and ethics are already seen as being in tension) seeking to act in a case where religion and ethics make competing validity claims has no recourse to a religious metatheory that gives a certain prima facie precedence to religious claims. All she can do is to ask which system is more basic to her identity as a practical agent -and then with an ironic chuckle say &quot;oops, it looks like I&#039;ve reached the point in this language game where I don&#039;t really know how to &#039;go on&#039;; hopefully history sorts things out.&quot;]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Prof. Ross&#8217;s approach treads along the same fault line that either does or does not isolate ethics from metaethics. If we approach a religion&#8217;s theory of revelation as its metatheory, then the question is whether the metatheroy is normatively neutral. In adopting a constructivist metatheory Ross is very much lined up with Habermas and others, in which case religious claims cannot be truth functional just like descriptive claims. Although I haven&#8217;t done so, I think you plug in a constructivist metatheory of religion into virtually any metaethical theory that attempts to understand the function of moral claims absent any metaphysical apparatus. Then, like Habermas, you can claim that saying &#8220;X is the halakhicly sanctioned thing to do&#8221; is a species of validity claim, not a claim to truth because the sentence &#8220;it is true that X is the halakhicly sanctioned thing to do&#8221; has not added anything to the first statement.</p>
<p>This raises a fair number of questions such as religion has apparently become a funny kind of ethics in which the test of validity is not universality, but in a (practical) religious claim standing in some particular&#8211;nearly impossible to specify&#8211;inferential relationship to other practical statements. In which case, why not get rid of the funny ethics and stick with ethics. To which the answer is something along the lines of the ineligibility of the form of life into which we were born. Ok, but now you still want to specify how ethical claims could ever stand in a sufficient inferential relation to religious claims such that ethics-the universal has any type of influence on religion, the particular or visa-versa.</p>
<p>Or, in other words, you may have solved the problem that naturalist descriptions of religion do not have to result in a reflexive anti-realsim, and can remain cognitive, but you have created a practical problem because an agent (who, unlike the ideal presented is not simply someone emerging wholly from a religious tradition, but the product of a modern discourse in which religion and ethics are already seen as being in tension) seeking to act in a case where religion and ethics make competing validity claims has no recourse to a religious metatheory that gives a certain prima facie precedence to religious claims. All she can do is to ask which system is more basic to her identity as a practical agent -and then with an ironic chuckle say &#8220;oops, it looks like I&#8217;ve reached the point in this language game where I don&#8217;t really know how to &#8216;go on&#8217;; hopefully history sorts things out.&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Shlomo		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/12/prof-tamar-ross-on-revelation-and-biblical-criticism/#comment-7840</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shlomo]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2013 08:26:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6030#comment-7840</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Whether or not Ross&#039;s ideas are correct, if they can only be expressed in such an impenetrable manner, they will never gain a significant following in the Jewish community.

[site editor note- Shlomo- read the new rule. No more mallinator accounts. Please get a verifyable account or I will have to install a sign-in.]]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Whether or not Ross&#8217;s ideas are correct, if they can only be expressed in such an impenetrable manner, they will never gain a significant following in the Jewish community.</p>
<p>[site editor note- Shlomo- read the new rule. No more mallinator accounts. Please get a verifyable account or I will have to install a sign-in.]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/12/prof-tamar-ross-on-revelation-and-biblical-criticism/#comment-7839</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2013 05:15:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6030#comment-7839</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/12/prof-tamar-ross-on-revelation-and-biblical-criticism/#comment-7838&quot;&gt;Shaya&lt;/a&gt;.

That was question one. i place that first. How do we deal with all this new data that contradicts the traditional understanding on history, chronology, province, and text? Answer: We need a new theory of revelation that can deal with the new data. 
The question assumes there is lots of this &quot;stuff&quot; out there that is historically true and without answers. 
In general, I cannot answer for her, but your question seems straightforward.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/12/prof-tamar-ross-on-revelation-and-biblical-criticism/#comment-7838">Shaya</a>.</p>
<p>That was question one. i place that first. How do we deal with all this new data that contradicts the traditional understanding on history, chronology, province, and text? Answer: We need a new theory of revelation that can deal with the new data.<br />
The question assumes there is lots of this &#8220;stuff&#8221; out there that is historically true and without answers.<br />
In general, I cannot answer for her, but your question seems straightforward.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
