<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: YCT Graduation Speech-Where is the Promised Land?	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2011 18:24:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: chakira		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3200</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[chakira]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2011 02:23:36 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3679#comment-3200</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3195&quot;&gt;tzvee&lt;/a&gt;.

Crisis rhetoric should be reserved for crises. I thought this was obvious and simple, but it turns out not to be. A crisis is defined as an internal contradiction in one way of viewing the world, one form of spirit, where it exhausts its own claims to totality. Let&#039;s contrast a crisis with a non crisis to see how this works. One classical idea of a crisis is the crisis of the French revolution. According to this view, the sycophantic kowtowing of the courtly class led to the demise of the very sovereign who formed the center of their cosmic pageantry. Ultimately the pageant is aporetic, as to debase myself before the king requires for there to be a substantial notion of self that is there to be annihilated.  So in the classical conception of crisis articulated in German idealism, Kant &quot;fulfills&quot; the French Revolution. That is, the philosophical notion of self legislating and morally autonomous subjectivity performatively enacts the subject required by the kabuki dance of Louis XVI. So there is an aporia immanent to one conception of the world-- it goes off the reservation precisely because it can fulfill almost every claim, but not the claim to totality. A crisis is related to what philosophers call &quot;having the world in view&quot; and is produced when we are blindsided by whatever schema we use to see the whole. 
Now let&#039;s take another crisis, the crisis of feminism, and give it a similar dialectical treatment. The crisis of feminism could be construed as historically having its roots within a vision of domesticity which prized certain forms of harmony, yet begged the question of the very domination used to produce said harmony. &quot;One vote per household&quot; actually sounds like a nice idea, until we realize that political personhood has the potential to fracture the world of the household and expose the domination implicit in its formation. Karl Marx famously pointed to the criticism of the &quot;Holy Family&quot; as stemming from the fact that it was holy-- secularization. Dialectical Materialism, although the latter term is a bugbear in this context, seeks to critique the family itself. The very consummation of the household as a political unit worthy of the harmony which makes household representation seemingly possible as an ideal at the same time exposes the political disenfranchisement of the subsumed political non people within the household. In any case, this is one possible trajectory, others could focus on the struggle with slavery or the high moral claims of protestants in the US which lead to an immanent need for a reevaluation of the political personhood of the female sex. When suffrage is granted, the violent underpinnings of disenfranchisement are exposed like the architecture Bataille thought we best see when its on fire. However, and this is where we LEARN something, now we know about this primordial scene of violence and we subsume it into the less explicitly violent world of the political. The agonal struggle of the household is transmuted and raised into a political struggle which may lack none of the naked jostling of its predeccesor while being a little less horrible and a little farther from home.
In any case, lets now take a world something like ours in which, as I said, a woman can be a corporate lawyer or even a Hedge fund manager. What are the relevant distinctions at work in our current historical crisis? Well we could limn it six different ways. Capital vs. labor is coming back in vogue (for a classic Marxist feel). We could frame the aporias of the political against representative democracy as Carl Schmitt attempted to do-- still works. We could say that our age is one of the technologization and deauthenticization and deracination of the world, something like Heidegger&#039;s vision of Gestell and the emergency of being in the time of the world picture. The point of these schemas is not that they are perfect or all encompassing, but they show us the constitutive blind spots of our current schemas. In representative democracy we have the issue of the exception. In technological society we have an obscuring of our very (human) being by contrivances meant to facilitate it. In valuing money as an arbiter of all else, we have lost sight of the normative, emotional and cognitive determinations that ultimately underpin its use. Whatever. 
The relevant distinction is not, female endocrinologist (taking time off for the kids) vs. male Cardiologist (no shabbos because he got a sweet deal from Columbia when who moved from NYU) who is now going to belt out Kesser (yes, its authentic nusach sefard, don&#039;t mess!) while she cannot even announce the Stein Bat Mitzvah. This is a slight inequality, not a crisis.
In articulating our criteria for crisis, we focused on its bringing into view the blind spots of an overarching conceptual schema. Lets talk about this case. Does it come close to doing that? Well, maybe if you never heard a geshmake Kesser before. But in all seriousness, for most people the deflationary and utterly commonsensical approach is to say that this is a pragmatic game. In the game of Bananagrams you will play in two hours, you form words from a Banana pouch. The game of shabbos prohibits you from playing it on the internet. Meanwhile the game of shul requires the pageantry of men and the relegation of women to an ancillary role they do not normally play in society. Comparing this to a drama is apt, if we remember that dramas often contain powerful kernels of our shared humanity. In other words, shul is a normative vision, but an attenuated and staged one. We can approach the world with a kind of &quot;as if&quot;-- as if words have perlocutionary and magical value or as if women and men aren&#039;t equal. For Durkheimians who come to schmooze, the latter is not the case (if you hang out with the right women who can hold court at a kiddush better than the wallflowers who comment on blogs). But even if you agree to some degree with the normative vision in shul, you return to your workaday life or your life of leisure enriched and enhanced by the experience, but with the world fundamentally unchanged. Perhaps what emerges from this is that cultural institutions are about the deferral of problems and the creation of weak normative frameworks to keep us outside the sturm und drang of historical spiritual upheaval (the reason why a permanent revolution is a contradiction) and to deaden our lives with the routinization which Max Scheler highlights as a hallmark of advanced age and a decline of world openness. Like any dramaturgy, shul can play at exciting struggles, political intrigue or messianic fervor. The point of this implicit conservatism is to moor us in a world of changing values with a knowingly false vision of constant and unchanging ones.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3195">tzvee</a>.</p>
<p>Crisis rhetoric should be reserved for crises. I thought this was obvious and simple, but it turns out not to be. A crisis is defined as an internal contradiction in one way of viewing the world, one form of spirit, where it exhausts its own claims to totality. Let&#8217;s contrast a crisis with a non crisis to see how this works. One classical idea of a crisis is the crisis of the French revolution. According to this view, the sycophantic kowtowing of the courtly class led to the demise of the very sovereign who formed the center of their cosmic pageantry. Ultimately the pageant is aporetic, as to debase myself before the king requires for there to be a substantial notion of self that is there to be annihilated.  So in the classical conception of crisis articulated in German idealism, Kant &#8220;fulfills&#8221; the French Revolution. That is, the philosophical notion of self legislating and morally autonomous subjectivity performatively enacts the subject required by the kabuki dance of Louis XVI. So there is an aporia immanent to one conception of the world&#8211; it goes off the reservation precisely because it can fulfill almost every claim, but not the claim to totality. A crisis is related to what philosophers call &#8220;having the world in view&#8221; and is produced when we are blindsided by whatever schema we use to see the whole.<br />
Now let&#8217;s take another crisis, the crisis of feminism, and give it a similar dialectical treatment. The crisis of feminism could be construed as historically having its roots within a vision of domesticity which prized certain forms of harmony, yet begged the question of the very domination used to produce said harmony. &#8220;One vote per household&#8221; actually sounds like a nice idea, until we realize that political personhood has the potential to fracture the world of the household and expose the domination implicit in its formation. Karl Marx famously pointed to the criticism of the &#8220;Holy Family&#8221; as stemming from the fact that it was holy&#8211; secularization. Dialectical Materialism, although the latter term is a bugbear in this context, seeks to critique the family itself. The very consummation of the household as a political unit worthy of the harmony which makes household representation seemingly possible as an ideal at the same time exposes the political disenfranchisement of the subsumed political non people within the household. In any case, this is one possible trajectory, others could focus on the struggle with slavery or the high moral claims of protestants in the US which lead to an immanent need for a reevaluation of the political personhood of the female sex. When suffrage is granted, the violent underpinnings of disenfranchisement are exposed like the architecture Bataille thought we best see when its on fire. However, and this is where we LEARN something, now we know about this primordial scene of violence and we subsume it into the less explicitly violent world of the political. The agonal struggle of the household is transmuted and raised into a political struggle which may lack none of the naked jostling of its predeccesor while being a little less horrible and a little farther from home.<br />
In any case, lets now take a world something like ours in which, as I said, a woman can be a corporate lawyer or even a Hedge fund manager. What are the relevant distinctions at work in our current historical crisis? Well we could limn it six different ways. Capital vs. labor is coming back in vogue (for a classic Marxist feel). We could frame the aporias of the political against representative democracy as Carl Schmitt attempted to do&#8211; still works. We could say that our age is one of the technologization and deauthenticization and deracination of the world, something like Heidegger&#8217;s vision of Gestell and the emergency of being in the time of the world picture. The point of these schemas is not that they are perfect or all encompassing, but they show us the constitutive blind spots of our current schemas. In representative democracy we have the issue of the exception. In technological society we have an obscuring of our very (human) being by contrivances meant to facilitate it. In valuing money as an arbiter of all else, we have lost sight of the normative, emotional and cognitive determinations that ultimately underpin its use. Whatever.<br />
The relevant distinction is not, female endocrinologist (taking time off for the kids) vs. male Cardiologist (no shabbos because he got a sweet deal from Columbia when who moved from NYU) who is now going to belt out Kesser (yes, its authentic nusach sefard, don&#8217;t mess!) while she cannot even announce the Stein Bat Mitzvah. This is a slight inequality, not a crisis.<br />
In articulating our criteria for crisis, we focused on its bringing into view the blind spots of an overarching conceptual schema. Lets talk about this case. Does it come close to doing that? Well, maybe if you never heard a geshmake Kesser before. But in all seriousness, for most people the deflationary and utterly commonsensical approach is to say that this is a pragmatic game. In the game of Bananagrams you will play in two hours, you form words from a Banana pouch. The game of shabbos prohibits you from playing it on the internet. Meanwhile the game of shul requires the pageantry of men and the relegation of women to an ancillary role they do not normally play in society. Comparing this to a drama is apt, if we remember that dramas often contain powerful kernels of our shared humanity. In other words, shul is a normative vision, but an attenuated and staged one. We can approach the world with a kind of &#8220;as if&#8221;&#8211; as if words have perlocutionary and magical value or as if women and men aren&#8217;t equal. For Durkheimians who come to schmooze, the latter is not the case (if you hang out with the right women who can hold court at a kiddush better than the wallflowers who comment on blogs). But even if you agree to some degree with the normative vision in shul, you return to your workaday life or your life of leisure enriched and enhanced by the experience, but with the world fundamentally unchanged. Perhaps what emerges from this is that cultural institutions are about the deferral of problems and the creation of weak normative frameworks to keep us outside the sturm und drang of historical spiritual upheaval (the reason why a permanent revolution is a contradiction) and to deaden our lives with the routinization which Max Scheler highlights as a hallmark of advanced age and a decline of world openness. Like any dramaturgy, shul can play at exciting struggles, political intrigue or messianic fervor. The point of this implicit conservatism is to moor us in a world of changing values with a knowingly false vision of constant and unchanging ones.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3199</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2011 01:49:57 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3679#comment-3199</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3198&quot;&gt;avakesh&lt;/a&gt;.

avakesh- if you have them handy, can you cite them.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3198">avakesh</a>.</p>
<p>avakesh- if you have them handy, can you cite them.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: avakesh		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3198</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[avakesh]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2011 01:48:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3679#comment-3198</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I am overwhelmed by the sheer erudition of responses. Thank you. Let me just reference R. HIRSCH to Genesis 12:8 and 20:1]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I am overwhelmed by the sheer erudition of responses. Thank you. Let me just reference R. HIRSCH to Genesis 12:8 and 20:1</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Yehuda		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3197</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Yehuda]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2011 01:05:12 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3679#comment-3197</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[AS&#039;s response was devastating and totally accurate except for one thing --replace &quot;reasonably knowledgeable &quot; with &quot;minimally knowledgeable.&quot;  But I think people should be fairer to Rabbi Linzer and YCT.  A lot (not all) of the people they hope to minister to are people to whom these questions and issues are relevant and even pressing IF they are to be religious at all (e.g. college students who could be involved or could drop out of religion altogether depending on their influences on campus).  So while Rabbi Linzer&#039;s speech may be laughable to some, it reflects that YCT is actually doing an important service to God and B&#039;nai Yisrael by reaching out to the marginally committed.

[siteowner comment- please use real email address next time.]]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>AS&#8217;s response was devastating and totally accurate except for one thing &#8211;replace &#8220;reasonably knowledgeable &#8221; with &#8220;minimally knowledgeable.&#8221;  But I think people should be fairer to Rabbi Linzer and YCT.  A lot (not all) of the people they hope to minister to are people to whom these questions and issues are relevant and even pressing IF they are to be religious at all (e.g. college students who could be involved or could drop out of religion altogether depending on their influences on campus).  So while Rabbi Linzer&#8217;s speech may be laughable to some, it reflects that YCT is actually doing an important service to God and B&#8217;nai Yisrael by reaching out to the marginally committed.</p>
<p>[siteowner comment- please use real email address next time.]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: tzvee		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3195</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tzvee]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2011 00:20:39 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3679#comment-3195</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[chakira says, &quot;So what happens 40 minutes a week in shul is sort of ancillary. So there is no “crisis” of feminism, even if there is a problem.&quot; What do you mean, &quot;sort of ancillary&quot;? Is the definition that in our tribe women sit in the back or is that just a bit of meaningless (ancillary) theater? If the latter, then how sad a drama we play out. If the former, then well and good. You are in or out, your choice. Unless you believe that tribal life is God-given and obligatory.. Do you? Yes or no?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>chakira says, &#8220;So what happens 40 minutes a week in shul is sort of ancillary. So there is no “crisis” of feminism, even if there is a problem.&#8221; What do you mean, &#8220;sort of ancillary&#8221;? Is the definition that in our tribe women sit in the back or is that just a bit of meaningless (ancillary) theater? If the latter, then how sad a drama we play out. If the former, then well and good. You are in or out, your choice. Unless you believe that tribal life is God-given and obligatory.. Do you? Yes or no?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3188</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2011 00:32:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3679#comment-3188</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Jon, I have no idea where you see either venom or cynicism in my remarks.  The view I expressed is a general point how to have a happy and active secular and Torah intellectual life.  I am not fed up with MO in suburbia, right or left. I did not say a bad word about Rabbi Linzer or Hartman or Green. In my book they are important Jewish thinkers and I try to read and understand what they have to say. To be honest the question of how to give more substance to MO is not high on my Jewdar screen. My main interests are Israeli politics, the disappearance of the Diaspora, various philosophical issues, gossip and social
 commentary, preferably if they have a humorous aspect.  I have this anarchist idea that all the different stripes are experiments in Jewish life, and everything else equal I am more than happy to say a good word for most groups and I have. I am on good terms with
 many different bloggers from hyper chasidish and litvish to farbissen atheists. I have also spoken out on behalf of liberal-leftist values on right wing proto fascist blogs. I might not be cutting edge, the Holocaust is still on my mind as are the great books produced in the century before the Holocaust.  Gehlen, Schmitt,(see Taubes on Paul), Heidegger and Deluze might indeed be the future of Jewish thought , and I would have a difficult time getting on with such a program. But  that is another sin entirely.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Jon, I have no idea where you see either venom or cynicism in my remarks.  The view I expressed is a general point how to have a happy and active secular and Torah intellectual life.  I am not fed up with MO in suburbia, right or left. I did not say a bad word about Rabbi Linzer or Hartman or Green. In my book they are important Jewish thinkers and I try to read and understand what they have to say. To be honest the question of how to give more substance to MO is not high on my Jewdar screen. My main interests are Israeli politics, the disappearance of the Diaspora, various philosophical issues, gossip and social<br />
 commentary, preferably if they have a humorous aspect.  I have this anarchist idea that all the different stripes are experiments in Jewish life, and everything else equal I am more than happy to say a good word for most groups and I have. I am on good terms with<br />
 many different bloggers from hyper chasidish and litvish to farbissen atheists. I have also spoken out on behalf of liberal-leftist values on right wing proto fascist blogs. I might not be cutting edge, the Holocaust is still on my mind as are the great books produced in the century before the Holocaust.  Gehlen, Schmitt,(see Taubes on Paul), Heidegger and Deluze might indeed be the future of Jewish thought , and I would have a difficult time getting on with such a program. But  that is another sin entirely.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: chakira		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3185</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[chakira]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2011 03:33:05 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3679#comment-3185</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3184&quot;&gt;Jon&lt;/a&gt;.

I honestly did not write anything cynical. I was just asking about the place of the crisis rhetoric in MO since it seems irrelevant. I was not arguing one way or the other about if it should be there, just wondering why it is there, and what it does. Please read the posts again.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3184">Jon</a>.</p>
<p>I honestly did not write anything cynical. I was just asking about the place of the crisis rhetoric in MO since it seems irrelevant. I was not arguing one way or the other about if it should be there, just wondering why it is there, and what it does. Please read the posts again.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Jon		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3183</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jon]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2011 03:22:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3679#comment-3183</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3177&quot;&gt;IH&lt;/a&gt;.

IH: Literally could not have put it more effectively myself.

AS, Chakira, EJ: I am overwhelmed by the venom of your cynicism. Up until now I didn’t understand what people meant when they referred to cynicism as a negative trait, but you learn something new every day, I suppose. I guess this is what my friends feel like when they’re listening to me.

We got it. You’re all fed up with the pettiness of Jewish politics, the aggrandizement of the alleged suburban struggle, the transformation of Judaism into a psychological commodity. So am I. So where’s the constructive aspect of your criticism?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3177">IH</a>.</p>
<p>IH: Literally could not have put it more effectively myself.</p>
<p>AS, Chakira, EJ: I am overwhelmed by the venom of your cynicism. Up until now I didn’t understand what people meant when they referred to cynicism as a negative trait, but you learn something new every day, I suppose. I guess this is what my friends feel like when they’re listening to me.</p>
<p>We got it. You’re all fed up with the pettiness of Jewish politics, the aggrandizement of the alleged suburban struggle, the transformation of Judaism into a psychological commodity. So am I. So where’s the constructive aspect of your criticism?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Nechama		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3182</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nechama]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2011 02:04:51 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3679#comment-3182</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[AS: Brilliant.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>AS: Brilliant.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: David Corwin		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3180</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[David Corwin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2011 21:48:29 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3679#comment-3180</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3171&quot;&gt;ej&lt;/a&gt;.

In struggling on a math problem, even if you don&#039;t solve the problem, mathematicians widely agree that you yourself gain something by having struggled. (Maybe I&#039;m guilty of dragging the analogy too far, but it could have broader implications.)]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3171">ej</a>.</p>
<p>In struggling on a math problem, even if you don&#8217;t solve the problem, mathematicians widely agree that you yourself gain something by having struggled. (Maybe I&#8217;m guilty of dragging the analogy too far, but it could have broader implications.)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: chakira		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3179</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[chakira]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2011 20:00:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3679#comment-3179</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3178&quot;&gt;AS&lt;/a&gt;.

How about continuing with the theme of &quot;vayhi binosah aron?&quot;-- Sometimes you need to cut and paste a bit in order to make up an appealing version of the Torah.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3178">AS</a>.</p>
<p>How about continuing with the theme of &#8220;vayhi binosah aron?&#8221;&#8211; Sometimes you need to cut and paste a bit in order to make up an appealing version of the Torah.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3178</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2011 19:52:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3679#comment-3178</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3177&quot;&gt;IH&lt;/a&gt;.

How about something along the lines of: try to be the with it, culturally fluent, tolerant, competent, and reasonably knowledgeable rabbis we trained you to be. Don&#039;t take yourselves too seriously, but don&#039;t act like fools either. If you plan on going post denominational please don&#039;t mention us, and for gosh sake, don&#039;t do anything that lands rabbis in the pages of the NY Post. Now go forth and conquer the promised land of college campuses and left-leaning synagogues.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3177">IH</a>.</p>
<p>How about something along the lines of: try to be the with it, culturally fluent, tolerant, competent, and reasonably knowledgeable rabbis we trained you to be. Don&#8217;t take yourselves too seriously, but don&#8217;t act like fools either. If you plan on going post denominational please don&#8217;t mention us, and for gosh sake, don&#8217;t do anything that lands rabbis in the pages of the NY Post. Now go forth and conquer the promised land of college campuses and left-leaning synagogues.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: IH		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/10/yct-graduation-speech-where-is-the-promised-land/#comment-3177</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[IH]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2011 19:34:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3679#comment-3177</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Maybe it&#039;s just me, but Bill Safire&#039;s words come to mind when reading this comment thread:  &quot;&quot;nattering nabobs of negativism&quot;.  

Question: if you were giving R. Linzer&#039;s YCT graduation speech, what would you say?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Maybe it&#8217;s just me, but Bill Safire&#8217;s words come to mind when reading this comment thread:  &#8220;&#8221;nattering nabobs of negativism&#8221;.  </p>
<p>Question: if you were giving R. Linzer&#8217;s YCT graduation speech, what would you say?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
