<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Pentecostal Philosophy of Science can Breslov Epistemology be far behind?	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/06/pentecostal-philosophy-of-science-can-breslov-epistemology-be-far-behind/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/06/pentecostal-philosophy-of-science-can-breslov-epistemology-be-far-behind/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Oct 2010 15:35:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/06/pentecostal-philosophy-of-science-can-breslov-epistemology-be-far-behind/#comment-1739</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 08 Oct 2010 15:35:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2144#comment-1739</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[EJ-
It would be nice if someone would write a introduction to Talmudic reasoning using Foot, Anscombe, and others. Something like Rav Amiel&#039;s Middot leHaker HaHalakhah for a new century.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>EJ-<br />
It would be nice if someone would write a introduction to Talmudic reasoning using Foot, Anscombe, and others. Something like Rav Amiel&#8217;s Middot leHaker HaHalakhah for a new century.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: lawrence kaplan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/06/pentecostal-philosophy-of-science-can-breslov-epistemology-be-far-behind/#comment-1728</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lawrence kaplan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Oct 2010 18:50:29 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2144#comment-1728</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Trolley problem ( changing tracks)  is similar to the arrow problem  (deflecting its direction) raised  by the  Hazon Ish,   recently discussed by Michael Harris in the  TUMJ.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Trolley problem ( changing tracks)  is similar to the arrow problem  (deflecting its direction) raised  by the  Hazon Ish,   recently discussed by Michael Harris in the  TUMJ.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/06/pentecostal-philosophy-of-science-can-breslov-epistemology-be-far-behind/#comment-1726</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Oct 2010 18:16:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2144#comment-1726</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[(my hand slipped...the comment is in the wrong place. Sorry.) cont... I think of Buber as doing normative ethics and offering a view about the good life. Why is Foot relevant?

One more point. Yesterday the topic on Rabbi Maryles&#039; blog was whether Roosevelt should have bombed Auschwitz. Someone asked me if halachically an Orthodox Jew could be the one to do this. I knew little about the correct final halacha, but I pointed to the Wikipedia entry on the trolley car problem. The literature has by now become voluminous and very difficult, and is at the center of many difficult and diverse moral questions. (Active/passive, forseen but unintended consequences, sacrificing one for the good of many, etc..) I see one of Ms. Foot&#039;s main contributions was that she started and inspired  this way of doing moral philosophy, a way that is very close to talmudic style thought.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>(my hand slipped&#8230;the comment is in the wrong place. Sorry.) cont&#8230; I think of Buber as doing normative ethics and offering a view about the good life. Why is Foot relevant?</p>
<p>One more point. Yesterday the topic on Rabbi Maryles&#8217; blog was whether Roosevelt should have bombed Auschwitz. Someone asked me if halachically an Orthodox Jew could be the one to do this. I knew little about the correct final halacha, but I pointed to the Wikipedia entry on the trolley car problem. The literature has by now become voluminous and very difficult, and is at the center of many difficult and diverse moral questions. (Active/passive, forseen but unintended consequences, sacrificing one for the good of many, etc..) I see one of Ms. Foot&#8217;s main contributions was that she started and inspired  this way of doing moral philosophy, a way that is very close to talmudic style thought.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/06/pentecostal-philosophy-of-science-can-breslov-epistemology-be-far-behind/#comment-1725</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Oct 2010 17:56:51 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2144#comment-1725</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[You&#039;ve written so many interesting posts lately it&#039;s difficult for me to pick one. I&#039;ll talk about Philippa Foot. I remember her looking like a bird, very proper and feminine, I even think she wore high heels. By way of contrast Ms. Anscombe with her pants, sensible shoes and and thin cigars looked like a dyke, except that Ms Anscombe had a brood of children with Peter Geach and was uber Catholic,  while Ms. Foot was quite liberal and had no children. I think The Guardian said that she even had an affair with Iris Murdoch. 

I learnt about Foot through Judith Thomson who I used to &quot;talk to  in learning &quot; about the trolley car problem and the case of finding yourself one day hooked up to a vilonist, which changed the nature of the abortion debate for  at least a generation. So for me the significance of Ms. Foot is that she was one of the first to use our opinions about concrete examples from which we try to develop our understanding. I never found the emotivists plausible so her work in that area was less exciting. I am not clear why she would be relevant to Buber, unless Buber was offering a meta ethical definition, maybe. I]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>You&#8217;ve written so many interesting posts lately it&#8217;s difficult for me to pick one. I&#8217;ll talk about Philippa Foot. I remember her looking like a bird, very proper and feminine, I even think she wore high heels. By way of contrast Ms. Anscombe with her pants, sensible shoes and and thin cigars looked like a dyke, except that Ms Anscombe had a brood of children with Peter Geach and was uber Catholic,  while Ms. Foot was quite liberal and had no children. I think The Guardian said that she even had an affair with Iris Murdoch. </p>
<p>I learnt about Foot through Judith Thomson who I used to &#8220;talk to  in learning &#8221; about the trolley car problem and the case of finding yourself one day hooked up to a vilonist, which changed the nature of the abortion debate for  at least a generation. So for me the significance of Ms. Foot is that she was one of the first to use our opinions about concrete examples from which we try to develop our understanding. I never found the emotivists plausible so her work in that area was less exciting. I am not clear why she would be relevant to Buber, unless Buber was offering a meta ethical definition, maybe. I</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
