<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>anti-intellectualism &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/tag/anti-intellectualism/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Mar 2010 19:49:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='kavvanah.wordpress.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/c9f111237f93750b6b994fc5185d49c3?s=96&#038;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>anti-intellectualism &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>From conservative anti-intellectualism to liberal anti-intellectualism</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/04/from-conservative-anti-intellectualism-to-liberal-anti-intellectualism/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/04/from-conservative-anti-intellectualism-to-liberal-anti-intellectualism/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 04 Mar 2010 19:49:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[popular religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[anti-intellectualism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=899</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Taken from an emergent Church blog in which the author is frustrated by the new form anti-intellectualism of the emergent Church. It is no longer the right wing rejection of college,liberalism, and ideas, rather now it is a new liberal &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/04/from-conservative-anti-intellectualism-to-liberal-anti-intellectualism/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>Taken from an emergent Church blog in which the author is frustrated by the new form anti-intellectualism of the emergent Church. It is no longer the right wing rejection of college,liberalism, and ideas, rather now it is a new liberal anti-intellectualism. Does it ring true about Jewish circles? Can one only preach to the choir for a short time before it is anti-intellectual? Does communal experience and anecdote trump coherent articulation among modern Orthodox Jews?</strong></p>
<p>From conservative anti-intellectualism to liberal anti-intellectualism:<br />
This one has me the most frustrated.  I was drawn to the emerging church conversation because I saw vigorous questioning and thoughtful exploration&#8230; And certainly there are several young, postmodern emerging/emergent theologians who are making rigorous arguments and thoughtful claims.  But I&#8217;ve become more and more concerned at a <strong>creeping anti-intellectualism among some of the loudest voices who rest on rhetorical questions, anecdotal evidence, and communal experiences over philosophical and theological articulation and argument. </strong> This, I believe, follows from the previous inversions because your don&#8217;t have to really say anything or land anywhere because we are all merely in an endless conversation.  Essentially, everything is a rhetorical display without any real substance. <strong> And really, you can only score so many rhetorical points before you are only preaching to the choir (which is a form a fundamentalism itself, is it not?).</strong>  I have been a part of numerous conversations that only go so deep before an implied anti-intellectualism takes over.<br />
When a certain form of radical questioning takes the well worn paths of protestant liberalism, or mirror forms of Hegelianism, it does not good to just assert that &#8220;we&#8221; aren&#8217;t doing that old thing, you have to actually show how things are different, you have to defend and articulate what is going on.<br />
This is the role of an &#8216;organic theologian&#8217;, to both articulate within a community what is happening, and express to larger communities why it makes sense.  To only do the former without the latter is to perpetuate a fundamentalism on the other side of the equation.  Hence my claim of an inverted anti-intellectualism.  Fundamentalist, Evangelicals, Hippies, the Seeker-Church, and now many Missional/Emergent types play this card as a way of calling into question the power of the establishment.  Now I&#8217;m not saying there aren&#8217;t issues of power going on, but have faith in your ideas and practices, show the world, make your case, and make a difference.  Don&#8217;t just claim that the powers are keeping you out without even actually making an argument so saying that others won&#8217;t understand. <a href="http://churchandpomo.typepad.com/conversation/2010/03/the-inversion-of-fundamentalism-some-postmodern-varients.html">Taken from here.</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/04/from-conservative-anti-intellectualism-to-liberal-anti-intellectualism/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
