<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>day schools &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/tag/day-schools/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 May 2010 03:13:57 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='kavvanah.wordpress.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/c9f111237f93750b6b994fc5185d49c3?s=96&#038;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>day schools &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>Peter Beinart on Day Schools</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/25/peter-beinart-on-day-schools/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/25/peter-beinart-on-day-schools/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2010 03:13:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[avi chai]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[day schools]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[peter beinart]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1364</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Back in 1999, Beinart framed the rise of day schools as a rejection of the original acceptance of public school. The growth of Jewish Day Schools is an abandonment of the American public square. Beinart pointed out that the rise &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/25/peter-beinart-on-day-schools/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Back in 1999, Beinart framed the rise of day schools as a rejection of the original acceptance of public school. The growth of Jewish Day Schools is an abandonment of the American public square.</p>
<p>Beinart pointed out that the rise of day school had other factors than the obvious religious commitment.  Even though day schools were originally for ideologically driven Orthodox who have not totally integrated into America, Day Schools became a form of private school for those moving up the latter. </p>
<p>Now, it seems the drive for day schools is the ideological need to create an enclave, in many classes an upper middle class Orthodox enclave.  In this type of school, what counts? the education or the creation of the enclave?  Some families are clearly still interested in creating private schools better than the public schools while others no longer ask if the day school if better than the public school in social studies, English, arts, or college preparation.  Beinart reminds us to account for the role of the school in social mobility,class and caste. At the end of the twentieth century, day schools were “in” but the word “day school” may have had three different meanings- <strong>a prep school for Jews, a community school for identity, and a day school to create an enclave. </strong><a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/11/peripheral-vision/"> Studies done by Avi Chai</a> do not differentiate types of schools or factor in class and caste. (<a href="http://www.peje.org/docs/GrowthToronto.pdf">One of the decent studies available on the web</a>, which was done privately by Alex Pomson, shows that in Toronto day schools are not growing relative to population increase.)</p>
<p>Jews supported public school because it helped enforce the separation of Church and State.  Jews did   encourage Christian kids to go to pre-Vatican II Catholic and Protestant schools because it would not have helped their integration. In those days, thinking of America as a Christian country would have meant Jews are excluded. Now, Jews do not worry about the possibility if there are Christian schools that do not offer an American secular narrative  Jews do not worry about being outsiders. Nor do American Orthodox Jews currently worry about the possibility of Afrocentric, Muslim, Hindu, and Sikh private schools.</p>
<p>What  do day school parents feel about the melting pot? I would suspect that many are oblivious or against. Or it is only useful for everyone else. Do some of the parents see that if you exclude yourself from the socialization of the rest of the country then you start to look sectarian? Or if you accept the melting pot for viewing sports and listening to Lady Gaga, but not for social science thinking and historical narrative  then you create a hybridization that may not work in all contexts.  (In the full article, Beinhart cheers for the creation of the New-Jew HS in Boston as outside the box.)</p>
<p><a href="http:// http://www.theatlantic.com/past/issues/99oct/9910jewishschools.htm">Read full version of Beinart on Jewish schools here.</a></p>
<blockquote><p>Preparing children for &#8220;the general American environment&#8221; meant public education as both practice and ideology. &#8220;The public school,&#8221; says Alvin I. Schiff, the Irving I. Stone Distinguished Professor of Education at Yeshiva University, in New York, &#8220;was considered sacred, holy. It was the method and setting by which Jews could become Americans.&#8221;<br />
All the talk about Jewish identity may also obscure a less high-minded reason for the Jewish-school boom: as Jews have moved up the economic ladder, their commitment to public education has waned.<br />
&#8220;As the public schools have eroded,&#8221; Miller says, &#8220;we are no longer being compared so much to public schools as to other independents.&#8221; Jewish leaders argue that because Jews make up such a small proportion of the U.S. population, the growth of Jewish schools has no real impact on the overall health of American public education. But public schools rely more heavily on Jewish support than the numbers would suggest, in part because Jewish organizations, fearful of any breakdown of the wall between Church and State, have traditionally lobbied hard against school vouchers and other government aid to private schools. As awareness grows that voucher programs might benefit financially strapped Jewish schools, that opposition may diminish.<br />
Yet such parents, by choosing Jewish schools, are preparing their children to lead more observant, less assimilated lives than they do. Some even describe the phenomenon as an inversion of a practice in nineteenth-century Europe whereby parents would remain Jewish but baptize their children.<br />
Why a growing number of relatively secular Jewish parents are abandoning the education model of their youth is a topic of considerable debate within the organized Jewish world</p>
<p>THERE is another, even more sensitive issue lurking behind the Jewish-school phenomenon. Earlier generations of Jews, according to Eduardo Rauch, of the Jewish Theological Seminary, in New York, sent their children to public school not simply as a means of ascending into the middle class but as a show of national loyalty. Today, in contrast, parents are willing to consider Jewish schools in part because they no longer fear being viewed as outsiders. They take their integration into mainstream America as a given. But what if earlier generations were correct &#8212; that full equality in an overwhelmingly Christian country is, in fact, reliant on Jewish willingness to participate in a common system of education?<br />
In fact, when discussing issues like Afrocentrism and bilingual education, American Jewish leaders sometimes bemoan the demise of the melting-pot ideal in this country. Yet separate religious schools both rely on that demise and exacerbate it. The Orthodox community, for its part, has rarely celebrated the melting pot, and generally worries less about total acceptance by the broader culture. </p></blockquote>
<p>For our last discussion about day schools, see here- <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/11/catholic-schools-and-jewish-day-schools/">Catholic Schools and Jewish Day Schools.</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/25/peter-beinart-on-day-schools/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Catholic Schools and Jewish Day Schools</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/11/catholic-schools-and-jewish-day-schools/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/11/catholic-schools-and-jewish-day-schools/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2010 16:06:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[popular religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sociology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[day school tuition]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[day schools]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[yeshiva tuition]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=518</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In the 1960’s the Catholic Ghetto walls came down. In the 1950&#8217;s Catholics went to Catholic school, lived in Catholic enclaves, and had all their social needs met by the catholic community.  One only left for graduate school or when &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/11/catholic-schools-and-jewish-day-schools/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the 1960’s the Catholic Ghetto walls came down. In the 1950&#8217;s Catholics went to Catholic school, lived in Catholic enclaves, and had all their social needs met by the catholic community.  One only left for graduate school or when certain professions required one to have non-Catholic co-workers.  In the nineteen sixties, everything changed. Catholics wanted in live in new locations,  new suburbs and exurbs, the idea that one should only live around Catholics declines and the cultural revolution of the 1960’s called into question the provincialism and parochialism of these enclaves.  Some of these Catholic Ghettos dissolved entirely – from near total allegiance to the Church to minimal attendance, and even then only by the elderly.</p>
<p>Catholic teaching taught that building a parochial school is more important than a Church and that one would lose one’s faith in public school.  Jews at this point were in favor of public schools, and many of the orthodox saw day schools as entirely unneeded for girls and a hot bed of Zionism.</p>
<p>The question is: Can the Orthodox Jewish community learn anything from the Catholic example? Are there things to learn about rapid declines of enclaves? Are there any reasons it wont happen to places like Teaneck? Will the young gen y- millennials share their parents Modern Orthodox provincialism?  What about when they move to new cities, new professions or disdain living with the gen-x’ers? Dont just say we are committed to our religion in a way that Catholics are not.  Catholics were more committed and  had a much longer tradition of day schools.</p>
<p>Let’s turn to day schools. The Catholic system lost most of its attendees in the nineteen sixties. By the end of the decade they were down to 15%.  N ow 40 years later they find themselves as an unsustainable system strapped for cash and may have to close. What can Orthodox Jews learn from it? I am not sure but we should ask ourselves what we can learn.</p>
<p>The quotes below are from a variety of papers. Some are based on a 2007 Notre Dame Study and some from the Bergen county schools. One factor they cite is that without nuns they have to pay real salaries for teachers. Is anyone here old enough to remember when Jewish day school teachers were seriously underpaid? We cannot go back to hiring Holocaust survivors who don&#8217;t live in our communities or to being months behind on salary payments.</p>
<p>Also many Jews and Catholics went to parochial school to avoid the public school in immigrant neighborhoods. We don&#8217;t live in immigrant neighborhoods anymore and many public schools are of the same class and caste as the parochial schools. The article also points out that we expect more. We are not first generation college bound anymore. There are currently high expectations for a school. When parents were lacking in either general  or Jewish studies they expected less. Now what?</p>
<blockquote><p>Many parents of children in Catholic schools attended these schools themselves and look back nostalgically at a day when Catholic schools, just a step past “The Bells of St. Mary’s,” were staffed by nuns, brothers and priests. Today, however, they account for a mere 4% of the staff, many of them in administration.</p>
<p>The glory days of the U.S. Catholic parochial school are gone, according to a new University of Notre Dame report, and the church must rethink its mission in order to recapture the school system&#8217;s lost luster.<br />
The nuns and priests who educated generations of American Catholics are almost gone, retired or deceased.. Faculty salaries are too low while tuitions and costs are rising, the report says.</p>
<p>Catholic schools are in steep decline, their enrollment having “steadily dropped by more than half from its peak of five million 40 years ago.”Among the better-known reasons: 1) nuns and priests who once staffed teaching positions have retired and their ranks have not been renewed in the near-total absence of new American “vocations”; 2) as urban Catholics suburbanized over the past two generations, Church officials for various reasons did not choose to follow them out by establishing suburban schools in large numbers; 3) having fully entered the mainstream of American life, Catholics are less drawn than previously to separate institutions.</p>
<p>There was a time when parochial schools seemed almost omnipresent, when the daily migration of kids in plaid clothes seemed to fill every street. However, with enrollments plummeting and one school after another closing its doors, the torrent of Catholic school kids has become a trickle, and it looks like the days of Catholic education may well be numbered.</p>
<p>When it comes to Catholic education in America, the numbers are downright startling. In 1965, approximately half of all Catholic families sent their kids to parochial schools; today, roughly 15% do so. While there are numerous reasons for this, the big one seems to be that the cost of parochial school has vastly increased. Once upon a time, Catholic classes were largely taught by clerics. Today, however, fewer Catholics are choosing to enter the priesthood or the nunnery; in fact, one statistic states that there are presently more nuns over 90 than under 50 years old.</p>
<p>Another concern has been a reduction in religious definition. For many people, Catholicism has become less of an all-consuming lifestyle and more of a part-time identity. Where Catholic education was once a responsibility for Catholic parents, it is increasingly becoming an expensive luxury.</p>
<p>Furthermore, in areas where public education has improved, parochial education has suffered. For example, in Northern Virginia, where I grew up, Catholic schools once offered the best educational choices. However, as the area&#8217;s schools have improved, Catholic education has simply become a more expensive option.</p></blockquote>
<p>You might have not seen the former paragraphs which were from NYT and other papers. But what about those who live in Bergen county? Did you not see the Bergen record two months ago? Has anyone called any of the Catholic parochial schools to see if anything can be brainstormed together? This article is on the remaining 15% of Catholics still going to parochial school having to leave because of the 2009 recession. They closed 40 out of 137 schools in the last few years. In addition, the local public schools which uses licensed teachers are currently seen as offering a superior education.</p>
<blockquote><p>Bergen Record &#8211; Catholic schools enrollment drop blamed on economy<br />
Friday, November 13, 2009 BY TONY GICAS</p>
<p>CLIFTON — The economic downturn has created frightening unemployment rates, forced many Americans to foreclose on their homes, brought sticker shock into the nation&#8217;s grocery stores and has even changed the way people plan their children&#8217;s education.</p>
<p>More specifically, many New Jerseyans have either decided to take their children out of parochial schools or send them to public schools because of the financial commitment required at most Catholic schools.</p>
<p>According to Brian Gray, a spokesman for the National Catholic Education Association, enrollment at America&#8217;s Catholic schools reached its peak in the 1960s with about 5.2 million students. By 1980 that number had dropped to approximately 3.1 million and last year the nationwide enrollment hit 2.19 million.</p>
<p>In September 2000, the Newark Archdiocese had 137 grade schools in Union, Essex, Hudson and Bergen counties. Now, it has just 97. The school population in neighboring Paterson jumped by 1,000 students this year, a 3.5 percent increase in the district that has about 28,000 students, the district reported.</p>
<p>&#8220;I think down the line if the economy continues this way the tuition at parochial schools will remain unaffordable to many and the numbers will continue to decline,&#8221; Tardalo said.</p>
<p>&#8220;Therefore they may desire a private education for their children, but if they have to they&#8217;ll opt to send their children to a public school.&#8221;</p>
<p>He said parochial schools offered &#8220;an equivalent educational experience&#8221; during his time as a Catholic school principal, however he did stipulate their teachers do not face the same licensing requirements as public school teachers.</p></blockquote>
<p>I exclude from my discussion the wealthy Jewish prep schools like Ramaz becuase they are based on having a financial endowment  and have a different constituency. The question remains- Will the average Jewish days schools decline the way the Catholic schools did? Why not? Why do we think we have a more sustainable system than the Catholic schools? Even if everyone struggles to keep their kids in their current day school, will those 10  years younger than you want to enter this rat race? Will your kids want to continue this struggle? Anyone have good data about those moving to the new Sun Belt suburbs? I have no solutions, only historical questions.</p>
<p>This post came from running into a neighbor HF in the grocery for whom this is a major concern. It is a write-up of a discussion that occurred by meat aisle. I do want to write this up as an op-ed at some point.</p>
<p>Copyright © 2010 Alan Brill · All Rights Reserved</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/11/catholic-schools-and-jewish-day-schools/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>25</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Peripheral Vision</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/11/peripheral-vision/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/11/peripheral-vision/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2009 05:30:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[sociology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[avi chai]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[day schools]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marvin Schick]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=15</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In the new &#8220;Census of Jewish Day Schools in the United States 2008-09&#8221; released this week by Marvin Schick We have the following statistic: Outside of New York and New Jersey, 47% of day school students are enrolled in non-Orthodox &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/11/peripheral-vision/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the new &#8220;Census of Jewish Day Schools in the United States 2008-09&#8221; released this week by Marvin Schick</p>
<p>We have the following statistic:</p>
<blockquote><p>Outside of New York and New Jersey, 47% of day school students are enrolled in non-Orthodox schools.</p></blockquote>
<p>Yet 83% of all day school students are in orthodox schools. It emphasizes again the role of regional differences and the enormous difference between center and periphery. The very image of a day school is different out of NY-NJ.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.avi-chai.org/Static/Binaries/Publications/Key_Findings_of_2008_09_Day_School_Census_Final.pdf" target="_self">Report</a></p>
<p>It was usually the same in most countries. In Congress Poland, Cracow had Yeshivot and Italian cultural influence, Lublin only had the yeshivot, while Podolia, the birthplace of Hasidism, was out of town. A major economic center, but culturally on the periphery.  Similarly in Spain, Castille was not the same as cultured Gerona. Many peripheries  were sources of new ideas.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/11/peripheral-vision/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
