<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>post-evangelical &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/tag/post-evangelical/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Dec 2012 16:36:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='kavvanah.wordpress.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/c9f111237f93750b6b994fc5185d49c3?s=96&#038;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>post-evangelical &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>Quarreling with Orthodoxy- more post-orthodoxy</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/26/quarreling-with-orthodoxy-more-post-orthodoxy/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/26/quarreling-with-orthodoxy-more-post-orthodoxy/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2010 19:10:19 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[modern orthodoxy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[post-evangelical]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[post-orthodox]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[post-orthodoxy]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1743</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Here is a book review from internetmonk.com, the blog from which I first adapted the term post-evangelical to post-orthodox. The problems of emphasis on body count and any technique or argument is good is it makes someone religious are obvious &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/26/quarreling-with-orthodoxy-more-post-orthodoxy/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here is a book review from internetmonk.com, the blog from which I first adapted the term post-evangelical to post-orthodox.  The problems of emphasis on body count and any technique or argument is good is it makes someone religious are obvious in the Orthodox community.  The sentimentality and materialism of the community are standard critiques of Orthodoxy. His first problem of provincialism takes a bit more imagination to understand. Provincialism means that Orthodoxy means following the opinions of Teaneck, Riverdale, or YU and not the full gamut of the tradition. It also means that Orthodoxy is following the social enclave and mores of frum neighborhoods more than following God. The blog notes that now we need a book of  solutions. </p>
<blockquote><p>From <a href="http://www.internetmonk.com/archive/im-book-review-a-lovers-quarrel-with-the-evangelical-church">internetmonk: A Lover’s Quarrel with the Evangelical Church</a></p>
<p>By Chaplain Mike<br />
Warren Cole Smith’s book, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Lovers-Quarrel-Evangelical-Church/dp/1606570285/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1280170846&amp;sr=1-1">A Lover’s Quarrel with the Evangelical Church </a> has a title with which I resonate. If you’ve been reading Internet Monk for any length of time, you’ll know that we describe ourselves in two ways: We are evangelicals. We’re having struggles with the church. We are engaged in a critique of the church which bears Jesus’ name. We have become convinced that it is not very Jesus-shaped these days.</p>
<p> Many of us call ourselves “post-evangelical”—that is, we no longer feel comfortable within the system known as the American evangelical church.<br />
In this book, Warren Cole Smith sets forth the question many of us are asking: What is it about evangelical theology or evangelical practice that is both so appealing and so troubling? (p.8 )</p>
<p><strong>One of the great contributions Smith makes is that he gives names to the chains that bind us in cultural captivity.</strong> These are:<br />
•	<strong>The New Provincialism:</strong> Evangelicalism has so cut itself off from history and Biblical and church tradition that, “the evangelical church risks ceasing to be a Christian church at all.” (p. 60)</p>
<p>•	<strong>The Triumph of Sentimentality:</strong> “Sentimentality is the result of our unwillingness to realign our desires with the reality of the world, but rather to remake the world in accordance with our desires” (p. 67). Having rejected history and our theological legacy, today’s evangelicalism is all about creating an alternate reality—through highly efficient, full-service megachurches, through technologically-generated “worship experiences,” through therapeutic, positive-thinking, and prosperity-Gospel preaching.</p>
<p>•	<strong>The Christian-Industrial Complex: </strong>The “Christian market” has expanded so dramatically over the past generation, that a vast industry has grown up to supply products to satisfy its desires. It’s the American way. Now, many aspects of church life are driven by target marketing rather than by theologically-informed, pastorally-sensitive ordained and accountable leaders.</p>
<p>•	<strong>Body-Count Evangelism:</strong> As any evangelical will tell you—size matters. Smith shows how today’s evangelicalism, fueled by such trends as the growth of the parachurch movement, has bought fully into the revivalist tradition with its emphasis on numbers, scale, and spectacle.</p>
<p>•	<strong>The Great Stereopticon:</strong> Rejecting the long understood fact that “the medium is the message,” evangelicalism has adopted the philosophy that any means is OK as long as one is communicating the right message. However, as Smith observes, “When you change the medium, you change the message, whether you intend to or not and though the words remain exactly the same. It is a lesson the evangelical church has not yet learned.”</p>
<p>I would love to see Warren Cole Smith write a second book for us—A Lover’s Proposal for the Evangelical Church—in which he might flesh out these suggestive ideas and help guide evangelicalism back to a more Jesus-shaped way.</p></blockquote>
<p><strong>From the Amazon review</strong><br />
<em>Smith argues that we evangelicals are just as prone to being power-hungry, materialistic and being builders of our own empires as anybody else, to the detriment of community.<br />
Evangelicals are also often guilty of a new provincialism. Provincialism usually means our outlook is narrowly determined by our small localized setting. For evangelicals, our narrowness is due to being stuck only in the &#8220;now.&#8221; </em></p>
<p><strong>Now how would we solve each of these? What would be the chapters of the book about orthodoxy? </strong></p>
<p>Copyright © 2010 Alan Brill • All Rights Reserved</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/26/quarreling-with-orthodoxy-more-post-orthodoxy/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>6</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Post Orthodoxy and Post Evangelicalism again</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/20/post-orthodoxy-and-post-evangelicalism-again/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/20/post-orthodoxy-and-post-evangelicalism-again/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2010 20:40:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[popular religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sociology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[post-evangelical]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[post-orthodox]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[post-orthodoxy]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=607</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Since many did feel there is something to the comparison between Post-evangelical and Post-Orthodoxy, I will continue exploring it a bit more. Sometimes there are moments that capture a certain feeling. 1946-7 was the feeling of the returning GI not &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/20/post-orthodoxy-and-post-evangelicalism-again/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Since many did feel there is something to the comparison between Post-evangelical and Post-Orthodoxy, I will continue exploring it a bit more.</p>
<p>Sometimes there are moments that capture a certain feeling. 1946-7 was the feeling of the returning GI not going back to his hometown. 1959-was the threat of nuclear attack, 1968 was the sexual revolution and the counter-culture, and 1984 was the year of the Yuppie.None of these moments create a denomination they affect all denominations. The returning GI’s created all the suburban congregations of all denominations.</p>
<p>And the social mood of the returning GI’s- should not be quickly conflated with Film Noir and French Existentialism of the same years. Different trends and mood can occur at the same time.</p>
<p>This year is a sense of the post-Evangelical era. (There is also post-Mormonism)  It may not really kick-in for another few years. (The same way that those people who watch MadMen are able to see that things are unraveling toward the late 1960’s.) Evangelical religion was driven back by a variety of things such as the Scopes trial and Elmer Gantry in 1926. It retreated and then in the 1950’s wanted to be modern, educated and relevant.  It wanted to show that it does not have to be seen as backwards, rather it should be seen as intellectual and modern. It started growing again as a reaction to the 1970’s. By the 1990’s they were seen as mainstream.  They could show themselves as doctors, lawyers, and politicians; they are no longer backward.</p>
<p>Traditional Orthodoxy was Yiddish speaking and seen as not modern, not scientific, not family oriented, not democratic, not educated. Post WWII Modern Orthodoxy responded to these limits with concern for the modern. Then,  with the return to religion in the 1980’s, Centrist Orthodoxy embraced conservative positions on social and cultural issues combined with an identification with Yuppie values (The latter point itself is  big and important topic). And like the new Evangelicals, it effaced history and had a non sacramental approach (mizvot no longer change the worlds and performance is not cultivated). It shared a dispensational eschatology with evangelicals, Biblical promises are happening now but only as applied to Israel.</p>
<p>To return to the original Post-Evangelical post. <a href="http://www.internetmonk.com/archive/what-do-i-mean-by-post-evangelical">The Christian Blogger IM in his post What Do I Mean by Post-Evangelical? August 7, 2006 </a>notes some the history outlined above. He notes that Evangelicals were “Attempting, and largely failing, to establish a non-fundamentalist identity.” He offers a variety of thought of new turns of thought including: there is more possibilities in the classic texts and more relevant interpretations than currently taught; the boundaries of in and out matter less and the current boundary may not be true, creed is important but it is not to be used in an authoritarian way, show respect to those of other denominations; interpretation only occurs in a complex human matrix; the meaning does not fall from the sky in a magical or timeless way;  He also notes that he does not worry if some post-evangelicals are heretical or out of step- it will sort itself out over time. He states that the clergy’s role is not to define who is right and wrong. We need to return to the sources and to the spirit (experience, prophecy, intuition).</p>
<blockquote><p>We must be aware that there is far more in the Bible than the Reformation dealt with, and that many of our problems today are addressed by those hitherto unnoticed or undeveloped aspects of the Bible.</p>
<p>Those who want to bang the drum for a 450-year old tradition are dooming themselves to irrelevance. Our only concern is to avoid being beat up by them as they thrash about in their death-throes. I mean that I do not recognize the boundary lines of American evangelicalism as the boundary lines of true Christianity. I mean that creeds and confessions have positive and defining roles, but do not function as popes and unassailable authorities.</p>
<p>I mean that it has become virtually impossible to practice any form of Christian community that does not interact in some way with the larger church in history and reality. (I salute those who attempt to practice pure forms of fundamentalism, etc. They have my respect.) I mean that I do not share the hostility and suspicion of all things Catholic or catholic that is endemic to evangelicalism. I mean that I recognize that Christian belief emerges from a matrix of the text of Holy Scripture, the history of interpretation, cultural and sub-cultural presuppositions, the use of reason, the place of experience, the wisdom of the teachers of the larger church and the work of the Holy Spirit in revealing more light. I embrace this more complex understanding of Christian belief as part of the great stream of Christian existence, and I reject any notions that Christian belief falls from the sky as a magic book that exists apart from other components of human experience.</p>
<p>I mean that words like “postmodern,” “emerging” and “missional” are in the process of being defined and filled with meaning, and are not to be ridiculed and rejected out of hand because some who use them are out of step or even heretical.</p>
<p>I mean that I reject the idea that the primary role of a minister is to define other Christians as wrong. . I mean that the death of evangelicalism opens the door for a return to the sources…I mean that our reverence for previous epochs and events in church history must be tempered with an awareness that the work of the Holy Spirit in the church continues, and what was believed in the past is not immune from the light that may break forth in the ongoing present.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.internetmonk.com/archive/what-do-i-mean-by-post-evangelical">Full version here. </a></p></blockquote>
<p>And in <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/01/the-emergent-church-and-orthodoxy/">the article on the Emergent Church that I posted here “The Emergent Church and Orthodoxy” </a>the author listed at least four points worth considering: Prophecy, greater focus on worship and ritual, not being worried about boundaries, and liberal politics.</p>
<p>I ask the Gen-Y/Millennials out there: How do they see themselves different than Centrism? What do they think are the sins and excesses of Centrism?</p>
<p>I ask again: How much of this is applicable to changes within Orthodoxy?  Does it sound familiar? Are their differences? Is this change inevitable? Which of these will change Orthodoxy more and which will change it less?</p>
<p>If I wanted I could collect the Facebook answers to the info line &#8220;Religious Views&#8221; to show that something is up. I have hundreds of examples of those raised Orthodox defining themselves in all sorts of convoluted ways. Don&#8217;t worry I will not do it, but a such a listing of self-identifications bespeaks a mood.</p>
<p>Remember, this is a moment or a mood – not an ideology or denomination. Post-evangelical is like Yuppie or returning GI – a set of values that will play itself out in a variety of diverse ways. How will these winds blow over the face of traditional practice? What will be the VARIED responses? I await details from those in the field.</p>
<p>Copyright © 2010 Alan Brill • All Rights Reserved</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/20/post-orthodoxy-and-post-evangelicalism-again/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>8</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Emergent Church and Orthodoxy</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/01/the-emergent-church-and-orthodoxy/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/01/the-emergent-church-and-orthodoxy/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2010 20:13:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Neo-Hasidism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[popular religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sociology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[spirituality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[emergent church]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[post-evangelical]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[post-modern]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[post-orthodox]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=449</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[There are a variety of post-modern turns to religion: including Post-modern Christianity, post-liberalism, emergent church, weak theology, post-evangelical, theology without Being, minimal theology, Paleo-orthodoxy, and radical orthodoxy. (Personally, I  do not necessarily agree with, or accept, or identify with any &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/01/the-emergent-church-and-orthodoxy/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There are a variety of post-modern turns to religion: including <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Postmodern_Christianity">Post-modern Christianity</a>, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Post-liberal_theology">post-liberalism,</a> emergent church, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weak_theology">weak theology, </a>post-evangelical, theology without Being, minimal theology, Paleo-orthodoxy, and<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radical_orthodoxy"> radical orthodoxy. </a>(Personally, I  do not necessarily agree with, or accept, or identify with any of them  except post-liberalism) Some of the new turns are liberal and some are orthodox.  Some are academic and some are popular. Some are ideas and some are social tends. And some are for everyone. while others are only for gen x and gen y – leaving the baby boomers out.  We live in a fluid decade where a Jew raised in the reform movement who starts wearing Zizit, putting on tefillin, and keeping Kosher can still be comfortable in Reform and where those raised Orthodox are still part of the social entity Orthodoxy regardless of believe or practice. Even within Orthodoxy, an ecstatic breslov Carlbachian, a scholarly interested in academic Talmud, a baby-boomer fighting what they perceive as chumrot, and someone advocating GLBT awareness- may or may not have anything in common with each other. .</p>
<p>Since my blog post on post –evangelicalism has generated an interest- I will offer a bit more on a related topic- The EMERGENT CHURCH. But when you read it, the question remains to map out where Judaism is similar and where it is different than the Evangelicals. As I asked in the first post: What needs to be added in the Jewish case? Are Jews playing themselves out in the same way? Where are the differences?<br />
Here is the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emerging_church">WIKI definition of the emergent church</a> – I am not sure how it relates to Jews.</p>
<blockquote><p>The <strong>emerging church</strong> (sometimes referred to as the <strong>emergent movement</strong>) is a Christian movement of the late 20th and early 21st century that crosses a number of theological boundaries: participants can be described as evangelical, post-evangelical, liberal, post-liberal, charismatic, neocharismatic and post-charismatic. Participants seek to live their faith in what they believe to be a &#8220;postmodern&#8221; society. Proponents of this movement call it a &#8220;conversation&#8221; to emphasize its developing and decentralized nature, its vast range of standpoints and its commitment to dialogue. What those involved in the conversation mostly agree on is their disillusionment with the organized and institutional church and their support for the deconstruction of modern Christian worship, modern evangelism, and the nature of modern Christian community.</p>
<p>The emerging church favors the use of simple story and narrative. Members of the movement often place a high value on good works or social activism, including missional living or new monasticism.<sup> </sup>Many in the emerging church emphasize the here and now. The movement favors the sharing of experiences via testimonies, prayer, group recitation, sharing meals and other communal practices, which they believe are more personal and sincere than propositional presentations of the Gospel.</p></blockquote>
<p><strong>I am not sure how much the younger generation of Jews are using narrative, are doing good works, charismatic, or creating a new monasticism</strong>.</p>
<p>There was a good article a full three years ago attempting to unpack the Emergent Church that will be helpful in comparing Jewish trends to Evangelical ones.</p>
<blockquote><p><a href="http://www.christianitytoday.com/ct/2007/february/11.35.html">Five Streams of the Emerging Church<strong> </strong></a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.christianitytoday.com/ct/2007/february/11.35.html"><strong>Scot McKnight</strong> </a>| posted 1/19/2007</p>
<p>Following are five themes that characterize the emerging movement. I see them as streams flowing into the emerging lake. No one says the emerging movement is the only group of Christians doing these things, but together they crystallize into the emerging movement.</p>
<p><strong>Prophetic (or at least provocative)</strong></p>
<p>One of the streams flowing into the emerging lake is prophetic rhetoric. The emerging movement is consciously and deliberately provocative. Emerging Christians believe the church needs to change, and they are beginning to live as if that change had already occurred. Since I swim in the emerging lake, I can self-critically admit that we sometimes exaggerate.</p>
<p>Brian McLaren in Generous Orthodoxy: &#8220;Often I don&#8217;t think Jesus would be caught dead as a Christian, were he physically here today. … Generally, I don&#8217;t think Christians would like Jesus if he showed up today as he did 2,000 years ago. In fact, I think we&#8217;d call him a heretic and plot to kill him, too.&#8221; McLaren, on the very next page, calls this statement an exaggeration. Still, the rhetoric is in place..</p>
<p><strong>Postmodern: </strong>Mark Twain said the mistake God made was in not forbidding Adam to eat the serpent. Had God forbidden the serpent, Adam would certainly have eaten him. When the evangelical world prohibited postmodernity, as if it were fruit from the forbidden tree, the postmodern &#8220;fallen&#8221; among us—like F. LeRon Shults, Jamie Smith, Kevin Vanhoozer, John Franke, and Peter Rollins—chose to eat it to see what it might taste like. We found that it tasted good, even if at times we found ourselves spitting out hard chunks of nonsense. Postmodernity is the collapse of inherited metanarratives (overarching explanations of life)</p>
<p>Jamie Smith, a professor at Calvin College, argues in <em>Who&#8217;s Afraid of Postmodernity?</em> (Baker Academic, 2006) that such thinking is compatible, in some ways, with classical Augustinian epistemology.</p>
<p>Others minister <em>with</em> postmoderns. That is, they live with, work with, and converse with postmoderns, accepting their postmodernity as a fact of life in our world. Such Christians view postmodernity as a present condition into which we are called to proclaim and live out the gospel.</p>
<p>They don&#8217;t deny truth, they don&#8217;t deny that Jesus Christ is truth, and they don&#8217;t deny the Bible is truth.</p>
<p>From a theological perspective, this fixation with propositions can easily lead to the attempt to use the finite tool of language on an absolute Presence that transcends and embraces all finite reality. Languages are culturally constructed symbol systems that enable humans to communicate by designating one finite reality in distinction from another. The truly infinite God of Christian faith is beyond all our linguistic grasping, as all the great theologians from Irenaeus to Calvin have insisted, and so the struggle to capture God in our finite propositional structures is nothing short of linguistic idolatry.</p>
<p><strong>Praxis-oriented</strong></p>
<p><strong>Worship:</strong> I&#8217;ve heard folks describe the emerging movement as &#8220;funky worship&#8221; or &#8220;candles and incense&#8221; or &#8220;smells and bells.&#8221; It&#8217;s true; many in the emerging movement are creative, experiential, and sensory in their worship gatherings.</p>
<p>They ask these sorts of questions: Is the sermon the most important thing on Sunday morning? If we sat in a circle would we foster a different theology and praxis? If we lit incense, would we practice our prayers differently? If we put the preacher on the same level as the congregation, would we create a clearer sense of the priesthood of all believers?</p>
<p><strong>Orthopraxy:</strong> A notable emphasis of the emerging movement is orthopraxy, that is, right living. The contention is that <em>how a person lives</em> is more important than <em>what he or she believes</em>. Many will immediately claim that we need both or that orthopraxy flows from orthodoxy. Most in the emerging movement agree we need both, but they contest the second claim: Experience does not prove that those who <em>believe</em> the right things <em>live</em> the right way. No matter how much sense the traditional connection makes, it does not necessarily work itself out in practice. Public scandals in the church—along with those not made public—prove this point time and again.</p>
<p><strong>Missional:</strong> The foremost concern of the praxis stream is being <em>missional</em>. What does this mean? First, the emerging movement becomes missional by participating, with God, in the redemptive work of God in this world.  Second, it seeks to become missional by participating in the community where God&#8217;s redemptive work occurs. The church is the community through which God works and in which God manifests the credibility of the gospel.Third, becoming missional means participating in the holistic redemptive work of God in this world. The Spirit groans, the creation groans, and we groan for the redemption of God</p>
<p><strong>Post-evangelical &#8211;</strong>-A fourth stream flowing into the emerging lake is characterized by the term <em>post-evangelical</em>. The emerging movement is a protest against much of evangelicalism as currently practiced. It is post-evangelical in the way that neo-evangelicalism (in the 1950s) was post-fundamentalist. It would not be unfair to call it postmodern evangelicalism. This stream flows from the conviction that the church must always be reforming itself.</p>
<p>The vast majority of emerging Christians are evangelical theologically. But they are post-evangelical in at least two ways.</p>
<p><strong>Post-systematic theology:</strong> The emerging movement tends to be suspicious of systematic theology. Why? Not because we don&#8217;t read systematics, but because the diversity of theologies alarms us, no genuine consensus has been achieved, God didn&#8217;t reveal a systematic theology but a storied narrative, and no language is capable of capturing the Absolute Truth who alone is God. Frankly, the emerging movement loves ideas and theology. It just doesn&#8217;t have an airtight system or statement of faith.</p>
<p>Hence, a trademark feature of the emerging movement is that we believe all theology will remain a conversation about the Truth who is God in Christ through the Spirit, and about God&#8217;s story of redemption at work in the church. No systematic theology can be final.</p>
<p><strong>In versus out:</strong> An admittedly controversial element of <strong>post-evangelicalism is that many in the emerging movement are skeptical about the &#8220;in versus out&#8221; mentality of much of evangelicalism.</strong> Even if one is an exclusivist (believing that there is a dividing line between Christians and non-Christians), the issue of who is in and who is out pains the emerging generation. This emerging ambivalence about who is in and who is out creates a serious problem for evangelism.</p>
<p><strong>Political</strong> A final stream flowing into the emerging lake is politics. Tony Jones is regularly told that the emerging movement is a latte-drinking, backpack-lugging, Birkenstock-wearing group of 21st-century, left-wing, hippie wannabes. Put directly, they are Democrats. And that spells &#8220;post&#8221; for conservative-evangelical-politics-as-usual.</p></blockquote>
<p><strong>Now—where does this apply to the new generation of modern Orthodox Jews and where do they differ? Why? This is not Baby-boomer liberal Orthodoxy – so where is it going? Do not take this one article and treat it as the definitive word or as the best definition. Dont make it into a Truth. There are many other articles, books, and differing opinions on Emergents, especially since it is a conversation. It was chosen as a temporary quck -fix for clarity. But the question is where do Jews fit into the conversation?</strong> <strong>Which of these five points apply to Young Jews and which dont?</strong></p>
<p>© Alan Brill 2010</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/01/the-emergent-church-and-orthodoxy/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>14</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Disappointed Belief – more to ponder on post-evangelical and its Jewish parallels.</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/14/disappointed-belief-%e2%80%93-more-to-ponder-on-post-evangelical-and-its-jewish-parallels/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/14/disappointed-belief-%e2%80%93-more-to-ponder-on-post-evangelical-and-its-jewish-parallels/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2009 23:37:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[popular religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christine Smallwood]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[James Wood]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[killing the buddha]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Malcolm Gladwell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[post-evangelical]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[post-orthodox]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=359</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[To help clarify those who thought that the prior post on post-evangelical-here had something to do with post-modern, or Post- Toasties. Let us recap,  the last 30 years witnessed a major upturn in conservative religion, many of the children are &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/14/disappointed-belief-%e2%80%93-more-to-ponder-on-post-evangelical-and-its-jewish-parallels/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>To help clarify those who thought that the<a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/19/is-there-a-post-orthodox-judaism-that-corresponds-to-post-evangelical/"> prior post on post-evangelical-here </a>had something to do with post-modern, or Post- Toasties. Let us recap,  the last 30 years witnessed a major upturn in conservative religion, many of the children are moving on to new positions. But they do so as ex-Evangelicals who are no longer believers or observant, they do not become liberals or mainline.</p>
<p>Here we have a recent panel on the topic. Some of the interesting points: They did not portray their religious years as dark or anti-intellectual, but they found that the plausibility structure had broken. I wish the interviewer had spent more time asking specifics on what was no longer tenable. From the full article, one gets a sense that liberal political views rendered one outside the community, as does commitment to being an intellectual and not just educated.</p>
<p>I find it fascinating that their own narratives start with why their parents became Evangelical in the first place. Also that they are left with a moral sense for literature and ideas.  And as the article itself points out they are left disappointed. What will fill that disappointment for them? Their families? SO how does this play out for Judaism?</p>
<blockquote><p><a href="http://killingthebuddha.com/ktblog/new-york-literati-on-growing-up-evangelical/">New York Literati on Growing Up Evangelical </a>by Kiera Feldman</p>
<p>Malcolm Gladwell and James Wood of The New Yorker and Christine Smallwood of The Nation…discussed how their intellectual lives were shaped by their religious backgrounds. Notably, evangelicalism was not portrayed as something one must inevitably cast-off to live a life of the mind; there were no narratives of recovery, of journeys from the darkness of ignorant faith to the light of reason. To varying degrees, all three panelists traced their thinking to their evangelical upbringings—yet not a one of them today is among the believers.<br />
Gladwell described his upbringing in Canada as liberal evangelical (though his parents, brother, and sister-in-law have since become Mennonites). He seemed to understand his religious self in patrilineal terms, focusing on the story of his father’s faith in lieu of his own. We learned that his father, has spent a lifetime trying to reconcile faith and reason. Ultimately, Gladwell didn’t find these efforts “convincing.” Yet he inherited his father’s project. I have remained within the evangelical tradition,”<br />
Wood called for a “disappointed belief,” but stopped short of explaining what, exactly, that might entail.<br />
All three cited its influence on their modes of reading today. Wood described himself as “marked” by the idea of “high stakes” in literature.<br />
What to put in the hole left by the loss of belief? Alas, nothing, said Gladwell. “My life is less full and real as a result,” he said.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/14/disappointed-belief-%e2%80%93-more-to-ponder-on-post-evangelical-and-its-jewish-parallels/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Is there a Post-Orthodox Judaism that Corresponds to Post Evangelical?</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/19/is-there-a-post-orthodox-judaism-that-corresponds-to-post-evangelical/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/19/is-there-a-post-orthodox-judaism-that-corresponds-to-post-evangelical/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2009 17:49:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[popular religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sociology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Internet Monk]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[post-evangelical]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[post-orthodox]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=293</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Many of those who were raised as Evangelical in the recent Great Awakening of Religion are not returning to the Evangelical Faith of their parents. Statistics vary from 25%-80%. The Great return to religion is winding down.&#160; Those raised with &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/19/is-there-a-post-orthodox-judaism-that-corresponds-to-post-evangelical/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Many of those who were raised as Evangelical in the recent Great Awakening of Religion are not returning to the Evangelical Faith of their parents. Statistics vary from 25%-80%. The Great return to religion is winding down.&nbsp; Those raised with an intense Evangelical faith don&#8217;t naturally blend back into&nbsp; mainline liberal Churches. They are specifically ex-evangelicals who have adapted liberal position.</p>
<p>So too in American Judaism, despite the triumphalism of orthodoxy Judiasm in the last quarter century and phony online statistics &#8211; Orthodoxy is witnessing similar phenomena.&nbsp; We also have a large number of people who are ex-Orthodox, not believing in what they were taught, and adopting liberal positions but that does not mean they are comfortable with liberal Judiasm. Read the following and ask yourself: <b>how many of them also apply to someone distancing him/herself from his/her Orthodox upbringing?</b> <b>How many are being argued on the Jewish blogs?</b></p>
<blockquote><p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Post-evangelical"><b>Post-evangelicalism</b></a> is a term used to describe former adherents of Evangelicalism. includes a variety of people who have distanced themselves from mainstream evangelical Christianity for theological, political, or cultural reasons. Most who describe themselves as post-evangelical are still adherents of the Christian faith in some form.</p>
<p>Post-evangelical critiques of the evangelical church concern include but are not limited to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Individualism and lack of theological depth</li>
<li>Anti-intellectualism</li>
<li>Narrow or excessively partisan political views</li>
<li>Lack of engagement in art, media, and society</li>
<li>Materialism and consumerism</li>
<li>Insensitivity toward homosexuals</li>
</ul>
<p>Christianity Today explains that post-evangelicals have become willingly disassociated with the mainstream evangelical belief system over difficulties with any combination of at least the following issues:</p>
<p>1. Questions over Biblical innerrancy. Questions may relate to the Biblical record of history, contradictions between scientific and scriptural explanations of the nature of the Universe and humanity (e.g., the origin of the Universe, homosexuality) or the discrepancies in descriptions of the personality of God in the different books of the Bible. Shrouding these issues, are are how the cultural understandings and lingustical limitations of the written word have influenced the way Scripture has been recorded and handed down throughout the ages.</p>
<p>2 The moral failure of prominent evangelical leaders. Such failure has cast doubt over the entire evangelical movement.</p>
<p>3 &nbsp;Many post-evangelicals have come of age during times of increasing multi-cultural awareness in Western society. They are presented with the educational lessons of the validity of all cultures and necessity for a pluralistic world-view.</p>
<p>Publications identifying as post-evangelical include the blog <a href="http://www.internetmonk.com/">Internet Monk </a></p></blockquote>
<p>Now that was fun. How many sounded familiar? Any to add in the Jewish case?&nbsp;Do you think they have played themselves out in the same way in the Jewish community?</p>
<p>h/t &#8211;Here&nbsp; is a&nbsp;<a href="http://www.internetmonk.com/archive/three-questions-about-post-evangelicalism">recent blog post </a>from the blog InternetMonk on the topic.</p>
<p><b>Update-</b>&nbsp;<b><a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/01/the-emergent-church-and-orthodoxy/">please see this blog&#8217;s continued discussion on post-evangelical here.</a> This one is important for the discussion of post-orthodox,</b> and further discussion here <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/20/post-orthodoxy-and-post-evangelicalism-again/">on post-Orthodox,</a> &lt;a<br />
<a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/27/post-is-the-name-of-a-breakfast-cereal/">And on the idea of labels and&nbsp; &#8220;post&#8221; see here</a><br />
<a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/29/rick-warrens-new-agendawhat-we-can-learn-from-it/">And here on some of the changes within the evangelicals that may play itself out among Jews.</a></p>
<p><strong>Update Dec 2012-</strong> <strong>After three years, the concept of a post-Orthodox moment still seems valid. Here are some later posts on the same topic.</strong><br />
A <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/20/post-orthodoxy-and-post-evangelicalism-again/">continuation of this post defining post-Orthodox- here,</a><br />
<a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/29/erosion-beyond-post-orthodox/">A 2011 update on erosion- here</a>,<br />
 <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/30/1980%E2%80%99s-and-the-coining-of-the-term-post-orthodox/">the history of the term- here. </a></p>
<p>Copyright © 2009 · All Rights Reserved</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/19/is-there-a-post-orthodox-judaism-that-corresponds-to-post-evangelical/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>11</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
