<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Zachary Braiterman takes on the Tikvah Fund, Jewish Review of Books, and Jewish Ideas Daily	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/06/zachary-braiterman-takes-on-the-tikvah-fund-jewish-review-of-books-and-jid/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/06/zachary-braiterman-takes-on-the-tikvah-fund-jewish-review-of-books-and-jid/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2011 19:57:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Josh		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/06/zachary-braiterman-takes-on-the-tikvah-fund-jewish-review-of-books-and-jid/#comment-3584</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2011 19:57:36 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4067#comment-3584</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/06/zachary-braiterman-takes-on-the-tikvah-fund-jewish-review-of-books-and-jid/#comment-3583&quot;&gt;AS&lt;/a&gt;.

Don&#039;t be disingenuous. That is politics in a very different sense from what we are discussing.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/06/zachary-braiterman-takes-on-the-tikvah-fund-jewish-review-of-books-and-jid/#comment-3583">AS</a>.</p>
<p>Don&#8217;t be disingenuous. That is politics in a very different sense from what we are discussing.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/06/zachary-braiterman-takes-on-the-tikvah-fund-jewish-review-of-books-and-jid/#comment-3583</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2011 19:43:11 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4067#comment-3583</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/06/zachary-braiterman-takes-on-the-tikvah-fund-jewish-review-of-books-and-jid/#comment-3582&quot;&gt;Josh&lt;/a&gt;.

I don&#039;t disagree, but I didn&#039;t think I was being cynical. As a student of academic Jewish studies one proceeds at one&#039;s peril without any sense of the various aims that were present from the beginnings of Wissenschaft and the continuing tensions within academic Jewish studies and its place in Jewish secularism.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/06/zachary-braiterman-takes-on-the-tikvah-fund-jewish-review-of-books-and-jid/#comment-3582">Josh</a>.</p>
<p>I don&#8217;t disagree, but I didn&#8217;t think I was being cynical. As a student of academic Jewish studies one proceeds at one&#8217;s peril without any sense of the various aims that were present from the beginnings of Wissenschaft and the continuing tensions within academic Jewish studies and its place in Jewish secularism.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Josh		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/06/zachary-braiterman-takes-on-the-tikvah-fund-jewish-review-of-books-and-jid/#comment-3582</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2011 18:11:52 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4067#comment-3582</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The cynicism that AS trots out with his quip about &quot;navigating&quot; the ideological rapids of academia strikes me as incompatible with many of the self described goals of many academic fields. It does not seem clear to me how american notions of Liberalism or Conservatism would map onto, lets say, Shlomo Ibn Gabirol, Leone Modena, Paul Celan. Or what it would tell us about Phenomenology for that matter. It seems like the dichotomies of our politics are a lot less fertile than the same fissures in (for example) German politics in the 18th-20th Centuries, which gave us everyone from Bruno Bauer and Arnold Gehlen to Adorno. For some reason, the fights between Habermas and Schmitt seem more relevant even to understanding Zohar than whatever the American equivalent would be. So yeah, its all political. And all politics are not created equal.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The cynicism that AS trots out with his quip about &#8220;navigating&#8221; the ideological rapids of academia strikes me as incompatible with many of the self described goals of many academic fields. It does not seem clear to me how american notions of Liberalism or Conservatism would map onto, lets say, Shlomo Ibn Gabirol, Leone Modena, Paul Celan. Or what it would tell us about Phenomenology for that matter. It seems like the dichotomies of our politics are a lot less fertile than the same fissures in (for example) German politics in the 18th-20th Centuries, which gave us everyone from Bruno Bauer and Arnold Gehlen to Adorno. For some reason, the fights between Habermas and Schmitt seem more relevant even to understanding Zohar than whatever the American equivalent would be. So yeah, its all political. And all politics are not created equal.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Arie Folger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/06/zachary-braiterman-takes-on-the-tikvah-fund-jewish-review-of-books-and-jid/#comment-3581</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arie Folger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2011 12:26:11 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4067#comment-3581</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Methinks the lady doth protest too much. Isn&#039;t he implying that absent the Tikva Fund, there might be similar opposite sources at play that may have denied people the freedom to express more conservative views in academia? Aren&#039;t the Liberal rabbinical schools and related institutions almost reflexively liberal? So what would the world look like without Tikva (or rather, what did it look like before Tikva)?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Methinks the lady doth protest too much. Isn&#8217;t he implying that absent the Tikva Fund, there might be similar opposite sources at play that may have denied people the freedom to express more conservative views in academia? Aren&#8217;t the Liberal rabbinical schools and related institutions almost reflexively liberal? So what would the world look like without Tikva (or rather, what did it look like before Tikva)?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/06/zachary-braiterman-takes-on-the-tikvah-fund-jewish-review-of-books-and-jid/#comment-3580</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2011 10:34:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4067#comment-3580</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This article has two parts that make different points. One is about the  activities of the Tikvah fund in connection with academic Jewish Studies. This seems to me to be the more problematic issue. Yet, it seems that with a somewhat more open declaration of its agenda the problems would be mitigated to a large extent. The second issue, that the JRB has an agenda, seems like something of a non-issue. If you are reading it on a semi-regular basis then you could probably figure that out without too much difficulty, and as far as I know few magazines or journals put the words &quot;liberal,or &quot;conservative&quot; in their masthead. Now, whatever the ultimate goal of Tikvah is vis a vis JRB, can we all agree that giving money to people to write articles with little mass appeal will have little effect on much of anything? Further, Braiterman really pushes an idea of ideological guilt by association: Take for instance his remarks on a review by Shaul Maggid:

&quot;Appearing in a Review whose animus against liberalism and Jewish Renewal is across the board, even the most cautious embrace of a religious tradition or the mildest criticism of new forms of Jewish expression take a conservative slant the reviewer never intended.&quot;

This seems to me more attempt at at a subtle rebuke of the author for deigning to be published in JRB. The idea that the review takes a slant not intended by the author is ludicrous unless it was subtly edited by the magazine.

One last point: &quot;It is my contention that non-partisan and apolitical scholarship and even moderate left of center political opinion (usually related to Israel) are used as cover to insinuate conservative ideas about Jewish religion and culture into a more liberal American Jewish milieu.&quot; Whether this is true or not, look at it from a right wing Israeli academic&#039;s perspective: conservative ideas about Jewish religion and culture are used to insinuate left of center political opinion related to Israel.

Instead it seems to me that this simply is the hybrid position of places funded by Tikvah like the Shalem Center: attempts at reconstituting traditional aspects of Jewish religion and culture with (at least by Israeli standards) left of center political thought.

In any case, as someone who is both younger and part of a younger branch of academia that has attained degree of political importance I tend to see this kind of ideological background as part of the academic landscape that one learns to navigate. In my field the perceived liberal tilt of the academic mainstream is now countered by a concerted effort to fund conservative think tanks and publications. And that fact is not apparent by merely visiting their websites. Perhaps it has been naive thus far of those in Jewish studies to deny that the field, by its very subject matter is , at its core, intensely political.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This article has two parts that make different points. One is about the  activities of the Tikvah fund in connection with academic Jewish Studies. This seems to me to be the more problematic issue. Yet, it seems that with a somewhat more open declaration of its agenda the problems would be mitigated to a large extent. The second issue, that the JRB has an agenda, seems like something of a non-issue. If you are reading it on a semi-regular basis then you could probably figure that out without too much difficulty, and as far as I know few magazines or journals put the words &#8220;liberal,or &#8220;conservative&#8221; in their masthead. Now, whatever the ultimate goal of Tikvah is vis a vis JRB, can we all agree that giving money to people to write articles with little mass appeal will have little effect on much of anything? Further, Braiterman really pushes an idea of ideological guilt by association: Take for instance his remarks on a review by Shaul Maggid:</p>
<p>&#8220;Appearing in a Review whose animus against liberalism and Jewish Renewal is across the board, even the most cautious embrace of a religious tradition or the mildest criticism of new forms of Jewish expression take a conservative slant the reviewer never intended.&#8221;</p>
<p>This seems to me more attempt at at a subtle rebuke of the author for deigning to be published in JRB. The idea that the review takes a slant not intended by the author is ludicrous unless it was subtly edited by the magazine.</p>
<p>One last point: &#8220;It is my contention that non-partisan and apolitical scholarship and even moderate left of center political opinion (usually related to Israel) are used as cover to insinuate conservative ideas about Jewish religion and culture into a more liberal American Jewish milieu.&#8221; Whether this is true or not, look at it from a right wing Israeli academic&#8217;s perspective: conservative ideas about Jewish religion and culture are used to insinuate left of center political opinion related to Israel.</p>
<p>Instead it seems to me that this simply is the hybrid position of places funded by Tikvah like the Shalem Center: attempts at reconstituting traditional aspects of Jewish religion and culture with (at least by Israeli standards) left of center political thought.</p>
<p>In any case, as someone who is both younger and part of a younger branch of academia that has attained degree of political importance I tend to see this kind of ideological background as part of the academic landscape that one learns to navigate. In my field the perceived liberal tilt of the academic mainstream is now countered by a concerted effort to fund conservative think tanks and publications. And that fact is not apparent by merely visiting their websites. Perhaps it has been naive thus far of those in Jewish studies to deny that the field, by its very subject matter is , at its core, intensely political.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Chris E		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/06/zachary-braiterman-takes-on-the-tikvah-fund-jewish-review-of-books-and-jid/#comment-3579</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chris E]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2011 09:33:51 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4067#comment-3579</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Taking the first review - I often wonder whether certain neo-conservatives use of the Noble Lie/Useful fiction doesn&#039;t undermine their project in the long term.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Taking the first review &#8211; I often wonder whether certain neo-conservatives use of the Noble Lie/Useful fiction doesn&#8217;t undermine their project in the long term.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Shai Secunda		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/06/zachary-braiterman-takes-on-the-tikvah-fund-jewish-review-of-books-and-jid/#comment-3578</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shai Secunda]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2011 08:16:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4067#comment-3578</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[There&#039;s so much to investigate and discuss with Tikvah&#039;s influence. Instead, Braiterman goes ahead and &quot;proves&quot; that the Jewish Review of Book&#039;s politics are right-leaning. And therefore? And Zeek&#039;s are left leaning. And therefore? I view that as a wasted opportunity . Also, I challenge anyone to read the review and substitute the word &quot;liberal&quot; for &quot;conservative&quot; - for those readers who don&#039;t view &quot;conservative&quot; as a bad word, it&#039;s unclear what the problem is. Finally, his mental acrobatics for defending Posen are more than a stretch - especially when he admits to receiving funding from them. 
Finally, he hopelessly confuses &quot;Neo-con&quot; and &quot;Orthodox Jewish&quot; and much much more in his misguided &quot;numerical&quot; analysis of JRB.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There&#8217;s so much to investigate and discuss with Tikvah&#8217;s influence. Instead, Braiterman goes ahead and &#8220;proves&#8221; that the Jewish Review of Book&#8217;s politics are right-leaning. And therefore? And Zeek&#8217;s are left leaning. And therefore? I view that as a wasted opportunity . Also, I challenge anyone to read the review and substitute the word &#8220;liberal&#8221; for &#8220;conservative&#8221; &#8211; for those readers who don&#8217;t view &#8220;conservative&#8221; as a bad word, it&#8217;s unclear what the problem is. Finally, his mental acrobatics for defending Posen are more than a stretch &#8211; especially when he admits to receiving funding from them.<br />
Finally, he hopelessly confuses &#8220;Neo-con&#8221; and &#8220;Orthodox Jewish&#8221; and much much more in his misguided &#8220;numerical&#8221; analysis of JRB.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Jon		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/06/zachary-braiterman-takes-on-the-tikvah-fund-jewish-review-of-books-and-jid/#comment-3577</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jon]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2011 03:53:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4067#comment-3577</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Come on. Braiterman needs a lot more than that to substantiate an accusation like that. Otherwise I could do the same thing back - Braiterman is a (if I remember correctly) secular Jew specializing in liberal Jewish thought, and wants to undermine anything put out by the Tikvah Fund by painting it with the brush of evil right-wingedness. Any suggestion that he is merely interested in the effect the Tikvah Fund has on academic freedom is merely a front for his pugnacious secularism and creates a neutral space for his anti-religious ideas that would not receive the same positive attention otherwise.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Come on. Braiterman needs a lot more than that to substantiate an accusation like that. Otherwise I could do the same thing back &#8211; Braiterman is a (if I remember correctly) secular Jew specializing in liberal Jewish thought, and wants to undermine anything put out by the Tikvah Fund by painting it with the brush of evil right-wingedness. Any suggestion that he is merely interested in the effect the Tikvah Fund has on academic freedom is merely a front for his pugnacious secularism and creates a neutral space for his anti-religious ideas that would not receive the same positive attention otherwise.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Larry Yudelson		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/06/zachary-braiterman-takes-on-the-tikvah-fund-jewish-review-of-books-and-jid/#comment-3576</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Larry Yudelson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2011 03:45:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4067#comment-3576</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[He accurately pegs JROB of aspiring towards Commentary at its 1965 heyday. He neglects to include an important corollary: All Jewish scholarship since 1965 has no place in the journal. Most notably, that includes Neusner&#039;s discovery that things they say in the Talmud ain&#039;t necessarily so, as well as the post-Hertz acceptance of the Documentary Hypothesis. The result is a journal incapable of reviewing the university press volumes that advertise in its pages.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>He accurately pegs JROB of aspiring towards Commentary at its 1965 heyday. He neglects to include an important corollary: All Jewish scholarship since 1965 has no place in the journal. Most notably, that includes Neusner&#8217;s discovery that things they say in the Talmud ain&#8217;t necessarily so, as well as the post-Hertz acceptance of the Documentary Hypothesis. The result is a journal incapable of reviewing the university press volumes that advertise in its pages.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
