<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: The New Metaphysicals Post #2	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/06/the-new-metaphysicals-post-2/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/06/the-new-metaphysicals-post-2/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2010 10:51:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Kevin Rothman		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/06/the-new-metaphysicals-post-2/#comment-1298</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kevin Rothman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2010 10:51:32 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1622#comment-1298</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[though i would also like to add that this is, in my opinion, only due to an unnecessary interpretation of &quot;faith&quot; as &quot;belief in&quot; ... i.e. faith as a form of knowledge instead of &quot;faithful to&quot; or &quot;in faith with&quot;... working from the latter standpoint all of these questions become superfluous]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>though i would also like to add that this is, in my opinion, only due to an unnecessary interpretation of &#8220;faith&#8221; as &#8220;belief in&#8221; &#8230; i.e. faith as a form of knowledge instead of &#8220;faithful to&#8221; or &#8220;in faith with&#8221;&#8230; working from the latter standpoint all of these questions become superfluous</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Kevin Rothman		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/06/the-new-metaphysicals-post-2/#comment-1297</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kevin Rothman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2010 10:47:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1622#comment-1297</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I do not think that neo-hasidim are alone in their rejection of western canons, even within orthodox judaism.  I know many many quite mainstream people who show great mistrust of the medical establishment and prefer practitioners of homeopathy etc.  with no demonstrated medical value.  Aside from breslovers who follow a specific injunction to avoid doctors at all costs, I see this in two lights:

1- the rejection of western knowledge re-affirms adoption of traditional values
2-there is a perceived antagonism of the establishment towards minority groups (often true).  When I worked as a teacher in liberty city (urban slum) in miami many many families consulted the voudoo doctors (there are many hatians in the neighborhood) instead of medical doctors because they felt de-valued and ignored by the latter.  

i think that the use of scientific terms while rejecting science speaks to a certain wishful thinking: that science itself will demonstrate its own falsehood (which is the very argument that the Lubavitcher Rebbe attempts to make in many of his letters on the subject)

but beyond that, does not all orthodoxy at some level have to reject the notion of western science  as-free-inquiry?  there is a great deal that can and should be put up to debate even within orthodoxy, but certain things can never go up for debate without orthodoxy ceasing to be orthodox.  Eg. what if it could somehow be proven without a shadow of a doubt that there never was a mass gathering at Sinai.  While it could reasonably be argued: the point is not whether it happened or not, but that in principle we ground the legitimacy of our law in divine mandate.... this is not orthodoxy; the validity of the law is grounded in its formal institutionalization at sinai by God.  but to retain this construction of validity would then demand an explicit valuation of belief over fact; it would be to reject the western canon.  So i think the question becomes more blatant among the new-agers, but it runs much deeper... to the core of revealed religion itself (not just jewish orthodoxy)]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I do not think that neo-hasidim are alone in their rejection of western canons, even within orthodox judaism.  I know many many quite mainstream people who show great mistrust of the medical establishment and prefer practitioners of homeopathy etc.  with no demonstrated medical value.  Aside from breslovers who follow a specific injunction to avoid doctors at all costs, I see this in two lights:</p>
<p>1- the rejection of western knowledge re-affirms adoption of traditional values<br />
2-there is a perceived antagonism of the establishment towards minority groups (often true).  When I worked as a teacher in liberty city (urban slum) in miami many many families consulted the voudoo doctors (there are many hatians in the neighborhood) instead of medical doctors because they felt de-valued and ignored by the latter.  </p>
<p>i think that the use of scientific terms while rejecting science speaks to a certain wishful thinking: that science itself will demonstrate its own falsehood (which is the very argument that the Lubavitcher Rebbe attempts to make in many of his letters on the subject)</p>
<p>but beyond that, does not all orthodoxy at some level have to reject the notion of western science  as-free-inquiry?  there is a great deal that can and should be put up to debate even within orthodoxy, but certain things can never go up for debate without orthodoxy ceasing to be orthodox.  Eg. what if it could somehow be proven without a shadow of a doubt that there never was a mass gathering at Sinai.  While it could reasonably be argued: the point is not whether it happened or not, but that in principle we ground the legitimacy of our law in divine mandate&#8230;. this is not orthodoxy; the validity of the law is grounded in its formal institutionalization at sinai by God.  but to retain this construction of validity would then demand an explicit valuation of belief over fact; it would be to reject the western canon.  So i think the question becomes more blatant among the new-agers, but it runs much deeper&#8230; to the core of revealed religion itself (not just jewish orthodoxy)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
