<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Orthodoxy Both Uncomfortable and Envious Of Evangelicals	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/27/orthodoxy-both-uncomfortable-and-envious-of-evangelicals/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/27/orthodoxy-both-uncomfortable-and-envious-of-evangelicals/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2011 05:01:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: HS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/27/orthodoxy-both-uncomfortable-and-envious-of-evangelicals/#comment-3427</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[HS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2011 05:01:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3930#comment-3427</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/27/orthodoxy-both-uncomfortable-and-envious-of-evangelicals/#comment-3426&quot;&gt;chakira&lt;/a&gt;.

A rabbi introducing &quot;shabbat casual&quot;  would most likely occur in an area where there is only one Modern Orthodox institution (or, one Orthodox institution).  If there is more than one, that rabbi would be more easily subject to negative comparison, simply on the basis of clothing.  The rabbi would also be likely well-established and/or tenured, such that the rabbi is less likely to feel a need to take measures to appear formal.   Yet, the rabbi would need to be young enough to want to take this unusual stand of informality, and confident enough to look good without the additional layers.  

So you&#039;re looking for rabbi with 5-10 years in a one-shul town, to start this trend.  Maybe you can find Prof. Brill some sermons too.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/27/orthodoxy-both-uncomfortable-and-envious-of-evangelicals/#comment-3426">chakira</a>.</p>
<p>A rabbi introducing &#8220;shabbat casual&#8221;  would most likely occur in an area where there is only one Modern Orthodox institution (or, one Orthodox institution).  If there is more than one, that rabbi would be more easily subject to negative comparison, simply on the basis of clothing.  The rabbi would also be likely well-established and/or tenured, such that the rabbi is less likely to feel a need to take measures to appear formal.   Yet, the rabbi would need to be young enough to want to take this unusual stand of informality, and confident enough to look good without the additional layers.  </p>
<p>So you&#8217;re looking for rabbi with 5-10 years in a one-shul town, to start this trend.  Maybe you can find Prof. Brill some sermons too.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: chakira		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/27/orthodoxy-both-uncomfortable-and-envious-of-evangelicals/#comment-3426</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[chakira]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Jul 2011 21:32:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3930#comment-3426</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I have a more prosaic and sartorial question. When will we see Orthodoxy drop the aesthetic pretense and emulate the positive, down home style of Evangelicals? Really, really, we need to not wear suits every shabbos in the summer. Someone needs to be the first Rabbi to wear a nice polo shirt and khakis. It is so weird to make shul an extension of the office, at least as far as black suits are concerned. Modern Orthodox Jews actually already spend more than enough time in such drab attire]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have a more prosaic and sartorial question. When will we see Orthodoxy drop the aesthetic pretense and emulate the positive, down home style of Evangelicals? Really, really, we need to not wear suits every shabbos in the summer. Someone needs to be the first Rabbi to wear a nice polo shirt and khakis. It is so weird to make shul an extension of the office, at least as far as black suits are concerned. Modern Orthodox Jews actually already spend more than enough time in such drab attire</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Ariel Rackovsky		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/27/orthodoxy-both-uncomfortable-and-envious-of-evangelicals/#comment-3424</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ariel Rackovsky]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Jul 2011 18:08:58 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3930#comment-3424</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This is a pretty educated crowd, who are quite well read. For those who don&#039;t necessarily know the terms,  I try and define them in context. For example, I gave a working definition of the term pre-millenial dispensation when I described it- &quot;even though many Christian Zionists are dispensational premillenialists who don’t believe they can do anything to hasten the arrival of the Messiah.&quot;

As far as how sacred envy of Evangelicals changes Orthodoxy, I&#039;m still not sure. Consider the sociological breakdown: The more chareidi elements are already quite unabashed about practicing Judaism openly and using political advantage to advocate for themselves, and are also the ones who, in the main, are involved in outreach. The &quot;flipped out&quot; generation of Modern Orthodoxy aligns with them. They don&#039;t necessarily need to be envious of evangelicals though they may interact with them on social issues . Those in the Modern Orthodox community who align with far-right Israeli causes also use the vocabulary of faith and Biblical promise in their support of Israel. This was aimed at more of a center-left crowd whose support of Israel is primarily on political grounds, who are discomfited by extremist, messianic rhetoric, who are not particularly involved in outreach  and who are often concerned about appearing or acting &quot;too religious.&quot; Whether they will embrace the challenge of evangelism, and how it will affect this community, remains to be seen.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is a pretty educated crowd, who are quite well read. For those who don&#8217;t necessarily know the terms,  I try and define them in context. For example, I gave a working definition of the term pre-millenial dispensation when I described it- &#8220;even though many Christian Zionists are dispensational premillenialists who don’t believe they can do anything to hasten the arrival of the Messiah.&#8221;</p>
<p>As far as how sacred envy of Evangelicals changes Orthodoxy, I&#8217;m still not sure. Consider the sociological breakdown: The more chareidi elements are already quite unabashed about practicing Judaism openly and using political advantage to advocate for themselves, and are also the ones who, in the main, are involved in outreach. The &#8220;flipped out&#8221; generation of Modern Orthodoxy aligns with them. They don&#8217;t necessarily need to be envious of evangelicals though they may interact with them on social issues . Those in the Modern Orthodox community who align with far-right Israeli causes also use the vocabulary of faith and Biblical promise in their support of Israel. This was aimed at more of a center-left crowd whose support of Israel is primarily on political grounds, who are discomfited by extremist, messianic rhetoric, who are not particularly involved in outreach  and who are often concerned about appearing or acting &#8220;too religious.&#8221; Whether they will embrace the challenge of evangelism, and how it will affect this community, remains to be seen.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: David Wolkenfeld		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/27/orthodoxy-both-uncomfortable-and-envious-of-evangelicals/#comment-3423</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[David Wolkenfeld]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Jul 2011 17:16:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3930#comment-3423</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Apropos to this discussion: See Leon Wieseltier&#039;s response to &quot;The Response&quot; on The New Republic website.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Apropos to this discussion: See Leon Wieseltier&#8217;s response to &#8220;The Response&#8221; on The New Republic website.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/27/orthodoxy-both-uncomfortable-and-envious-of-evangelicals/#comment-3422</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Jul 2011 16:01:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3930#comment-3422</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Ariel-
How do Orthodox congregants come to have knowledge of Evangelical terms like replacement theology and premillennial dispensation? How do they know enough to use the terms without your needing to define them in a sermon? 

How far do you see this sacred envy of Evangelicals changing Orthodoxy?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ariel-<br />
How do Orthodox congregants come to have knowledge of Evangelical terms like replacement theology and premillennial dispensation? How do they know enough to use the terms without your needing to define them in a sermon? </p>
<p>How far do you see this sacred envy of Evangelicals changing Orthodoxy?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Ariel Rackovsky		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/27/orthodoxy-both-uncomfortable-and-envious-of-evangelicals/#comment-3421</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ariel Rackovsky]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Jul 2011 15:46:26 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3930#comment-3421</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I am Ariel Rackovsky, who delivered the sermon in question- thank you for sharing and for the positive press! I delivered this sermon because the JC is exactly the demographic that is made extremely nervous by evangelical Christians. In truth, this sermon arose from a discussion I had with a friend of mine who is making aliyah in a few weeks, and who is going to be working together with Rabbis on educating evangelical Christians about Zionism and Israel. When he told me about the various Christian groups he was already interacting with, we began having an argument about their motives, intent and whether his new initiative represented &quot;sleeping with the enemy.&quot; He challenged me to evaluate the issue of Jewish Christian relations dispassionately, especially since  groups like CUFI are now becoming the establishment in terms of political support for Israel. Also helpful in formulating my thoughts were my friend Avraham Bronstein&#039;s descriptions of the Rev. John Hagee&#039;s visit to the Hampton Synagogue. I am still thinking about this issue, and how we are to profess our faith unabashedly in public as evangelical Christians do, especially as Orthodox clergy are (as you have pointed out in the past) borrowing the vocabulary and the institutional models of megachurches. 

Starting in mid November, I will be assuming the position of Rabbi at the Irving Place Minyan, a new minyan in Woodmere with some 120 families.   I hope to continue posting my sermons online there as well.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I am Ariel Rackovsky, who delivered the sermon in question- thank you for sharing and for the positive press! I delivered this sermon because the JC is exactly the demographic that is made extremely nervous by evangelical Christians. In truth, this sermon arose from a discussion I had with a friend of mine who is making aliyah in a few weeks, and who is going to be working together with Rabbis on educating evangelical Christians about Zionism and Israel. When he told me about the various Christian groups he was already interacting with, we began having an argument about their motives, intent and whether his new initiative represented &#8220;sleeping with the enemy.&#8221; He challenged me to evaluate the issue of Jewish Christian relations dispassionately, especially since  groups like CUFI are now becoming the establishment in terms of political support for Israel. Also helpful in formulating my thoughts were my friend Avraham Bronstein&#8217;s descriptions of the Rev. John Hagee&#8217;s visit to the Hampton Synagogue. I am still thinking about this issue, and how we are to profess our faith unabashedly in public as evangelical Christians do, especially as Orthodox clergy are (as you have pointed out in the past) borrowing the vocabulary and the institutional models of megachurches. </p>
<p>Starting in mid November, I will be assuming the position of Rabbi at the Irving Place Minyan, a new minyan in Woodmere with some 120 families.   I hope to continue posting my sermons online there as well.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: FL		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/27/orthodoxy-both-uncomfortable-and-envious-of-evangelicals/#comment-3420</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[FL]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Jul 2011 15:40:12 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3930#comment-3420</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Rabbi Shmuel Herzfeld posts his sermons at http://www.rabbishmuel.com/browse.cgi?type=torah_sermons
I believe some will be published next year.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rabbi Shmuel Herzfeld posts his sermons at <a href="http://www.rabbishmuel.com/browse.cgi?type=torah_sermons" rel="nofollow ugc">http://www.rabbishmuel.com/browse.cgi?type=torah_sermons</a><br />
I believe some will be published next year.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/27/orthodoxy-both-uncomfortable-and-envious-of-evangelicals/#comment-3419</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Jul 2011 14:59:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3930#comment-3419</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/27/orthodoxy-both-uncomfortable-and-envious-of-evangelicals/#comment-3418&quot;&gt;Elli&lt;/a&gt;.

Thank you. That is exactly what I am looking for. The Rabbis that give a sense of what is actually going on without having to be a talking head for an organization. Keep them coming. 
I still have not figured out how to separate wheat from chaff in twitter, maybe one is not supposed to.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/27/orthodoxy-both-uncomfortable-and-envious-of-evangelicals/#comment-3418">Elli</a>.</p>
<p>Thank you. That is exactly what I am looking for. The Rabbis that give a sense of what is actually going on without having to be a talking head for an organization. Keep them coming.<br />
I still have not figured out how to separate wheat from chaff in twitter, maybe one is not supposed to.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Elli		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/27/orthodoxy-both-uncomfortable-and-envious-of-evangelicals/#comment-3418</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Elli]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Jul 2011 14:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3930#comment-3418</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Rabbi Mitchell Wohlberg of Beth Tfiloh posts all of his sermons. http://www.bethtfiloh.com/sermons
He&#039;s a great darshan, but I&#039;m not sure if he&#039;s what you&#039;re looking for. He posts on his blog and on twitter, too.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rabbi Mitchell Wohlberg of Beth Tfiloh posts all of his sermons. <a href="http://www.bethtfiloh.com/sermons" rel="nofollow ugc">http://www.bethtfiloh.com/sermons</a><br />
He&#8217;s a great darshan, but I&#8217;m not sure if he&#8217;s what you&#8217;re looking for. He posts on his blog and on twitter, too.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
