<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Arthur Green- Radical Judaism #1 of 5 posts	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/06/arthur-green-radical-judaism-1/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/06/arthur-green-radical-judaism-1/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2010 04:44:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: evanstonjew		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/06/arthur-green-radical-judaism-1/#comment-793</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[evanstonjew]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2010 18:18:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1084#comment-793</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I have ordered but not yet read Rabbi Green&#039;s book, and everything depends on the details. What I am looking for is a constructive argument that panentheism is connected to a particular moral theory and politics. Just as materialism need not generate a Masrxist view or positing a transcendent God need not require an aristocratic hierarchy, what is it about process theology that ties it to a renewal program? 

I have learnt much from the book by Clayton and Peacocke &quot;In Whom We Live and Move and Have Our Being.&quot; There are so many different interpretations of what panentheist formulas come down to it is no easy matter to evaluate.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have ordered but not yet read Rabbi Green&#8217;s book, and everything depends on the details. What I am looking for is a constructive argument that panentheism is connected to a particular moral theory and politics. Just as materialism need not generate a Masrxist view or positing a transcendent God need not require an aristocratic hierarchy, what is it about process theology that ties it to a renewal program? </p>
<p>I have learnt much from the book by Clayton and Peacocke &#8220;In Whom We Live and Move and Have Our Being.&#8221; There are so many different interpretations of what panentheist formulas come down to it is no easy matter to evaluate.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: C.M.		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/06/arthur-green-radical-judaism-1/#comment-792</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[C.M.]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2010 09:47:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1084#comment-792</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/06/arthur-green-radical-judaism-1/#comment-790&quot;&gt;evanstonjew&lt;/a&gt;.

EJ- I think you are missing the point of what Green and others in his camp emphasize. They do not believe they are weakening the Jewish People or our future, and believe that they are offering a universalistic, reconstructionistic, ethical imperatives-oriented form of Judaism which speaks to contemporary sensibilities and psycho-spiritual yearnings, both from within and outside the tradition. However, I do agree with your claims, although I feel they are irrelevant and not germane to the topic at hand.  Yet, the entire gestalt does leave us at the end of the discussion with a dichotomy that will forever characterize religious dialogue and inquiry, a sort of archetypical element in all religions (to borrow from Jung)-  the conflict between universalism and particularism. It seems that in our diversity, the question becomes whether this dichotomy influences what we view as acceptable in the realm of ritual and practice. The CCAR views the challenges of particularism and universalism as having a clear manifest effect on practice, and clearly advocates blessing interfaith unions as part of their two-field belief- a) Universalism, and b) Incorporating the demands of the times into their &quot;halakhic&quot; praxis, as a  &quot;sha&#039;at dechak&quot; of sorts, for lack of a better term. 

The question is, however, in the theology of Green and his comrades, to what extent does halakha play a role, and how do these thinkers view ritual demands and the notion of being commanded amid their belief that what suits the individual relatively, psychologically, and spiritually can legitimately derive from both Non-Jewish and Jewish sources (although, I always do ask myself how these individuals can legitimately lay claim to a religious system, Hasidism, which itself stresses the importance of halakha and stringency at times, particularism, as in the case of the Tanya, although this is negligible, and in the case of the Polish schools of Ger and others, the necessity of be iyun study of the Talmud). I think it would be safe to say that lomdus and being medakdek in mitzvos are not priorities among Green&#039;s school, just as how I view the Carlebach minyan, a ubiquitous element of Neo-Hasidism, as utilized today, as a disingenuous and halakhically problematic phenomenon.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/06/arthur-green-radical-judaism-1/#comment-790">evanstonjew</a>.</p>
<p>EJ- I think you are missing the point of what Green and others in his camp emphasize. They do not believe they are weakening the Jewish People or our future, and believe that they are offering a universalistic, reconstructionistic, ethical imperatives-oriented form of Judaism which speaks to contemporary sensibilities and psycho-spiritual yearnings, both from within and outside the tradition. However, I do agree with your claims, although I feel they are irrelevant and not germane to the topic at hand.  Yet, the entire gestalt does leave us at the end of the discussion with a dichotomy that will forever characterize religious dialogue and inquiry, a sort of archetypical element in all religions (to borrow from Jung)-  the conflict between universalism and particularism. It seems that in our diversity, the question becomes whether this dichotomy influences what we view as acceptable in the realm of ritual and practice. The CCAR views the challenges of particularism and universalism as having a clear manifest effect on practice, and clearly advocates blessing interfaith unions as part of their two-field belief- a) Universalism, and b) Incorporating the demands of the times into their &#8220;halakhic&#8221; praxis, as a  &#8220;sha&#8217;at dechak&#8221; of sorts, for lack of a better term. </p>
<p>The question is, however, in the theology of Green and his comrades, to what extent does halakha play a role, and how do these thinkers view ritual demands and the notion of being commanded amid their belief that what suits the individual relatively, psychologically, and spiritually can legitimately derive from both Non-Jewish and Jewish sources (although, I always do ask myself how these individuals can legitimately lay claim to a religious system, Hasidism, which itself stresses the importance of halakha and stringency at times, particularism, as in the case of the Tanya, although this is negligible, and in the case of the Polish schools of Ger and others, the necessity of be iyun study of the Talmud). I think it would be safe to say that lomdus and being medakdek in mitzvos are not priorities among Green&#8217;s school, just as how I view the Carlebach minyan, a ubiquitous element of Neo-Hasidism, as utilized today, as a disingenuous and halakhically problematic phenomenon.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: evanstonjew		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/06/arthur-green-radical-judaism-1/#comment-790</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[evanstonjew]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2010 22:26:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1084#comment-790</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Being of a liberal temperament I can understand Judaism without dogmas. I’ve been around enough to see most Jews  think of Judaism as a religion without halacha. And being an old leftie, I personally think of  Judaism as without any allegiance to the decisions of the State of Israel. Even the Holocaust philosophically understood is without uniqueness; our blood is not redder than other victims of murder.  

After a while it occurred to me that perhaps Judaism is about being without…a religion without any qualities. But I shied away of such a prospect, color me charedi,  because like many others I have  a common history,  culture,  and community with other Jews and a special feeling for these Jews. From which it followed quite naturally, that I favor my people over others, just as I favor my family over others, both in their hopes and dreams as well as in their affliction and woes. 

If we follow this idea of  expansion of consciousness, where there is neither Jew nor Greek, where my moral, (not simply prudential) obligations includes  obligations to  things like rain forests and oceans, and of course endangered species, then the theologically important sense of peoplehood will disappear. From a high enough madreiga I can be in communion with my table. In such a space  grandiose ideas of connectedness to a world network taken quite literally seem plausible . We become in the end a religion without definiteness, without walls. 

The CCAR recently recommended that Reform rabbis participate in and perform intermarriages. Most American Jews have been thinking intermarriage is no big deal  for some time. I would conjecture  Rabbi Green’s theology  reinforces these  ideas.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Being of a liberal temperament I can understand Judaism without dogmas. I’ve been around enough to see most Jews  think of Judaism as a religion without halacha. And being an old leftie, I personally think of  Judaism as without any allegiance to the decisions of the State of Israel. Even the Holocaust philosophically understood is without uniqueness; our blood is not redder than other victims of murder.  </p>
<p>After a while it occurred to me that perhaps Judaism is about being without…a religion without any qualities. But I shied away of such a prospect, color me charedi,  because like many others I have  a common history,  culture,  and community with other Jews and a special feeling for these Jews. From which it followed quite naturally, that I favor my people over others, just as I favor my family over others, both in their hopes and dreams as well as in their affliction and woes. </p>
<p>If we follow this idea of  expansion of consciousness, where there is neither Jew nor Greek, where my moral, (not simply prudential) obligations includes  obligations to  things like rain forests and oceans, and of course endangered species, then the theologically important sense of peoplehood will disappear. From a high enough madreiga I can be in communion with my table. In such a space  grandiose ideas of connectedness to a world network taken quite literally seem plausible . We become in the end a religion without definiteness, without walls. </p>
<p>The CCAR recently recommended that Reform rabbis participate in and perform intermarriages. Most American Jews have been thinking intermarriage is no big deal  for some time. I would conjecture  Rabbi Green’s theology  reinforces these  ideas.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: C.M.		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/06/arthur-green-radical-judaism-1/#comment-784</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[C.M.]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2010 03:26:32 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1084#comment-784</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I concur- Green&#039;s view of God does seem to be comport with the way in which Eliade stresses hierophanies as establishing the sacred order in the world and rendering a sacred space of sorts, such as in Moshe before the burning bush. I also do see very strong concerns among those you cite- take Green&#039;s view of Shabbat. While he is the first to acknowledge that &quot;Shabbat, the day of holiness and rest, is the central religious institution of the Jewish people,&quot; he views this as independent of any halakhic strictures associated with Shmirat Shabbat and contends that Shabbat is about creating a sacred time and space for consciousness, as opposed to following the lamed -tet melakhot, as evidenced in his 10 commandments of Shabbat, which focus on interpersonal Ich-Du, and psychological  elements, and of course, encourage reading Heschel, as opposed to the Rav, who unlike the former, viewed Shabbat as precisely lamed-tet melakhot, as opposed to &quot;an island in time&quot; or any sort of neo-mystical constructions focusing on the dimensions of time and space.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I concur- Green&#8217;s view of God does seem to be comport with the way in which Eliade stresses hierophanies as establishing the sacred order in the world and rendering a sacred space of sorts, such as in Moshe before the burning bush. I also do see very strong concerns among those you cite- take Green&#8217;s view of Shabbat. While he is the first to acknowledge that &#8220;Shabbat, the day of holiness and rest, is the central religious institution of the Jewish people,&#8221; he views this as independent of any halakhic strictures associated with Shmirat Shabbat and contends that Shabbat is about creating a sacred time and space for consciousness, as opposed to following the lamed -tet melakhot, as evidenced in his 10 commandments of Shabbat, which focus on interpersonal Ich-Du, and psychological  elements, and of course, encourage reading Heschel, as opposed to the Rav, who unlike the former, viewed Shabbat as precisely lamed-tet melakhot, as opposed to &#8220;an island in time&#8221; or any sort of neo-mystical constructions focusing on the dimensions of time and space.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
