<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Fulbright Senior Scholar Award in Varanasi	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/27/fulbright-senior-scholar-award-in-varanasi/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/27/fulbright-senior-scholar-award-in-varanasi/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2013 12:29:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Irrelevant		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/27/fulbright-senior-scholar-award-in-varanasi/#comment-8954</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Irrelevant]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2013 12:29:20 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6309#comment-8954</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I have seen contradictions in different articles about whether HIndu views of monotheism are in response to Abrahamic religions or not. I&#039;d really appreciate any light shed. 

Thanks and Good Shabbos]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have seen contradictions in different articles about whether HIndu views of monotheism are in response to Abrahamic religions or not. I&#8217;d really appreciate any light shed. </p>
<p>Thanks and Good Shabbos</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Ira Rohde		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/27/fulbright-senior-scholar-award-in-varanasi/#comment-8944</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ira Rohde]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2013 04:05:03 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6309#comment-8944</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The project sounds interesting. I assume you are dealing with primarily with &quot;orthodox&quot; forms of Hinduism only, and not breakaway sects, such as Jains and Buddhists or Sikhs. How they define their Hindu &quot;orthodoxy&quot; should be interesting, since there is such a difference in practice among groups, and I assume that an &quot;orthopraxis&quot; definition of Hinduism is out of the question. How much are different groups Vishnu-centered or Shiva-centered or Brahma-centered? How much is worship still based upon other gods, local or otherwise? How is &quot;orthodoxy&quot; defined: Does it still have to do with affirming the authority of the Vedas and other canonized texts, even though these texts have in them reminiscences of sacrifices which are no longer performed? Do they still venerate the traditional &quot;shastras&quot; or Hindu &quot;tractates&quot;? How do they venerate and carry on their more philosophical and interpretive traditions, ancient and medieval? How is marriage linked to family ties and becoming a respected ba`al habayit, a householder, rather than on modern Western notions of romantic love?
I always find it inspiring that in India, older &quot;orthodox&quot; religious forms, (albeit transformed in many ways) based upon following an orchestrated way of life, largely succeeded (albeit over a long period of time) in their struggle with their &quot;daughter&quot; religions which began as heretical breakaways.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The project sounds interesting. I assume you are dealing with primarily with &#8220;orthodox&#8221; forms of Hinduism only, and not breakaway sects, such as Jains and Buddhists or Sikhs. How they define their Hindu &#8220;orthodoxy&#8221; should be interesting, since there is such a difference in practice among groups, and I assume that an &#8220;orthopraxis&#8221; definition of Hinduism is out of the question. How much are different groups Vishnu-centered or Shiva-centered or Brahma-centered? How much is worship still based upon other gods, local or otherwise? How is &#8220;orthodoxy&#8221; defined: Does it still have to do with affirming the authority of the Vedas and other canonized texts, even though these texts have in them reminiscences of sacrifices which are no longer performed? Do they still venerate the traditional &#8220;shastras&#8221; or Hindu &#8220;tractates&#8221;? How do they venerate and carry on their more philosophical and interpretive traditions, ancient and medieval? How is marriage linked to family ties and becoming a respected ba`al habayit, a householder, rather than on modern Western notions of romantic love?<br />
I always find it inspiring that in India, older &#8220;orthodox&#8221; religious forms, (albeit transformed in many ways) based upon following an orchestrated way of life, largely succeeded (albeit over a long period of time) in their struggle with their &#8220;daughter&#8221; religions which began as heretical breakaways.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Matty		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/27/fulbright-senior-scholar-award-in-varanasi/#comment-8935</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Matty]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2013 04:08:05 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6309#comment-8935</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Looks really beautiful and your project sounds fascinating. Is there any interaction, past or present, between the Sikh community and the Jewish community? Or are you focusing exclusively on Jewish-Hindu interactions?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Looks really beautiful and your project sounds fascinating. Is there any interaction, past or present, between the Sikh community and the Jewish community? Or are you focusing exclusively on Jewish-Hindu interactions?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Jon Baker		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/27/fulbright-senior-scholar-award-in-varanasi/#comment-8929</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jon Baker]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2013 19:04:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6309#comment-8929</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I see your reports from the Jewish-Hindu Summits, where declarations were made that both Judaism and Hinduism were monotheistic.  IIRC, during the Indian Hair Wig debacle, there was a big question that even if the intellectual elites (who would attend summits, I suppose) believed that God was One with many Aspects, the folk religion was polytheistic. In which case, which idea was most relevant for determining whether hair-cutting for Indian worship made the hair &quot;offered to idols&quot; and thus unusable by observant Jews, or not.

Maybe, being there, and being a rav sensitive to interfaith issues, you can verify whether the common people believe in one god or many, thus, whether there is a question at all.  And if there is, which idea should be most relevant, although that last may be above your pay grade.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I see your reports from the Jewish-Hindu Summits, where declarations were made that both Judaism and Hinduism were monotheistic.  IIRC, during the Indian Hair Wig debacle, there was a big question that even if the intellectual elites (who would attend summits, I suppose) believed that God was One with many Aspects, the folk religion was polytheistic. In which case, which idea was most relevant for determining whether hair-cutting for Indian worship made the hair &#8220;offered to idols&#8221; and thus unusable by observant Jews, or not.</p>
<p>Maybe, being there, and being a rav sensitive to interfaith issues, you can verify whether the common people believe in one god or many, thus, whether there is a question at all.  And if there is, which idea should be most relevant, although that last may be above your pay grade.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/27/fulbright-senior-scholar-award-in-varanasi/#comment-8906</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2013 12:47:36 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6309#comment-8906</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/27/fulbright-senior-scholar-award-in-varanasi/#comment-8904&quot;&gt;Jeff&lt;/a&gt;.

The libraries and even the major collections have a few dozen 19th century works. Both the Delhi national library and BHU library each have about 35 books like Robertson Smith and Disraeli. 
yes indeed, Nathan Katz is involved.
Methodists and immigrants from many other countries have very low rates of retention n the fold. Greeks and other Orthodox groups also have a high rate of retention.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/27/fulbright-senior-scholar-award-in-varanasi/#comment-8904">Jeff</a>.</p>
<p>The libraries and even the major collections have a few dozen 19th century works. Both the Delhi national library and BHU library each have about 35 books like Robertson Smith and Disraeli.<br />
yes indeed, Nathan Katz is involved.<br />
Methodists and immigrants from many other countries have very low rates of retention n the fold. Greeks and other Orthodox groups also have a high rate of retention.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Jeff		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/27/fulbright-senior-scholar-award-in-varanasi/#comment-8905</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jeff]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2013 12:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6309#comment-8905</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Oh, and I&#039;ve heard of Swami Dayananda. Someone I know from my days managing the Buddhist Center is a devotee of his (if he&#039;s the same Dayananda). I understand he&#039;s a scholar of Vedanta. I wasn&#039;t aware he&#039;s been involved in Hindu-Jewish dialogue.

I&#039;ve been of the opinion for years that Judaism and Vedanta have more in common than do Judaism and Buddhism, particularly in their conceptualizations of the Godhead as an undifferentiated ultimate reality (although you do find it in Buddhism, but don&#039;t say that within earshot of the Buddhists).]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Oh, and I&#8217;ve heard of Swami Dayananda. Someone I know from my days managing the Buddhist Center is a devotee of his (if he&#8217;s the same Dayananda). I understand he&#8217;s a scholar of Vedanta. I wasn&#8217;t aware he&#8217;s been involved in Hindu-Jewish dialogue.</p>
<p>I&#8217;ve been of the opinion for years that Judaism and Vedanta have more in common than do Judaism and Buddhism, particularly in their conceptualizations of the Godhead as an undifferentiated ultimate reality (although you do find it in Buddhism, but don&#8217;t say that within earshot of the Buddhists).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Jeff		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/10/27/fulbright-senior-scholar-award-in-varanasi/#comment-8904</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jeff]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2013 12:22:14 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6309#comment-8904</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This is interesting. This is what I was asking you about the other day.

•	&lt;i&gt;As part of the new multifaith America, the Hindus representatives emphasized that they can learn from Jews about community building as a Diaspora minority in America.&lt;/i&gt;

I’m sure you’re aware that was the reason behind the Dalai lama’s desire for dialogue, that led to the Dharamsala discussions.

•	&lt;i&gt;There is almost no knowledge of the Judaism here and not even basic Jewish books.&lt;/i&gt;

I’m surprised to hear this. After all these years of Jews going to India and two decades of the Internet, I’d have thought there would be at least some basic knowledge.

•	In your earlier article, from which you draw above, you stated, &lt;i&gt;Recent studies found that, on average, Jews and Hindus are the most educated religious groups in the United States, with similar economic structures and the highest retention rate of believers.&lt;/i&gt; Did you really feel the data then supported the idea that Jews (all Jews, not merely the Orthodox) have a high retention rate? My understanding is that the figures demonstrate otherwise.

•	Is Nathan Katz involved in these encounters or at the Delhi conference?

•	I am staying at the Benares Hindu University, the oldest and largest in Asia, a university founded in the colonial period by the Annie Besant.

Will you become a Theosophist now? ;-)]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is interesting. This is what I was asking you about the other day.</p>
<p>•	<i>As part of the new multifaith America, the Hindus representatives emphasized that they can learn from Jews about community building as a Diaspora minority in America.</i></p>
<p>I’m sure you’re aware that was the reason behind the Dalai lama’s desire for dialogue, that led to the Dharamsala discussions.</p>
<p>•	<i>There is almost no knowledge of the Judaism here and not even basic Jewish books.</i></p>
<p>I’m surprised to hear this. After all these years of Jews going to India and two decades of the Internet, I’d have thought there would be at least some basic knowledge.</p>
<p>•	In your earlier article, from which you draw above, you stated, <i>Recent studies found that, on average, Jews and Hindus are the most educated religious groups in the United States, with similar economic structures and the highest retention rate of believers.</i> Did you really feel the data then supported the idea that Jews (all Jews, not merely the Orthodox) have a high retention rate? My understanding is that the figures demonstrate otherwise.</p>
<p>•	Is Nathan Katz involved in these encounters or at the Delhi conference?</p>
<p>•	I am staying at the Benares Hindu University, the oldest and largest in Asia, a university founded in the colonial period by the Annie Besant.</p>
<p>Will you become a Theosophist now? 😉</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
