<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Presbyterian Church in Canada and the Jews- 2011 edition	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/08/presbyterian-church-in-canada-and-the-jews-2011-edition/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/08/presbyterian-church-in-canada-and-the-jews-2011-edition/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2011 13:32:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Arie Folger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/08/presbyterian-church-in-canada-and-the-jews-2011-edition/#comment-3602</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arie Folger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2011 13:32:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4083#comment-3602</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[With my teacher the blogmaster&#039;s permission, I also hope we can continue this debate here (and I hope others will chime in).

Thank you for the detailed answer, Mark. I will try to respond to the salient points.

Your point about Jerusalem is interesting, and I would ask a few Presbyterians to chime in and say how they see what you wrote. Quite obviously I agree we should pray for the peace of all of Israel, and for the entire world. My worry is only that what is supposed to be a statement of support for Jews turns out to be hijacked for Middle East politics. But hey, if the target audience reads it like you do, then you will turn out to be right, and this discussion can then stand as some commentary on the wording.

Your elaboration of how experience the word &quot;reformy&quot; should remind us - I guess - that, coming from different faiths, we each have our respective cultural baggages, and they are not always similar. I am more likely to be familiar with Reform Jewish concepts than with Presbyterian ones, and my antennas will sooner detect this intra-Jewish debates (though on many points, Reform philosophy has come quite a long way since the Pittsburgh Platform).

Third point: critique well taken. Perhaps I may suggest: &quot;As Christians, we look forward in hope to God’s full redemption - and we recognize that Jews, too, look forward to God&#039;s redemption, within the framework of their faith and beliefs - ...&quot; though it does suffer from being too wordy. Let&#039;s see what other commenters, or the eminent blogmaster, may suggest.

Thank you, too, for the conversation, and do keep up the efforts to bring about more mutual respect in the world.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>With my teacher the blogmaster&#8217;s permission, I also hope we can continue this debate here (and I hope others will chime in).</p>
<p>Thank you for the detailed answer, Mark. I will try to respond to the salient points.</p>
<p>Your point about Jerusalem is interesting, and I would ask a few Presbyterians to chime in and say how they see what you wrote. Quite obviously I agree we should pray for the peace of all of Israel, and for the entire world. My worry is only that what is supposed to be a statement of support for Jews turns out to be hijacked for Middle East politics. But hey, if the target audience reads it like you do, then you will turn out to be right, and this discussion can then stand as some commentary on the wording.</p>
<p>Your elaboration of how experience the word &#8220;reformy&#8221; should remind us &#8211; I guess &#8211; that, coming from different faiths, we each have our respective cultural baggages, and they are not always similar. I am more likely to be familiar with Reform Jewish concepts than with Presbyterian ones, and my antennas will sooner detect this intra-Jewish debates (though on many points, Reform philosophy has come quite a long way since the Pittsburgh Platform).</p>
<p>Third point: critique well taken. Perhaps I may suggest: &#8220;As Christians, we look forward in hope to God’s full redemption &#8211; and we recognize that Jews, too, look forward to God&#8217;s redemption, within the framework of their faith and beliefs &#8211; &#8230;&#8221; though it does suffer from being too wordy. Let&#8217;s see what other commenters, or the eminent blogmaster, may suggest.</p>
<p>Thank you, too, for the conversation, and do keep up the efforts to bring about more mutual respect in the world.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Mark		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/08/presbyterian-church-in-canada-and-the-jews-2011-edition/#comment-3601</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mark]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2011 12:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4083#comment-3601</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thank you for the detailed response, Arie. (And I hope the moderator of the blog does not mind the discussion continuing.)

On &#039;homeland&#039; to &#039;safe haven&#039;, you make a very fair point. I thought the original (and, let&#039;s face it, final) version of the document was basically suggesting that Jews do not belong anywhere but Israel, and this change was a reaction to that. It is a tough balance to strike, and I am open to other attempts at reaching it.

As for praying for the regions surrounding Jerusalem, I&#039;m afraid I can&#039;t change that. Do we not want to pray for the peace of Hebron, Tiberias, and Tsfat, too? Aren&#039;t they important for Jews, too? In my experience, Christians are very willing to pray for Jerusalem, but rarely for the rest of the country. But I need to be honest--this is not an issue I considered until my spouse challenged me to consider why Christians never seem to pray for any particular city in the region other than Jerusalem (and occasionally Bethlehem).

With the declaration that the proposed emendations are &#039;reformy&#039;, I think we get to the core of the misunderstanding. The pun in our blog tagline, Reform(ed) refers to both Reform Judaism (my spouse) and Reformed (ie, Calvinist) Christianity (me); when you said that you thought my proposed emendations were aimed at making the document more Reformed, I thought you were accusing me of trying to impose an even stronger Christian framework into the document--I&#039;m a lot happier to be accused of liberal ecumenism. I&#039;m not sure that I would agree that this means simply declaring all religions are okay and hoping that means we can get along. I certainly do not believe that it is about requiring outside validation as if it is necessary for someone to judge the validity of your religion. That being said, the idea of Judaism being an equally valid covenant *is* a tenet of classic Calvinism, and one I would like my church to remember. This isn&#039;t about giving you (or my spouse, or any other Jewish person) external validation--it&#039;s about reminding Christians, at least those who come from roughly the same theological tradition that I do, what our own faith says about how to treat others. 

This moves on to the next point you raise, concerning the change from &#039;Christians and Jews&#039; to &#039;As Christians, we share with Jews&#039;. To me it seemed that the original and eventually final reading suggested that the statement being made was a joint effort, when really it came only from Presbyterian theologians. I thought it disingenuous to make any inference that Christians can do anything other than state their own beliefs. I cannot imagine any real interfaith dialogue happening when one group assumes they speak for another, precisely because each group will define terms like &#039;redemption&#039; differently. Thus, what I was trying to accomplish and what you read seem to be utterly opposite, which is more than a little disappointing. How would you suggest amending this passage to respect better the differences in understanding that actually exist?

All in all, I am flattered by the time you take in reading emendations which went nowhere. Thank you for your comments; they are helpful as I look back over the whole issue. And I greatly appreciate the support you offer on the key point of not forgetting that Canadian Jews belong just as much as other Canadians, and for the call to real dialogue. Thank you so much for the conversation.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thank you for the detailed response, Arie. (And I hope the moderator of the blog does not mind the discussion continuing.)</p>
<p>On &#8216;homeland&#8217; to &#8216;safe haven&#8217;, you make a very fair point. I thought the original (and, let&#8217;s face it, final) version of the document was basically suggesting that Jews do not belong anywhere but Israel, and this change was a reaction to that. It is a tough balance to strike, and I am open to other attempts at reaching it.</p>
<p>As for praying for the regions surrounding Jerusalem, I&#8217;m afraid I can&#8217;t change that. Do we not want to pray for the peace of Hebron, Tiberias, and Tsfat, too? Aren&#8217;t they important for Jews, too? In my experience, Christians are very willing to pray for Jerusalem, but rarely for the rest of the country. But I need to be honest&#8211;this is not an issue I considered until my spouse challenged me to consider why Christians never seem to pray for any particular city in the region other than Jerusalem (and occasionally Bethlehem).</p>
<p>With the declaration that the proposed emendations are &#8216;reformy&#8217;, I think we get to the core of the misunderstanding. The pun in our blog tagline, Reform(ed) refers to both Reform Judaism (my spouse) and Reformed (ie, Calvinist) Christianity (me); when you said that you thought my proposed emendations were aimed at making the document more Reformed, I thought you were accusing me of trying to impose an even stronger Christian framework into the document&#8211;I&#8217;m a lot happier to be accused of liberal ecumenism. I&#8217;m not sure that I would agree that this means simply declaring all religions are okay and hoping that means we can get along. I certainly do not believe that it is about requiring outside validation as if it is necessary for someone to judge the validity of your religion. That being said, the idea of Judaism being an equally valid covenant *is* a tenet of classic Calvinism, and one I would like my church to remember. This isn&#8217;t about giving you (or my spouse, or any other Jewish person) external validation&#8211;it&#8217;s about reminding Christians, at least those who come from roughly the same theological tradition that I do, what our own faith says about how to treat others. </p>
<p>This moves on to the next point you raise, concerning the change from &#8216;Christians and Jews&#8217; to &#8216;As Christians, we share with Jews&#8217;. To me it seemed that the original and eventually final reading suggested that the statement being made was a joint effort, when really it came only from Presbyterian theologians. I thought it disingenuous to make any inference that Christians can do anything other than state their own beliefs. I cannot imagine any real interfaith dialogue happening when one group assumes they speak for another, precisely because each group will define terms like &#8216;redemption&#8217; differently. Thus, what I was trying to accomplish and what you read seem to be utterly opposite, which is more than a little disappointing. How would you suggest amending this passage to respect better the differences in understanding that actually exist?</p>
<p>All in all, I am flattered by the time you take in reading emendations which went nowhere. Thank you for your comments; they are helpful as I look back over the whole issue. And I greatly appreciate the support you offer on the key point of not forgetting that Canadian Jews belong just as much as other Canadians, and for the call to real dialogue. Thank you so much for the conversation.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Arie Folger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/08/presbyterian-church-in-canada-and-the-jews-2011-edition/#comment-3592</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arie Folger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 10 Sep 2011 19:58:38 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4083#comment-3592</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Let&#039;s see. How about: deleting the word &quot;homeland&quot; when referring to Israel, leaving only &quot;safe haven&quot;? Israel is not just a safe haven and wasn&#039;t created as a response to the Holocaust, it&#039;s our historic home, whether we are her citizens or not and whether we live there or not.

How about: adding &quot;all the surrounding regions&quot; to the Presbytarian commitment to pray for Jerusalem, which, while a noble addition, is really entirely out of place there, unless one wants to relativize the importance of Jerusalem for Jews?

In a different vein, the proposed emendations also seek to push one particular view of how Christians should see Jews, namely as having an equally valid covenant. I am flattered. Of course I do believe in the validity of the Jewish covenant, but really, I never bother demanding that from Christians (I actually go around telling my audiences in interfaith meetings that I do not need external validation for my faith; I am sufficiently secure and truly trust Jewish tradition - that suffices for the validation of my path to salvation). The proposed emendation seems to me to come from a why can&#039;t we all get along your religion is right my religion is right ecumenical mindset. That seems reformy to me, though not necessarily Jewish Reform, just reform / liberal.

I am not sure what was meant with the emendation replacing &quot;As Christians, and Jews we look forward in hope to God’s full redemption&quot; with &quot;As Christians, we share with Jews a hope in God’s full redemption,&quot; but it surely seems to create additional commonality, ignoring the fact that there are some very significant differences in how Jews and Christians each imagine &quot;God’s full redemption.&quot; So this seems more of the same, see the immediately previous paragraph. The very last emendation, a closing statement, is similarly inspired by this kind of spirit, which more orthodox people of all faiths may formulate very differently.

However, I very much appreciate the attempt to tone down the missionary zeal that seeps through that document, as well as the overt attempt to underline that Jews are every bit as much at home in Canada (and elsewhere) as Christians. And I similarly commend emendations that seek to explicitly include real proper non-misisonizing interfaith dialogue in the document.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Let&#8217;s see. How about: deleting the word &#8220;homeland&#8221; when referring to Israel, leaving only &#8220;safe haven&#8221;? Israel is not just a safe haven and wasn&#8217;t created as a response to the Holocaust, it&#8217;s our historic home, whether we are her citizens or not and whether we live there or not.</p>
<p>How about: adding &#8220;all the surrounding regions&#8221; to the Presbytarian commitment to pray for Jerusalem, which, while a noble addition, is really entirely out of place there, unless one wants to relativize the importance of Jerusalem for Jews?</p>
<p>In a different vein, the proposed emendations also seek to push one particular view of how Christians should see Jews, namely as having an equally valid covenant. I am flattered. Of course I do believe in the validity of the Jewish covenant, but really, I never bother demanding that from Christians (I actually go around telling my audiences in interfaith meetings that I do not need external validation for my faith; I am sufficiently secure and truly trust Jewish tradition &#8211; that suffices for the validation of my path to salvation). The proposed emendation seems to me to come from a why can&#8217;t we all get along your religion is right my religion is right ecumenical mindset. That seems reformy to me, though not necessarily Jewish Reform, just reform / liberal.</p>
<p>I am not sure what was meant with the emendation replacing &#8220;As Christians, and Jews we look forward in hope to God’s full redemption&#8221; with &#8220;As Christians, we share with Jews a hope in God’s full redemption,&#8221; but it surely seems to create additional commonality, ignoring the fact that there are some very significant differences in how Jews and Christians each imagine &#8220;God’s full redemption.&#8221; So this seems more of the same, see the immediately previous paragraph. The very last emendation, a closing statement, is similarly inspired by this kind of spirit, which more orthodox people of all faiths may formulate very differently.</p>
<p>However, I very much appreciate the attempt to tone down the missionary zeal that seeps through that document, as well as the overt attempt to underline that Jews are every bit as much at home in Canada (and elsewhere) as Christians. And I similarly commend emendations that seek to explicitly include real proper non-misisonizing interfaith dialogue in the document.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Mark		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/08/presbyterian-church-in-canada-and-the-jews-2011-edition/#comment-3590</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mark]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2011 18:28:38 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4083#comment-3590</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/08/presbyterian-church-in-canada-and-the-jews-2011-edition/#comment-3589&quot;&gt;Arie Folger&lt;/a&gt;.

Thank you for your comment, Arie, but would you mind sharing what in particular about the proposed (in my dreams) emendations to the statement makes it read as concentrating more on being Reformed than on openness? My attempt was to make the statement--which could never be more than a one-sided statement as it was never written by or addressed to anyone other than Canadian Presbyterians--more focused on acceptance of Jews as Jews and less focused on evangalism and upholding Reformed Christian identity at the expense of other faiths; if I&#039;ve failed at that, I&#039;d like to know exactly how, so I can do better.

P.S. To anyone following the link to the final statement: the link takes you to the whole record of acts and proceedings of the 2011 General Assembly, which can be unwieldy for even the most dedicated Presbyterian. The final statement can be found starting on page 42.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/08/presbyterian-church-in-canada-and-the-jews-2011-edition/#comment-3589">Arie Folger</a>.</p>
<p>Thank you for your comment, Arie, but would you mind sharing what in particular about the proposed (in my dreams) emendations to the statement makes it read as concentrating more on being Reformed than on openness? My attempt was to make the statement&#8211;which could never be more than a one-sided statement as it was never written by or addressed to anyone other than Canadian Presbyterians&#8211;more focused on acceptance of Jews as Jews and less focused on evangalism and upholding Reformed Christian identity at the expense of other faiths; if I&#8217;ve failed at that, I&#8217;d like to know exactly how, so I can do better.</p>
<p>P.S. To anyone following the link to the final statement: the link takes you to the whole record of acts and proceedings of the 2011 General Assembly, which can be unwieldy for even the most dedicated Presbyterian. The final statement can be found starting on page 42.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Arie Folger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/08/presbyterian-church-in-canada-and-the-jews-2011-edition/#comment-3589</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arie Folger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2011 16:33:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4083#comment-3589</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Leaving aside the elephant in the room that the closing statement proclaiming their commitment to missionizing to Jews essentially totally undoes any openness and acceptance they may have tried to project to the Jewish community, in many ways, the published statement is superior to the proposed edits of the &quot;Kippa and Collar&quot; blog. It is quite clearly that a considerable source of of those edits is not so much a desire to be more accepting of Jews as it is really about being more - as in the blog&#039;s tag line - Reform(ed).

That said, the Presbiterians&#039; continuing commitment to missionizing to Jews is troubling. When a Christian missionizes Jews, even with the most peaceful and pleasant of intentions, he or she cannot escape the heavy weight of history linking him or her to the violent Inquisitors, Crusaders and other sundry Christian antisemites of the past. For the sake of continuing progress of interfaith work, and for the sake of a more peaceful, tolerant society, they should learn to be more reserved in this area.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Leaving aside the elephant in the room that the closing statement proclaiming their commitment to missionizing to Jews essentially totally undoes any openness and acceptance they may have tried to project to the Jewish community, in many ways, the published statement is superior to the proposed edits of the &#8220;Kippa and Collar&#8221; blog. It is quite clearly that a considerable source of of those edits is not so much a desire to be more accepting of Jews as it is really about being more &#8211; as in the blog&#8217;s tag line &#8211; Reform(ed).</p>
<p>That said, the Presbiterians&#8217; continuing commitment to missionizing to Jews is troubling. When a Christian missionizes Jews, even with the most peaceful and pleasant of intentions, he or she cannot escape the heavy weight of history linking him or her to the violent Inquisitors, Crusaders and other sundry Christian antisemites of the past. For the sake of continuing progress of interfaith work, and for the sake of a more peaceful, tolerant society, they should learn to be more reserved in this area.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alana		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/08/presbyterian-church-in-canada-and-the-jews-2011-edition/#comment-3586</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alana]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2011 06:10:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4083#comment-3586</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thanks for the link--though I should offer a slight correction: I&#039;m not a Rabbi, just a PhD who teaches in Theology/Religious Studies.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thanks for the link&#8211;though I should offer a slight correction: I&#8217;m not a Rabbi, just a PhD who teaches in Theology/Religious Studies.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
