<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Only Zaddikim can Save us	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/23/only-zaddikim-can-save-us/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/23/only-zaddikim-can-save-us/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2010 23:51:24 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Kevin Rothman		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/23/only-zaddikim-can-save-us/#comment-1428</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kevin Rothman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2010 23:51:24 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1724#comment-1428</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[word.  I hear you on that]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>word.  I hear you on that</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Dina		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/23/only-zaddikim-can-save-us/#comment-1426</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dina]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2010 19:37:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1724#comment-1426</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Know where we need saddiqim? - in the skhunot - and not just in Israel, but here too. There is massive misery in Israel (1/3 of Israeli children suffer from hunger) and here too. I am tired of hearing that working class and poor Jews don&#039;t exist, which is what I heard in the 1988 Tikkun Conference at the Penta Hotel. That kind of stereotyping feeds right into the &#039;rich Jews&#039; myth and is also running rampant yet again. You know who was a saddiq? Michael Gold, at least when he wrote that book _Jews without Money_ in the 1930s, but the Communists and Communism are passé, for better or worse. And with the destruction of the social safety net all we are left with are the religious institutions, like in the 19th century. For years the only shuls that didn&#039;t constantly ask people for money but gave out saddaqah in abundance was Chabad. And like it or not, and personally I don&#039;t like their politics, but Chabad shuls are more diverse in terms of socioeconomic class and often in terms of bringing Sephardim and Mizrahim and Ashkenazim together, despite the historical cultural running over of Mizrahi and Sephardi culture by Ashkenazi hassidut. Where I live the Sephardim and Mizrahim mostly attend the Chabad shuls. And the only shul I know of doing saddaqah in Skhunat Ha-Tikva is an off-shoot of Chabad. This is why their numbers of increasing so much and will continue to do so unless everyone else makes gemilut hasadim their number one priority, especially in these times. Gemilut hasidim also applies to the larger community and not just to Jews, but given the stereotypes about Jews and money even Jewish organizations and leaders often forget to &#039;take care of their own&#039; - which is kind of hard to do when you don&#039;t think they exist.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Know where we need saddiqim? &#8211; in the skhunot &#8211; and not just in Israel, but here too. There is massive misery in Israel (1/3 of Israeli children suffer from hunger) and here too. I am tired of hearing that working class and poor Jews don&#8217;t exist, which is what I heard in the 1988 Tikkun Conference at the Penta Hotel. That kind of stereotyping feeds right into the &#8216;rich Jews&#8217; myth and is also running rampant yet again. You know who was a saddiq? Michael Gold, at least when he wrote that book _Jews without Money_ in the 1930s, but the Communists and Communism are passé, for better or worse. And with the destruction of the social safety net all we are left with are the religious institutions, like in the 19th century. For years the only shuls that didn&#8217;t constantly ask people for money but gave out saddaqah in abundance was Chabad. And like it or not, and personally I don&#8217;t like their politics, but Chabad shuls are more diverse in terms of socioeconomic class and often in terms of bringing Sephardim and Mizrahim and Ashkenazim together, despite the historical cultural running over of Mizrahi and Sephardi culture by Ashkenazi hassidut. Where I live the Sephardim and Mizrahim mostly attend the Chabad shuls. And the only shul I know of doing saddaqah in Skhunat Ha-Tikva is an off-shoot of Chabad. This is why their numbers of increasing so much and will continue to do so unless everyone else makes gemilut hasadim their number one priority, especially in these times. Gemilut hasidim also applies to the larger community and not just to Jews, but given the stereotypes about Jews and money even Jewish organizations and leaders often forget to &#8216;take care of their own&#8217; &#8211; which is kind of hard to do when you don&#8217;t think they exist.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: avraham rosenblum		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/23/only-zaddikim-can-save-us/#comment-1422</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[avraham rosenblum]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 29 Jul 2010 14:56:52 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1724#comment-1422</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I am working on it.  I am trying to figure out what made the Mir Yeshiva in Brooklyn thirty years ago special. The closest idea i have been able to figure out is the devotion to a great book --the Gemara Babli with a little Musar thrown in. Perhaps there is something intangible in great books that produces quality people?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I am working on it.  I am trying to figure out what made the Mir Yeshiva in Brooklyn thirty years ago special. The closest idea i have been able to figure out is the devotion to a great book &#8211;the Gemara Babli with a little Musar thrown in. Perhaps there is something intangible in great books that produces quality people?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Kevin Rothman		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/23/only-zaddikim-can-save-us/#comment-1416</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kevin Rothman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 29 Jul 2010 00:22:32 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1724#comment-1416</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[but how is that any different from what is already going on and is failing?  talmud, rambam, etc. are taught in most yeshivot and the problems we are discussing still exist.  I think there has to be more than a simple return to the sources.  it must be a critical return, one willing to draw blood and have blood drawn.  there must be risk, otherwise it is altogether too complacent and suspect from the start]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>but how is that any different from what is already going on and is failing?  talmud, rambam, etc. are taught in most yeshivot and the problems we are discussing still exist.  I think there has to be more than a simple return to the sources.  it must be a critical return, one willing to draw blood and have blood drawn.  there must be risk, otherwise it is altogether too complacent and suspect from the start</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: avraham rosenblum		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/23/only-zaddikim-can-save-us/#comment-1414</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[avraham rosenblum]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 28 Jul 2010 19:07:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1724#comment-1414</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Not a counter culture musar movement--rather a movement based on the great books of torah--i.e. Torah, Talmud (with Tosphot) Rambam. Musar sefaim are not on that level of greatness or depth--but they are important.
(I would add to the great sefarim list the arizal and rebbi nachmans&#039;s books).
I think there should be a clear distinction between great and suburban, Let’s face the fact that most kabala books are  quite good in promoting insanity and seem to have the same effect on people as a good night in a bar or at an ecstasy party
,]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Not a counter culture musar movement&#8211;rather a movement based on the great books of torah&#8211;i.e. Torah, Talmud (with Tosphot) Rambam. Musar sefaim are not on that level of greatness or depth&#8211;but they are important.<br />
(I would add to the great sefarim list the arizal and rebbi nachmans&#8217;s books).<br />
I think there should be a clear distinction between great and suburban, Let’s face the fact that most kabala books are  quite good in promoting insanity and seem to have the same effect on people as a good night in a bar or at an ecstasy party<br />
,</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Kevin Rothman		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/23/only-zaddikim-can-save-us/#comment-1404</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kevin Rothman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2010 19:59:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1724#comment-1404</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[the distinction i make is between the levinasian sort of anarchism and that of the lubavitcher rebbe.  in the rebbe&#039;s writings (and here I am thinking more of his work from 1990 forward.  I have written on this subject if you would like to read it.)  there is a hasidic reworking of hegel&#039;s &quot;identity of identity and non-identity&quot; theory.  I do not know if this was intended or if it just emerged naturally from the directionality of kabbalistic thought in Habad, it is, however (in my opinion) distinct.  while hegel points towards a totality and a totalitarianism of the absolute (following Rosenzweig here), in the sublimation of the particular in the universal there must be (if the equation he employs in &quot;the difference btwn fitche&#039;s and schelling&#039;s philosophy&quot; is actually an equation) a reciprocal denigration of the absolute to the particular.  Taking both of these in hand, one is left with a dissolution of heirarchy and, in this sense, an anarchy.  However, this is an anarchic that immolates the individuality of either side of the equation.  It is, in this sense, an anethical anarchy.  Yet, it is this very blur that marks, for the rebbe, the manifestation of atsmut elokut, or, in hegelian terms, the absolute. (i could say a lot more on this but I will refrain.... this is also where i totally disagree with wolfson regarding his reference to buddhist sources to explain the rebbe)  

the levinasian anarchic is an absolute ethical responsibility for the other that predates my freedom.  it is an anarchic of transcendence whereby no logic in the sense of hegel&#039;s equation can subsist between two entities such that no law can carry both.  he mitigates this somewhat in the notion of justice, but it is nonetheless the foundation of his system.

I agree that a large scale revolution would be disasterous (and when was any revolution successful anyway?).  but I am not talking about that, I am talking about a dissolution of the institutionality of modern Judaism and returning it to a mode of questioning rather than a mode of answering.

i also hear you on the coolness factor; however, I question whether the sort of elevated sense of importance the syrian or any other of our more insular communities have of themselves is ultimately a good.  I think that while it serves an ethnically useful purpose, it is an open gate for self-justifying moral degeneration.  coolness itself is ultimately, in my opinion, rather empty, ultimately self defeating, and undermines itself in its being sought (trying to be cool is the least cool thing there is, one must simply be cool)...and, in my opinion, this comes from the cessation of seeming and the commencement of being.  this being is a renouncement of labels, of ways of being.  for judaism, this would mean setting aside the institutions and denominations we are defined in and by and simply letting the analysis of texts, traditions, and concepts speak for itself... instead of the selective reading that all present denominations are guilty of.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>the distinction i make is between the levinasian sort of anarchism and that of the lubavitcher rebbe.  in the rebbe&#8217;s writings (and here I am thinking more of his work from 1990 forward.  I have written on this subject if you would like to read it.)  there is a hasidic reworking of hegel&#8217;s &#8220;identity of identity and non-identity&#8221; theory.  I do not know if this was intended or if it just emerged naturally from the directionality of kabbalistic thought in Habad, it is, however (in my opinion) distinct.  while hegel points towards a totality and a totalitarianism of the absolute (following Rosenzweig here), in the sublimation of the particular in the universal there must be (if the equation he employs in &#8220;the difference btwn fitche&#8217;s and schelling&#8217;s philosophy&#8221; is actually an equation) a reciprocal denigration of the absolute to the particular.  Taking both of these in hand, one is left with a dissolution of heirarchy and, in this sense, an anarchy.  However, this is an anarchic that immolates the individuality of either side of the equation.  It is, in this sense, an anethical anarchy.  Yet, it is this very blur that marks, for the rebbe, the manifestation of atsmut elokut, or, in hegelian terms, the absolute. (i could say a lot more on this but I will refrain&#8230;. this is also where i totally disagree with wolfson regarding his reference to buddhist sources to explain the rebbe)  </p>
<p>the levinasian anarchic is an absolute ethical responsibility for the other that predates my freedom.  it is an anarchic of transcendence whereby no logic in the sense of hegel&#8217;s equation can subsist between two entities such that no law can carry both.  he mitigates this somewhat in the notion of justice, but it is nonetheless the foundation of his system.</p>
<p>I agree that a large scale revolution would be disasterous (and when was any revolution successful anyway?).  but I am not talking about that, I am talking about a dissolution of the institutionality of modern Judaism and returning it to a mode of questioning rather than a mode of answering.</p>
<p>i also hear you on the coolness factor; however, I question whether the sort of elevated sense of importance the syrian or any other of our more insular communities have of themselves is ultimately a good.  I think that while it serves an ethnically useful purpose, it is an open gate for self-justifying moral degeneration.  coolness itself is ultimately, in my opinion, rather empty, ultimately self defeating, and undermines itself in its being sought (trying to be cool is the least cool thing there is, one must simply be cool)&#8230;and, in my opinion, this comes from the cessation of seeming and the commencement of being.  this being is a renouncement of labels, of ways of being.  for judaism, this would mean setting aside the institutions and denominations we are defined in and by and simply letting the analysis of texts, traditions, and concepts speak for itself&#8230; instead of the selective reading that all present denominations are guilty of.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: pierre		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/23/only-zaddikim-can-save-us/#comment-1401</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pierre]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2010 18:01:48 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1724#comment-1401</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Perhaps the closest Judaism has to Cath. saints, who were similarly often either distant or apart from their faith to one degree or another in one aspect or another  - is BTs. But Catholicism and Judaism are distinct in ways that escape many people; you are mikvah-ed into Catholicism, where Judaism is vastly born Jews.  A BT is not &#039;baptised&#039; - they are affirming a fundamental aspect of themself already there - the Ger/convert/the baptisted - are rejecting one, if not many aspects of their being.  

Also BTs often admit to having been &quot;sold&quot; the Judaism they are measured by; saints in hagiographies of ancient and recent vintage, not the case. Many of Judaism most recent martyrs were so often for &#039;simply&#039; being Jews tragically murdered - were a certain of them were martyred in acting their faith or asserting principles of it in sacrifice. Judaism for various reasons (that I do not judge), has a virtue, doctrine and achievement in simply existing as a Jew.

Not so many inside the hierarchies of either have been deemed &#039;saints&#039;; but Judaism has a way of making as many of them as possible to be saints, not as the catholic celebration of lives transformed (think R. Wolbe and his BT/not-BT status..), but as simple motivation and source of inspiration of the Artscroll variety. Most saints come from outside either Establishment - and it&#039;s hardly as if every pope has earned the status, even as far as the church is concerned.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Perhaps the closest Judaism has to Cath. saints, who were similarly often either distant or apart from their faith to one degree or another in one aspect or another  &#8211; is BTs. But Catholicism and Judaism are distinct in ways that escape many people; you are mikvah-ed into Catholicism, where Judaism is vastly born Jews.  A BT is not &#8216;baptised&#8217; &#8211; they are affirming a fundamental aspect of themself already there &#8211; the Ger/convert/the baptisted &#8211; are rejecting one, if not many aspects of their being.  </p>
<p>Also BTs often admit to having been &#8220;sold&#8221; the Judaism they are measured by; saints in hagiographies of ancient and recent vintage, not the case. Many of Judaism most recent martyrs were so often for &#8216;simply&#8217; being Jews tragically murdered &#8211; were a certain of them were martyred in acting their faith or asserting principles of it in sacrifice. Judaism for various reasons (that I do not judge), has a virtue, doctrine and achievement in simply existing as a Jew.</p>
<p>Not so many inside the hierarchies of either have been deemed &#8216;saints&#8217;; but Judaism has a way of making as many of them as possible to be saints, not as the catholic celebration of lives transformed (think R. Wolbe and his BT/not-BT status..), but as simple motivation and source of inspiration of the Artscroll variety. Most saints come from outside either Establishment &#8211; and it&#8217;s hardly as if every pope has earned the status, even as far as the church is concerned.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/23/only-zaddikim-can-save-us/#comment-1400</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2010 17:19:58 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1724#comment-1400</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[There is indeed a big difference between anarchism and lawlessness, and my point as it stands is incorrect. At this point I am becoming confused by your use of the term anarchic as in the eschatology of the Lubavitcher Rebbe. If it isn&#039;t  antinomian, is it the abolishing of all authority and  concentrations of power? The dismantling of concentrations of capital must be worldwide, since one country at a time would be a disaster for the country. It seems to me to be an impossible quixotic goal. I do not understand this anarchic ideal.
As for &#039;polishing narcissism is not enough&#039;, I disagree. Many of the problems Judaism faces  comes on my view  from narcissistic deficits, and anything that would help heal these wounds is worthwhile. As an example, the disappearance  of American non-Orthodox Jewish life is a result of the young thinking it’s more stylish, cooler, to walk away than to stay. In communities like the Persian or Syrian Jews where there is a much greater ‘stulzkeit’, a much greater sense of being part of something fabulous, intermarriage is not a serious problem. In my opinion being told that tachlis haadam is the American Jewish World Service will not make religious life more attractive. Tikun haolam is basically a variant of utilitarianism, and is more compatible with a secularized Christianity. If you are thinking about sensitivity to others on a personal level, there is nothing on the left to compare to  the Protestant novel. 
You are also right about what Wolfson is saying. I deliberately misread Wolfson, because unless I can find concrete empirical examples I become very confused. For me so far, seeing the cosmos as in The Purloined Letter gives me a headache; to wit  that what is revealed is betzem a secret and vice versa. Similarly I would explain the idea that the spiritual will be revealed through its opposite in terms of the new idea that consciousness is an epiphenomena. I acknowledge that the way you put it is closer to the text.

I wish this was a venue where we could elaborate on these ideas in a slow and more systemic way. Hopefully more some other time]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There is indeed a big difference between anarchism and lawlessness, and my point as it stands is incorrect. At this point I am becoming confused by your use of the term anarchic as in the eschatology of the Lubavitcher Rebbe. If it isn&#8217;t  antinomian, is it the abolishing of all authority and  concentrations of power? The dismantling of concentrations of capital must be worldwide, since one country at a time would be a disaster for the country. It seems to me to be an impossible quixotic goal. I do not understand this anarchic ideal.<br />
As for &#8216;polishing narcissism is not enough&#8217;, I disagree. Many of the problems Judaism faces  comes on my view  from narcissistic deficits, and anything that would help heal these wounds is worthwhile. As an example, the disappearance  of American non-Orthodox Jewish life is a result of the young thinking it’s more stylish, cooler, to walk away than to stay. In communities like the Persian or Syrian Jews where there is a much greater ‘stulzkeit’, a much greater sense of being part of something fabulous, intermarriage is not a serious problem. In my opinion being told that tachlis haadam is the American Jewish World Service will not make religious life more attractive. Tikun haolam is basically a variant of utilitarianism, and is more compatible with a secularized Christianity. If you are thinking about sensitivity to others on a personal level, there is nothing on the left to compare to  the Protestant novel.<br />
You are also right about what Wolfson is saying. I deliberately misread Wolfson, because unless I can find concrete empirical examples I become very confused. For me so far, seeing the cosmos as in The Purloined Letter gives me a headache; to wit  that what is revealed is betzem a secret and vice versa. Similarly I would explain the idea that the spiritual will be revealed through its opposite in terms of the new idea that consciousness is an epiphenomena. I acknowledge that the way you put it is closer to the text.</p>
<p>I wish this was a venue where we could elaborate on these ideas in a slow and more systemic way. Hopefully more some other time</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Kevin Rothman		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/23/only-zaddikim-can-save-us/#comment-1394</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kevin Rothman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2010 13:44:54 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1724#comment-1394</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[a quote (often cited during Habad gatherings) from mendle futerfas, a prominent habad mashpia from the previous generation, comes to mind: &quot;the other man&#039;s gashmiyut is my ruchniyut&quot;]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>a quote (often cited during Habad gatherings) from mendle futerfas, a prominent habad mashpia from the previous generation, comes to mind: &#8220;the other man&#8217;s gashmiyut is my ruchniyut&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Kevin Rothman		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/23/only-zaddikim-can-save-us/#comment-1390</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kevin Rothman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2010 03:43:22 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1724#comment-1390</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I think there is a difference between lawlessness and anarchism.  The former stands in opposition to the law and defies it for personal gain, the latter maintains the anethical foundation of any sort of coersion and works for the other man.  I also do not think that Butler is the only example of the radical left one could or should draw on, you are taking an extreme example to make a point.  While levinas, for example, ultimately acknowledges a system of third parties, his views are essentially anarchic (and even the justice embodied in the third party system is one grounded in the anarchy of &quot;I-other&quot;).  Is he also &quot;bad for the Jews and Israel&quot;?  

If, in citing wolfson you are referring to his work on the lubavitcher rebbe (and even if you are not, this work is relevent) the notion of messianism and the davar gashmi there is precisely anarchic.  the spirituality of the davar gashmi is so and radically so by virtue of the fact that matter unto itself is contentless and, therefore, correlates to the essential contentlessness of the essence of God that is the advent of the messianic in the lubavitcher rebbe&#039;s eschatology.  This contentlessness erases the division between man and man and man and God whereby law is stripped of its legal format... becomes uncommanded in its commandedness or, in other words, becomes self-ordained.  I do not necessarily ascribe to this sense of the anarchic (i prefer levinas), because it has deeply hegelian, and, therefore, (paradoxically) totalitatian, undertones, but anarchic it is nonetheless.

aesthetic sublimation may be an easier way to turn the ocean liner from gross narcissism, but it is a way that does not reach shore... and I am not even certain it really even turns away from gross narcissism if it is, in the end, self-directed.  i think that today spirituality must be a spiritual for the other man if it is to have any worth at all.  polishing narcissism just isnt enough... and if that is all we can offer then I think we would be selling an inferior product.  greater demands must be made.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think there is a difference between lawlessness and anarchism.  The former stands in opposition to the law and defies it for personal gain, the latter maintains the anethical foundation of any sort of coersion and works for the other man.  I also do not think that Butler is the only example of the radical left one could or should draw on, you are taking an extreme example to make a point.  While levinas, for example, ultimately acknowledges a system of third parties, his views are essentially anarchic (and even the justice embodied in the third party system is one grounded in the anarchy of &#8220;I-other&#8221;).  Is he also &#8220;bad for the Jews and Israel&#8221;?  </p>
<p>If, in citing wolfson you are referring to his work on the lubavitcher rebbe (and even if you are not, this work is relevent) the notion of messianism and the davar gashmi there is precisely anarchic.  the spirituality of the davar gashmi is so and radically so by virtue of the fact that matter unto itself is contentless and, therefore, correlates to the essential contentlessness of the essence of God that is the advent of the messianic in the lubavitcher rebbe&#8217;s eschatology.  This contentlessness erases the division between man and man and man and God whereby law is stripped of its legal format&#8230; becomes uncommanded in its commandedness or, in other words, becomes self-ordained.  I do not necessarily ascribe to this sense of the anarchic (i prefer levinas), because it has deeply hegelian, and, therefore, (paradoxically) totalitatian, undertones, but anarchic it is nonetheless.</p>
<p>aesthetic sublimation may be an easier way to turn the ocean liner from gross narcissism, but it is a way that does not reach shore&#8230; and I am not even certain it really even turns away from gross narcissism if it is, in the end, self-directed.  i think that today spirituality must be a spiritual for the other man if it is to have any worth at all.  polishing narcissism just isnt enough&#8230; and if that is all we can offer then I think we would be selling an inferior product.  greater demands must be made.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/23/only-zaddikim-can-save-us/#comment-1389</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2010 03:04:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1724#comment-1389</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[EJ-
I fail to see where your low-brow mix would create any ethical concern. We are actually heading to that sort of mix and it is getting worse. We also had that sort of mix in pre WWII Poland - the  mix of all sorts of things like Gerrer sports caster - and it was a as decadent as it came. See Pikarz and others.
It may have been fun but it was not ethical in any way. On top of it, Polish urban life remained parochial even as they had all sorts of modern polish culture.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>EJ-<br />
I fail to see where your low-brow mix would create any ethical concern. We are actually heading to that sort of mix and it is getting worse. We also had that sort of mix in pre WWII Poland &#8211; the  mix of all sorts of things like Gerrer sports caster &#8211; and it was a as decadent as it came. See Pikarz and others.<br />
It may have been fun but it was not ethical in any way. On top of it, Polish urban life remained parochial even as they had all sorts of modern polish culture.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Geoff		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/23/only-zaddikim-can-save-us/#comment-1388</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Geoff]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2010 02:21:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1724#comment-1388</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I’ll place myself in the camp of your friends who have some hope for a new Musar movement of one sort or another.  I think that efforts to nurture a counter-cultural Musar movement, a movement which encourages substantial individual efforts to cultivate a wide range of virtues, can improve our chances of creating more-saintly behavior and a greater ability to recognize saints among us.  Aspects of the nineteenth-century Musar movement are, as you note, entirely foreign to contemporary America, but the focus on cultivating virtues does have some significant resonance, at least counter-culturally, as I tried to lay out in a recent article at http://www.iasc-culture.org/publications_article_2010_Summer_claussen.php.  (Pardon the errant colon in the article title there, which will hopefully be gone within another day.)  There, I focused on efforts to revive aspects of the Musar movement’s legacy among non-Orthodox Jews, and found myself somewhat encouraged by those ongoing efforts.  The dynamic within American Orthodoxy is different, and Orthodoxy offers its own challenges, especially with its (increasing?) valorization of the teleological suspension of the ethical (as you mentioned in the name of R. Ethan Tucker in your most recent post).  But the general story in Orthodoxy is the same: efforts at promoting serious Musar practice within Orthodoxy are also largely counter-cultural, though part of their attraction is because of culturally-mainstream American values like the drive for “sincerity” (as Adam Seligman et al. put it) which have certainly permeated Orthodoxy as well.  

Musar practice won’t capture the suburban—or urban!—masses, whether in Orthodoxy or beyond it, even in its fairly-Americanized (less-foreign).  But I think that it offers some hope for shaping people to be somewhat more like tzaddikim, or at least orienting us towards serious visions of what tzaddikim might look like.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’ll place myself in the camp of your friends who have some hope for a new Musar movement of one sort or another.  I think that efforts to nurture a counter-cultural Musar movement, a movement which encourages substantial individual efforts to cultivate a wide range of virtues, can improve our chances of creating more-saintly behavior and a greater ability to recognize saints among us.  Aspects of the nineteenth-century Musar movement are, as you note, entirely foreign to contemporary America, but the focus on cultivating virtues does have some significant resonance, at least counter-culturally, as I tried to lay out in a recent article at <a href="http://www.iasc-culture.org/publications_article_2010_Summer_claussen.php" rel="nofollow ugc">http://www.iasc-culture.org/publications_article_2010_Summer_claussen.php</a>.  (Pardon the errant colon in the article title there, which will hopefully be gone within another day.)  There, I focused on efforts to revive aspects of the Musar movement’s legacy among non-Orthodox Jews, and found myself somewhat encouraged by those ongoing efforts.  The dynamic within American Orthodoxy is different, and Orthodoxy offers its own challenges, especially with its (increasing?) valorization of the teleological suspension of the ethical (as you mentioned in the name of R. Ethan Tucker in your most recent post).  But the general story in Orthodoxy is the same: efforts at promoting serious Musar practice within Orthodoxy are also largely counter-cultural, though part of their attraction is because of culturally-mainstream American values like the drive for “sincerity” (as Adam Seligman et al. put it) which have certainly permeated Orthodoxy as well.  </p>
<p>Musar practice won’t capture the suburban—or urban!—masses, whether in Orthodoxy or beyond it, even in its fairly-Americanized (less-foreign).  But I think that it offers some hope for shaping people to be somewhat more like tzaddikim, or at least orienting us towards serious visions of what tzaddikim might look like.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/23/only-zaddikim-can-save-us/#comment-1387</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2010 02:14:03 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1724#comment-1387</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Radical politics forever is Trotskeyism  and Anarchism, both of  which down before they could get started.  In some sense charedim and settlers  are anarchists and that is the problem. So are lehavdil,  crooks and swindlers, child molesters and wife beaters, shirkers and free riders,  and all those others who  think we are entitled to be the exception forever. Practical anarchism is going to get us one day in big trouble, so I fail to see the need for more.
I would agree aestheticism being fundamentally indulgent and I would add  meditation and the many ways of achieving higher levels of  spirituality. The existence of an ostensible (self) object like the shechina, does not change the picture; and if it does, so does beauty in all its immanentist  instantiations  in material  objects. (See Wolfson’s book on the relation between a davar gashmi and a gilui of spirituality in messianic times.)
My idea rests on the thought that our problems and our strengths, once you get past the bravado, is based on an intense and sometimes defensive and damaged narcissism. Aestheticism is one of many possible sublimations of narcissism, with the advantage that it does not require immoral behavior. Speaking schematically I would argue it a lot easier and safer to turn the ocean liner called Judaism towards an aesthetic sublimation than in a left radical direction. Judith Butler might be  a secular Jewish saint, but she is bad news for Jews and Israel. I realize aestheticism took on a fascist orientation in Italy and elsewhere. But we are from having that problem.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Radical politics forever is Trotskeyism  and Anarchism, both of  which down before they could get started.  In some sense charedim and settlers  are anarchists and that is the problem. So are lehavdil,  crooks and swindlers, child molesters and wife beaters, shirkers and free riders,  and all those others who  think we are entitled to be the exception forever. Practical anarchism is going to get us one day in big trouble, so I fail to see the need for more.<br />
I would agree aestheticism being fundamentally indulgent and I would add  meditation and the many ways of achieving higher levels of  spirituality. The existence of an ostensible (self) object like the shechina, does not change the picture; and if it does, so does beauty in all its immanentist  instantiations  in material  objects. (See Wolfson’s book on the relation between a davar gashmi and a gilui of spirituality in messianic times.)<br />
My idea rests on the thought that our problems and our strengths, once you get past the bravado, is based on an intense and sometimes defensive and damaged narcissism. Aestheticism is one of many possible sublimations of narcissism, with the advantage that it does not require immoral behavior. Speaking schematically I would argue it a lot easier and safer to turn the ocean liner called Judaism towards an aesthetic sublimation than in a left radical direction. Judith Butler might be  a secular Jewish saint, but she is bad news for Jews and Israel. I realize aestheticism took on a fascist orientation in Italy and elsewhere. But we are from having that problem.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
