<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>jewish meditation &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/tag/jewish-meditation/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2010 05:28:31 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='kavvanah.wordpress.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/c9f111237f93750b6b994fc5185d49c3?s=96&#038;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>jewish meditation &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>Meditation Conference</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/20/meditation-conference/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/20/meditation-conference/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2010 03:50:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Buddhism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1312</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The organizers of the meditation conference assumed meditation was a means of sitting and saying a verbal focus which would lead to calm, well-being, and better health. They wanted to find out how this truth of meditation plays itself out &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/20/meditation-conference/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The organizers of the meditation conference assumed meditation was a means of sitting and saying a verbal focus which would lead to calm, well-being, and better health. They wanted to find out how this truth of meditation plays itself out in the religions and cultures of the world. Instead, they found themselves with over fifty experts on meditation techniques in Buddhism, Hinduism, Daoism, Islam, Christianity, and Judaism saying that this definition of meditation is not found in the traditional texts or traditional meditation communities.  There was a feeling that Western people, in America and Europe, have an idea of meditation and speak of meditation as a know entity that was unknown to the academics in the field. </p>
<p>We felt that we could have used a panel session on where this idea of mediation came from and how in the last 35 years in has become part of Western religion and spirituality. In short, we pieced together that the theosophists and translators of the sacred books of the east created a version of mediation as psychology. In the 1970’s when TM and Zen became popular as well as reading the older works, then we get a flurry of books on “what is meditation.” By the 1980’s we can speak of the “meditation of poetry”, the “meditation of surfing”  the “meditation of yoga” or the “meditation of Chabad fabrengen”  A rightful possession of American spirituality that Americans  wont let experts take away from them. Herbert Benson created the relaxation response and formulated meditation as a form of calm and healthy wellbeing. But this definition is not a traditional one. This was further removed from any tradition by psycho neurology that used its own definitions not accepted by any known religion- except contemporary spirituality. Even frum jews love to use the word when it does not correspond to anything in traditional texts.</p>
<p>So the conference ran as follows:</p>
<p>The calmness of meditation is claimed to be based on the Indic concept of Samadhi, but Samadhi is not calmness, rather a secession of emotions, desires, thoughts, and brain functions so one can transcend the world. Indian and Buddhism meditation is not about calmness and wellness- it is about pain and suffering and rubbing your nose in the inevitability of suffering. Zen is not very calm and includes sweat inducing koans, being hit by the Roshi, unquestioning tasks,  and pain.  Jewish texts on hitbddedut and kavvanah are about coming closer to God sometimes via ecstasy and emotional upheaval.</p>
<p>The modern definition takes out the purpose of meditation in India or China which is to either escape the world or seek enlightenment. And it has little to do with the Jewish and Islamic themes of God in the heart, or the Tibetan and Daoist alchemical techniques for longevity.  After the presentation on vipassana, any vestiges of the opening premises were gone.  Vipassana was originally the national ideal of Burma for a educated well cultivated approached to stoically wait for the British colonialists to leave.  It was then modernized in the Vietnam War, but still little to do with the current practice of that name. There was little respect for the Dalai Lama at the conference with his promising this-worldly happiness and well being for those who meditate, when his own Tibetan traditions do not teach that. </p>
<p>There was a general consensus that most current practices performed in the west were recent. They were either from the term of the 20th century and involved modernization and Westernization. We find Buddhists reading William James and rediscovering new techniques in manuscript.  Then there are new versions of the 1960’s. Finally, there was consensus that anyone claiming tradition and authority in the US teaching “meditation” in the modern sense was either a charlatan or a student of one.  Trust those who either acknowledge they are doing something modern or those who don’t promise calm and well being. Everyone saw a decrease in interest in traditional forms of meditation since the 1990&#8217;s becuase everyone now knows that they want this new Western meditation &#8211; but they want it with a Yoga, Hasidic, or QiGong veneer.</p>
<p>From a Jewish point of view, this means that Ramak, Ari”zl, Chabad, and Rav Nahman all have versions of hitbodedut, hitbonenut, kavvanah, and yihud but there is nothing gained conceptually or linguistically by calling them meditation and they have little to do with any clinical calming technique.  (it might have briefly made sense in the 1970’s when stolid religion was breaking down and the BT world was aiming in this realm.)  The reliance of the Piesetzna and Menachem Eckstein on modern psychology is par for the course-as is Aryeh Kaplan’s reading of the Dover Publishing Co. books from the early 20th century on Tibetan and Chinese meditation.  And sitting for mindfulness before davening is not Buddhist, not Jewish, not Indian but it is American new age spiritual. Sitting before davening has little to do with the Ramak or Ari”zl. </p>
<p>By the end we concluded that there is use for term like visualization, body techniques, or mental apophasis.<br />
One can speak of a Jewish kavvanah of the Ramak as a form of visualization. But it does not share the formal aspects of sitting of the Zen tradition and it lacks the ending of mental  facilities like Samadhi and it lack to goal to escape the world of most Buddhist practices.  It does not have the mental requirements of Jnana. Yet, there is more to the analogy than just visions since it does take one to a place above the “pain of this world”  creating some very weak similarity to Jnana and Samadhi. But the goal of daat and berakhah are very unYogic. One can also find close similarities to Sufis and certain out of context Daoist similarities.</p>
<p>Now what? We shall see if they get funding for follow-up conferences.</p>
<p>[Natan – I know that your approach disagrees. I have read your material so you don’t have to send it to me again as comments.]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/20/meditation-conference/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Cordovero on the nature of Prayer</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2010 02:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[devekut]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[moshe cordovero]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[prayer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1230</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[For those following the more pietistic discussion on Ramak’s prayer, here is some more for discussion. The first text is on devekut. The second text is on the inability of prayer to rise without ascending level by level through the &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For those following the more pietistic discussion on Ramak’s prayer, here is some more for discussion. The first text is on devekut. The second text is on the inability of prayer to rise without ascending level by level through the known levels. One cannot prayer directly to the Eyn Sof. Any reactions or insights? I am delivering a conference paper next week on the topic, so all observations are helpful. Any insights to the meditation process?</p>
<p><strong>Devekut</strong></p>
<p>“Through these mysteries, a man is able to cleave to his master with will…”<br />
A person can cleave to Him through directing his will to the mystery of the sefirot, the Tetragrammaton, and the [other] Divine names. One who does not know the mystery of how to cleave to Him will not have the ability to grasp (beit ahizah),  because His place of grasping is through His sefirot, His precious names and holy Tetragrammaton.<br />
“In directing the heart to know the wisdom of His dominance in the highest mystery.” The dominance of hokhmah is a wondrous mystery. The first way to reach a state of cleaving to the Divine (devekut) is through the study of the mysteries of the Torah and the understanding of the hidden secrets in the Torah.<br />
The second is “when he worships his Master in prayer,” that is, the mystery of prayer and the way of cleaving to Him.<br />
“He will cleave like a flame in a coal&#8221;—for man’s will and soul that ascend from the walls of his heart will certainly be bound to the supernal palaces. Thus, man should first meditate on repairing malkhut, Her repairs are the mystery of the palaces, which bind and cleave together with malkhut like a flame bound in a coal, while his soul and meditation are a flame from the coal that is malkhut. Similarly, the palaces that spread out from and cleave to Her are like a flame spreading out from amidst the coal, yet cleaving to it. Because of this, the [palaces] return to their source and are swallowed up in Her through his soul that returns and is swallowed in its source. With the soul’s ascent, the [palaces] are raised as well, since only through the soul can they spread out below. Now this is the mystery of man’s intention and breath of his mouth created from the vapor of his mouth and the soul (neshamah) arising through breath (neshimah), that they cleave and return to their source. If it happens that the palaces, and further, the hizonim, spread out from there, he should meditate on binding and unifying her specifically from the palace of paved sapphire (livnat hasappir) and higher. There is the beginning of holy cleaving, binding themselves in unification.<br />
 <br />
<strong>Ascent of prayers</strong></p>
<p>When the Shekhinah is completely filled with prayers, then the prayers rise and ascend to a place where there is no pain and no lack.<br />
The purpose of ascent into worship of God is so the prayer should reach this place. Some people meditate in times of need, as it is written, &#8220;Israel are wise in that they know how to pray in times of need.&#8221; However, better and more meritorious is he who raises all of his prayers there [even not in a time of need].<br />
This form of worship is more desirable because it does not come out of pain or need, but rather from cleaving through worship to the true Object of worship.<br />
The masses think that the intention reaches there by itself; they are completely outside the palace, so that when they call the king from afar, the king does not answer them.<br />
Rather, it is necessary to call to the gatekeeper. The gatekeeper takes them in his hand and brings them into the control of the princes, from prince to prince of each palace, until they are brought to the king in his chamber, where they will find Him and bring their needs before Him.<br />
For those who pray or cleave to Ein Sof by itself, their goal remains far from them. He is only close to the one who knows His palaces and gatekeepers.<br />
Indeed,  for those who speak to the gatekeeper which is the attribute of malkhut, the attribute will bring them to the higher attributes higher, level after level through all the levels.<br />
These people will certainly enter to the King, Ein Sof, the Root of all roots, in His room, a wondrous place, and speak with Him, in the mystery of the ascent of prayer. Immediately, it will be powerful.  </p>
<p>Copyright © 2010 Alan Brill • All Rights Reserved</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>20</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Teaching Meditation</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/16/teaching-meditation/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/16/teaching-meditation/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2010 00:06:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kavvanah]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=964</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The cartoon seeks to make fun, but I find it quite serious. Is there any other way to teach meditation than in the language of those you are teaching. If one teaches a kavvanah from Rabbi Isaac the blind or &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/16/teaching-meditation/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/computer-yoga.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="929" data-permalink="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/computer-yoga/" data-orig-file="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/computer-yoga.jpg" data-orig-size="400,350" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;}" data-image-title="computer yoga" data-image-description="" data-medium-file="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/computer-yoga.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/computer-yoga.jpg?w=400" src="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/computer-yoga.jpg?w=500" alt="" title="computer yoga"   class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-929" srcset="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/computer-yoga.jpg 400w, https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/computer-yoga.jpg?w=150 150w, https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/computer-yoga.jpg?w=300 300w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></a></p>
<p>The cartoon seeks to make fun, but I find it quite serious. Is there any other way to teach meditation than in the language of those you are teaching. If one teaches a kavvanah from Rabbi Isaac the blind or Rabbi Moses Cordovero does one teach medieval cosmology and medieval science to explain it? What if it is a once a week meditation class and one wants to get down to practice. Should one use the language of bittul or of &#8220;clear your cache and history? Should one imagine light at the bottom of emanation or a blank web page? Is this modernizing into new age like neo-hasidism or the only way to do things?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/16/teaching-meditation/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/computer-yoga.jpg" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">computer yoga</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rabbi Morgenstern and Meditation</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/09/rabbi-morgenstern-and-meditation/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/09/rabbi-morgenstern-and-meditation/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2010 04:28:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Hasidism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neo-Hasidism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[popular religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rabbis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[spirituality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ashlag]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Derech yihud]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[derekh yihud]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rav Itchie Mayer Morgenstern]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sheva Eynayim]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tu beshevat]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yitzhak Meir Moregenstern]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[YM Erlanger]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=751</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When someone mentions Jewish meditation to me the first thing I think of are the Haredi Kabbalitic mediators. I think of Y.M Erlanger who in his Sheva Eynayim and in classes in Heimishe Yeshivos is teaching Hasidut combined with Abulafia &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/09/rabbi-morgenstern-and-meditation/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When someone mentions Jewish meditation to me the first thing I think of are the Haredi Kabbalitic mediators. I think of Y.M Erlanger who in his <em>Sheva Eynayim</em> and in classes in Heimishe Yeshivos is teaching Hasidut combined with Abulafia and I think of Yitzhak Meir Moregenstern who is reorganizing early Kabbalah, Ramak, Ari, and Abulafia as Hasidut.  Erlanger’s starts with the statements in <em>Sefer Habesht al Hatorah </em>and introduces ever more esoteric material and at the end of the last volume, he introduces Abulafia with a warning that the material that he is about to teach is not for everyone, and not everyone should enter the Pardes, and even if you do enter this may not be for you. In contrast, Rabbi  Morgenstern called Rav Itchie Mayer Morgenstern starts everyone on the real stuff.</p>
<p>R. Morgenstern is a Haredi descendant of the Kotzker and lived most of his life in England and has moved to Jerusalem and set up a Beit Midrash. You can find videos of him teaching and singing with Anglos on the web.  See<a href="http://dixieyid.blogspot.com/2007/11/rav-itchie-mayer-shalosh-sheudos.html"> here,</a> <a href="http://dixieyid.blogspot.com/2007/05/chochma-vs-bina-practical_30.html">here </a>and <a href="http://dixieyid.blogspot.com/2007/05/chochma-vs-bina-practical.html">here.</a><br />
He has attached a real following. He gives weekly public shiurim in kavvanot, in Komarno, and Ramhal. He has an email list serve for his Torah, his kabbalah, and for assorted teachings (Hebrew, English, and Yiddish).  Send an email here to subscribe tc7@neto.bezeqint.net </p>
<p>He seems to have read some generic books on “How to Meditate” or “Meditation for Everyone” and in his work <em>Derekh Yihud</em> he reorganizes traditional  kabbalistic practices into an order that reflects the general mediation world. The topics are sitting, breathing, visualizing, creating an avir in front of one, colors, and  a unified vision.  He freely takes pieces of Abulafia, Ramak,  and early kabbalah to create a Jewish meditation manual in line with the non-Jewish ones. The work <em>Derekh Yihud</em> opens up a new path of reorganizing the older materials based on modern principles.</p>
<p>I see him as potentially the future.  Rav Ashlag wrote in the 1930’s and took the meditation, medieval worldview and fantasy out of the Kabbalah and replaced it was science, communism, Schopenhauer, and a closed system. Now everything from the Kabbalah Centre to Bnai Baruch to Michael Leitman are his spiritual descendents. Rabbi Morgensten is teaching the young grandchildren of the Rebbes and many  in Kolel and he also accepts the varied pneumatics of Jerusalem as his students.  When all those students take their positions as Rebbes, Ramim, and teachers then the meditation format of breathing and visualization will be the tradition.  If the trend continues,  in 2050 this will be mainstream Kabbalah. </p>
<p>I had originally planned this post before my computer crash when I received the following two weeks ago. It offers a concise taste of <em>Derekh Yihud.</em> Morgenstern advises to close the eyes and see the hidden lights  in order to achieve bliss. One turns from this world to the airspace and achieves a vision of the Throne. Lights, then hidden mind, and finally the source of the soul and the Throne.</p>
<blockquote><p>
When a Jew spends time in hisbodedus before his Creator, he closes his eyes so as not to be enticed by the illusory pleasures of this world because he doesn’t want to be connected to them.<br />
When he closes his eyes in this way, he is able to see the brilliant hues that are rooted in the “hidden mind” of Mocha Sesima’ah, and he begins to derive pleasure from spiritual reality, from the fact that Hashem is revealed through a myriad of shades and hues of dveikus. He starts to feel Hashem’s light and glory within himself, and how all of the pleasures of this world are null and void, are like a mere sliver of light, compared with the delight of dveikus that is a composite of all possible forms of bliss.</p>
<p>So when a person seals his vision against the illusory nature of this world, he rises to the place of the “airspace” and its “membrane,” which is really the source of the human soul and its throne of glory. In that place it can be said, “From my flesh, I see G-d.” One begins to enjoy a vision of the ultimate Kisei HaKavod upon which the “form of a person sat.”<br />
The final three plagues parallel these three states of dveikus:<br />
First, a person must meditate and be misboded on the expansive Binah light of Hashem.<br />
Then he must ascend to the place of the “hidden mind” which is the counterpart of the holy darkness of turning aside from this-worldly concerns to receive “light in all his dwellings.” With this, he destroys the klippah of the impure firstborn and rises further to the place of the “membrane of the airspace” and the “airspace” itself which correlates to the level of the Da’as of Atik and which reveals to him the source of his neshamah that “sits upon the throne.”<br />
 “It is revealed and known before Your Kisei HaKavod&#8230;” Meaning, through coming to the level of the Kisei HaKavod, we are able to subdue all of the klippos and utterly “smite Egypt through their firstborns.”</p></blockquote>
<p>This past week he sent out a special Tu beShevat essay. He opens the essay stating that was asked why Hayyim Vital did not mention TuBeshevat and answers in the name of R. Haayim Cohen that it is a hidden quality. And when pressed why does everyone do it today? He turns to R. Aharon Halevi of Strashelye explaining that since we are lesser today everyone learns Kabbalah since they do not grasp the real depth anyway.  The essay is a running account of his Torah and the questions he received Tu Beshevat-Shabbat Shrah. There are many interesting points in it including -We are told of the joy from the recent publishing  of Vital’s alchemy and magic.</p>
<p>Copyright © 2010 Alan Brill • All Rights Reserved</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/09/rabbi-morgenstern-and-meditation/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>31</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Jewish Meditation 1995-2005</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/26/meditation-1995-2005/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/26/meditation-1995-2005/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2010 14:21:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Buddhism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[populations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[spirituality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[chochmat halev]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish meditation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=644</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Here is an account from The Forward that parallels what I have seen in the field. In the early and mid nineties there was a great desire for the technical aspects of meditation and Jewish meditation. Then, after only 5 &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/26/meditation-1995-2005/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here is an account from The Forward that parallels what I have seen in the field. In the early and mid nineties there was a great desire for the technical aspects of meditation and Jewish meditation. Then, after only 5 years it started broadening into all forms of spirituality especially musical forms and emotional healing. And finally right before our eyes, it all stops around 2005. People started coming to a class listed as Jewish meditation and assumed that it has something to do with guitars, bongos and chanting. In 1995, people wanted meditation and came with Zen or Vipasssana backgrounds and then flash it was gone by 2005, leaving revivalism in its wake.</p>
<p>Even the local Buddhist center here in NJ, gave daily and weekly meditation classes in 2000 and now only offers a once a month introduction to Happiness, saving any serious meditation instruction for biannual retreats.</p>
<blockquote><p>Chochmat HaLev came to life in the 1990s… One of these teachers, Rabbi Avram Davis, proposed creating a Jewish meditation center that could be a community resource…. Chochmat HaLev was launched, first as a series of classes in 1992 to 1993, and then as a nonprofit organization in 1995&#8230; In focusing on Jewish meditation, Gefen and Davis were at the forefront of a wave of interest in training a generation of Jewish “spiritual leaders,” who could bring meditation to their own congregations and lead meditation retreats and workshops for nonaffiliated Jews. So in addition to holding its own retreats and workshops, Chochmat pioneered a year-long leadership program with an initial cohort of 40 students.</p>
<p>Something happened on the communal meditation cushion, however. Joined by their interest in Jewish spirituality, the initial group felt a desire to pray together — a development that took Gefen by surprise. Davis, however, had thought of offering services from the beginning, because for him, Jewish meditation could exist only as part of a larger practice.</p>
<p>From the start, Davis led Chochmat’s services, distinguished by the constant thrum of a six-piece band composed of guitar, bass, drum set, keyboards and vocalists, its musical direction owed in equal parts to Rabbi Shlomo Carlebach, American rock and Moroccan beats. During a typical service, continuing today, participants dance in the aisles, clap, stomp their feet and sway with hands in the air, in an atmosphere most reminiscent of evangelical rapture</p>
<p>From 2000 to 2005, Chochmat HaLev functioned much like a cross between an institute for Jewish spirituality and an independent minyan.  Holding these two very different organizations together was a tight-knit, supportive community.</p>
<p>The year 2005 marked a crisis for Chochmat. The meditation school had essentially vanished. Aside from one year-long distance-learning program, the school was not offering more classes than an active synagogue. And because of its regular religious services, Chochmat was no longer seen as a non-denominational resource center: Its original mission was gone.</p>
<p>In 2005, the Chochmat board decided to become a functioning synagogue, and Avram Davis chose to leave.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.forward.com/articles/123815/">Full version</a></p></blockquote>
<p>Now Jewish meditation is once again for the few.People still do visualizations &#8211; part motivational part Neo-hasidic as a way to get psyched or as a means of bringing a moment of silence or a visualization into a regular service.  People are very sympathetic, &#8220;lets do it for a few minutes or a mini-course&#8221; and then let&#8217;s move on.</p>
<p>More on the year 2000 from<a href="http://zeek.forward.com/articles/116253/"> the same author</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>The year 2000 would see the establishment of the New York-based Institute of Jewish Spirituality, a Jewish meditation center run by Rabbi Sheila Pelz Weinberg; Makor Or, a San Francisco-based center founded by Rabbi Alan Lew (z’’l) and Norman Fischer; as well as a new emphasis on meditation at Elat Chayyim under Rabbi Jeff Roth and a burst of books on the topic (among them books by Gefen and Davis).</p></blockquote>
<p>Ten years ago there was a meditation moment.</p>
<p><strong>UPDATE &#8211; see the detailed rundown by Len Moskowitz in the Comments section. The comment shows that there is no diminution. </strong><br />
Copyright © 2010 Alan Brill • All Rights Reserved</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/26/meditation-1995-2005/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Lubavitcher Rebbe on Transcendental Meditation</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/30/the-lubavitcher-rebbe-on-transcendental-meditation/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/30/the-lubavitcher-rebbe-on-transcendental-meditation/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2009 20:45:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neo-Hasidism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[popular religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rabbis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[avodah zarah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fabrengen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kosher TM]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lubavitcher Rebbe]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Maharishi Mahesh Yogi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Maharishi Mahesh Yogi jewish]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transcendental meditation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=322</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Back in July 1979,  a rabbi sitting outside on a porch in the Catskils, with a friend or older bachur, he was listening to the Fabrengen. I was called over to listen to it because the Rebbe was speaking about &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/30/the-lubavitcher-rebbe-on-transcendental-meditation/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Back in July 1979,  a rabbi sitting outside on a porch in the Catskils, with a friend or older bachur, he was listening to the Fabrengen. I was called over to listen to it because the Rebbe was speaking about Transcendental Meditation, he assumed that I would be interested.  I was not particularly enthralled since all I heard was “avodah zarah,”  “idols, incense and gurus” “worship of the sun and moon,” “it is OK for doctors to teach.” At the time, I felt that it did not reach the issues and was too removed, too Biblical, and was not really showing understanding.  Beyond that he treated TM as a pathology to be dealt with by physicians. He did not want any connection of meditation to Kabbalah.  Yet, for some reason I still remember the event, the cloudy evening, and my reaction, especially my disappointing mulling it over for some time that evening.</p>
<p>Yesterday, someone sent me a question on Yoga and Judaism, and after an initial email the response reminded me of the Rebbe’s sicha.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.chabad.org/multimedia/livingtorah_cdo/aid/858581/jewish/Kosher-Meditation.htm">So here an audio- video of the original.</a></p>
<p>The Rebbe compares TM to the avodah zarah of the sun and the moon. The Rebbe does not address other religions but deals with the issue as part of the problem of cults. He wants the creation of something new called &#8220;Jewish meditation&#8221; to wean people away from TM. It should be seen as a medical problem and should only be taught by someone who  knows the laws of avodah zarah. It is interesting that the Rebbe is careful not to call all of it “ruah tumah” or “klipot nogah.” Rather, the problem is the incense, bowing, and the false gods or treating the guru as a deity. The patriarch Abraham is portrayed as engaged in solitude, yet the Rebbe does not want this new invention of Jewish meditation connected to Kabbalah, it should be done clinically by physicians.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.sichosinenglish.org/books/sichos-in-english/3/17.htm"> Here are selections from the translation.</a></p>
<blockquote><p>There in an issue, which is connected with the physical and psychological health of many Jews, that demands attention. It is quite possible that these words will have no effect. Nevertheless, the health of a Jew is such an important matter, that efforts should be made even when there is not a sure chance of success.</p>
<p>This issue is the idea of meditation. Meditation has its roots in the very beginning of the Jewish heritage. The Torah commentaries explain that Avraham and the other patriarchs chose to be shepherds so that they could spend their time in solitude.</p>
<p>The sun, the moon, and the stars are necessary for life of earth. They bring about manifold goodness. However, they also have been worshipped as false gods. One might ask (as the Talmud asks): “Since they have been worshipped as false gods, shouldn’t they be destroyed? However, should G-d destroy the world because of the foolishness of the idol-worshipers?” The same concept applies in regard to meditation. Though essentially good, meditation can also be destructive. There are those who have connected meditation to actually bowing down to an idol or a man and worshipping it or him, bringing incense before them etc.</p>
<p>The cults have spread throughout the U.S. and throughout Israel as well.</p>
<p>They have called it by a refined name “transcendental meditation” i.e. something above limits, above our bounded intellects. However, they have also incorporated into the procedures the bringing of incense and other practices that are clearly “Avodah Zorah,” the worship of false gods.</p>
<p>Since we are living within the darkness of Golus, many Jewish youth have fallen into this snare. Before they became involved with this cult, they were troubled and disturbed. The cult was able to relate to them and bring them peace of mind. However, their meditation is connected with Avodah Zorah, burning incense and bowing to a Guru, etc. Since the aspects of idol worship are not publicized, there are those who have not raised their voices in protest. They don’t know if such a protest would be successful and since no one has asked them, why should they enter a questionable situation.</p>
<p>Two conditions must be taken into consideration: 1) meditation should only be used by those who need it. A healthy person doesn’t need meditation. On the contrary, if he begins to meditate he will hurt his psychological health. The only meditation that all should carry out is one which is part of one’s service to G-d, for the <em>Shulchan Aruch</em> states that before each prayer one must meditate on “the greatness of G-d and the humble state of man.” However, that meditation is done with a fixed time and a fixed intent. Its goal is not to calm one’s nerves. 2) The meditation must be based on a Kosher idea or a Torah concept e.g. Shema Yisroel, the meanings of the prayers. Thus, this will bring one to an awareness of the greatness of G-d and the humble nature of man.</p>
<p>Also, since as in all treatments, the healer gains a certain amount of control over his patient, we must take care that the professional who is leading the meditation have a clear and well defined knowledge of what is permitted according to the <em>Shulchan Aruch,</em> what leads to Avodah Zorah, etc.</p>
<p>Even in Yerushalayim, the holy city, such a center has been established. I, myself, received a brochure from such an institution. It was professionally produced, containing pictures and a description of how in Yerushalayim, a center for meditation has been set up. They purchase American addresses, and send them this brochure. It makes a powerful impression and arouses curiosity. Thus, we can see how serious the situation is.</p>
<p>In view of this situation, psychologists, psychoanalysts, etc. have a holy duty to advance their knowledge of meditation, and work to develop a Kosher program. Furthermore, since we live in a country in which publicity plays a large role, efforts must be made to publicize the treatment in the broadest means possible.</p>
<p>Furthermore, this treatment should not be connected with any side issues. There are those who maintain that meditation must be connected with the secrets of Torah. Meditation on the secrets of Torah is very important, particularly in the present age when the Wellsprings of Chassidus must be spread outwards. However, the subject at hand is different. There are Jews who are involved in “Avodah Zorah,” worship of false gods, who must be saved. This is the first priority. If one begins by teaching the secrets of Torah, it is extremely likely that the majority of them will not respond. Even the few who might show an interest should be separated from “Avodah Zorah” first.</p>
<p>We cannot sit and wait practically until someone asks to be helped. We have to approach those who are afflicted and speak their language, without mixing in any other Mitzvos. Our object should be merely the Mitzvah of healing their troubled psyches.</p>
<p>Each one of us knows such a doctor. We can interest a doctor in such activities, and he will find a way to attract those who have fallen into these snares.</p>
<p>In all the other exiles, the redemption did not involve the entire Jewish people. However, the Messianic redemption will reach every Jew. The prophet Isaiah (27:12) declares: “You will be collected one by one” from even the furthest extremes of Golus. These efforts to draw Jews away from the Golus of “Avodah Zorah” will help hasten the fulfillment of the prophecy. The Talmud states that all the appointed times for Moshiach’s coming have passed, and everything depends on Teshuvah. When the Jewish people do Teshuvah, they will immediately be redeemed.</p></blockquote>
<p>In 1979, The Rebbe had a yehidus with a couple from Australia, where he said the same thing.</p>
<p>Already in the prior year in 1978, the Rebbe turned to a doctor to help him with this request to develop meditation without idolatry. It gets reprinted around the web as if the Rebbe was answering a question from the doctor rather, in fact, the Rebbe was seeking out the doctor. Notice the Rebbe’s citation of  the Federal Court case.and his assumption that much of this is already part of medical practice. I did include parts that are similar to the Sicha- <a href="http://portraitofaleader.blogspot.com/2007/10/needless-to-say-on-my-part-i-will-do.html">full version here</a>, and <a href="http://www.crownheights.info/index.php?itemid=12180">here.</a> We can see the Rebbe&#8217;s thought in formation</p>
<blockquote><p>By the Grace of G-d Teveth, 5738<br />
In as much as these movements involve certain rites and rituals, they have been rightly regarded by Rabbinic authorities as cults bordering on, and in some respects actual, Avodah Zarah (idolatry). Accordingly Rabbinic authorities everywhere, and particularly in Eretz Yisroel, ruled that these cults come under all the strictures associated with Avodah Zarah, so that also their appurtenances come under strict prohibition.</p>
<p>Moreover, the United States Federal Court also ruled recently that such movements, by virtue of embracing such rites and rituals, must be classifies as cultic and religious movements. (Of. Malnak V. Maharishi Mahesh Yogi, U.S.D.C. of N.J. 76-341, esp. pp. 36-50, 78)On the other hand, certain aspects of the said movements, which are entirely irrelevant to religious worship or practices, have a therapeutic value, particularly in the area of relieving mental stress.</p>
<p>It follows that if these therapeutic methods – insofar as they are utterly devoid of any ritual implications – would be adopted by doctors specializing in the field of mental illness, it would have two-pronged salutary effect: Firstly, in the view of the fact that these methods are therapeutically effective, while there are, regretfully, many who could benefit from such treatment, this is a matter of healing of the highest order, since it has to do with mental illness. It would, therefore, be very wrong to deny such treatment to those who need it, when it could be given by a practicing doctor.</p>
<p>Secondly, and this too is not less important, since there are many Jewish sufferers who continue to avail themselves of these methods though the said cults despite the Rabbinic prohibition, it can be assumed with certainty that many of them, if not all, who are drawn to these cults by the promise of mental relief, would prefer to receive the same treatment from the medical profession – if they had a choice of getting it the kosher way. It would thus be possible to save many Jews from getting involved with the said cults.</p>
<p>It is also known, though not widely, that there are individual doctors who practice the same or similar methods at T.M. and the like. However, it seems that these methods occupy a secondary or subordinate role in their procedures. More importantly, there is almost a complete lack of publicity regarding the application of these methods by doctors, and since the main practice of these doctors is linked with the conventional neurological and psychiatric approach, it is generally assumed that whatever success they achieve is not connected with results obtained from methods relating to T.M. and the like; results which the cults acclaim with such fanfare.</p>
<p>In light of the above, it is suggested and strongly urged that:</p>
<p>Appropriate action be undertaken to enlist the cooperation of a group of doctors specializing in neurology and psychiatry who would research the said methods with a view to perfecting them and adopting them in their practice on a wider scale.</p>
<p>All due publicity be given about the availability of such methods from practicing doctors.</p>
<p>This should be done most expeditiously, without waiting for this vital information to be disseminated through medical journals, where research and findings usually take a long time before they come to the attention of practicing physicians. This would all the sooner counteract the untold harm done to so many Jews who are attracted daily to the said cults, as mentioned in the opening paragraph.</p>
<p>In conclusion: This memo is intended for all Rabbis, doctors, and layman who are in a position to advance the cause espoused herein, the importance of which needs no further elaboration.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/30/the-lubavitcher-rebbe-on-transcendental-meditation/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>31</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Can Kabbalah be translated into a modern idiom?</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/04/can-kabbalah-be-translated-into-a-modern-idiom/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/04/can-kabbalah-be-translated-into-a-modern-idiom/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 04 Nov 2009 00:57:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bahir]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[les lancaster]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sefer Yetsirah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sefer Yetzirah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[trans-personal psychology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=204</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I found an interesting article written for  the BBC from a transpersonal psychologist in England The essence of Jewish meditation By Professor Les Lancaster The very nice and sensitive essay shows the problems in trying to translate Kabbalah on meditation &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/04/can-kabbalah-be-translated-into-a-modern-idiom/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I found an interesting article written for  the BBC from a transpersonal psychologist in England<strong> The essence of Jewish meditation</strong><strong> </strong><em>By<a href="http://www.ljmu.ac.uk/Psychology/71506.htm"> Professor Les Lancaster</a> </em>The very nice and sensitive essay shows the problems in trying to translate Kabbalah on meditation in modern terms.</p>
<p>It lets me ask about the process of presenting Jewish kavvanot to a modern audience.</p>
<p>The basic worldview for the kabbalist is the sefirotic chart, arranged as concentric circles, a Jacob’s ladder or chain of being, expressed with medieval philosophic language.  A kabbalist’s view of God and the world was arranged in nestled chains, God emanates into the world. This cosmology of chains is not just a points on a cord, but vast realms, lights, and colors, a realm to transverse, a way of marking off distance. This cosmology was accepted as based on the Jewish tradition, the experiential truth of the method, and as part of accepting the theology of the Kabbalah.  This worldview, for them, was as corrigible as a map. Meaning that unlike a dream where no incorrect dream, Kabbalah is a vision correctable based on the writings and visions of others. For the kabbalists the kabbalistic worldview is objective, subject to correct and incorrect turns, and offers a reproducible mental world. One chooses one path, one worldview, and follows it. The traditional meditator does not credit the human mind or imagination with these depths, rather he starts with a map obtained through the study of Kabbalah.</p>
<p>But I am trying to pin down how we get from my description of the past to the following:</p>
<p><em> </em></p>
<blockquote><p>What is Jewish meditation?</p>
<p>It involves shifting the centre of gravity of the mind away from the sense of &#8216;I&#8217; which normally dominates our goals. Like all meditative practices, Jewish mystical techniques are directed towards enhancing this second form of thinking. At the same time, these practices cultivate an awareness of the divine presence in all things.<br />
The objective of meditation is to engage with these deeper currents.</p>
<p>One of the major texts of Kabbalah, the 12th-century Bahir, writes that the biblical prophet Habakkuk &#8216;understood God&#8217;s thought.&#8217; It tells us:<br />
<em>&#8220;Just as human thought has no end, for even a mere mortal can think and descend to the end of the world, so too the ear also has no end and is not satiated.&#8221;</em><br />
Jewish mystical practices enable us to use thought to &#8216;descend to the end of the world&#8217;, that is, to plumb the depths where mind and physical reality are no longer separate.</p>
<p>The goals of Jewish meditation<br />
-heighten one&#8217;s understanding of the Torah<br />
-develop an understanding of ritual and other religious observances<br />
-give direction to prayer<br />
-increase one&#8217;s awareness of others&#8217; needs</p>
<p>One of the oldest texts that describes Jewish meditation practices is the Sefer Yetsirah. Consider the following extract:<br />
<em>&#8220;Ten dimensions of nothingness. Their measure is ten to which there is no end.</em><em><br />
</em><em>A depth of beginning, a depth of end; a depth of good, a depth of evil; a depth of above, a depth of below; a depth of east, a depth of west; a depth of north, a depth of south.</em><br />
<em>The unified Master &#8211; God faithful King &#8211; rules over all of them, from His holy dwelling place, until eternity of eternities.&#8221;</em><br />
The meditation based on this passage entails consciously building up a deep sense of your place in relation to the dimensions.</p>
<p>The meditation continues with the first of the six directions of space. What is immediately above you? Air&#8230; the ceiling&#8230; other rooms&#8230; the roof&#8230; birds&#8230; sky&#8230; vastness of space&#8230; the infinite that cannot be formed in the mind&#8230;<br />
It is as if you generate a beam of light from within that is gradually extended further and further whilst, at the same time, maintaining your awareness of the centre, the heart as the source of light&#8230; And then continue into the remaining directions. You may glimpse your inner core suspended at the heart of a web of infinite interconnections.</p></blockquote>
<p>We have the idea of limitless expanse, which was originally sefirot, treated as the depths of the mind. I understand the need for the psychology. Yet what happens to the Neoplatonic depth? Identifying mind and physical reality has a bit of a countercultural sound to it. Gone is the need to go through an ascent to reach God either by chambers, cosmos, worlds, souls. The author, similar to the popular pamphlets issued by the school of the Magid of Mezerich pushed away the meditation of the Kabblah. Early Hasidism thought that though emotional enthusiasm one could ascend through all the worlds, sefirot, and chambers. Here entering the depth of one’s mind has the same effect.</p>
<p>I get confused by the goals. Does it help by giving one esoteric knowledge? Does it mean viewing one’s mitzvot and prayer as taking place in the kabbalistic cosmology?  And why claim it will make one more sensitive to the needs of others. At least, Buddhists will distinguish between jhana (knowledge) and metta (love-kindness). Here it seems everything is blurred.</p>
<p>In his use of Sefer Yetzirah, we have the conversion of a scientific-cosmological text into a meditation on space. Deep of divinity becomes depth of the soul.In this modern version, one looks into the inner core of the self, the heart, and the limits of the ordinary mind. One is not told about the traditional phrases “fixed order of lights” “the infinity of God” or the need to identify with the Divine will.”</p>
<p>I find much of our presentations of Kabbalah on the popular level to be modern psychology. I do think we need to use modern psychology and not medieval psychology, but what are the boundaries for a successful translation? Many of the popular Orthodox presentations are straight pop-psych and new age. What is the limit in modernizing the medieval?</p>
<p><a href="http://solitude-hisbodedus.blogspot.com/2009/10/essence-of-jewish-meditation.html">Hat tip: Solitude</a>&#8211; it cites the full version. For the <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/judaism/worship/meditation_1.shtml">original BBC- here</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/04/can-kabbalah-be-translated-into-a-modern-idiom/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>8</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
