<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Modern Orthodoxy- Modern meant Moral Self-transformation	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/14/modern-orthodoxy-modern-meant-moral-self-transformation/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/14/modern-orthodoxy-modern-meant-moral-self-transformation/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2009 02:18:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Grey		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/14/modern-orthodoxy-modern-meant-moral-self-transformation/#comment-335</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Grey]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2009 02:18:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=356#comment-335</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Also I don&#039;t think about anyone following my vision these days but me. I could never get that Shaalvim guy to change his hashkafa because he&#039;s concentrated his entire religious experience into what he did in the beis. It&#039;s a shame that without that he doesn&#039;t know what to do.

He adopted the view because it appealed to him, but I don&#039;t think he consciously understood why he made the choice. Since you&#039;re asking, the only thing I could hope for the MO community is a greater understanding of itself so that they&#039;d be a bit more conscious of where they are and what they want. Many of them don&#039;t engage with God and the tradition as externalities, but delve internally for that projected idealism. Many of them don&#039;t see doubt as part and parcel to a life of faith. For a religious denomination that prided itself on engaging the outside world, this has implications. An RCA rav recently sad that one should not send their kids to a secular college because of the 25% chance they&#039;ll leave the fold. How did we get to seeing the university as the problem here and not ourselves?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Also I don&#8217;t think about anyone following my vision these days but me. I could never get that Shaalvim guy to change his hashkafa because he&#8217;s concentrated his entire religious experience into what he did in the beis. It&#8217;s a shame that without that he doesn&#8217;t know what to do.</p>
<p>He adopted the view because it appealed to him, but I don&#8217;t think he consciously understood why he made the choice. Since you&#8217;re asking, the only thing I could hope for the MO community is a greater understanding of itself so that they&#8217;d be a bit more conscious of where they are and what they want. Many of them don&#8217;t engage with God and the tradition as externalities, but delve internally for that projected idealism. Many of them don&#8217;t see doubt as part and parcel to a life of faith. For a religious denomination that prided itself on engaging the outside world, this has implications. An RCA rav recently sad that one should not send their kids to a secular college because of the 25% chance they&#8217;ll leave the fold. How did we get to seeing the university as the problem here and not ourselves?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Grey		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/14/modern-orthodoxy-modern-meant-moral-self-transformation/#comment-334</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Grey]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2009 01:24:03 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=356#comment-334</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Well I used to have the engineer&#039;s approach to learning that seems to come along with the Brisker conceptual understanding of sugyas. That certainly is a popular trend and part of the culture&#039;s general message.

I guess I couldn&#039;t buy it for that long. It was too neat, too contained in an abstract world in my head. Texts are messier than a shanna bet guy&#039;s chakiras, and if your maskanas have no real effect on your life, again it doesn&#039;t leave your head. The religious experience is reduced to the intellectual exercise, so they fixate on that high. Or else they invent their own historiographies throw in some kabballah... the Rav believed that for the tradition to remain relevant it must engage people intellectually. They seem to be using their heads no matter how psuedo-scientific or pseudo-scholarly they get.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Well I used to have the engineer&#8217;s approach to learning that seems to come along with the Brisker conceptual understanding of sugyas. That certainly is a popular trend and part of the culture&#8217;s general message.</p>
<p>I guess I couldn&#8217;t buy it for that long. It was too neat, too contained in an abstract world in my head. Texts are messier than a shanna bet guy&#8217;s chakiras, and if your maskanas have no real effect on your life, again it doesn&#8217;t leave your head. The religious experience is reduced to the intellectual exercise, so they fixate on that high. Or else they invent their own historiographies throw in some kabballah&#8230; the Rav believed that for the tradition to remain relevant it must engage people intellectually. They seem to be using their heads no matter how psuedo-scientific or pseudo-scholarly they get.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/14/modern-orthodoxy-modern-meant-moral-self-transformation/#comment-332</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2009 01:01:51 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=356#comment-332</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/14/modern-orthodoxy-modern-meant-moral-self-transformation/#comment-331&quot;&gt;Grey&lt;/a&gt;.

I do not think it is transformation or nothing. It meant something.
You mentioned in the last post that you have a l’tzaref et a habriyot approach with the requisite intellectual and moral rigor. There are many MO teachers in the more American programs that do not take that approach. They take the approach of &quot;lets give them as much as possible so that when it wears off, there will still be more left&quot; And the students themselves take approaches of seeing themselves a sinner and putting on a black hat will help keep them from their sins. You seem to have a perfection of the self approach, many have an approach of &quot;unless I am watched I go back to my old ways. So once again it is not even right wing as straw man, but they add all things they do because they feel it is good for them.
Since you mention magical realism and teaching a classroom, you seem to have a humanities sensibility. Some out there approach learning Torah like an engineer solving a problem or a puzzle. They will piece everything together in their own mind and then say QED - this is the original intention They will fit history, sociology, kabbalah, and Bible into their calculations. The product will seem right wing but once again it serves the MO person&#039;s own needs.
There is a need for better analysis of the year in Israel than currently available.

Grey-
What should be the aspiration to replace autonomy and rationality? Why will others go along with your vision?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/14/modern-orthodoxy-modern-meant-moral-self-transformation/#comment-331">Grey</a>.</p>
<p>I do not think it is transformation or nothing. It meant something.<br />
You mentioned in the last post that you have a l’tzaref et a habriyot approach with the requisite intellectual and moral rigor. There are many MO teachers in the more American programs that do not take that approach. They take the approach of &#8220;lets give them as much as possible so that when it wears off, there will still be more left&#8221; And the students themselves take approaches of seeing themselves a sinner and putting on a black hat will help keep them from their sins. You seem to have a perfection of the self approach, many have an approach of &#8220;unless I am watched I go back to my old ways. So once again it is not even right wing as straw man, but they add all things they do because they feel it is good for them.<br />
Since you mention magical realism and teaching a classroom, you seem to have a humanities sensibility. Some out there approach learning Torah like an engineer solving a problem or a puzzle. They will piece everything together in their own mind and then say QED &#8211; this is the original intention They will fit history, sociology, kabbalah, and Bible into their calculations. The product will seem right wing but once again it serves the MO person&#8217;s own needs.<br />
There is a need for better analysis of the year in Israel than currently available.</p>
<p>Grey-<br />
What should be the aspiration to replace autonomy and rationality? Why will others go along with your vision?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Grey		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/14/modern-orthodoxy-modern-meant-moral-self-transformation/#comment-331</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Grey]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2009 23:55:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=356#comment-331</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I mentioned the right-wing conspiracy as a sort of straw-man. It says more to me about how conspiracy theories are needed by some to explain why MO has its identity crisis.

As for freedom without leaving yeshiva, that&#039;s not true in the literal or figurative sense--the literal freedom of movement they have is much more than they did under their parents&#039; homes. Restaurants? That&#039;s nothing. There are drug scandals, late night boozing, and incredible excesses with the same people later deciding to stay until midnight in the beis. I know more than one person who did leave the yeshiva permanently.

Internal narratives are certainly at work here, and I saw them being written. The year in Israel is a much more complicated equation that any catch-all explication I&#039;ve heard or read. Even the Shaalvim guy you heard interviewed--I&#039;d bet had the unexpected happen often in his year in Israel even while ending up in the expected place. The internal narrative necessarily begins with them as a product of their communities--for better or worse--and ends with them in a reevaluated state. Is it right to say that because they haven&#039;t turned down the middle class benefits, the change which clearly meant something to them really means nothing?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I mentioned the right-wing conspiracy as a sort of straw-man. It says more to me about how conspiracy theories are needed by some to explain why MO has its identity crisis.</p>
<p>As for freedom without leaving yeshiva, that&#8217;s not true in the literal or figurative sense&#8211;the literal freedom of movement they have is much more than they did under their parents&#8217; homes. Restaurants? That&#8217;s nothing. There are drug scandals, late night boozing, and incredible excesses with the same people later deciding to stay until midnight in the beis. I know more than one person who did leave the yeshiva permanently.</p>
<p>Internal narratives are certainly at work here, and I saw them being written. The year in Israel is a much more complicated equation that any catch-all explication I&#8217;ve heard or read. Even the Shaalvim guy you heard interviewed&#8211;I&#8217;d bet had the unexpected happen often in his year in Israel even while ending up in the expected place. The internal narrative necessarily begins with them as a product of their communities&#8211;for better or worse&#8211;and ends with them in a reevaluated state. Is it right to say that because they haven&#8217;t turned down the middle class benefits, the change which clearly meant something to them really means nothing?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/14/modern-orthodoxy-modern-meant-moral-self-transformation/#comment-317</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2009 13:20:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=356#comment-317</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The freedom has become a form of Amish Rumspringa giving them a period of freedom. But that fits into life back home. They can enjoy freedom without have to leave yeshiva. I think it was discussed on Lookjed. And just like the Amish, without retooling or a new support system the majority will always return back home. And the current version is not like the austerity of the Yeshivot of the 1970&#039;s and early 1980s. They enjoy and value spending money at restaurants and going home for passover, and buying an entire range of religious products to confirm their year. Few are opting out of the middle class life and they know in their minds that they want to live the material benefits of back home. My basic point was that, except in a few cases,  it is not a right wing conspiracy.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The freedom has become a form of Amish Rumspringa giving them a period of freedom. But that fits into life back home. They can enjoy freedom without have to leave yeshiva. I think it was discussed on Lookjed. And just like the Amish, without retooling or a new support system the majority will always return back home. And the current version is not like the austerity of the Yeshivot of the 1970&#8217;s and early 1980s. They enjoy and value spending money at restaurants and going home for passover, and buying an entire range of religious products to confirm their year. Few are opting out of the middle class life and they know in their minds that they want to live the material benefits of back home. My basic point was that, except in a few cases,  it is not a right wing conspiracy.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Grey		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/14/modern-orthodoxy-modern-meant-moral-self-transformation/#comment-316</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Grey]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2009 22:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=356#comment-316</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I saw something very different from my time in Israel. First of all emotion and projected ideal is pretty Israeli too when I think about it. But aside from that, while I think that particular Shaalvim guy&#039;s response was telling, it&#039;d be ridiculous to say his it epitomizes what the year in Israel is going for.  To me it&#039;s true that a lot of Shaalvim or Gush guys try to turn their intellectual process in learning into an emotional pseudo-religious high. I personally always saw it (influenced by the Rav) as a process of l&#039;tzaref et a habriyot, with the intellectual and personal discipline of leaning and applying the halachah. But in other yeshivahs you find people who go for the same pseudo-religious experience (again as I see it) in shmoneh esrei, where they struggle for that emotional flow in tfilah to the point that they confuse certain rishonim&#039;s ideas of l&#039;atzmo and l&#039;makom. 

Sorry if my own hashkafah was injected a little in that tangent, but what I&#039;m trying to get to is that while you do have these as general trends, what I saw in Israel was an incredible amount of freedom that was radically different from the structured and sheltered existence these kids had known all their lives. Whether they stop being observant or not, they&#039;re far away from that middle class American household and can choose to make whatever they want to of the structure of yeshiva life. Few of even the more obedient kids would take that opportunity to simply accept more of what&#039;s being taught. They look to make it their own, at least, or even to decide for themselves how much want it. It might not be a coherent or lasting response to the American Ortho middle-class condition, but most of the time it is &lt;i&gt;necessarily&lt;/i&gt; a response.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I saw something very different from my time in Israel. First of all emotion and projected ideal is pretty Israeli too when I think about it. But aside from that, while I think that particular Shaalvim guy&#8217;s response was telling, it&#8217;d be ridiculous to say his it epitomizes what the year in Israel is going for.  To me it&#8217;s true that a lot of Shaalvim or Gush guys try to turn their intellectual process in learning into an emotional pseudo-religious high. I personally always saw it (influenced by the Rav) as a process of l&#8217;tzaref et a habriyot, with the intellectual and personal discipline of leaning and applying the halachah. But in other yeshivahs you find people who go for the same pseudo-religious experience (again as I see it) in shmoneh esrei, where they struggle for that emotional flow in tfilah to the point that they confuse certain rishonim&#8217;s ideas of l&#8217;atzmo and l&#8217;makom. </p>
<p>Sorry if my own hashkafah was injected a little in that tangent, but what I&#8217;m trying to get to is that while you do have these as general trends, what I saw in Israel was an incredible amount of freedom that was radically different from the structured and sheltered existence these kids had known all their lives. Whether they stop being observant or not, they&#8217;re far away from that middle class American household and can choose to make whatever they want to of the structure of yeshiva life. Few of even the more obedient kids would take that opportunity to simply accept more of what&#8217;s being taught. They look to make it their own, at least, or even to decide for themselves how much want it. It might not be a coherent or lasting response to the American Ortho middle-class condition, but most of the time it is <i>necessarily</i> a response.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/14/modern-orthodoxy-modern-meant-moral-self-transformation/#comment-314</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2009 20:00:03 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=356#comment-314</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I totally agree with the first paragraph.
But your second paragraph. I think the year in Israel was not haredi conspiracy or in contrast to their American life. 
The goal of the year is emotion and projected ideal. They need that for their American reasons, it keeps out questions, it leads to an emotive religion, and it is a peak experience that builds a type of Orthodoxy that people wanted. I recently sat on a dissertation committee for a dissertation that interviewed a Shaalavim-YU guy. The guy said that learning gives him a high, a sense of flow like playing basketball but learning is from God while basketball is not. But he knows that he will not have it once he goes to work. I see that this internal narrative is the transformation caused by the year in Israel, not a haredi plot. And I see the year and this narrative  as sustaining as middle class-life.  learning for a sense of flow is similar to the way some current American Pentecostalism works.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I totally agree with the first paragraph.<br />
But your second paragraph. I think the year in Israel was not haredi conspiracy or in contrast to their American life.<br />
The goal of the year is emotion and projected ideal. They need that for their American reasons, it keeps out questions, it leads to an emotive religion, and it is a peak experience that builds a type of Orthodoxy that people wanted. I recently sat on a dissertation committee for a dissertation that interviewed a Shaalavim-YU guy. The guy said that learning gives him a high, a sense of flow like playing basketball but learning is from God while basketball is not. But he knows that he will not have it once he goes to work. I see that this internal narrative is the transformation caused by the year in Israel, not a haredi plot. And I see the year and this narrative  as sustaining as middle class-life.  learning for a sense of flow is similar to the way some current American Pentecostalism works.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Grey		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/14/modern-orthodoxy-modern-meant-moral-self-transformation/#comment-313</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Grey]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2009 19:45:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=356#comment-313</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I like it. But I also try to recall Sander Gilman&#039;s &lt;i&gt;Jewish Self-Hatred&lt;/i&gt; when considering our self-definitions. Disregarding the rav and the central thinkers in and of themselves, many of us didn&#039;t just criticize everyone else for being irrational or not modern. We were criticizing the backwards Jew, whom we imagined society rejecting.

A friend of mine just sent me an article from the New Vilna Review,, basically outlining a chareidi conspiracy against the MO community consisting of Leib Tropper and the year in Israel. Why couldn&#039;t the year in Israel speak (potentially) to the kind of self-transformation you&#039;re talking about. It could--again potentially--respond to the middle class, American, ortho life on multiple levels, and not just a rational/ethical one? Meh. Just a thought.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I like it. But I also try to recall Sander Gilman&#8217;s <i>Jewish Self-Hatred</i> when considering our self-definitions. Disregarding the rav and the central thinkers in and of themselves, many of us didn&#8217;t just criticize everyone else for being irrational or not modern. We were criticizing the backwards Jew, whom we imagined society rejecting.</p>
<p>A friend of mine just sent me an article from the New Vilna Review,, basically outlining a chareidi conspiracy against the MO community consisting of Leib Tropper and the year in Israel. Why couldn&#8217;t the year in Israel speak (potentially) to the kind of self-transformation you&#8217;re talking about. It could&#8211;again potentially&#8211;respond to the middle class, American, ortho life on multiple levels, and not just a rational/ethical one? Meh. Just a thought.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Jonathan Hirsch		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/14/modern-orthodoxy-modern-meant-moral-self-transformation/#comment-254</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jonathan Hirsch]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2009 18:14:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=356#comment-254</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Perhaps part of what holds Modern Orthodoxy back is it is too tied to legitamating a Suburban lifestyle , perhaps  it needs to focus more on personal intraspection (not define things by rigt and left ) perhaps there are many statements in Chazal which talk about Ethical refinement these teachings need to gain greater prominence and focus]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Perhaps part of what holds Modern Orthodoxy back is it is too tied to legitamating a Suburban lifestyle , perhaps  it needs to focus more on personal intraspection (not define things by rigt and left ) perhaps there are many statements in Chazal which talk about Ethical refinement these teachings need to gain greater prominence and focus</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
