<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>philosophy &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/category/uncategorized/philosophy/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Jul 2010 16:24:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='kavvanah.wordpress.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/c9f111237f93750b6b994fc5185d49c3?s=96&#038;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>philosophy &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>David Shasha on Kellner, Idel, and Nationalism</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/08/david-shasha-on-kellner-idel-and-nationalism/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/08/david-shasha-on-kellner-idel-and-nationalism/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2010 21:16:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[israel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[david shasha]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[menachem Kellner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Moshe idel]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1643</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[David Shasha is a proponent of all things Sefardi and a radical follower of Jose Faur who envisions a Levantine synthesis of Jewish and Arabic humanism. Shasha offers a critique of Kellner, Idel and others as destroying the humanistic foundations &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/08/david-shasha-on-kellner-idel-and-nationalism/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>David Shasha is a proponent of  all things Sefardi and a radical follower of Jose Faur who envisions a Levantine synthesis of Jewish and Arabic humanism. Shasha offers a critique of Kellner, Idel and others as destroying the humanistic foundations of Judaism. He claims that they destroy the foundation of Maimonidean humanism even if they accept Maimonides. Kellner advocates for the rationalism of Maimonides but back-handedly considers the Maimonideans as too demanding for the common person, as rejecting folk religion, and as not the Jewish tradition. Shasha demands that Maimonides be considered the tradition or else Maimonideans would always be in a defensive position. If one does not live in a rational world then all the power is in the magical hand of the rabbis. </p>
<p>Shasha places blame at the feet of Moshe Idel who explores the magical, irrational, and mythic forces in Judaism but who also maintains that this theurgic world is the world of the Talmudic Rabbis. For Idel, the Rabbinic tradition is magical. Kabbalah is not a Gnostic intruder into Judaism but the very meaning of the commandments for the Rabbis. Once Jews studied Saadyah, Ibn Ezra, Maimonides, Gersonides as the traditon, now they read Abulafia and Zohar. For Shasha, this is tantamount to a return to idolatry and the source of militant nationalism. <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/david-shasha/dangerous-mystic-motifs-i_b_637535.html">Full Version here.</a></p>
<p>Shasha writes:<br />
<em>At the center of this controversy is the vexing question of Jewish authenticity.<br />
In his 2006 study &#8220;Maimonides&#8217; Confrontation with Mysticism,&#8221; Menachem Kellner adopts an approach that has become standard in most Jewish circles, writing:</p>
<blockquote><p>&#8220;The Jewish world in which Maimonides lived was uncongenial to the austere, abstract, demanding vision of Torah which he preached. Evidence from a wide variety of sources shows that Jews in Maimonides&#8217; day &#8211; common folk and scholars alike &#8211; accepted astrology, the magical use of divine names, appeals to angels, etc.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p></em><em> In a noble attempt to elevate the thinking of Maimonides, Kellner&#8217;s arguments bizarrely lend credence to the positions of the anti-Maimonideans.</em><br />
<em>In the book&#8217;s conclusion he states:</em></p>
<blockquote><p>The world favored by Maimonides&#8217; opponents, on the other hand, is an &#8220;enchanted&#8221; world. Many of Maimonides&#8217; opponents, in his day and ours, do indeed accept the efficacy of charms and amulets, and fear the harm of demons and the evil eye. But it is not in that sense that I maintain that they live in an enchanted world. Theirs is not a world which can be explained in terms of the unvarying workings of divinely ordered laws of nature; it is not a world which can be rationally understood. It is a world in which the notion of miracle loses all meaning, since everything that happens is a miracle. In such a world instructions from God, and contact with the divine in general, must be mediated by a religious elite who alone can see the true reality masked by nature. This is the opposite of an empowering religion, since it takes their fate out of the hands of Jews, and, in effect, puts it into the hands of the rabbis.</p></blockquote>
<p><em>We can see the tension at the heart of Kellner&#8217;s argument, a tension that forces his hand in accepting the absolute authenticity of the mystical-occult tradition of the Kabbalah and rejecting the Jewish validity of Maimonidean rationalism.</p>
<p>Kellner&#8217;s book contains a forward by Hebrew University professor Moshe Idel, perhaps the single most influential academic in the world of Judaica, a winner of the prestigious Israel Prize and a ubiquitous presence in the world of Jewish studies. Idel has relentlessly promoted the pro-magic, neo-pagan, anti-rational strain of Jewish tradition also called Kabbalah. </p>
<p>Idel&#8217;s scholarly project has been designed to affirm the authenticity of the mystical-occult Kabbalah and undermine the validity of the rational standards of Religious Humanism. As we see in a representative passage in his seminal 1988 work &#8220;Kabbalah: New Perspectives&#8221;:</em></p>
<blockquote><p>Kabbalah can be viewed as part of a restructuring of those aspects of rabbinic thought that were denied authenticity by Maimonides&#8217; system. Far from being a total innovation, historical Kabbalah represented an ongoing effort to systematize existing elements of Jewish theurgy, myth, and mysticism into a full-fledged response to the rationalistic challenge.<br />
It is, however, possible to assume that, if the motifs transmitted in those unknown [Kabbalistic] circles formed part of an ancient weltanschauung, their affinities to the rabbinic mentality would be more organic and easily absorbed into the mystic cast of Judaism.<br />
According to this hypothesis, we do not need to account for why ancient Jews took over Gnostic doctrines, why they transmitted them, and, finally, how this &#8216;Gnostic&#8217; Judaism was revived in the Middle Ages by conservative Jewish authorities. </p></blockquote>
<p>Shasha concludes:</p>
<p><em>This has led to the rejection of Sephardic Jewish Humanism as formulated by Maimonides and an affirmation of an ethnocentric Jewish chauvinism based on the magical mysticism of Kabbalistic theurgy. It is a Judaism that rejects the tenets of a critical reading of the Jewish past and has led us to the sort of ideological purity and militant nationalism that has become characteristic of the intractable impasse in the Middle East. Though this occult process has been secularized by Zionism, it is apparent that the ideological values of the mystical continue to animate the Jewish self-perception in a nationalistic sense.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/08/david-shasha-on-kellner-idel-and-nationalism/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>10</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Is God a Delusion? A Reply to Religion’s Cultured Despisers</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/18/is-god-a-delusion-a-reply-to-religion%e2%80%99s-cultured-despisers/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/18/is-god-a-delusion-a-reply-to-religion%e2%80%99s-cultured-despisers/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Jun 2010 23:04:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophy]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1556</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The books by the new atheists were widely read and eye opening for those raised in the prior decades of religious certainty but they garnered little praise from professional philosophers. Everyone has heard the arguments before in Bertram Russel&#8217;s &#8220;Why &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/18/is-god-a-delusion-a-reply-to-religion%e2%80%99s-cultured-despisers/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The books by the new atheists were widely read and eye opening for those raised in the prior decades of religious certainty but they garnered little praise from professional philosophers. Everyone has heard the arguments before in Bertram Russel&#8217;s <em>&#8220;Why I am not a Christian&#8221;</em> Tom Paine&#8217;s delightful <em>Age of Reason</em>, and the Joseph Lewis&#8217; less delightful <em>The Bible Unmasked</em>. Most of the cultured responses were snarky or dismissive to the atheists as not knowing the history of ideas. </p>
<p>But now we have an interesting new volume that answers the new atheists as part of a book designed for an undergraduate introduction to philosophy course or introduction to religion, God a Delusion? A Reply to Religion’s Cultured Despisers by Eric Reitan. The book won an award as an outstanding academic work. It does not refute the atheists as much as use them to open the discussion about Anselm, Aquinas, and Schleiermacher. I am always on the lookout for good &#8220;teaching&#8221; books. This one looks like it would be appropriate for the right class, bothered by these problems. It would be a good introduction for those who only know the popular literature. It would also be useful for someone trying to explain Saadya and Maimonidean theism to a contemporary fideist.</p>
<blockquote><p>Is God a Delusion? A Reply to Religion’s Cultured Despisers</p>
<p>Eric Reitan’s latest book, Is God a Delusion? A Reply to Religion’s Cultured Despisers was named an Outstanding Academic Title of 2009. Here he tells us how he was motivated to write the book partly in response to the misrepresentations of religious thought he discovered in Richard Dawkins’ The God Delusion, but also by a very personal desire to reconcile his deep intuitions about ultimate reality with open intellectual inquiry.</p>
<p>Why did you decide to write Is God a Delusion?<br />
Eric Reitan: One day a few years ago, a colleague of mine handed me a photocopied page from a book, without any identifying information, and asked me to evaluate it as I would a student paper. On that page the unknown author attempted to summarize and then critique the first three of Aquinas’ “Five Ways” for proving God’s existence. I say “attempted” because the author got the arguments wrong and then critiqued them at precisely the points of misunderstanding.</p>
<p>As it turns out, that page was taken from Richard Dawkins’ The God Delusion. And so I became curious about the book and bought a copy. By the time I was finished I found myself thinking, “You know, I could write an entire introduction to the philosophy of religion just by noting what Dawkins has to say about classic questions in the field, pointing out his oversights and errors, and then introducing the reader to the more developed ideas of great thinkers.</p>
<p>What’s the central concern of the book, and why is it important?<br />
ER: Is God a Delusion? addresses the range of new atheist challenges to religion, not for the purely negative aim of exposing their shortcomings, but for the more productive purpose of trying to identify the parameters within which religion can be both intellectually respectable and morally benign. <strong>I’m surprised at how often the book has been mistakenly dubbed an apologetic response to the new atheists…and then criticized as a poor example of apologetics because it fails to defend the kind of religion that the new atheists are attacking. But my aim in the book was never to defend what the new atheists attack, but rather to show that their objections to theistic religion are not as sweeping as the new atheists present them as being. That is, there is a way to believe in God, a way to live a life of religious faith, that does not fall prey to new atheist objections. </p>
<p>To a lesser extent, I also wanted to explore where and how religion goes wrong. Why is it that religion as we encounter it in the world so regularly strays outside the parameters of reasonableness and moral decency? Unlike the new atheists, I don’t think the answer lies in something essential to religion itself. Rather, I think it is the result of certain common human failings—such things as the need for certainty even where certainty can’t be had, and the propensity to find meaning and self-worth through membership in groups that define themselves </strong>against opposing groups.</p>
<p>And what is it that draws you to this topic?<br />
This juxtaposition led me on a personal struggle of sorts—the struggle to find religion characterized not only by a sincere desire to live in connection with the transcendent but also by the values I couldn’t set aside: intellectual openness and honesty, compassion, and a respect for fellow humanity that reaches across the differences that so often separate us. My search for the former brought me first into a deep flirtation with modes of religion that challenged the latter—which isn’t surprising, since my most powerful religious influence during childhood had been my mother’s father, with whom I shared a special bond but who was a preacher in a tradition that tended towards exclusivism and suspicion of free thought.</p>
<p>In any event, that personal struggle has made me deeply interested in the issues I explore in the book. I’ve experienced first hand and struggled personally with the notion, so characteristic of much of the contemporary public discourse on religion, that we must choose between masters: religion or science, faith or reason, God or our fallible human conscience. In my personal life I traced out in intuitive terms a path between these false dichotomies. In Is God a Delusion?, my aim is to trace out that same path on a more intellectual level.<br />
What sort of reaction do you hope it will get?</p>
<p>ER: At this point, it’s hard to separate my hopes from the actual reactions the book has already generated. I was deeply gratified, of course, that Is God a Delusion? was named a Choice Outstanding Academic Title of 2009, and I’ve been thrilled every time a philosopher or theologian in some other part of the world contacted me to express appreciation for the book. This kind of response from the academic world is in many ways more than I could have hoped for.</p>
<p>The response from atheist readers has been mixed, but in many ways pretty well tracks what I was hoping to do with the book in relation to that audience. Some atheist readers have found in the book a development of a species of religion they can respect even if they don’t agree with it—and then engaged me in stimulating discussions about key points of disagreement. </p>
<p>What sort of audience did you have in mind when you wrote it?<br />
But I also hope that the book can be profitably used in undergraduate philosophy of religion courses. Although it’s no longer the introduction to the philosophy of religion I had originally intended to write, much of that original idea still shapes the book. I suspect that philosophy of religion teachers will notice very quickly that the topics I cover are some of the staple issues in the field, as are many of the thinkers I discuss. In fact, in my own philosophy of religion course I’ve been pairing my book with The God Delusion and a traditional philosophy of religion anthology, basically with the aim of doing what I’d originally thought to do in the book—and it has proved to be very successful in getting students to see the relevance of philosophical work to issues of contemporary significance. Also, it just makes the course more fun.<br />
Is there another book you wish you could claim credit for?<br />
I also find so much to admire in Charles Taylor’s short and accessible treatment of William James’ religious thought, Varieties of Religion Today, that I’d love to claim credit for it.<br />
<a href="http://religioncompass.wordpress.com/2010/06/15/is-god-a-delusion/"><br />
Read the whole interview here.</a>
</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/18/is-god-a-delusion-a-reply-to-religion%e2%80%99s-cultured-despisers/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>50 Philosophy Blogs</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/18/50-philosophy-blogs/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/18/50-philosophy-blogs/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Jun 2010 22:00:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1540</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Here is a nice list of 50 philosophy blogs. It has all the best ones Some are single author professional academics like the Leiter Report, others are multi-author academic like PEA soup, and Continental Philosophy blog is an essential bulletin &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/18/50-philosophy-blogs/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://onlinechristiancolleges.net/50-philosophy-blogs-to-help-you-find-the-meaning-of-life/">Here is a nice list of 50 philosophy blogs.</a> It has all the best ones  Some are single author professional academics like the Leiter Report, others are multi-author academic like PEA soup, and Continental Philosophy blog is an essential bulletin board. Warning:Some of the blog have little patience for non-philosophers and some of them will eat a religious apologist alive. On the other hand, the Evangelical blogs are devoted to warrant to believe and justifying their epistemology. </p>
<p><strong>Update:<br />
oops &#8211; the links to the 15 dont work- so you have to go to the original source.</strong> I dont have time to find the problem.</p>
<p>Enjoy<br />
<a href="http://onlinechristiancolleges.net/50-philosophy-blogs-to-help-you-find-the-meaning-of-life/">Here is the list of all 50 Philosophy Blogs.</a></p>
<p>Below are a sample of fifteen of them</p>
<p>1. Leiter Reports: A Philosophy Blog<br />
Brian Leiter at the University of Chicago blogs frequently on subjects pertaining to philosophies – both the figures behind them and the people who enjoy spending time interpreting their meanings.<br />
2. Experimental Philosophy<br />
Read the ideologies and news stories behind experimental philosophy through the writings of a wonderful and diverse plethora of contributors.<br />
3. Think Tonk<br />
Clayton Littlejohn digs deeply into philosophy, politics, and how the 2 different subjects influence and come to be influenced by the other.<br />
4. Continental Philosophy<br />
Because “continental philosophy” covers ideologies from Europe (sans the British Isles), this blog and bulletin board provides diverse content from underneath that particular label.<br />
5. Life in the Dream<br />
Dr. Gregory Tucker blends Buddhism and other “Eastern” philosophies with traditional psychotherapy to present some very intriguing insights into the nature of reality, perception, and suffering.<br />
7. Philosophy Talk<br />
Philosophy Talk is a blog and a podcast for anyone who wants to try and make sense of how other people make sense of the world. They cover a wide spectrum of topics that illustrate philosophy’s role in human existence, including politics, business, social constructs, and more.<br />
8. Philosophy’s Other: Theory on the Web<br />
To borrow a phrase from Eugene Hütz, Philosophy’s Other could very well be considered the “super theory for supereverything.” It covers mankind’s perceptions of tops as diverse as architecture, psychology, and rhetoric in addition to discussing journal publications and conferences.<br />
10. PEA Soup<br />
Myriad diverse contributors gaze into how humanity processes the ins and outs of existence, ethics, and academia with the hopes of facilitating rewarding, intellectual discussions in its readers.<br />
14. Thoughts Arguments and Rants<br />
5 authors regularly weigh in on a variety of different philosophical topics, frequently looking into political and social issues along the way.<br />
15. philosophy bites<br />
David Edmonds and Nigel Warburton host a podcast and a blog emphasizing the ideas and movements supported by the biggest names in philosophy today..<br />
21. Certain Doubts<br />
Affiliated with Baylor University, the Certain Doubts blog concerns itself with any and all topics relating back to epistemology.<br />
23. Epistemic Value<br />
Anyone searching for knowledge regarding knowledge and meaning would do well to catch up with the writings (and events!) featured on this blog.<br />
24. It’s Only A Theory<br />
Science and philosophy aficionados must bookmark It’s Only A Theory to read up on all the latest news and views regarding how the two intertwine.<br />
34. Larval Subjects<br />
The concept behind this philosophy blog certainly piques a fair amount of interest. Rather than peering into and trying to make sense of the old, Larval Subjects seeks to explore and develop new philosophies from new, very small kernels of ideas..<br />
41. The Prosblogion<br />
All religious philosophies exist as some of the most controversial, subjective, and complex topics for debate, and The Prosblogion does not shy away from addressing any of the ones that ever have and ever will crop up.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/18/50-philosophy-blogs/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Cambridge Companion to Leo Strauss,</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/08/the-cambridge-companion-to-leo-strauss/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/08/the-cambridge-companion-to-leo-strauss/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Jun 2010 03:57:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[leo strauss]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1497</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[There is a new anthology of articles on Leo Strauss reviewed on ndpr. The review points out that all the articles present Stauss as a modern secularist. None of them present his work as having tensions between the Neo-Platonic and &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/08/the-cambridge-companion-to-leo-strauss/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There is a new anthology of articles on Leo Strauss reviewed on ndpr. The review points out that all the articles present Stauss as a modern secularist. None of them present his work as having tensions between the Neo-Platonic and the contemporary situation. Rather than the approaches to Strauss that emphasize the natural order, the classic text, or the role of the philosopher-king, here we have a flexible pragmatic thinker. We dont have the Strauss that flirted with Orthodoxy in the 1930&#8217;s, nor the Strauss that looked for word plays in the 1970s. And those who just read the theological work <strong>God Interrupted </strong>by Benjamin Lazier will not find continuity. We have a Strauss that believed in philosophy and showed how it survived the assaults of religion and politics. The tension of religion and revelation will never be solved so we have to learn about techniques like esotericism to survive.</p>
<blockquote><p>Steven B. Smith (ed.), The Cambridge Companion to Leo Strauss, Cambridge UP, 2009, 307pp., $28.99 (pbk),<br />
Reviewed by Samuel A. Chambers, Johns Hopkins University<br />
<a href="http://ndpr.nd.edu/review.cfm?id=19673">Full version here.</a></p>
<p><strong>Philosophy is threatened on the one side by a politics that would destroy it (3, 33) and on the other by a set of religious principles that would replace its search for knowledge with the positive content of revelation (115, 174). </strong></p>
<p>In one of the stronger pieces in the volume, perhaps especially for those who are not close readers of Strauss&#8217;s entire body of work, Leora Batnitzky demonstrates… that Strauss was a non-believing Jew, an atheist who early in life embraced a strictly political zionism (43). While Strauss obviously understood the role that religious principles played in supporting social order, there is simply little reason to take him as a religious believer. </p>
<p>Strauss never sought a wholesale return to the pre-modern. The general argument, that Strauss does not simply or literally wish to return to ancient Philosophy, is repeated by numerous authors (7, 41-42, 93, 117, 173), but Catherine Zuckert makes this case most forcefully in her subtle exploration of the way in which Strauss returns to premodern thought. She quotes Strauss&#8217;s most important statement on this issue: &#8220;only we living today can possibly find a solution to the problems of today&#8221; (117).</p>
<p>As most contributors to this volume read Strauss, <strong>he saw the conflict between reason and revelation as irresolvable because the positions from which they argue are incommensurable. Revelation can be neither supported by nor blended with reason</strong>; this was the main problem Strauss identified in medieval philosophy, especially Thomism (58). <strong>Nor, however, can the former be refuted by the latter;</strong> this was potentially a problem for the earlier, perhaps more dogmatically atheistic Strauss who was tempted by this possibility, before later recognizing the complete incompatibility of the two. Indeed, it is Strauss&#8217;s later understanding of the fundamental importance of these two &#8220;roots of western civilization&#8221; (94), that reveals him fully &#8212; according to most of the contributors here &#8212; as a thoroughly non-dogmatic philosopher who believes in no universal moral standards, no singular truth. Smith emphasizes this perhaps unexpected or controversial point (one that certainly cuts against the grain of many criticisms of Strauss) when he insists that there is nothing absolutist about Strauss&#8217;s thought, and that his &#8220;return to nature&#8221; was a return to &#8220;flexible&#8221; standards (33). </p>
<p>Some readers may balk at the picture of a Strauss with flexible standards, as a skeptical thinker, as one who returned to a &#8220;nature&#8221; in premodern thought that was not fixed and eternal. But those readers are well-advised to engage closely with the readings in this volume, with the work of Strauss, and perhaps also with the writings of the classic political philosophers that Strauss and his followers have championed. </p>
<p>Strauss&#8217;s most explicit statement on interpretive method, &#8220;Persecution and the Art of Writing,&#8221; also stands as his most famous piece of writing (27). While it is well known that Strauss claimed to have &#8220;rediscovered&#8221; the ancient art of &#8220;esoteric&#8221; writing, this volume clarifies an important related point: precisely this rediscovery led Strauss to his own personal revolution in thought. </p>
<p>One of the little jewels of this collection, especially for those not already well steeped in the secondary literature on Strauss, is the exegesis by Laurence Lampert (and the summary by Smith and others) of the letters Strauss wrote to Jacob Klein in 1938 and 1939. These letters, only recently published in German and still untranslated into English, show clearly that Strauss did not develop his hermeneutics independently of his own readings, but truly did &#8220;discover&#8221; it in the sense that he came upon a way to make sense of a text that, for Strauss, was previously mysterious or full of contradictions. In the first letter that Lampert quotes, Strauss tells Klein that &#8220;Maimonides is getting more and more exciting&#8221; (63) and from this point on Strauss&#8217;s excitement only builds, with each letter more full of thrill than the previous one. <strong>Strauss is thrilled because for him Maimonides makes sense when one sees that &#8220;Maimonides in his beliefs was absolutely no Jew&#8221; (64, emphasis in original) and therefore he cannot be read as a &#8220;Jewish philosopher&#8221; writing a guide for believers. He must be read, instead, as a non-believer, writing a &#8220;radical critique of the Torah&#8221; that sounds to believers as if it is merely a repetition of the Torah, yet which adds &#8220;&#8216;little&#8217; &#8216;additions'&#8221; to signal to a few select readers (philosophers) what the text is really all about (65). Strauss&#8217;s better-known and (as Smith notes) much maligned theory of esoteric writing is contained in this kernel of insight (3). Philosophers like Maimonides who write under conditions of persecution (conditions in which to state plainly the truth in the face of dominant opinion would be to court disaster) must therefore produce texts that contain within them two very much distinct and at times utterly contradictory meanings. This then sets up the requirements for how good readers, those that Strauss refers to with an ambiguity that some might find ominous as &#8220;the few,&#8221; will read.</strong></p>
<p>One problem with esoteric writing as a general theory of interpretation is that it becomes very difficult to know when to take an author at his or her word. Thus, my telling you that I have not written this review esoterically may in fact be the secret signal I give to a certain few readers that I am in fact writing esoterically, and to indicate to them that they should make sure to read me as such. Indeed, on Lampert&#8217;s interpretation of him, this is precisely what Strauss does in his essay on Halevi. </p>
<p>Here are the steps of the various readings, starting with Halevi&#8217;s text and then moving to Strauss&#8217;s reading of Halevi and Lampert&#8217;s reading of Strauss.<br />
1) <strong>Halevi omits a discussion of the conflict between believer and philosopher.</strong><br />
2A) Strauss says the omission is intentional, designed to show esoterically that this conflict is exactly what matters most. (78)<br />
2B) But Strauss then goes on to say that we should not &#8220;lay too much emphasis on this line of approach&#8221; (79).<br />
3) Lampert then argues that this last line is Strauss&#8217;s esoteric claim: &#8220;to not lay too much emphasis on this approach is to take this approach&#8221; (79).</p>
<p>To sum up, Halevi omits what is, in fact, most important; Strauss downplays what is, in fact, most significant. But if we know that Halevi is writing esoterically (and can only interpret him properly because of this knowledge) and if we know Strauss is also writing esoterically in his interpretation (ditto), then we therefore know how to read Strauss on Halevi.</p>
<p>Moreover, <strong>Strauss felt certain that only a few were fit for the life of philosophy that he championed, and he therefore argued fairly directly that philosophy must be protected from the many who are simply unfit for it as a way of life.</strong> For this reason, much of Strauss&#8217;s political philosophy seems designed to make sure that philosophy can continue to exist, but precisely as a private and sheerly pedagogical affair (85, 150).</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/08/the-cambridge-companion-to-leo-strauss/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Meaning and Mystery: What it means to believe in God&#8211;David M. Holley</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/06/meaning-and-mystery-what-it-means-to-believe-in-god-david-m-holley/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/06/meaning-and-mystery-what-it-means-to-believe-in-god-david-m-holley/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 07 May 2010 04:06:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sociology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[david holley]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[meaning and mystery]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1259</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A book that is getting many good reviews from both academics and religious publications is David Holly, Meaning and Mystery. Holly approaches the question of the belief in God from a post-secular and post liberal perspective, God is part of &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/06/meaning-and-mystery-what-it-means-to-believe-in-god-david-m-holley/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A book that is getting many good reviews from both academics and religious publications is  David Holly, Meaning and Mystery. Holly approaches the question of the belief in God from a post-secular and post liberal perspective, God is part of our lives in a  non-foundational way and the criteria for believe is whether God is part of our narrative. He takes from Charles Taylor the idea that we all create narratives or social imaginaries to make meaning of our lives. He also takes from all the new studies on evangelicals that people adopt Evangelical beliefs because it fits into their personal narratives.  Hence, belief in God is non-foundational and based on our personal histories. God cannot be proved or disproved. Neither philosophy or science play a role in the belief in God. Someone who does not have God in their life cannot communicate with someone who does since they have different life stories.  He does invoke Pascal and cheer for belief in ways that don’t fit with Charles Taylor, but many points of his are good. He seems to be working on a sequel on how the question of falsification is dealt with in a personal narrative approach. </p>
<p><a href="http://www.churchtimes.co.uk/content.asp?id=93175">Here is a review from a religious publication.</a><br />
<em><br />
ONE of the myths of post-modernism is that we have entered the age of no meta-narratives.<br />
Non¬sense. We are in the age of many meta-narratives.  David Holley doesn’t even bother with the modern/post-modern question. He simply argues that it is these “life-orienting” meta-narratives that determine belief in God, or otherwise. This is the thesis expounded clearly and credibly in the first chapter, so that there is a certain inevitability about his attack on the “God of the Philosophers” who is the end point of a logical or empirical argument rather than an idea central to a life-orienting narrative that is accepted because it makes sense of experience, and is a plausible and practical guide for action. </p>
<p>Holley maintains that atheism is as dependent as theism on such life-orienting narratives.. Of course, such narratives require a degree of receptivity on our part if they are to be life-orienting, and it is in the nature of human freedom that they should be capable of being resisted.</p>
<p>Holley effectively exposes the worst excesses of rationalism and scientism that characterize many contemporary despisers of religion. Here he owes a significant debt to Alexander MacIntyre when it comes to seeing the very idea of virtues and values as incompatible with a purely naturalistic version of reality.<br />
This leaves the way clear for him to demonstrate how narratives that include God are more likely to offer meaning to our lives than those that do not.<br />
The final chapter deals with how we relate to religious and non-religious views other than our own. Holley contends that trying to evaluate various world-views from a standpoint outside any of them is impossible. We can address them only from within the life-orienting narrative we have adopted, and that way we can accommodate doubt and uncertainty without compromising the narrative that works for us. </em></p>
<p><a href="http://religioncompass.wordpress.com/2010/05/05/books-meaning-and-mystery-what-it-means-to-believe-in-god">From a scientific study of religion review interview:</a></p>
<p><em>What’s the central concern of the book, and why is it important?<br />
DH: While the question of God’s existence is typically dealt with as a theoretical issue, I claim that it makes most sense to treat it as a practical question. Each of us needs what I call a life-orienting story, a narrative that relates a picture of what is ultimately real to individual experience in a way that makes a particular way of living intelligible and attractive. Some narratives of this kind include God and some explicitly exclude God. Reflective judgment about God occurs in the context of considering alternative narratives that might provide orientation for a way of living. In that context the issue is not only whether the understanding provided by a narrative coheres with what we take to be the facts, but whether or not it has the power to engage a person in a way of life she finds worthy. </p>
<p>And what is it that draws you (personally) to this topic?<br />
DH: I am struck by the way religious claims and religious ways of life seem virtually unintelligible to some people. In the introduction to the book I cite one author who questions whether anyone actually believes in God because he thinks of the belief as a hypothesis that lacks any evidential support. Both believers and unbelievers are tempted to construe the issue in this way, and as a result the discussion gets sidetracked from the kind of belief intelligent religious people hold and the considerations that actually persuade them. </p>
<p>What sort of reaction do you hope it will get?<br />
DH: I would like to persuade people that standard ways of thinking about God’s existence do not get to the heart of the matter. I’d like to reconfigure the discussion between believers and nonbelievers away from arguments about an isolated proposition to consideration of alternative narratives that might structure a way of life. I expect that some people will misunderstand my book, imagining that I am advocating some kind of disregard of rational evidence. Instead, I am trying to show what kind of reflection is appropriate for cases where we inevitably end up believing some practical narrative (naturalistic or theistic) that cannot be established on purely empirical grounds. </em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/06/meaning-and-mystery-what-it-means-to-believe-in-god-david-m-holley/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>5</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Beyond Theodicy- Sarah Pinnock</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/06/beyond-theodicy-sarah-pinnock/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/06/beyond-theodicy-sarah-pinnock/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 06 May 2010 05:45:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gabriel Marcel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jurgen Moltmann]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[martin buber]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[metz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sarah Pinnock]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theodicy]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1252</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Clergy regularly publish op-eds and sermons about how we will never know why evil happens, nevertheless we have to rise to respond to the suffering. Many times these sermons are treated by those who quote it as brilliant innovation. Sometimes &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/06/beyond-theodicy-sarah-pinnock/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Clergy regularly publish op-eds and sermons about how we will never know why evil happens, nevertheless we have to rise to  respond to the suffering. Many times these sermons are treated by those who quote it as brilliant innovation. Sometimes even the author praises himself in his own op-ed for his own deep insight and sublime rationality. Yet, as long as we have vocal clergy who blame earthquakes, volcanoes, and floods on the sins of the country, then it sustains these op-ed writers in their sense of superiority.  However, the distinction between theodicy and our need to respond was a common theme of most existential authors.  Sarah K. Pinnock , <em>Beyond Theodicy: Jewish and Christian Continental Thinkers Respond to the Holocaust</em> (2002) surveys this topic.</p>
<p>The book is eight years old, but I finally got around to reading it.  Pinnock contextualizes nicely by surveying the deterioration of the belief in theodicy entering the 20th century and the new attempts by evangelical philosophers to restore theodicy. The majority of the book is on the four opinions of Marcel, Buber, Bloch (via Moltmann) and Metz.  The book started as a dissertation and would not be good reading, to put it mildly, for those not used to academic reading.</p>
<p>The first position that she presents is Gabriel Marcel , who rejects theodicy but claims that we need to accept mystery of God  without an attempt at justification. The goal is empathy and meaning  in our lives; not to prevent suffering or protest.  There are similarities to Victor Frankl and Erich Fromm.</p>
<p>The second position that she presents is Martin Buber, who has a greater collective sense than Marcel. For Marcel, meaning is personal, while for Buber meaning is to better the world. In the prophetic faith of Judaism  one engages in moral acts, prayer, protest in the face of suffering which builds community. Buber introduces the discussion of how Job is a better source for today than Isaiah’s suffering servant. Finally, Buber speaks of how we rise from fate to destiny when we orient our lives around God.  When we live in an I-thou toward others and build a community of destiny then even fate is transformed “Fate—with its eyes, hitherto severe, suddenly full of light—looks like grace itself” (102). (On the near complete reliance of Soloveitchik  on some of these paragraphs of Buber, a different review would be needed.)</p>
<p>Pinnock’s goal was to compare the existentialists with the Marxists, so her next thinker was Bloch’s concept of hope as used by Jurgen Moltmann. Hegel downplayed suffering.  The role of hope in Bloch and Moltmann is to bring the fate of history in correspondence with the destined redemption.  Moltmann  offers a mystical solidarity of man and God. For Moltmann, the Christian cross shows how to suffer in a meaningful way and shows the real possibility for redemption. The Marxist hope mandates a need for change or at least dignity before death. </p>
<p>Finally, Metz  rejects the parallel of human to divine suffering.  Human suffering is about painful despair, hopeless, and futility. It means broken shattered  lives. To use a Jewish example, the pain of the slaughter of children in the Holocaust is not just an exile of the shekhinah or God crying. Metz introduces the theme of memory, where one has to integrate the  truth of past into one’s life and in addition to investigate the causes of the suffering. The goal is to change the world, to protest, to investigate the socio-political causes of the pain, and to create a better society. </p>
<p>She concludes her book with comparisons during which she asks: Are these existential answers philosophy, psychology, or pastoral care?  Certainly, many of the clergy versions are sheer pastoral comfort and should not be praised as philosophy. (Hashem yirahem)</p>
<p>The best part of the book is now the ability to analyze the options of the theologians who write that that we respond to suffering in the real world. Does the essay state that we respond in personal meaning, in building community, in restoring dignity, or to actually change the world? What did the author stress and what did the author leave out. Do we change the world or ourselves? Do we have to empathize with the sufferer or only help them? These distinctions allow us to stand on their shoulders and formulate better responses and responses that actually address the suffering at hand.  If the book would be expanded, I would have liked to see chapters on Camus, Tillich, Benjamin, and Ricoeur since these authors are already making many cameos. A full comparison would be helpful for fleshing out the existential ethic.</p>
<p>Copyright © 2010 Alan Brill • All Rights Reserved</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/06/beyond-theodicy-sarah-pinnock/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Hadot: philosophy as a way of life</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/26/hadot-philosophy-as-a-way-of-life/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/26/hadot-philosophy-as-a-way-of-life/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Apr 2010 04:52:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[aristotle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pierre Hadot]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[plato]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1184</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Pierre Hadot (1922 &#8211; April 24, 2010) just died Hadot taught all of us, or at least reminded us, that for ancients philosophy was a way of life, a way for self-perfection and eternity and not an abstract knowledge. To &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/26/hadot-philosophy-as-a-way-of-life/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>Pierre Hadot</strong> (1922 &#8211; April 24, 2010) just died</p>
<p>Hadot taught all of us, or at least reminded us, that for ancients philosophy was a way of life, a way for self-perfection and eternity and not an abstract knowledge. To understand why the monotheists Plato, Aristotle, and Zeno the Stoic were important for Maimonides or for that matter any medieval Jewish thinker, then one should read Hadot. Everyone from Idel to Boyarin is dependent on Hadot’s work</p>
<p>Hadot’s <em>Philosophy as a Way of Life: Spiritual Exercises from Socrates to Foucault</em> (Blackwell, 1995) Organized more on ideas</p>
<p>Hadot, Pierre, <em>What is Ancient Philosophy?</em>, Harvard University Press, 2002, Organized more on history</p>
<p>Here are some paragraphs from online book review to get a sense. <a href="http://www2.bc.edu/~whitakal/Pierre%20Hadot%20Review.htm">From Here</a></p>
<p>Hadot identified and analyzed the &#8220;spiritual exercises&#8221; used in ancient philosophy</p>
<p>By &#8220;spiritual exercises&#8221; Hadot means &#8220;practices &#8230; intended to effect a modification and a transformation in the subject who practice them. The philosophy teacher&#8217;s discourse could be presented in such a way that the disciple, as auditor, reader, or interlocutor, could make spiritual progress and transform himself within.</p>
<p>For Hadot, the fundamental distinction lies between &#8220;philosophy&#8221; and &#8220;philosophical discourse.&#8221; For example, after surveying the schools of Plato and Aristotle and their successors in the Hellenistic and late antique worlds, he explains, &#8220;Throughout this investigation, we have recognized the existence of a philosophical life&#8211;more precisely, a way of life&#8211;which can be characterized as philosophical and which is radically opposed to the way of life of nonphilosophers.</p>
<p>How then did the philosophical life (as opposed to philosophical discourse) die, or appear to die? Hadot draws attention to the movement under the Roman Empire away from philosophy as dialogue or research and towards philosophy as commentary on the &#8220;great books&#8221; of the past (see 149-157). As the 2<sup>nd</sup> century AD Platonist Taurus complained, &#8220;There are even some [students] who want to read Plato&#8211;not in order to make their lives better, but in order to adorn their language and their style; not in order to become more temperate, but in order to acquire more charm&#8221; (150).</p>
<p><a href="http://ndpr.nd.edu/review.cfm?id=1376">And from here.</a></p>
<p>What is ancient philosophy? Pierre Hadot makes very clear what he thinks it is not: it is not the deposit of philosophical concepts, theories and systems to be found in the surviving texts of Graeco-Roman antiquity, the subject matter of courses of study in the curricula of modern universities.</p>
<p>In the author’s own words, “Philosophical discourse . . . originates in a choice of life and an existential option—not vice-versa . . . . This existential option, in turn, implies a certain vision of the world, and the task of philosophical discourse will therefore be to reveal and rationally to justify this existential option, as well as this representation of the world” (p. 3). Moreover, philosophy both as a way of life and as its justifying discourse is not the attainment and deployment of wisdom, but “merely a preparatory exercise for wisdom” which “tend[s] toward wisdom without ever achieving it” (p. 4). It is the primary purpose of this book to establish these</p>
<p><em>Plato and the Academy</em> (chapter 5). According to Hadot, Plato’s goal in founding the Academy was the creation of “an intellectual and spiritual community whose job it would be to train new human beings . . . (p. 59). The program of training and research in the Academy from the various branches of mathematics to dialectic had primarily an ethical aim, which was to purify the mind and to “learn to live in a philosophical way . . . to ensure . . . a good life and thereby the ’salvation’ of the soul” (p. 65). To achieve this aim various “spiritual exercises” mentioned in several Platonic dialogues including, notably, the practice of death in the <em>Phaedo</em> (64a) and the (practice of?) transcendence over all that is mundane described in the <em>Theaetetus</em> (173d–175e) would have been instituted in the Academy. All these exercises have as their aim the transformation of the self.</p>
<p><em>Aristotle and His School</em> (chapter 6). Aristotle, according to Hadot’s account, founded the Lyceum on the model of the Academy—at least with the same ethical goal in mind, if not the same intellectual practices.</p>
<p><em>The Hellenistic Schools</em> (chapter 7). Hadot’s general thesis is most easily demonstrated in the cases of the various Hellenistic schools which arose in the late fourth century BCE. The idea that Epicurus and Zeno (respectively the founders of Epicureanism and Stoicism) established their schools to create communities which pursued some shared way of life to attain a shared spiritual goal is not new, and Hadot demonstrates very effectively how the physical and epistemological theories of these schools were intended to support their spiritual goals. This is true not only of the “dogmatists” (Epicureans and Stoics as well as Platonists and Aristotelians, all of whom affirmed positive doctrines) but also of their opponents, the “skeptics,” who recommended the suspension of belief as the proper path to their spiritual goal. In addition, Hadot shows convincingly that these various spiritual goals, differently described in the different schools—for example, for the Epicureans it was a life of stable pleasure achieved by the limitations of one’s appetites while for the Stoics it was a life of self-coherence, lived in conformity to Nature or Reason—all involved the goal of self-transformation. Each school had its own set of spiritual exercises designed to lead its adherents to the achievement of its particular version of that goal.</p>
<p><em>Schools in the Imperial Period</em> (chapter 8). The development of philosophy in the age of the Roman Empire is characterized by two outstanding phenomena. The first is a change in pedagogy. Philosophy classes began to be devoted to the reading and exegesis of the texts by the school’s founders, and instructors began in increasing measure to write commentaries on those texts to assist comprehension among their students. The second is the eventual decline of Epicureanism and Stoicism and the ascendancy and development of Platonism (synthesized with Aristotelianism in the Neoplatonism of Plotinus) as the dominant philosophy of late antiquity.</p>
<p>The final part of the book (“Interruption and Continuity: The Middle Ages and Modern Times”) may be summarized more briefly. Hadot credits the rise of Christianity with the decline of philosophy practiced as a way of life. Christianity positioned itself as a “philosophy” (in Hadot’s sense) with its own regimen of spiritual exercises and spiritual goals, and as this religion came to eclipse the various pagan philosophies, it usurped their spiritual function.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/26/hadot-philosophy-as-a-way-of-life/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>My New Book Just Came Out-Judaism and Other Religions</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/13/my-new-book-just-came-out-judaism-and-other-religions/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/13/my-new-book-just-came-out-judaism-and-other-religions/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 14 Feb 2010 00:43:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Buddhism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[spirituality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[alan brill]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr Brill]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jewish interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Judaism and other religions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[nathan Katz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rabbi Brill]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rabbi David Rosen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ruth Langer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=785</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[My book Judaism and Other Religions is to be officially released on March 2nd by Palgrave-Macmillan. But it is already available in the warehouse and available for purchase, Be the first one on your block to own one. Buy it &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/13/my-new-book-just-came-out-judaism-and-other-religions/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My book <strong>Judaism and Other Religions</strong> is to be officially released on March 2nd by Palgrave-Macmillan. But it is already available in the warehouse and available for purchase, Be the first one on your block to own one. Buy it now:</p>
<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Judaism-Other-Religions-Models-Understanding/dp/0230622267/ref=ntt_at_ep_dpt_2">Click here to buy it at Amazon </a></strong></p>
<p><a href="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="165" data-permalink="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/about/brill0230622267-2/" data-orig-file="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg" data-orig-size="396,594" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;}" data-image-title="Brill0230622267" data-image-description="" data-medium-file="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg?w=200" data-large-file="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg?w=396" class="alignleft size-medium wp-image-165" title="Brill0230622267" src="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg?w=200&#038;h=300" alt="" width="200" height="300" srcset="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg?w=200&amp;h=300 200w, https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg?w=100&amp;h=150 100w, https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg 396w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /></a></p>
<p><strong>Editorial Reviews</strong></p>
<p>“This wide-ranging but carefully organized collection of Jewish thought about other religions constitutes an indispensable resource for Jews and non-Jews engaged in interreligious relations today and for Jews seeking to develop a text-based contemporary Jewish theology of religions for our global world. Brill accompanies his lucid presentations of each approach with insightful critiques that will help guide their contemporary applications.”—Ruth Langer, Associate Professor of Jewish Studies, Theology Department Associate Director, Center for Christian-Jewish Learning, Boston College</p>
<p>“Serious Jewish engagement with other religions has substantially deepened and widened in recent years, both stimulating and responding to an increasing interest in Judaism from within the other world religions. Brill’s book provides essential access to the classical sources within the Jewish tradition relevant to this encounter.”—Rabbi Dr. David Rosen, International Director of Interreligious Affairs, AJC</p>
<p>“This is an excellent work: reflective, engaging, well-written, and perhaps most important—timely. Brill knows both the theoretical foundations for interreligious dialogue and rabbinic approaches to ‘other religions.’ It is a fine piece of scholarship, and it is also creative in bringing together three fields of discourse in a way they have not before been aligned. It blends both traditional and modern thinking about interreligious dialogue, and it analyzes these materials convincingly.”—Nathan Katz, Professor of Religious Studies, Florida International University</p>
<p><strong>Product Description</strong></p>
<p>With insight and scholarship, Alan Brill crisply outlines the traditional Jewish approaches to other religions for an age of globalization. He provides a fresh perspective on Biblical and Rabbinic texts, offering new ways of thinking about other faiths. In the majority of volume, he develops the categories of theology of religions for Jewish texts. He arranges the texts according classification widely used in interfaith work: inclusivist, exclusivist, universalist, and pluralist.</p>
<p>Judaism and Other Religions is essential for a Jewish theological understanding of the various issues in encounters with other religions. With passion and clarity, Brill argues that in today’s world of strong religious passions and intolerance, it is necessary to go beyond secular tolerance toward moderate and mediating religious positions.</p>
<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Judaism-Other-Religions-Models-Understanding/dp/0230622267/ref=ntt_at_ep_dpt_2">Click here to buy it at Amazon </a></strong></p>
<p>There is a forthcoming sequel volume <strong>Judaism and World Religions,</strong> which will be available at the end of 2010.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/13/my-new-book-just-came-out-judaism-and-other-religions/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>10</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg?w=200" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">Brill0230622267</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Habermas and Halakhah -Guest post from AS</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/04/habermas-and-halakhah-guest-post-from-as/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/04/habermas-and-halakhah-guest-post-from-as/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2010 18:39:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[30940391]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[halakhic theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[habermas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[habermas and halakhah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[halachic rationality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[halakhic discourse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[halakhic rationality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[meta-halakhah]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=716</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[[My intended posts for this week are still on an external hard-drive, but I was lucky enough to have a guest post from AS] AS writes in a comment: Right now I can only offer the following brief comment that &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/04/habermas-and-halakhah-guest-post-from-as/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>[My intended posts for this week are still on an external hard-drive, but I was lucky enough to have a guest post from AS]</p>
<p><strong>AS writes in a comment:</strong></p>
<p>Right now I can only offer the following brief comment that overly compresses what could be at least a book chapter. Those not familiar with Habermas should note that he talks about communicative rationality as an aspect of modernity. Therefore this constitutes a consciously external and modern critique of halakhah &#8211; although one that perhaps reveals the paradoxes in modern apologetics.</p>
<p>Before starting we need to ask how to characterize halakhic claims. More specifically we must ask where the binding normative force of halakhic claims come from. Sociology could adequately describe a community in which a certain species of claims were taken to be binding, along with the varieties of social coercion that are employed to ensure compliance, but this would not but this would not account for internal rules of justification that are capable of shaping beliefs.</p>
<p>One obviously wrong answer is to assume that halakhic claims aspire to truth, and that the truth conditions are correspondence to the revealed will of God. The binding force of halakhah in both ritual and moral domains derives solely from the authority of a just God.</p>
<p>This is the wrong picture for a few reasons, mostly because halakhah is &#8220;not in heaven.&#8221; The correctness of a halakhah derives not from its correspondence with a revealed word, but at least in part because <strong>it comes to be regarded as the correct interpretation of a text by means of a rational, internally consistent, discourse. </strong>The metatheory of halakhah, were it ever to be carefully explained, would not need to make any reference to God whatsoever in describing how halakhah functions to determine its correctness. <strong>At best there is some God-granted authority to interpret at the very root, but within the discourse this authority is neither appealed to or contested </strong>(except rhetorically), so it is moot.</p>
<p><strong>Halakhah can therefore be construed as a species of rational communicative discourse.</strong>  Indeed, in its internal dialectics it seems to aspire to be a rational discourse in that it follows rules of interpretation, precedent, etc. that are universally recognizable by all participants.  If this is the case then a Habermasian would likely say that halakhic claims, like moral claims, aspire not to truth (having conditions of rightness constituted independent of the halakhic community) but rather to validity.</p>
<p>In general Habermas thinks that normative validity claims implicitly contains not merely the intersubjective ought, but to the universal/deontological. <strong>The deontological nature and binding force of normative claims stems from the idea the very participation in a discursive practice presupposes the acceptance of certain normative principles</strong>. In other words, we could not exist as a community of language-users capable of achieving basic communicative rationality (like coordinating behavior) without background normative assumptions which everyone implicitly relies upon in any discursive practice.</p>
<p>Now clearly halakhic claims cannot be &#8220;redeemed&#8221; in the same way that Habermas thinks that regular normative claims can &#8211; nor would we expect as much. We would liken halakhic discourse in many ways to legal discourse. But Habermas claims (and here it is simply easier to quote) that:</p>
<p><em>&#8220;Discourse theory explains the legitimacy of law by means of procedures and communicative presuppositions that, once they are legally institutionalized, ground the supposition that the process of making and applying the law lead to rational outcomes.&#8221; This rationality is proved not by the outcomes themselves, but procedurally &#8220;by the fact that addressees are treated as free and equal members of an association of legal subjects.&#8221;</em><br />
<strong><br />
Because halakhah is an exclusionary discourse that does not even aspire to procedural equality</strong>, because addressees are not treated as equal, and because this inequality, instead of bearing a very high burden of rational justification is claimed to lie in a revealed metaphysical ontology, <strong>its claim to communicative rationality breaks down.</strong></p>
<p>Halakhic discourse does not devolve into literal incoherence, and anyone familiar with legal discourse will not find it entirely foreign. But this is precisely because rabbis address each other, and sometimes learned laypersons, as equals (it by no means breaks from communicative rationality simply by appeal to various metaphysical processes or the like). <strong>On Habermasian grounds it breaks from communicative rationality when it treats its subjects unequally who themselves have no part in shaping the discourse.</strong></p>
<p><strong>At this point halakhah either makes a sharp premodern return to a mythical worldview, or remains modern but employs an instrumental rationality in its treatment of some of its subjects </strong>(I don’t think it’s quite strategic rationality because it lacks the pretense of equal participation). I think that both of these are in play. Sometimes in contemporary halakhah difference and exclusion are justified naturalistically (in a sense because some subjects do not transcend nature, they are regarded as a part of the natural world to be intervened upon) and sometimes by appeal to a premodern mythology. And sometimes it is a rather interesting hybrid. [end of AS guest post]</p>
<p><strong>For those who are less familiar with Habermas, I [AB] add some links and definitions. Basic <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jürgen_Habermas">wiki biography</a> , <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Communicative_action">communicative action</a>, and the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_sphere">public sphere</a>, as well as the <a href="http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/habermas/">SEP on Habermas</a>. Even from the links and the short definitions below, it may be enough to have some serious discussion. For those, who need a translation, a deontological claim, in this context, means something is assur or muttar. </strong></p>
<p><strong>From Wiki on rationality </strong><br />
<em>Jürgen Habermas considers his major contribution to be the development of the concept and theory of communicative reason or communicative rationality, which distinguishes itself from the rationalist tradition by locating rationality  in structures of interpersonal linguistic communication  rather than in the structure of either the cosmos or the knowing subject.</em><br />
<strong><br />
From Wiki on the the public sphere</strong><br />
<em>The public sphere is an area in social life where people can get together and freely discuss and identify societal problems, and through that discussion influence political action. It is &#8220;a discursive space in which individuals and groups congregate to discuss matters of mutual interest and, where possible, to reach a common judgment.&#8221; The public sphere can be seen as &#8220;a theater in modern societies in which political participation is enacted through the medium of talk&#8221;  and &#8220;a realm of social life in which public opinion can be formed&#8221;.</p>
<p>  Habermas stipulates that, due to specific historical circumstances, a new civic society emerged in the eighteenth century. Driven by a need for open commercial arenas where news and matters of common concern could be freely exchanged and discussed &#8211; accompanied by growing rates of literacy, accessibility to literature, and a new kind of critical journalism &#8211; a separate domain from ruling authorities started to evolve across Europe. &#8220;In its clash with the arcane and bureaucratic practices of the absolutist state, the emergent bourgeoisie gradually replaced a public sphere in which the ruler’s power was merely represented before the people with a sphere in which state authority was publicly monitored through informed and critical discourse by the people&#8221;.</p>
<p>In his historical analysis, Habermas points out three so-called &#8220;institutional criteria&#8221; as preconditions for the emergence of the new public sphere. </p>
<p>   1. Disregard of status: Preservation of &#8220;a kind of social intercourse that, far from presupposing the equality of status, disregarded status altogether. [&#8230;] Not that this idea of the public was actually realized in earnest in the coffee houses, salons, and the societies; but as an idea it had become institutionalized and thereby stated as an objective claim. If not realized, it was at least consequential.&#8221; (loc.cit.)<br />
   2. Domain of common concern: &#8220;&#8230; discussion within such a public presupposed the problematization of areas that until then had not been questioned. The domain of ‘common concern’ which was the object of public critical attention remained a preserve in which church and state authorities had the monopoly of interpretation. [&#8230;] The private people for whom the cultural product became available as a commodity profaned it inasmuch as they had to determine its meaning on their own (by way of rational communication with one another), verbalize it, and thus state explicitly what precisely in its implicitness for so long could assert its authority.&#8221; (loc.cit.)<br />
   3. Inclusivity: However exclusive the public might be in any given instance, it could never close itself off entirely and become consolidated as a clique; for it always understood and found itself immersed within a more inclusive public of all private people, persons who – insofar as they were propertied and educated – as readers, listeners, and spectators could avail themselves via the market of the objects that were subject to discussion. The issues discussed became ‘general’ not merely in their significance, but also in their accessibility: everyone had to be able to participate. [&#8230;] Wherever the public established itself institutionally as a stable group of discussants, it did not equate itself with the public but at most claimed to act as its mouthpiece, in its name, perhaps even as its educator – the new form of bourgeois representation&#8221; (loc.cit.).</em></p>
<p><strong>On Rationality and Communication</strong>:</p>
<p><em>Communicative action for Habermas is possible given human capacity for rationality. This rationality, however, is &#8220;no longer tied to, and limited by, the subjectivistic and individualistic premises of modern philosophy and social theory.&#8221;[1]  Instead, Habermas situates rationality as a capacity inherent within language, especially in the form of argumentation. &#8220;We use the term argumentation for that type of speech in which participants thematize contested validity claims and attempt to vindicate or criticize them through argumentation.&#8221;[2]  The structures of argumentative speech, which Habermas identifies as the absence of coercive force, the mutual search for understanding, and the compelling power of the better argument, form the key features from which intersubjective rationality can make communication possible. Action undertaken by participants to a process of such argumentative communication can be assessed as to their rationality to the extent which they fulfill those criteria.</em></p>
<p>And for those who in their ignorance call anything they have not read post-modern- <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jürgen_Habermas#Habermas_versus_Postmodernists">Here is Habermas&#8217; rejection of post-modernism in a nutshell.</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/04/habermas-and-halakhah-guest-post-from-as/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Vattimo and Theology</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/30/vattimo-and-theology/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/30/vattimo-and-theology/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2010 04:49:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gianni vattimo]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[thomas guarino]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[vattimo]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[weak faith]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=676</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[There is a new series by Continuum Book that engages contemporary philosophy from a theological perspective. Adorno and Theology, Wittgenstein and Theology, Habermas and Theology,  Girard and Theology, Zizek and Theology. They are also offering new readings for the 21st &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/30/vattimo-and-theology/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.continuumbooks.com/search/default.aspx?Text=and+theology">There is a new series by Continuum Book </a>that engages contemporary philosophy from a theological perspective. Adorno and Theology, Wittgenstein and Theology, Habermas and Theology,  Girard and Theology, Zizek and Theology. They are also offering new readings for the 21<sup>st</sup> century of Kant and Theology, Hegel and Theology, Kierkegaard and Theology. Most of them look good and will surely engage discussion.</p>
<p>This past week, I went to a book signing for <strong><em>Vattimo and Theology</em>&#8211; Thomas Guarino</strong></p>
<p>There is little good material on Gianni Vattimo in English but here is a <a href="http://www.sobriquetmagazine.com/mellownihilism.htm">book review in English</a> and here is <a href="http://giannivattimo.blogspot.com/">Vattimo’s blog</a> (in Italian- Columbia UP has a link to the blog embedded in a translation program).</p>
<p>Vattimo translated Gadaemer into Italian, and took hermeneutics to a Nietzsche influenced extreme. Everything is just interpretation, there is no truth in the text.</p>
<p>Now, how can a catholic priest teaching in a conservative seminary use an atheist, nihilist, gay, anti-clerical, anti-revelation thinker as a basis for a book? The approach not to take is to call this is heresy and forbidden and violates what we were taught. So what does that leave? One can show how other contemporary theologians have rejected his thought. (There is an article in Modern Theology- that does that)  Or one can take Vattimo’s positive points and re-graft them onto tradition.</p>
<p>Instead the author of the new book attempted the following two approaches. One can use it as a self-corrective for how tradition is currently being presented. One can use it to understand what current intellectuals are thinking so that one can respond to the issues of our age</p>
<p>Some of the points in the book:</p>
<p>Cardinal Ratzinger – decried the dictatorship of Relativism, Vattimo argued against Ratzinger that dogmatic claims are the bigger problem and let’s have charitable tolerance.</p>
<p>Secularism, in the post-religious sense, should not be decried but treated as a chance to practice the weak virtues of charity-love without dogma and as a vibrant fruit of religion. Religion has been kept out of the public sphere, but now that it is weakened, it should be brought back into the public sphere.</p>
<p>Vattimo says “I believe that I believe” – meaning that I have faith in the human concept of belief not in an object of believe. So whereas the Enlightenment taught we cant know the truth of religion, Vattimo argues that “faith” is the acceptance that one is heir to a library of the textual tradition of faith and to a socio-cultural world of religion. Modern rationalist liberals want to treat religion as symbolism, or metaphor. In contrast, Vattimo has faith in faith so he takes religion at face values but know that there is nothing behind it. There is no one meaning, all is a fable, all is interpretation, there is no truth out side the cave.</p>
<ul>
<li>&#8220;It is only thanks to      God that I&#8217;m an atheist&#8221;</li>
<li>&#8220;I believe that I      believe&#8221; (<em>credere di credere</em>)</li>
</ul>
<p>Guardino argues that this is not theologically sound. We need for revelation, and belief but Vattimo gives us an insight into our age. Guardino best line: “Vattimo makes cultural liberals look like scholastic divines”</p>
<p>Vattimo recites the Latin prayers from the Roman Breviary three times a day, and he says it is not because he believes but as an acceptance of tradition. There was a wide range of opinions what to make of that behavior. Does that give him a weak faith? Does ritual without a traditional sense of faith count? <strong>What would Jews make of this ritual behavior?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Unfortunately, we have nothing similar from the Jewish community. We do not have a series like this. There is little Jewish theological engagement since the early 1960’s, except among a few academics. Why cant Jews put out a series like this?<br />
</strong></p>
<p><strong>We spend all our time discussing bad ideology about our denominations, maybe responses to actual philosophers might better clarify our beliefs? Maybe a Reform and Orthodox response to Vattimo might teach us more than a rehashing of denominational generalities. </strong></p>
<p><strong>What can Jews learn from Vattimo? Does it reflect our congregants state of faith? How would we respond to Vattimo? What corrective does it offer us</strong>?</p>
<p><strong>How would an Orthodox author successful learn from a heretic?<br />
</strong></p>
<p>As a side point: It is interesting to watch the major philosopher of our age <a href="http://twitter.com/JHabermas">Jurgern Habermas learning to use Twitter.</a></p>
<p><a rel="bookmark" href="http://jonathanstray.com/jurgen-habermas-says-hes-not-on-twitter">Update: Jürgen Habermas says he’s not on Twitter</a></p>
<blockquote><p>Over the last several days there has been considerable <a href="http://twitter.com/#search?q=JHabermas">hubbub</a> around the fact that pioneering media theorist <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/J%C3%BCrgen_Habermas">Jürgen Habermas</a> might have signed up for Twitter as @JHabermas. This would be “important if true”, as Jay Rosen <a href="http://twitter.com/jayrosen_nyu/status/8423932947">put it</a>. Intrigued, I tracked him down through the University of Frankfurt. I succeeded in getting him on the phone at his home in Sternburg, and asked him if he was on Twitter. He said,</p>
<p>No, no, no. This is somebody else. This is a mis-use of my name.</p></blockquote>
<p>Copyright © 2010 Alan Brill • All Rights Reserved</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/30/vattimo-and-theology/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>12</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Moshe Halbertal on Amartya Sen</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/21/moshe-halbertal-on-amartya-sen/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/21/moshe-halbertal-on-amartya-sen/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Dec 2009 02:01:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ethics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[amartya Sen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish ethics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Rawls]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[justice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[moshe halbertal]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=372</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Moshe Halbertal has a review in TNR of  The Idea of Justice By Amartya Sen (Harvard University Press) He summarizes Sen as claiming that there is no one principle of justice and that there is no overarching ethical principle, we &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/21/moshe-halbertal-on-amartya-sen/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.tnr.com/article/environment-and-energy/the-ideal-and-the-real">Moshe Halbertal has a review in TNR </a>of  <em>The Idea of Justice</em> By Amartya Sen (Harvard University Press) He summarizes Sen as claiming that there is no one principle of justice and that there is no overarching ethical principle, we deal with the situation at hand. In this, Sen is against Rawl’s grand egalitarian system. Halbertal thinks that if Sen means that no grand theory that we cannot decide between theories then he is incorrect. But if he means that there should be no grand overall theory then he has a point. Halbertal thinks Sen shows too much sympathy for the libertarian position. Halbertal showing his own sympathies frames Sen as a pluralist.</p>
<p>Once upon a time, not that long ago a book like this would have received book reviews from Rabbis like Walter Wurzburger. They would discuss where the ideas in the book fit into various halakhic thinkers and how to formulate a Jewish version. Now we have a orthodox halakhic libertarianism facing a liberal non-philosophic egalitarianism. People use the term &#8220;values&#8221; as a way of moving beyond halakhic formalism, but there needs to be the prior discussion consisting of: which ethics?</p>
<p>As I said before, we lost out by not producing in the 1990’s a Jewish reading of Rawls, Nozick, Sandel, and Waltzer.  I believe at this point, it would still be well received. In addition, it is a shame that after the culture wars, Halbertal has to defend academic discourse on ethics from the charge of relativism. Not long ago, the introductory course in ethics taught Kantian deontology, utilitarianism, intuitionism, and prudence in equal measure and instructed the students that you need to know all of them for reasoned discourse.</p>
<blockquote><p><strong>In his introduction</strong> to <em>The Idea of Justice</em>, Amartya Sen asks the reader to imagine a scenario that will figure prominently throughout the book. Three children are arguing among themselves about which one of them should have a flute. The first child, Anne, is a trained musician who can make the best use of the flute. The second child, Bob, is the poorest of the three and owns no other toys or instruments. Clara, the third contender, happens to be the one who, with hard sustained labor, made the flute. Since philosophers try to reason about such distributive problems, each of the children can enlist support from a grand theory of justice that originated in what seems to be an impartial position in moral philosophy.</p>
<p>Utilitarians will opt for giving the flute to Anne, since their criteria for distribution is to give preference to the scheme that will maximize overall utility, thus granting the instrument to the individual who can derive the most pleasure out of it. Bob, the poorest child among the three, will be chosen by egalitarians, since the main concern of their distributive approach is to narrow social and economic gaps as much as possible. And libertarians, who emphasize rights-based ownership entitlements, will claim that Clara deserves the flute as the producer of the object, and that no other distributive concerns&#8211;egalitarian or utilitarian&#8211;can supersede her entitlement to what she naturally owns.</p>
<p>.Rawls himself defended an egalitarian position. According to Rawls, perfect equality should have been the rule, but rewarding capable people with differential income will create an incentive for them to raise the production of the sum total of goods, which in a system of fair distribution might end up benefiting the people who are at the bottom of the economic ladder.The ultimate merit of Rawls’s work did not lie only in his own theory, but in the extraordinarily broad discussion that it generated</p>
<p>G.A. Cohen’s in <em>Rescuing Justice and Equality</em>, which challenged Rawls from the left and advocated a stricter egalitarianism; and Robert Nozick’s sophisticated libertarian response in <em>Anarchy, State, and Utopia</em>; and Michael Walzer’s development, in <em>Spheres of Justice</em>, of a communitarian approach to the problem.</p>
<p>Sen rejects, as a matter of principle, the nature of Rawls’s project…According to Sen,<strong> </strong>a sustained and reasoned argument about justice should focus on a result-oriented comparative approach among different conditions, rather than on an attempt to formulate the philosophical conditions of a perfectly just society…. Injustices are altogether easier to identify than the conditions of perfect justice. And injustices can be identified on the basis of various and competing grand theories, which may overlap in such actual comparative judgments.</p>
<p>Grand theories become perverse when they postulate themselves as exclusive, when they wish to solve all the complex issues with one decisive and final principle.</p>
<p>The best way of making comparative judgments is by considering multiple points of view as they are refined by different theories, and weighing the diverse claims that they make.. Only when philosophy is deployed in this patient and pluralistic way can we apply it usefully to real people and real conditions….It is important to note also that Sen’s acceptance of the limited and relative force of each grand theory does not deteriorate into any kind of moral relativism. Pluralism is not relativism. Choosing between different approaches and policies is not an expression of taste or prejudice, a purely subjective effusion of passion.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/21/moshe-halbertal-on-amartya-sen/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Most important Post-WWII thought and Judaism</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/01/most-important-post-wwii-thought-and-judaism/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/01/most-important-post-wwii-thought-and-judaism/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2009 23:06:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Charles Taylor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Rawls]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ronald Dworkin]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=327</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As you read the list, which ones influenced Judiasm and which did not? Kuhn has not been used to discuss change, we usually still find the 19th century views of Hegel or von Savigny. From the comments here and elsewhere, &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/01/most-important-post-wwii-thought-and-judaism/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As you read the list, which ones influenced Judiasm and which did not? Kuhn has not been used to discuss change, we usually still find the 19th century views of Hegel or von Savigny. From the comments here and elsewhere, we desperately needed a Jewish follower of Rawls in 1990. Most people did not need Post-modernism or literary criticism, but they did need an updated, beyond Dewey, rational approach which Rawls would have provided. Dworkin is used by Halbertal- people here are still jumping to Robert Cover for the role of ethics in halakhah, when what they really need is Dworkin. Wittgenstein is part of the Orthodox intellectual&#8217;s toolkit but no substantive engagement. MacIntyre is converted into virtue drush. There is still time for Searle&#8217;s Speech Acts or Taylor&#8217;s ever-changing self to find a Jewish voice. Feyerabend is too much to hope for. Nevertheless, I am forever amazed when rabbis who pride themselves that they are contemporary philosophers who quote Dewey or James as their last significant thinker.</p>
<blockquote><p><a href="http://leiterreports.typepad.com/blog/2009/11/the-most-cited-books-in-postwwii-anglophone-philosophy.html">The Most Cited Books in Post-WWII Anglophone Philosophy</a> According to Google Scholar (in parentheses:  total number of on-line articles and books citing the book in question):</p>
<p>1.  Thomas Kuhn, <em>The Structure of Scientific Revolutions</em> (37,197)</p>
<p>2.  John Rawls, <em>A Theory of Justice</em> (26,768)</p>
<p>3.  Ronald Dworkin, <em>Taking Rights Seriously</em> (7,892)</p>
<p>4.  Ludwig Wittgenstein, <em>Philosophical Investigations</em> (7,169)</p>
<p>5.  Alasdair MacIntyre, <em>After Virtue</em> (6,579)</p>
<p>6.  Gilbert Ryle, <em>The Concept of Mind</em> (6,356)</p>
<p>6.  John Rawls, <em>Political Liberalism </em>(6,352)</p>
<p>8.  Robert Nozick, <em>Anarchy, State, and Utopia</em> (6,246)</p>
<p>8.  H.L.A. Hart, <em>The Concept of Law</em> (6,212)</p>
<p>10.  Richard Rorty, <em>Philosophy and the Mirror of Nature</em> (5,616)</p>
<p>11.  John Searle, <em>Speech Acts</em> (5,387)</p>
<p>12. Jerry Fodor, <em>Modularity of Mind</em> (5,050)</p>
<p>13.  Daniel Dennett, <em>Consciousness Explained</em> (4,810)</p>
<p>14. Saul Kripke, <em>Naming and Necessity</em> (4,535)</p>
<p>14. W.V.O. Quine, <em>Word and Object</em> (4,565)</p>
<p>Runners-up:   Paul Feyerabend, <em>Against Method</em> (4,420); Richard Rorty, <em>Contingency, Irony and Solidarity</em> (4,011); Charles Taylor, <em>Sources of the Self</em> (3,233); Jerry Fodor, <em>The Language of Thought</em> (3,292); Carl Hempel, <em>Aspects of Scientific Explanation</em> (3,137); David Chalmers, <em>The Conscious Mind </em>(3,065), Daniel Dennett, <em>The Intentional Stance </em>(2,985); Derek Parfit, <em>Reasons and Persons</em> (2,972).</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/01/most-important-post-wwii-thought-and-judaism/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Avot, Ibn Ezra, and Being a Mentch</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/10/avot-ibn-ezra-and-being-a-mentch/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/10/avot-ibn-ezra-and-being-a-mentch/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2009 02:49:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ethics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[liturgy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[613 Mizvot]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avigdor Shinan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ben-Zion Dinur]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[haaretz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hananel Mack]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ibn Ezra]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Micahel Wex]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pirkei avot]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yesod Mora]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[zvia Walden]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=237</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This year Haaretz did not translate their 2009 Rosh Hashanah Jewish culture supplement with its book reviews. The Hebrew edition had some interesting articles, including one by Etkes and a funky one by Haviva Pedaya. But this week they did &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/10/avot-ibn-ezra-and-being-a-mentch/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This year Haaretz did not translate their 2009 Rosh Hashanah Jewish culture supplement with its book reviews. The Hebrew edition had some interesting articles, including one by Etkes and a funky one by Haviva Pedaya. But this week they did translate their November 2009 literary supplement. There was a certain gentleness to all their choices. Here are three of the reviews.</p>
<p>The first review is on the new edition of Pirkei Avot that has been a runaway bestseller this Fall. It reminds us of the Israeli project of creating a Jewish cultural heritage, when the books by Dvir and Bialek Presses: Sefer HaAgadah, Sefer HaZemanin on the holidays, Mishnat HaZohar Sifrei Dorot, were on every shelf. They let the Jewish reader approach the Jewish classics outside of yeshiva, orthodoxy, and authority, the way we approach penguin paperback classics. So it is nice to know that the Pirkei Avot is a best seller. Dinur, creator of the Israeli educational curriculum, Beit Hatefuzot, and Yad VaShem, created the older edition. The review has a nice sense of the role of Avot and rabbinic literature on our proverbs and wisdom.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1126660.html">The art of succinct statements By Zvia Walden</a></p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Pirkei Avot: Perush Yisraeli Hadash , </strong><em>edited and annotated by Avigdor Shinan </em><em> Yedioth Ahronoth Books and the Avi Chai Foundation,<br />
</em></p>
<p><em> </em></p>
<p>&#8220;A fundamental challenge facing our generation &#8212; living in a country that also happens to be our ances­tral homeland &#8212; is figuring out the proper ways to preserve the spiritual and moral image of the individual and society in Israel.&#8221; Does this not sound very contemporary and disturbingly relevant? Yet these words were written in 1972 by Prof. Ben-Zion Dinur, who served as Israel&#8217;s third minister of education (1951-1955 ) and who initiated the draft­ing of the Martyrs&#8217; and Heroes&#8217; Remembrance Law in 1953, which officially established Yad Vashem. That same year, Dinur was also responsible for the law that established public education in Israel, in the wake of which the various ideological streams were united into a single school system.</p>
<p>Dinur made the preceding observation in the introduction to his annotated and explicated edition of Tractate Avot of the Mishna, that is, Pirkei Avot (Sayings of the Fathers ). He noted that he had begun work on the edition back in 1917-18, when he was teaching at the Tarbut teachers training college in Kiev. He continued his efforts when he served as a lecturer at the Hebrew teachers seminar in Jerusalem (today the David Yellin  Teachers College). Which is to say that Israel once had a liberal-minded education minis­ter, one who had actually taught (for years ) in teachers training schools. He diligently prepared his commentaries from a his­torical perspective, because he believed that knowledge of their context was crucial for under­standing their content. Imagine if we had cabinet ministers like that today.</p>
<p>Shinan&#8217;s new commentary on Pirkei Avot has featured prom­inently on the Israeli bestseller lists for weeks.</p>
<p>How can one explain the suc­cess of a volume such as Shinan&#8217;s? Is it due to the ever-growing thirst to &#8220;preserve the spiritual and moral image of the individual and society in Israel,&#8221; as Dinur had it? Or is it due to the acces­sible writing style of the editor, a professor of Hebrew literature at the Hebrew University? Or, per­haps native Hebrew speakers are attracted to this edition because Shinan chose to devote much at­tention to the Hebrew text and to connecting the tractate to names, places and landscapes in Israel, while sufficing with only a brief survey of Pirkei Avot&#8217;s tradi­tional commentators?</p>
<p>Phrases from Pirkei Avot have penetrated deep into modern Hebrew, even if many of those doing the quoting are unaware of where they first appeared.. Many Hebrew speakers in Israel might quote the phrase, &#8220;Love work, and hate lordship,&#8221; but few know its continuation, &#8220;and make not thyself known to the government&#8221; (chapter 1:10 )</p>
<p>The late Levi Eshkol be­longed to the generation that was familiar with the phrase, &#8220;The ledger is open and the hand is writing,&#8221; but many of the Young Turks working at the Finance Ministry today, who may well believe that &#8220;the workmen are sluggish,&#8221; have no idea that &#8220;the master of the house is urgent&#8221; (2:18). We are part of a generation that has become cut off from its cultural roots; we must carry out the difficult work to amend the situation.</p></blockquote>
<p>The second book reviewed is the Yesod Mora, a perennial Jewish classic on the need to have a broad education and the nature of mizvot. The book has fallen out of fashion in our era. Science, linguistics, mathematics, and philosophy were integrated into Torah. Ibn Ezra rejects the number 613 for the mizvot. He also criticizes the various Biblical and Talmudic scholars of his era for a too provincial education and worldview. Hananel Mack offers us the hypothetical of conjuring up the book that Ibn Ezra would write against the scholars of 2009.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1126666.html"> Thirteen gates to infinity By Hananel Mack</a></p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Yesod Mora </strong><em>Abraham Ibn Ezra, edited by Uriel Simon </em><em> Bar-Ilan University Press (Hebrew ), 272 pages, NIS 115</em></p>
<p><em> </em></p>
<p>One of Ibn Ezra&#8217;s late works is &#8220;Yesod Mora Vesod Hatorah&#8221; (&#8220;Foundation of Awe and the Secret of the Torah&#8221; ), commonly called by the first two words of its name, a book dedicated to examining the essence of the commandments and their place in religious thought and at the foundation of Jewish belief.</p>
<p>According to the editor, Prof. Uriel Simon, an expert in research of the Bible and its com­mentaries, particularly the works of Ibn Ezra: &#8221; His thinking is disjointed and jumpy, his arguments emotional, argumentative and associative, and his phrasing too abbrevi­ated, tending toward suggestion.&#8221;</p>
<p>According to him, a wise per­son&#8217;s approach to the holy writings and to religious philosophy requires a broad edu­cation encompassing all the branches of science, and must reject narrow-minded expertise in specific fields at the expense of others. This cosmopolitan position pre­vents those who do not share the breadth of Ibn Ezra&#8217;s perspective from properly understanding his writings, particularly those pertaining to philosophy and sci­ence.</p>
<p>According to Simon, &#8220;The first chapter is dedicated to a detailed proof of the re­ligious need for multidisciplinary educa­tion.&#8221; Toward that end, Ibn Ezra describes four types of &#8220;learned men of Israel&#8221; who specialize in narrow and defined fields of Torah and wisdom study but are unable to see the whole ensemble, and for whom, for this reason, even their fields of specializa­tion are found wanting.</p>
<p>Most of the remaining chapters deal with the Jewish religious mitzvot and their place in the system of belief and knowledge. Unlike other medieval books on the commandments, such as those of Rabbis Saadia Gaon, Maimonides and Nachmanides, here there is no discussion of halakha &#8212; religious law &#8212; and its minu­tiae; rather, the discussion is entirely on a theoretical level. Chapter two deals with the numbering of the commandments, wherein the scholar presents and criti­cizes the systems of several earlier &#8220;com­mandment-counters.&#8221;</p>
<p>Especially interesting is the status of the number 613, the traditional total number of all the commandments. The source of that enumeration is the homi­letical sermon of the Talmudic sage Rabbi Shamlai…Unlike many other homiletical sermons, this one was accepted with great serious­ness, although there were some who saw in Shamlai&#8217;s words a tale not to be taken too seriously; Ibn Ezra belonged to the lat­ter.</p>
<p>The afterword added to the new edition deals with the text&#8217;s polemical side. Simon draws to­gether the main points of criticism, some of it bitter, leveled by Ibn Ezra against the majority of learned scholars in Israel and Christian Europe, and to a lesser extent also those in Spain, for their tendency to over-specialization and for their lack of systematic education in the sciences.</p>
<p>Contemporary readers are invited to imagine the criticism, tongue-lashing and overt disdain that would have been elicit­ed from Ibn Ezra had he foreseen current trends in the world of Torah and yeshiva study.</p></blockquote>
<p>Finally, an interview with Michael Wex, author of &#8220;Born to Kvetch.&#8221; &#8220;Just Say Nu,&#8221; and this fall <strong>&#8220;How to Be a Mentsh (and Not a Shmuck )</strong><em> (Harper, 224 pages, $24 ).</em> Wex discusses how Yiddish culture valued character, being a mentch, and being.ehrliche.  They use to say frumkeit is for the galah, a yid is ehrliche. And a litvish lamdan was called a &#8220;tzelemer kop.&#8221; Wax points out the role of Pirkei Avot, that the average Jew was not learned and to avoid <em>khnoykishkay.</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1126667.html"> Questions &amp; Answers: A conversation with Michael Wex</a></p>
<blockquote><p>Judaism is all about refinement of character and becoming a better person; if performing ritual or ceremonial com­mandments or studying all day is not mak­ing you a better person, then there&#8217;s some­thing wrong with the way you&#8217;re doing it. And we&#8217;ve got a couple of thousand years of popular ethical manuals, starting with Pirkei Avot, to help show average people the right way to do things.</p>
<p>Post-Holocaust we&#8217;ve been given a rosy picture of pre-Hitler life in Europe, in which every Jew was a <em>talmid haham </em>[learned person]. That just wasn&#8217;t the case. People stammered out the prayers, but didn&#8217;t necessarily know that they meant. Much of the joke with Sholom Aleichem&#8217;s Tevye is that he&#8217;s always mistranslating biblical verses and rabbinic sayings, and people still argue about whether or not he &#8212; Tevye, I mean &#8212; was supposed to be doing so on purpose. What you got as a sort of counterbalance to the traditional exaltation of scholarship, was this idea that character is as important as anything else. This is re­ally just an idea that was re-expressed, that regained prominence, in early Hasidism. I talk a little about earlier instances of it, and the way people looked at things. In part it&#8217;s the idea about having the basic Jewish common sense to know when something of anything is too much. You look at some­thing like the story in the Talmud about the destruction of Jerusalem, about Kamtso and Bar Kamtso. Ultimately it turned on a piece of <em>khnoykishkayt</em> [hypocritical sanc­timoniousness], about being punctilious about the wrong things at the wrong time.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/10/avot-ibn-ezra-and-being-a-mentch/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
