<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Novak- Social Contract Part II of III parts	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/03/novak-social-contract-part-ii-of-iii-parts/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/03/novak-social-contract-part-ii-of-iii-parts/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2009 03:53:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Two Months &#171; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions: notes on Jewish theology and spirituality		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/03/novak-social-contract-part-ii-of-iii-parts/#comment-152</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Two Months &#171; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions: notes on Jewish theology and spirituality]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2009 03:53:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=200#comment-152</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[[...] one of big hits. On the other hand, I am quite surprised that no one is looking at the Novak posts here and here. I learned that three book reviews from Haaretz in a single post is too much. I also [...]]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] one of big hits. On the other hand, I am quite surprised that no one is looking at the Novak posts here and here. I learned that three book reviews from Haaretz in a single post is too much. I also [&#8230;]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Yonatan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/03/novak-social-contract-part-ii-of-iii-parts/#comment-140</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Yonatan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 09 Nov 2009 15:49:15 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=200#comment-140</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I could guess that the attraction could be to those who are themselves not scholars of Judaism who do not know how he is butchering the sources.

Additionally, as I noted above, there are very few &quot;Jewish&quot; political theories and theorists today. Having one available, even if he gets things wrong, gives publications fodder to discuss these issues.

Lastly, as I noted, he provides a counterbalance to the Jewish political left with more substance than people like Norman Podhoretz or David Klinghoffer. 

According to numerous articles over the last decade, the Jewish political/social rightwing is on the acendancy and is a political force to be reckoned with. However, there is no political theorist to give a clear explanation of their beliefs. Perhaps, people are turning to Novak as a way of explaining the Jewish Right.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I could guess that the attraction could be to those who are themselves not scholars of Judaism who do not know how he is butchering the sources.</p>
<p>Additionally, as I noted above, there are very few &#8220;Jewish&#8221; political theories and theorists today. Having one available, even if he gets things wrong, gives publications fodder to discuss these issues.</p>
<p>Lastly, as I noted, he provides a counterbalance to the Jewish political left with more substance than people like Norman Podhoretz or David Klinghoffer. </p>
<p>According to numerous articles over the last decade, the Jewish political/social rightwing is on the acendancy and is a political force to be reckoned with. However, there is no political theorist to give a clear explanation of their beliefs. Perhaps, people are turning to Novak as a way of explaining the Jewish Right.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/03/novak-social-contract-part-ii-of-iii-parts/#comment-133</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2009 16:29:46 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=200#comment-133</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/03/novak-social-contract-part-ii-of-iii-parts/#comment-132&quot;&gt;Yonatan&lt;/a&gt;.

I myself want to know what there is in his thought. Right now he is &quot;in&quot; and read and I want to find the attraction. I asked the person who drove me home last night about Novak and he reminded me of when Martha Nussbaum tore him apart at an academic conference. He was treated as interfaith and traditionalism by those whom read theology. But now he has a half a dozen works from important presses and is a key player in the Tikvah -Witherspoon events. He is getting reviewed in all the major publications. The stack of reviews on my table are all negative but I can blame that on the liberalism of the authors. I tried to be fair in my presentation- so what is the attraction?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/03/novak-social-contract-part-ii-of-iii-parts/#comment-132">Yonatan</a>.</p>
<p>I myself want to know what there is in his thought. Right now he is &#8220;in&#8221; and read and I want to find the attraction. I asked the person who drove me home last night about Novak and he reminded me of when Martha Nussbaum tore him apart at an academic conference. He was treated as interfaith and traditionalism by those whom read theology. But now he has a half a dozen works from important presses and is a key player in the Tikvah -Witherspoon events. He is getting reviewed in all the major publications. The stack of reviews on my table are all negative but I can blame that on the liberalism of the authors. I tried to be fair in my presentation- so what is the attraction?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Yonatan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/03/novak-social-contract-part-ii-of-iii-parts/#comment-132</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Yonatan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2009 16:11:57 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=200#comment-132</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Is Novak really as bad as you are presenting him? 

If so, what is his appeal other than speaking to the &quot;converted&quot;, who already adopt a social conservative position and who read Commentary and First Things? 

Of is his role to present a &quot;Jewish&quot; position to accompany the &quot;Christian&quot; and &quot;secular&quot; positions in the Neo-Conservative circles?

Perhaps Novak is appealing because of the lack of alternative Jewish political theories &#038; theorists. There are source books, such as Waltzer, et al., but not complete worldviews.

Or perhaps because many feel uncomfortable with Orthodox Judaisms Jewish particularism or Pan-Halakhicism.

Perhaps he is useful as a stand-in figure. One could present him on the right, someone else on the left and one could then teach a class on 21st Century American Jewish political theory.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Is Novak really as bad as you are presenting him? </p>
<p>If so, what is his appeal other than speaking to the &#8220;converted&#8221;, who already adopt a social conservative position and who read Commentary and First Things? </p>
<p>Of is his role to present a &#8220;Jewish&#8221; position to accompany the &#8220;Christian&#8221; and &#8220;secular&#8221; positions in the Neo-Conservative circles?</p>
<p>Perhaps Novak is appealing because of the lack of alternative Jewish political theories &amp; theorists. There are source books, such as Waltzer, et al., but not complete worldviews.</p>
<p>Or perhaps because many feel uncomfortable with Orthodox Judaisms Jewish particularism or Pan-Halakhicism.</p>
<p>Perhaps he is useful as a stand-in figure. One could present him on the right, someone else on the left and one could then teach a class on 21st Century American Jewish political theory.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
