<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Bi-religious afterschool program.	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/27/bi-religious-afterschool-program/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/27/bi-religious-afterschool-program/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Mar 2011 17:31:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Bi-Religious Eucation, or: How to Teach No Faith At All &#171; Rabbi Arie Folger&#8217;s Blog		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/27/bi-religious-afterschool-program/#comment-2853</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Bi-Religious Eucation, or: How to Teach No Faith At All &#171; Rabbi Arie Folger&#8217;s Blog]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Mar 2011 17:31:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3319#comment-2853</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[[...] Eucation, or: How to Teach No Faith At&#160;All  Prof. Alan Brill has a post up on his blog about a Bi-religious afterschool program, teaching both Judaism and Christianity, presumably to the [...]]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] Eucation, or: How to Teach No Faith At&nbsp;All  Prof. Alan Brill has a post up on his blog about a Bi-religious afterschool program, teaching both Judaism and Christianity, presumably to the [&#8230;]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Susan Katz Miller		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/27/bi-religious-afterschool-program/#comment-2847</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Katz Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Mar 2011 15:23:30 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3319#comment-2847</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Rabbi Scher,

I would point out that it was not me telling the story of Jesus in that post, but another interfaith parent, who reported the conversation to me, so I cannot tell you what else was said in that particular conversation. 

I will tell you that, as in many Jewish congregations, the members of our interfaith families community range from secular humanists, to agnostics, to spiritual &quot;believers,&quot; to mystics. So the balance of what is important to any particular set of parents, in terms of history/practice/belief, varies greatly. The parents are the most important teachers of the child, and we do not dictate how parents teach their children. However, parents who join our group (in contrast to secular humanist groups) have to be open to introducing their children to the idea of G-d, since this belief is central to both religions. 

We do not shy away from delving into the beliefs of both Judaism and Christianity, and encouraging children to think about and develop beliefs, nor do we dictate what those beliefs should be. For instance, in our Coming of Age class, teenagers wrestle with questions including &quot;What is G-d?&quot; &quot;Why do bad things happen?&quot; and &quot;Is there an afterlife?&quot;]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rabbi Scher,</p>
<p>I would point out that it was not me telling the story of Jesus in that post, but another interfaith parent, who reported the conversation to me, so I cannot tell you what else was said in that particular conversation. </p>
<p>I will tell you that, as in many Jewish congregations, the members of our interfaith families community range from secular humanists, to agnostics, to spiritual &#8220;believers,&#8221; to mystics. So the balance of what is important to any particular set of parents, in terms of history/practice/belief, varies greatly. The parents are the most important teachers of the child, and we do not dictate how parents teach their children. However, parents who join our group (in contrast to secular humanist groups) have to be open to introducing their children to the idea of G-d, since this belief is central to both religions. </p>
<p>We do not shy away from delving into the beliefs of both Judaism and Christianity, and encouraging children to think about and develop beliefs, nor do we dictate what those beliefs should be. For instance, in our Coming of Age class, teenagers wrestle with questions including &#8220;What is G-d?&#8221; &#8220;Why do bad things happen?&#8221; and &#8220;Is there an afterlife?&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Mordechai Y. Scher		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/27/bi-religious-afterschool-program/#comment-2846</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mordechai Y. Scher]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Mar 2011 14:38:12 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3319#comment-2846</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Mrs. Miller&#039;s comment and blog posts are interesting - but I think she avoids the notion that these a *religious* cultures we&#039;re talking about.  What people *believe* is at the core of these cultures; not just the outlines and narratives.  The recent post on Easter and Jesus is a case in point.  If her report there is fairly complete, then she told the *story* of Jesus in brief; but said nothing about what believers in Christianity think about, believe about Jesus and how that shapes their lives.  That isn&#039;t teaching an understanding of religion - that&#039;s more akin to cultural anthropology.  We see of course, the same thing, in the way American Jews commonly remove the religious notions from Jewish holidays and learning.  A holiday becomes a mere historical commemoration, devoid of any religious content or message.  That isn&#039;t practicing or teaching the religion anymore.  No matter which religion it is.  Beliefs and what they bring about are the core issues of any religious discussion.

That is what I meant about removing the integrity of the religious cultures involved.  Neither Judaism nor Christianity is being taught.  This is something brand new, really.  If it continues, then in a few generations it may acquire a name all its own.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Mrs. Miller&#8217;s comment and blog posts are interesting &#8211; but I think she avoids the notion that these a *religious* cultures we&#8217;re talking about.  What people *believe* is at the core of these cultures; not just the outlines and narratives.  The recent post on Easter and Jesus is a case in point.  If her report there is fairly complete, then she told the *story* of Jesus in brief; but said nothing about what believers in Christianity think about, believe about Jesus and how that shapes their lives.  That isn&#8217;t teaching an understanding of religion &#8211; that&#8217;s more akin to cultural anthropology.  We see of course, the same thing, in the way American Jews commonly remove the religious notions from Jewish holidays and learning.  A holiday becomes a mere historical commemoration, devoid of any religious content or message.  That isn&#8217;t practicing or teaching the religion anymore.  No matter which religion it is.  Beliefs and what they bring about are the core issues of any religious discussion.</p>
<p>That is what I meant about removing the integrity of the religious cultures involved.  Neither Judaism nor Christianity is being taught.  This is something brand new, really.  If it continues, then in a few generations it may acquire a name all its own.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Susan Katz Miller		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/27/bi-religious-afterschool-program/#comment-2844</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Katz Miller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Mar 2011 11:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3319#comment-2844</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I appreciate your open-minded post on interfaith families educating their children in both Judaism and Christianity, and the communities evolving to support those families. In particular, I am glad you found my blog, onbeingboth.com, and quoted my five suggestions for raising happy interfaith children. 

I want to point out, however, that although I find NY&#039;s Interfaith Community inspiring as the first group of its kind, and I have shared many deep conversation with Interfaith Community founder Sheila Gordon over many years, my blog is not affiliated with the Interfaith Community. I am an adult interfaith child, raising my interfaith children in Washington DC&#039;s Interfaith Families Project (iffp.net), a group that also teaches children both religions, but which evolved separately from NY&#039;s group. Such groups have arisen in several different cities, independently, and with slightly different structures and strategies.

Susan Katz Miller
onbeingboth.com]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I appreciate your open-minded post on interfaith families educating their children in both Judaism and Christianity, and the communities evolving to support those families. In particular, I am glad you found my blog, onbeingboth.com, and quoted my five suggestions for raising happy interfaith children. </p>
<p>I want to point out, however, that although I find NY&#8217;s Interfaith Community inspiring as the first group of its kind, and I have shared many deep conversation with Interfaith Community founder Sheila Gordon over many years, my blog is not affiliated with the Interfaith Community. I am an adult interfaith child, raising my interfaith children in Washington DC&#8217;s Interfaith Families Project (iffp.net), a group that also teaches children both religions, but which evolved separately from NY&#8217;s group. Such groups have arisen in several different cities, independently, and with slightly different structures and strategies.</p>
<p>Susan Katz Miller<br />
onbeingboth.com</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Mordechai Y. Scher		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/27/bi-religious-afterschool-program/#comment-2840</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mordechai Y. Scher]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Mar 2011 03:29:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3319#comment-2840</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Santa Fe, eh?  We&#039;re on the map!

Big challenge out here.  Many of the intermarriages are with Jewish husbands, so &#039;producing Jewish children&#039; isn&#039;t available as an out to finesse the issues.  Even a governor (chieftan) of Acoma pueblo, Solomon Bibo, was Jewish. (Married to the chief&#039;s granddaughter.  Sounds like a bad Jewish joke.)

On the other hand, we just try to teach Torah openly and honestly; but without going out of the way to emphasize things that will just widen the rift between congregations in the Jewish community.  As I see it, we have a big task just trying to create or restore some respect for Torah and tradition; and that requires that we be prepared to flex a bit and learn with whomever in the Jewish community wants it.  As for the non-Jewish community, we don&#039;t reach out to them; but we do respond positively to requests to speak to community groups of different sorts.

Let&#039;s face it.  You have to start by recognizing who your neighbors are before thinking about how to learn Torah with them.

Personally, I think the whole interfaith community approach lacks integrity; but one would have to assume a particular integrity to each individual religion in order to say it is being violated.  

It seems to me that the project you&#039;ve portrayed here just blurs the distinctions.  That, I believe, violates the integrity of each religious culture.  The parents, of course, were not thinking that way when they got married and started families.  Maybe, by hook or crook, the children will get some more clarity because of these meetings? But only if the distinctions are preserved and presented.  From what you&#039;re saying, that isn&#039;t what happens.

I thinking other signs of this trend are the Jewish Outreach Institute, and that intermarriage columnist (at the Forward?).]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Santa Fe, eh?  We&#8217;re on the map!</p>
<p>Big challenge out here.  Many of the intermarriages are with Jewish husbands, so &#8216;producing Jewish children&#8217; isn&#8217;t available as an out to finesse the issues.  Even a governor (chieftan) of Acoma pueblo, Solomon Bibo, was Jewish. (Married to the chief&#8217;s granddaughter.  Sounds like a bad Jewish joke.)</p>
<p>On the other hand, we just try to teach Torah openly and honestly; but without going out of the way to emphasize things that will just widen the rift between congregations in the Jewish community.  As I see it, we have a big task just trying to create or restore some respect for Torah and tradition; and that requires that we be prepared to flex a bit and learn with whomever in the Jewish community wants it.  As for the non-Jewish community, we don&#8217;t reach out to them; but we do respond positively to requests to speak to community groups of different sorts.</p>
<p>Let&#8217;s face it.  You have to start by recognizing who your neighbors are before thinking about how to learn Torah with them.</p>
<p>Personally, I think the whole interfaith community approach lacks integrity; but one would have to assume a particular integrity to each individual religion in order to say it is being violated.  </p>
<p>It seems to me that the project you&#8217;ve portrayed here just blurs the distinctions.  That, I believe, violates the integrity of each religious culture.  The parents, of course, were not thinking that way when they got married and started families.  Maybe, by hook or crook, the children will get some more clarity because of these meetings? But only if the distinctions are preserved and presented.  From what you&#8217;re saying, that isn&#8217;t what happens.</p>
<p>I thinking other signs of this trend are the Jewish Outreach Institute, and that intermarriage columnist (at the Forward?).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
