<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Anti-Intellectual Populism and Relgious Self-Understanding	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/26/anti-intellectual-populism-and-relgious-self-understanding/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/26/anti-intellectual-populism-and-relgious-self-understanding/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2011 13:47:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: MBG		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/26/anti-intellectual-populism-and-relgious-self-understanding/#comment-3652</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[MBG]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2011 13:47:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4169#comment-3652</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Like Josh I was thinking about the applicability to medical expertise.  While there is definitely an anti-establishment-medicine strain in some frum cultures (and i think also some evangelical subcultures) - i mean not vaccinating, homeopathy, etc - it seems to me that the dominant strain in orthodoxy is to be extremely deferential to doctors and their expertise.  Certainly in rabbinic litarature my feeling (I keep meaning to look into this seirously and haven&#039;t yet) is that frequently rabbis use &quot;but the doctors say he HAS to&quot; as a convenient crutch.  They rely on doctors to determine certain predicate facts based on which they can, for example, be lenient about something like shabbat or kashrut.  When the rabbis don&#039;t want to follow expert opinion (a simple case is pregnant women fasting, a less simple one is brain death) they know how to discount medical expert opinion, but usually in a local way - not by discounting the whole project of medical expertise.  I suspect medicine is privileged in part for social reasons (too many my-son-the-doctors), but that there is something else as well, which may have to do with people thinking of medicine as technology rather than akin to &quot;theoretical&quot; science, and perhaps also with a general american love of consuming more healthcare.  it&#039;s probably not because medicine is inherently less threatening.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Like Josh I was thinking about the applicability to medical expertise.  While there is definitely an anti-establishment-medicine strain in some frum cultures (and i think also some evangelical subcultures) &#8211; i mean not vaccinating, homeopathy, etc &#8211; it seems to me that the dominant strain in orthodoxy is to be extremely deferential to doctors and their expertise.  Certainly in rabbinic litarature my feeling (I keep meaning to look into this seirously and haven&#8217;t yet) is that frequently rabbis use &#8220;but the doctors say he HAS to&#8221; as a convenient crutch.  They rely on doctors to determine certain predicate facts based on which they can, for example, be lenient about something like shabbat or kashrut.  When the rabbis don&#8217;t want to follow expert opinion (a simple case is pregnant women fasting, a less simple one is brain death) they know how to discount medical expert opinion, but usually in a local way &#8211; not by discounting the whole project of medical expertise.  I suspect medicine is privileged in part for social reasons (too many my-son-the-doctors), but that there is something else as well, which may have to do with people thinking of medicine as technology rather than akin to &#8220;theoretical&#8221; science, and perhaps also with a general american love of consuming more healthcare.  it&#8217;s probably not because medicine is inherently less threatening.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/26/anti-intellectual-populism-and-relgious-self-understanding/#comment-3651</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2011 22:59:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4169#comment-3651</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/26/anti-intellectual-populism-and-relgious-self-understanding/#comment-3650&quot;&gt;(Professor Emeritus) Alan Jay Weisbard, Madison, WI&lt;/a&gt;.

I was once among a group of dept heads and assistant deans that went to an out-of town AAUP conference on introducing new ideas and diversity. From the criteria offered by the presenters on how to evaluate your student body, we found that our Orthodox students were just as hostile as the Evangelicals toward intellectual life and that our students actually demonized and dismiss knowledge and academia more than the Christian schools.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/26/anti-intellectual-populism-and-relgious-self-understanding/#comment-3650">(Professor Emeritus) Alan Jay Weisbard, Madison, WI</a>.</p>
<p>I was once among a group of dept heads and assistant deans that went to an out-of town AAUP conference on introducing new ideas and diversity. From the criteria offered by the presenters on how to evaluate your student body, we found that our Orthodox students were just as hostile as the Evangelicals toward intellectual life and that our students actually demonized and dismiss knowledge and academia more than the Christian schools.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: (Professor Emeritus) Alan Jay Weisbard, Madison, WI		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/26/anti-intellectual-populism-and-relgious-self-understanding/#comment-3650</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[(Professor Emeritus) Alan Jay Weisbard, Madison, WI]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2011 22:44:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4169#comment-3650</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Having now watched the video:
This video reflects a degree of anti-intellectualism that I have not often encountered among Jews, including highly observant Jews, at leading American universities, both private and public. Whether it is more typical of Jews raised in hareidi/yeshivish environments is beyond my experience and, you should forgive the expression, my expertise. In my world, college years are precisely when students should be challenged to think through their own commitments and test them against other perspectives and other life experiences. Insularity and unreflective indoctrination in any single belief system are not conducive to intellectual growth and development, or to a fully meaningful acceptance of any set of commitments, including religious commitments. While such assertions are usually targeted at faith-based institutions, it is an interesting question --and one rarely raised internally--whether secular institutions practice their own form of such indoctrination.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Having now watched the video:<br />
This video reflects a degree of anti-intellectualism that I have not often encountered among Jews, including highly observant Jews, at leading American universities, both private and public. Whether it is more typical of Jews raised in hareidi/yeshivish environments is beyond my experience and, you should forgive the expression, my expertise. In my world, college years are precisely when students should be challenged to think through their own commitments and test them against other perspectives and other life experiences. Insularity and unreflective indoctrination in any single belief system are not conducive to intellectual growth and development, or to a fully meaningful acceptance of any set of commitments, including religious commitments. While such assertions are usually targeted at faith-based institutions, it is an interesting question &#8211;and one rarely raised internally&#8211;whether secular institutions practice their own form of such indoctrination.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: (Prof. Emer.) Alan Jay Weisbard, Univ. Of Wisconsin		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/26/anti-intellectual-populism-and-relgious-self-understanding/#comment-3647</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[(Prof. Emer.) Alan Jay Weisbard, Univ. Of Wisconsin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2011 16:22:40 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4169#comment-3647</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Willful misreading would seem to have a substantial history in many faith traditions, certainly not least the rabbinic. Is the issue one of elite vs populist misreading? One specific to our living in a world of highly credentialed expertise?
To what degree are rulings of the ancient rabbis subject to revision based on subsequent expert knowledge inconsistent with the quasi- scientific (I.e., incorrect) underpinnings of their rulings?
For that matter, to what degree is the mass return to fundamentalist or orthodox forms of religion (and a corresponding assertiveness in the public domain) largely a response to a loss of prior felt certainties and claims of &quot;common&quot; sense in the face of the ever-expanding role of expert knowledge in many domains of modern life?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Willful misreading would seem to have a substantial history in many faith traditions, certainly not least the rabbinic. Is the issue one of elite vs populist misreading? One specific to our living in a world of highly credentialed expertise?<br />
To what degree are rulings of the ancient rabbis subject to revision based on subsequent expert knowledge inconsistent with the quasi- scientific (I.e., incorrect) underpinnings of their rulings?<br />
For that matter, to what degree is the mass return to fundamentalist or orthodox forms of religion (and a corresponding assertiveness in the public domain) largely a response to a loss of prior felt certainties and claims of &#8220;common&#8221; sense in the face of the ever-expanding role of expert knowledge in many domains of modern life?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Josh		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/26/anti-intellectual-populism-and-relgious-self-understanding/#comment-3641</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2011 02:53:29 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4169#comment-3641</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I would like a fuller description of the utility of each view and relative epistemological advantages and disadvantages. In as adversarial and charged an ideological climate as we seem to operate in, eschewing expert opinion could conceivably lead a person do to very intelligent things, like not assume most articles in NEJM are scientific or replicable. On the other hand, it could render a person, as you ably point out, denuded of facts and other perspectives and susceptible to any marketing guru clever enough to package a product to appeal to homespun skeptics. Still, in an environment where the autonomy of the sciences is not exactly sacrosanct and their politicization is kind of inevitable, you need to do some kind of discounting for all the crap. What&#039;s fascinating to me is the relative unsophistication of the homegrown experts, who have had a generation or two to perfect their craft, vis a vis academic experts. If politicization is anecdotaly so high, why is the payoff for shorting expert knowledge so low? Leads me to believe we are at some kind of false dichotomy.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I would like a fuller description of the utility of each view and relative epistemological advantages and disadvantages. In as adversarial and charged an ideological climate as we seem to operate in, eschewing expert opinion could conceivably lead a person do to very intelligent things, like not assume most articles in NEJM are scientific or replicable. On the other hand, it could render a person, as you ably point out, denuded of facts and other perspectives and susceptible to any marketing guru clever enough to package a product to appeal to homespun skeptics. Still, in an environment where the autonomy of the sciences is not exactly sacrosanct and their politicization is kind of inevitable, you need to do some kind of discounting for all the crap. What&#8217;s fascinating to me is the relative unsophistication of the homegrown experts, who have had a generation or two to perfect their craft, vis a vis academic experts. If politicization is anecdotaly so high, why is the payoff for shorting expert knowledge so low? Leads me to believe we are at some kind of false dichotomy.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Yossi		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/26/anti-intellectual-populism-and-relgious-self-understanding/#comment-3640</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Yossi]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2011 01:27:38 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4169#comment-3640</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Rav Avigdor Miller comes to mind.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rav Avigdor Miller comes to mind.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
