<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Authorship and the Individual	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/04/authorship-and-the-individual/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/04/authorship-and-the-individual/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2010 13:49:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Yonatan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/04/authorship-and-the-individual/#comment-378</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Yonatan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2010 13:49:54 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=480#comment-378</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[1) Upon reflection, I see in Halakhic writings that authorship is only attributed to a distinguishable or distinctive position. Everything else is seen as just quoting. 

Even if the author of a particular Halakhic work goes through the logic and sources and comes to the same conclusion, the position is generally attributed to the earlier author, with later authorities seen as jumping on the bandwagon.

So generally, authorship is generally attributed to the earliest source (e.g a Rashbah, even if 10 later sources adopt the same position).

2) Some recent moves in Brisker Lumdus strip all authorship from Halakhic authorities and (implicitly) argue that all legal positions are implicit in the original text/Halakha and that later writers are just making those positions manifest. E.g there are four ways to learn a Sugyah or understand a Halakha and then you find four Seforim who adopt those positions. 

They may be taking the position that within the Halakhic system authorship is not important because the system transcends individual authors.

3. As a side note, this is also Yohanan Petrovsky-Shtern criticism of Hasidei dekokhvaya’, “star-struck Hasidim,” that Gershon Scholem and his students viewed Jewish Intellectual History as the playing out of ideas implicit within Kabbalah.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>1) Upon reflection, I see in Halakhic writings that authorship is only attributed to a distinguishable or distinctive position. Everything else is seen as just quoting. </p>
<p>Even if the author of a particular Halakhic work goes through the logic and sources and comes to the same conclusion, the position is generally attributed to the earlier author, with later authorities seen as jumping on the bandwagon.</p>
<p>So generally, authorship is generally attributed to the earliest source (e.g a Rashbah, even if 10 later sources adopt the same position).</p>
<p>2) Some recent moves in Brisker Lumdus strip all authorship from Halakhic authorities and (implicitly) argue that all legal positions are implicit in the original text/Halakha and that later writers are just making those positions manifest. E.g there are four ways to learn a Sugyah or understand a Halakha and then you find four Seforim who adopt those positions. </p>
<p>They may be taking the position that within the Halakhic system authorship is not important because the system transcends individual authors.</p>
<p>3. As a side note, this is also Yohanan Petrovsky-Shtern criticism of Hasidei dekokhvaya’, “star-struck Hasidim,” that Gershon Scholem and his students viewed Jewish Intellectual History as the playing out of ideas implicit within Kabbalah.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Izgad		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/04/authorship-and-the-individual/#comment-372</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Izgad]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2010 00:28:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=480#comment-372</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&quot;This opens up the question of what rabbinic Jewish author were doing?&quot;

authors]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&#8220;This opens up the question of what rabbinic Jewish author were doing?&#8221;</p>
<p>authors</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Yonatan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/04/authorship-and-the-individual/#comment-368</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Yonatan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2010 16:12:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=480#comment-368</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Rabbi Dr. JB Soloveitchik, although not immersed in the philosophical background, did try to deal with issues of the role of the author in Halakhic works, in particular Chiddush &#038; Psak. 

His student Rabbi H. Schechter, (who I assume has not read any of these at all) does use these themes in his thought and argues that all writing including prophecy has an element of authorship. Interestingly enough, he has a very strong position for intellectual property.

Of course this does not address the larger issues. But at least JBS did try to bring these ideas into discussion, if not in a formal philosophical way.

When I read Dante, naively, I just assumed that the Cosmology was accurate, but his placing his enemies in various Hells was personal. They are examples. One could accept the Cosmology while rejecting Dante&#039;s personal vendettas.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rabbi Dr. JB Soloveitchik, although not immersed in the philosophical background, did try to deal with issues of the role of the author in Halakhic works, in particular Chiddush &amp; Psak. </p>
<p>His student Rabbi H. Schechter, (who I assume has not read any of these at all) does use these themes in his thought and argues that all writing including prophecy has an element of authorship. Interestingly enough, he has a very strong position for intellectual property.</p>
<p>Of course this does not address the larger issues. But at least JBS did try to bring these ideas into discussion, if not in a formal philosophical way.</p>
<p>When I read Dante, naively, I just assumed that the Cosmology was accurate, but his placing his enemies in various Hells was personal. They are examples. One could accept the Cosmology while rejecting Dante&#8217;s personal vendettas.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Arie Folger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/04/authorship-and-the-individual/#comment-356</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arie Folger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2010 08:05:40 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=480#comment-356</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Fascinating topic. I wonder whether this sheds any new [charitable] light on the pseudepigraphic kabbalistic works.  And still, despite my familiarity with the commonality of pseudepigraphic works in that genre, I still have trouble thinking outside the modern conceptual box of what authorship is supposed to be. I have gone so far as to tell authors of good halakhic treatises to IDENTIFY THEMSELVES AS AUTHORS rather than just write an address for where the book can be ordered. My argument being that it is not irrelevant who wrote it.

So, does this work shed new light on the genre of pseudepigraphic authorship? How the authors saw themselves in that process? How conscious they were that what they did might be perceived in a critical light? What was their theory of authorship? How would they claim they were mere transmitters when they included obvious chiddushim?

Just one nitpick, you remarked: &lt;em&gt;To consider the modern issues: Judaism never bought into the idea of the individual author and still has trouble with intellectual property of an author.&lt;/em&gt;

Intellectual property is not germane here. It is a legal concept, a created right, an artificial monopoly for the sake of promoting the arts and sciences, of promoting the publishing of creative works. But while it depends on the modern concept of authorship (one can&#039;t claim ownership if he isn&#039;t claiming to have meaningfully contributed), the reverse is not true. The modern concept of authorship does not require intellectual property legislation.

Thus, I don&#039;t see in Judaism&#039;s difficulty with intellectual property any reflection of what it thinks about authorship. Unlike many modern legislators, who bought Sonny Bono&#039;s arguments (think Sonny Bono Ammendment, which was prompted by Disney&#039;s fears of Mickey Mouse lapsing into the public domain - http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Copyright_Term_Extension_Act) line hook and sinker, Judaism recognizes that intellectual property is about creating an artificial monopoly to promote innovation, and hence resorted to the much more appropriate cherem for a limited time against whomever violated the legally sanctioned monopoly.

For our conversation, a different term would be more appropriate. Perhaps &quot;the authorial attribution?&quot;]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Fascinating topic. I wonder whether this sheds any new [charitable] light on the pseudepigraphic kabbalistic works.  And still, despite my familiarity with the commonality of pseudepigraphic works in that genre, I still have trouble thinking outside the modern conceptual box of what authorship is supposed to be. I have gone so far as to tell authors of good halakhic treatises to IDENTIFY THEMSELVES AS AUTHORS rather than just write an address for where the book can be ordered. My argument being that it is not irrelevant who wrote it.</p>
<p>So, does this work shed new light on the genre of pseudepigraphic authorship? How the authors saw themselves in that process? How conscious they were that what they did might be perceived in a critical light? What was their theory of authorship? How would they claim they were mere transmitters when they included obvious chiddushim?</p>
<p>Just one nitpick, you remarked: <em>To consider the modern issues: Judaism never bought into the idea of the individual author and still has trouble with intellectual property of an author.</em></p>
<p>Intellectual property is not germane here. It is a legal concept, a created right, an artificial monopoly for the sake of promoting the arts and sciences, of promoting the publishing of creative works. But while it depends on the modern concept of authorship (one can&#8217;t claim ownership if he isn&#8217;t claiming to have meaningfully contributed), the reverse is not true. The modern concept of authorship does not require intellectual property legislation.</p>
<p>Thus, I don&#8217;t see in Judaism&#8217;s difficulty with intellectual property any reflection of what it thinks about authorship. Unlike many modern legislators, who bought Sonny Bono&#8217;s arguments (think Sonny Bono Ammendment, which was prompted by Disney&#8217;s fears of Mickey Mouse lapsing into the public domain &#8211; <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Copyright_Term_Extension_Act" rel="nofollow ugc">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Copyright_Term_Extension_Act</a>) line hook and sinker, Judaism recognizes that intellectual property is about creating an artificial monopoly to promote innovation, and hence resorted to the much more appropriate cherem for a limited time against whomever violated the legally sanctioned monopoly.</p>
<p>For our conversation, a different term would be more appropriate. Perhaps &#8220;the authorial attribution?&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/04/authorship-and-the-individual/#comment-351</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2010 23:50:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=480#comment-351</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/04/authorship-and-the-individual/#comment-350&quot;&gt;Yosef&lt;/a&gt;.

Abulafia claims revelation and prophecy. On the Zohar, not everyone agrees with Melila- see Abrams below and his new article.  What the &quot;old-new words&quot; of the Zohar means can use better conceptualization.
You should definitely read Mary Carruthers and AJ Minnis carefully. And for the French see Roger Chartier.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/04/authorship-and-the-individual/#comment-350">Yosef</a>.</p>
<p>Abulafia claims revelation and prophecy. On the Zohar, not everyone agrees with Melila- see Abrams below and his new article.  What the &#8220;old-new words&#8221; of the Zohar means can use better conceptualization.<br />
You should definitely read Mary Carruthers and AJ Minnis carefully. And for the French see Roger Chartier.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Yosef		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/04/authorship-and-the-individual/#comment-350</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Yosef]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2010 23:43:38 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=480#comment-350</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[These questions fascinate me. I would certainly be more cautious than to claim that &quot;Kabbalistic works are seen as transmitting ancient knowledge or ascribed to older figures.&quot; Certainly not Abulafia, hes writing in a genre that blends manual and descriptions. And certainly not the zohar. It seems as though they are writing a text that is meant to awaken the reader (and the author?), to arouse one into affect and desire towards God, and its stylistic cannot be differentiated from this reader function. I certainly agree with you that these are such critical questions towards serious and insightful work in Medieval and Rabbinic studies.  
What is the up-to-date reading list in crit-theory on these issues? (After Foucault and Barthes)]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>These questions fascinate me. I would certainly be more cautious than to claim that &#8220;Kabbalistic works are seen as transmitting ancient knowledge or ascribed to older figures.&#8221; Certainly not Abulafia, hes writing in a genre that blends manual and descriptions. And certainly not the zohar. It seems as though they are writing a text that is meant to awaken the reader (and the author?), to arouse one into affect and desire towards God, and its stylistic cannot be differentiated from this reader function. I certainly agree with you that these are such critical questions towards serious and insightful work in Medieval and Rabbinic studies.<br />
What is the up-to-date reading list in crit-theory on these issues? (After Foucault and Barthes)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
