<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Interview with James Kugel round 3- The Kingly Sanctuary	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/07/13/interview-with-james-kugel-round-3-the-kingly-sanctuary/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/07/13/interview-with-james-kugel-round-3-the-kingly-sanctuary/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2014 21:07:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: David Rosenberg		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/07/13/interview-with-james-kugel-round-3-the-kingly-sanctuary/#comment-11106</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[David Rosenberg]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2014 21:07:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6593#comment-11106</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It&#039;s very good of Kugel to contextualize the modern scholarly enterprise, and to expand our awareness of the significance of revelation to Judaism (and thereby to all monotheistic religions).  His evocation of Jewish religious scholarship and biblical interpretation is splendid.

However, Kugel&#039;s viewpoint also allows for a glaring misunderstanding of Jewish history and culture.  Some of the Jewish thinkers he alludes to, whether Philo, Maimonides, and even Spinoza, were concerned about how the rest of humanity perceives Judaism (one could say the same for Second Isaiah).  No less than early Christianity and early source criticism, the popular opinion of the origin of Judaism and Israel remains one of a primitive people divinely inspired.  

What&#039;s wrong with that?  In that line of thinking, secular Israel and Jews today bear no cultural history that&#039;s worth anything special.  

Even the Israeli literary world, for the most part, feels no special connection with ancient Israel and the writers of Tanakh.  Kugel refers to these historical &quot;writers&quot;--and even Moses himself--as if they are only marginally relevant, which contributes to the notion that there&#039;s nothing special about Jewish historical culture, outside of its religion (even Iran&#039;s Supreme Leader might agree).  
The great art of the Torah and Tanakh, however, was created within a Hebraic culture at least as dynamic as the Elizabethan one that allowed for a Shakespeare, and it&#039;s our task today to clarify that for the sake of humanity and the well-being of modern Israel.  

It&#039;s still too easy to sweep the original writers under the rug and to suggest it doesn&#039;t matter, and anyway &quot;Who cares?&quot;  Yet the world at large still needs a larger context in which to understand the greatness of Jewish culture througout the centuries--but especially at its origin and in Solomonic Jerusalem.  

It&#039;s especially the task of literary writers today, Jewish ones, Israeli ones, to make that connection with their forebears in Jerusalem, yet they are not helped toward such awareness by Kugel&#039;s insights into tradition, valuable as they are.    
[David Rosenberg, author of &quot;A Literary Bible,&quot; &quot;The Book of J,&quot; etc.]]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It&#8217;s very good of Kugel to contextualize the modern scholarly enterprise, and to expand our awareness of the significance of revelation to Judaism (and thereby to all monotheistic religions).  His evocation of Jewish religious scholarship and biblical interpretation is splendid.</p>
<p>However, Kugel&#8217;s viewpoint also allows for a glaring misunderstanding of Jewish history and culture.  Some of the Jewish thinkers he alludes to, whether Philo, Maimonides, and even Spinoza, were concerned about how the rest of humanity perceives Judaism (one could say the same for Second Isaiah).  No less than early Christianity and early source criticism, the popular opinion of the origin of Judaism and Israel remains one of a primitive people divinely inspired.  </p>
<p>What&#8217;s wrong with that?  In that line of thinking, secular Israel and Jews today bear no cultural history that&#8217;s worth anything special.  </p>
<p>Even the Israeli literary world, for the most part, feels no special connection with ancient Israel and the writers of Tanakh.  Kugel refers to these historical &#8220;writers&#8221;&#8211;and even Moses himself&#8211;as if they are only marginally relevant, which contributes to the notion that there&#8217;s nothing special about Jewish historical culture, outside of its religion (even Iran&#8217;s Supreme Leader might agree).<br />
The great art of the Torah and Tanakh, however, was created within a Hebraic culture at least as dynamic as the Elizabethan one that allowed for a Shakespeare, and it&#8217;s our task today to clarify that for the sake of humanity and the well-being of modern Israel.  </p>
<p>It&#8217;s still too easy to sweep the original writers under the rug and to suggest it doesn&#8217;t matter, and anyway &#8220;Who cares?&#8221;  Yet the world at large still needs a larger context in which to understand the greatness of Jewish culture througout the centuries&#8211;but especially at its origin and in Solomonic Jerusalem.  </p>
<p>It&#8217;s especially the task of literary writers today, Jewish ones, Israeli ones, to make that connection with their forebears in Jerusalem, yet they are not helped toward such awareness by Kugel&#8217;s insights into tradition, valuable as they are.<br />
[David Rosenberg, author of &#8220;A Literary Bible,&#8221; &#8220;The Book of J,&#8221; etc.]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Aaron Koller		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/07/13/interview-with-james-kugel-round-3-the-kingly-sanctuary/#comment-11105</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Aaron Koller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2014 20:59:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6593#comment-11105</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I think, like your metaphor of the professor of philosophy with regard to atheism, that Prof. Kugel seems to appreciate (b) and (c), study them, teach them, but not espouse them. But perhaps you&#039;re right. Anyway, I&#039;m not sure the &quot;synthesis&quot; project is going all that well overall.....]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think, like your metaphor of the professor of philosophy with regard to atheism, that Prof. Kugel seems to appreciate (b) and (c), study them, teach them, but not espouse them. But perhaps you&#8217;re right. Anyway, I&#8217;m not sure the &#8220;synthesis&#8221; project is going all that well overall&#8230;..</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/07/13/interview-with-james-kugel-round-3-the-kingly-sanctuary/#comment-11104</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2014 20:55:52 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6593#comment-11104</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/07/13/interview-with-james-kugel-round-3-the-kingly-sanctuary/#comment-11103&quot;&gt;Aaron Koller&lt;/a&gt;.

He does not discard (b) and (c). He actually spends most of his academic life and thought there. He just keeps them disconnected. Many in the community have various forms of bifurcation or wearing two hats.They even feel comfortable doing that like changing out of one&#039;s business suit into jeans or sweats when getting home.  He wants to be honest to two forms of knowledge that are non-commensurate.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/07/13/interview-with-james-kugel-round-3-the-kingly-sanctuary/#comment-11103">Aaron Koller</a>.</p>
<p>He does not discard (b) and (c). He actually spends most of his academic life and thought there. He just keeps them disconnected. Many in the community have various forms of bifurcation or wearing two hats.They even feel comfortable doing that like changing out of one&#8217;s business suit into jeans or sweats when getting home.  He wants to be honest to two forms of knowledge that are non-commensurate.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Aaron Koller		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/07/13/interview-with-james-kugel-round-3-the-kingly-sanctuary/#comment-11103</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Aaron Koller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2014 20:48:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6593#comment-11103</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In 140 characters or less.... It has to start with (1) What we are trying to synthesize, and (2) Why bother. To sketch the direction at least, I assume the answer to (1) is something like: (a) the core of traditional Jewish religion, although there are hierarchies and value judgments to be made about what is &quot;core&quot;, and (b) the knowledge and (c) the fundamental values of the modern world. The answer to (2), I think, is &quot;because we start with the assumption that these are all not just heuristically valuable, but correct.&quot; Given that, there is no option other than to synthesize. Prof. Kugel is willing to discard all of (b), and - it seems - (c) as well. I don&#039;t think most modern people would follow him there.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In 140 characters or less&#8230;. It has to start with (1) What we are trying to synthesize, and (2) Why bother. To sketch the direction at least, I assume the answer to (1) is something like: (a) the core of traditional Jewish religion, although there are hierarchies and value judgments to be made about what is &#8220;core&#8221;, and (b) the knowledge and (c) the fundamental values of the modern world. The answer to (2), I think, is &#8220;because we start with the assumption that these are all not just heuristically valuable, but correct.&#8221; Given that, there is no option other than to synthesize. Prof. Kugel is willing to discard all of (b), and &#8211; it seems &#8211; (c) as well. I don&#8217;t think most modern people would follow him there.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Madel		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/07/13/interview-with-james-kugel-round-3-the-kingly-sanctuary/#comment-11102</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Madel]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2014 19:40:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6593#comment-11102</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/07/13/interview-with-james-kugel-round-3-the-kingly-sanctuary/#comment-11071&quot;&gt;Alan Brill&lt;/a&gt;.

The interview and the book reminded me of a Israeli novel I recently read on much of the substance of both.  You might find HAAZINU (LISTEN UP) by Yerachmiel ben-Yishye, published (2011) by Gefen Publishing House of Jerusalem, as enjoyable as I did.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/07/13/interview-with-james-kugel-round-3-the-kingly-sanctuary/#comment-11071">Alan Brill</a>.</p>
<p>The interview and the book reminded me of a Israeli novel I recently read on much of the substance of both.  You might find HAAZINU (LISTEN UP) by Yerachmiel ben-Yishye, published (2011) by Gefen Publishing House of Jerusalem, as enjoyable as I did.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/07/13/interview-with-james-kugel-round-3-the-kingly-sanctuary/#comment-11100</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2014 19:17:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6593#comment-11100</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Prof Koller,

What is your vision of synthesis? What is a  coherent Modern Orthodox Judaism?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Prof Koller,</p>
<p>What is your vision of synthesis? What is a  coherent Modern Orthodox Judaism?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Aaron Koller		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/07/13/interview-with-james-kugel-round-3-the-kingly-sanctuary/#comment-11098</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Aaron Koller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2014 18:29:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6593#comment-11098</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The intended audience consists of people who have read Hume, Hobbs, and Kant - as well as the millions more who live in the world shaped by their thought. If these people are told that they must choose between the findings of modern, rationalist, biblical scholarship, and an approach to the Torah that finds “its definitive interpretation in Talmud and midrash” – that these two are entirely incompatible and therefore one must choose – I am quite sure I know which they will choose. It may be that Prof. Kugel is correct, and that this portends the failure of any attempt at synthesis – and therefore the end of any coherent Modern Orthodox Judaism. But he should not think that he will ease people’s minds by telling them that the Talmud already said what there was to be said. The contributors to TheTorah.com (of which I am one) have tried to show that there are ways of synthesizing modern knowledge with traditional faith.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The intended audience consists of people who have read Hume, Hobbs, and Kant &#8211; as well as the millions more who live in the world shaped by their thought. If these people are told that they must choose between the findings of modern, rationalist, biblical scholarship, and an approach to the Torah that finds “its definitive interpretation in Talmud and midrash” – that these two are entirely incompatible and therefore one must choose – I am quite sure I know which they will choose. It may be that Prof. Kugel is correct, and that this portends the failure of any attempt at synthesis – and therefore the end of any coherent Modern Orthodox Judaism. But he should not think that he will ease people’s minds by telling them that the Talmud already said what there was to be said. The contributors to TheTorah.com (of which I am one) have tried to show that there are ways of synthesizing modern knowledge with traditional faith.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Rabbi Jonathan Gerard		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/07/13/interview-with-james-kugel-round-3-the-kingly-sanctuary/#comment-11097</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rabbi Jonathan Gerard]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2014 17:56:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6593#comment-11097</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The ancients understood many human processes which today we understand as internal (falling in love, being inspired...) as external--being struck by cupid&#039;s arrow, the spirit of God dwelling upon him, etc. 
When we speak of revelation--though the torah uses this language of externality (&quot;God said,,,&quot;) we can best understand what that Hebrew (va-y&#039;daber adonai el mosheh) meant to the ancient writer with our more accurate translation, &quot;Moses experienced God...&quot;
We must assume that how we function as human beings has not changed from biblical days until today--otherwise, there is no hope of recovering what the biblical writer meant or what Israelites experienced. What HAS changed is language, and how we use it to describe experience. 
Revelation, therefore, which is described in the Tanach as an external visitation of God to a prophet, can best be understood today as anyone&#039;s EXPERIENCE of God--that is, of anyone&#039;s experience of truth. This is Judaism&#039;s traditional definition of &quot;torah min ha-shamayim&quot;--Torah from God, revelation.
We tend to think, as the ancients did, of a God who is infinite OUT THERE. But it is just as reasonable to think of God as infinite WITHIN--within the soul, our psyche, that which makes us human, unique, sacred. 
And now we can understand why so many different &quot;voices&quot; in the Bible. A person under siege might experience God as desiring the genocide of Canaanites. A person living under very different circumstances might well experience God as promising a day when Egypt will be one with Israel and all will sit under their vines and their fig trees and no one will be afraid. Both experiences of &quot;God&quot; reflect a truth experienced by the writer. No one ever knows with certainty what &quot;God&quot; really thinks.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The ancients understood many human processes which today we understand as internal (falling in love, being inspired&#8230;) as external&#8211;being struck by cupid&#8217;s arrow, the spirit of God dwelling upon him, etc.<br />
When we speak of revelation&#8211;though the torah uses this language of externality (&#8220;God said,,,&#8221;) we can best understand what that Hebrew (va-y&#8217;daber adonai el mosheh) meant to the ancient writer with our more accurate translation, &#8220;Moses experienced God&#8230;&#8221;<br />
We must assume that how we function as human beings has not changed from biblical days until today&#8211;otherwise, there is no hope of recovering what the biblical writer meant or what Israelites experienced. What HAS changed is language, and how we use it to describe experience.<br />
Revelation, therefore, which is described in the Tanach as an external visitation of God to a prophet, can best be understood today as anyone&#8217;s EXPERIENCE of God&#8211;that is, of anyone&#8217;s experience of truth. This is Judaism&#8217;s traditional definition of &#8220;torah min ha-shamayim&#8221;&#8211;Torah from God, revelation.<br />
We tend to think, as the ancients did, of a God who is infinite OUT THERE. But it is just as reasonable to think of God as infinite WITHIN&#8211;within the soul, our psyche, that which makes us human, unique, sacred.<br />
And now we can understand why so many different &#8220;voices&#8221; in the Bible. A person under siege might experience God as desiring the genocide of Canaanites. A person living under very different circumstances might well experience God as promising a day when Egypt will be one with Israel and all will sit under their vines and their fig trees and no one will be afraid. Both experiences of &#8220;God&#8221; reflect a truth experienced by the writer. No one ever knows with certainty what &#8220;God&#8221; really thinks.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Joshua Berman		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/07/13/interview-with-james-kugel-round-3-the-kingly-sanctuary/#comment-11082</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joshua Berman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2014 13:45:03 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6593#comment-11082</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Deut 11:4 and 13:1 both warn, not to add or detract from the word of God.  The phrase is oft-found in ancient Near Eastern literature, and always refers to textual integrity - altering the words of the text (as opposed to &quot;changing norms of practice&quot;). Well-versed ancient readers and writers knew exactly what this meant. I wonder how that all squares with the scribal exegetical activity that Prof. Kugel describes.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Deut 11:4 and 13:1 both warn, not to add or detract from the word of God.  The phrase is oft-found in ancient Near Eastern literature, and always refers to textual integrity &#8211; altering the words of the text (as opposed to &#8220;changing norms of practice&#8221;). Well-versed ancient readers and writers knew exactly what this meant. I wonder how that all squares with the scribal exegetical activity that Prof. Kugel describes.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Joebug		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/07/13/interview-with-james-kugel-round-3-the-kingly-sanctuary/#comment-11076</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joebug]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 13 Jul 2014 20:53:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6593#comment-11076</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[By all means revelation cannot be proved and we cannot know what it really might mean for an infinite being to communicate with man, so in a strict logical sense we cannot say whether Torah is revelation or not.
But surely the argument is that if a text is so full of historical and scientific and indeed logical holes, then believing this text (and the be&#039;al pe wraparound text which predicates on these deficiencies in the end) to be the revelation of God, as opposed to say the Koran or the Mormon golden tablets or the Upanishads or even a sublime novel or artwork, is an untenable belief. 
Now Prof Kugel and many others including myself might want to hold on such beliefs because, as I heard an English vicar on the radio say recently, it&#039;s still better to believe in religion and a grander view of humanity even if the evidence seems to be against it. Fine. But to pretend that moderns can just ignore what science in its broad sense tells us about the Bible, and just split it off from the traditional Jewish interpretation, is also untenable. Surely Hume and Kant tell us that much about how we can come to knowledge.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By all means revelation cannot be proved and we cannot know what it really might mean for an infinite being to communicate with man, so in a strict logical sense we cannot say whether Torah is revelation or not.<br />
But surely the argument is that if a text is so full of historical and scientific and indeed logical holes, then believing this text (and the be&#8217;al pe wraparound text which predicates on these deficiencies in the end) to be the revelation of God, as opposed to say the Koran or the Mormon golden tablets or the Upanishads or even a sublime novel or artwork, is an untenable belief.<br />
Now Prof Kugel and many others including myself might want to hold on such beliefs because, as I heard an English vicar on the radio say recently, it&#8217;s still better to believe in religion and a grander view of humanity even if the evidence seems to be against it. Fine. But to pretend that moderns can just ignore what science in its broad sense tells us about the Bible, and just split it off from the traditional Jewish interpretation, is also untenable. Surely Hume and Kant tell us that much about how we can come to knowledge.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/07/13/interview-with-james-kugel-round-3-the-kingly-sanctuary/#comment-11071</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 13 Jul 2014 15:34:11 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6593#comment-11071</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Reminder to my new readers this is an academic blog, and to please read the rules for comments before posting. Also I need a real email address that matches your IP.
There is more in his book about his views of the religious life, prayer, and obedience. Go read the book ]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Reminder to my new readers this is an academic blog, and to please read the rules for comments before posting. Also I need a real email address that matches your IP.<br />
There is more in his book about his views of the religious life, prayer, and obedience. Go read the book </p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
