<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Mei HaShiloah on Korach	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/mei-hashiloah-on-korach/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/mei-hashiloah-on-korach/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2011 13:35:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Eric		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/mei-hashiloah-on-korach/#comment-3325</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eric]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2011 13:35:32 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3794#comment-3325</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Sounds like a derivative of (scientific?) determinism.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sounds like a derivative of (scientific?) determinism.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: SSecunda		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/mei-hashiloah-on-korach/#comment-3295</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[SSecunda]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 26 Jun 2011 07:13:26 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3794#comment-3295</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I have a fond memory of you teaching this to my ninth grade Maimonides class some 18 years ago. The way I recall you taught it then - filtered through my hazy ninth grade understanding and refracted through retrospection - was that the Ishbitzer was engaged in a wider project to rehabilitate the bad guys of the Good Book, and at the same time to completely turn our perception of who is good and who is bad on its head.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have a fond memory of you teaching this to my ninth grade Maimonides class some 18 years ago. The way I recall you taught it then &#8211; filtered through my hazy ninth grade understanding and refracted through retrospection &#8211; was that the Ishbitzer was engaged in a wider project to rehabilitate the bad guys of the Good Book, and at the same time to completely turn our perception of who is good and who is bad on its head.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: steve mcqueen		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/mei-hashiloah-on-korach/#comment-3286</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[steve mcqueen]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2011 11:08:31 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3794#comment-3286</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I studied this sefer last year, it is not simple.  In addition to trying to fathom what he was meaning I also wondered about who is audience was at the time.  One of the keys I used was the realisation that his teachings were so precious to his student that the student carried around fragments for years and after the Rebbe&#039;s death made the effort to collect fragments from others to produce the book.  (I am trying to recall what is said in the intro as to how the sefer was put together).  So his teachings made a major major impact on the students, which means they must be saying far more than a simple commentary on current events in the Jewish world would reveal.   The only thing I can think of that would have such an impact would be if the teachings were a highly effective tool in avodat Hashem, and working backwards from that position often allowed me to get a little it of what was going on.

Another point - he often says how every Jew has a fixed position in spirituality (if i have understood this correctly) so the reference to hierarchy must refer to this wider theme.  IIRC, his view of the hierarchy very much goes against modern ideas of how anyone can make anything of themselves.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I studied this sefer last year, it is not simple.  In addition to trying to fathom what he was meaning I also wondered about who is audience was at the time.  One of the keys I used was the realisation that his teachings were so precious to his student that the student carried around fragments for years and after the Rebbe&#8217;s death made the effort to collect fragments from others to produce the book.  (I am trying to recall what is said in the intro as to how the sefer was put together).  So his teachings made a major major impact on the students, which means they must be saying far more than a simple commentary on current events in the Jewish world would reveal.   The only thing I can think of that would have such an impact would be if the teachings were a highly effective tool in avodat Hashem, and working backwards from that position often allowed me to get a little it of what was going on.</p>
<p>Another point &#8211; he often says how every Jew has a fixed position in spirituality (if i have understood this correctly) so the reference to hierarchy must refer to this wider theme.  IIRC, his view of the hierarchy very much goes against modern ideas of how anyone can make anything of themselves.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
