<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Authentic Fakes Religion and American Popular Culture David Chidester	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/15/authentic-fakes-religion-and-american-popular-culture-david-chidester/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/15/authentic-fakes-religion-and-american-popular-culture-david-chidester/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2011 21:19:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/15/authentic-fakes-religion-and-american-popular-culture-david-chidester/#comment-2799</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2011 21:19:20 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3259#comment-2799</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The book blurb/intro sounds a bit incoherent to me.

In any event, &quot;authenticity&quot;  is clearly a normative concept implying a judgment about the worth of something. Unfortunately it is usually thrown around as a self-explanatory descriptive term. Once you think about it there is simply no description of  a social practice or artifact that marks it as authentic without recourse to some other evaluative criteria. And in most cases if you are self-consciously asking whether something that you are doing is &quot;authentic&quot; you are past the point of answering the question in the affirmative.

While it is descriptively empty, as far as I can tell, a&quot;authenticity&quot; appeals to people as a shortcut to achieving different varieties of transcendence. But the kind of transcendence that can be bought or achieved via the appropriation of collective memory is rather illusory.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The book blurb/intro sounds a bit incoherent to me.</p>
<p>In any event, &#8220;authenticity&#8221;  is clearly a normative concept implying a judgment about the worth of something. Unfortunately it is usually thrown around as a self-explanatory descriptive term. Once you think about it there is simply no description of  a social practice or artifact that marks it as authentic without recourse to some other evaluative criteria. And in most cases if you are self-consciously asking whether something that you are doing is &#8220;authentic&#8221; you are past the point of answering the question in the affirmative.</p>
<p>While it is descriptively empty, as far as I can tell, a&#8221;authenticity&#8221; appeals to people as a shortcut to achieving different varieties of transcendence. But the kind of transcendence that can be bought or achieved via the appropriation of collective memory is rather illusory.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
