<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: An Interview with Michah Gottlieb: Moses Mendelssohn as a Guide for Orthodoxy	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/18/an-interview-with-michah-gottlieb-moses-mendelssohn-as-a-guide-for-orthodoxy/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/18/an-interview-with-michah-gottlieb-moses-mendelssohn-as-a-guide-for-orthodoxy/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2015 11:26:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Elisheva Barre		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/18/an-interview-with-michah-gottlieb-moses-mendelssohn-as-a-guide-for-orthodoxy/#comment-13677</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Elisheva Barre]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2015 11:26:11 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4035#comment-13677</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[@ Jon Baker, I also thought that R. Yossef Kappach took into consideration the villification of Mandelson by the Haredim, but considering that Mendelshon himself signed R’ Moshe Dessauer, the question is rather how he signed his commentaty to the &quot;Malechet haHigayon&quot; (as R. K. has it, and not Milot as other translations). 
In any case, Rabbi Kappach suffered enough from the attacks of the Haredim on his father, grand&#039;father and himself to warrant prudence!]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>@ Jon Baker, I also thought that R. Yossef Kappach took into consideration the villification of Mandelson by the Haredim, but considering that Mendelshon himself signed R’ Moshe Dessauer, the question is rather how he signed his commentaty to the &#8220;Malechet haHigayon&#8221; (as R. K. has it, and not Milot as other translations).<br />
In any case, Rabbi Kappach suffered enough from the attacks of the Haredim on his father, grand&#8217;father and himself to warrant prudence!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: zjb		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/18/an-interview-with-michah-gottlieb-moses-mendelssohn-as-a-guide-for-orthodoxy/#comment-3556</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[zjb]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2011 01:03:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4035#comment-3556</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/18/an-interview-with-michah-gottlieb-moses-mendelssohn-as-a-guide-for-orthodoxy/#comment-3545&quot;&gt;S.&lt;/a&gt;.

Dear S:

Re: &quot;post-halakhic,&quot; I&#039;d put it this way, I guess. By &quot;post&quot; I don&#039;t mean &quot;anti&quot; or &quot;non.&quot; Consider how the great postmodern Lyotard makes so much hay out Barnett Newmann, a great modernist (abstract expressionist) painter. Or Derrida and Mallarme. In the same way that all the really good post-moderns were &quot;super modern&quot; and &quot;post,&quot; I&#039;d say the same about Mendelssohn, and I&#039;d probably say the same about Rosenzweig (Following this logic, Buber, of course was not post-halakhic). 

Clearly, Mendelssohn was an observant, &quot;halakhic&quot; Jew. But I think he was willing to push halakhah in ways that pushed the boundaries of what might have been *considered* and what might still in some cricles be considered more &quot;traditionalist&quot; forms of halakhic Judaism. Take for instance the flexibility expressed by him re: the controversy with Emden about Jewish burial, i.e. his willingness to bend the halakhah in the interest of the civil state. Or how his interest in &quot;law&quot; had less to do with law (psak) than with the poetry of ceremonial performance (in my opinion). Or his rejection of civic Jewish law after the Hurban. Or his rejection of coercion and coercive religious authority (especially his rejection of the herem). Or his skepticism re: appeals to the authority of miracle as a foundation for Jewish law. Or the easy concourse with gentiles. Or the deep, deep immersion in classical and German culture.

If you prefer, perhaps &quot;meta-halakhic&quot; is the better term, as it is more current in recent discussions. And perhaps &quot;post-traditional&quot; would also be a better term. I certainly did not mean the term &quot;post-halakhic&quot; to put anyone&#039;s teeth on edge since I don&#039;t see a radical negation in it usage.

I hope this makes sense to you.
Best,  -- zjb]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/18/an-interview-with-michah-gottlieb-moses-mendelssohn-as-a-guide-for-orthodoxy/#comment-3545">S.</a>.</p>
<p>Dear S:</p>
<p>Re: &#8220;post-halakhic,&#8221; I&#8217;d put it this way, I guess. By &#8220;post&#8221; I don&#8217;t mean &#8220;anti&#8221; or &#8220;non.&#8221; Consider how the great postmodern Lyotard makes so much hay out Barnett Newmann, a great modernist (abstract expressionist) painter. Or Derrida and Mallarme. In the same way that all the really good post-moderns were &#8220;super modern&#8221; and &#8220;post,&#8221; I&#8217;d say the same about Mendelssohn, and I&#8217;d probably say the same about Rosenzweig (Following this logic, Buber, of course was not post-halakhic). </p>
<p>Clearly, Mendelssohn was an observant, &#8220;halakhic&#8221; Jew. But I think he was willing to push halakhah in ways that pushed the boundaries of what might have been *considered* and what might still in some cricles be considered more &#8220;traditionalist&#8221; forms of halakhic Judaism. Take for instance the flexibility expressed by him re: the controversy with Emden about Jewish burial, i.e. his willingness to bend the halakhah in the interest of the civil state. Or how his interest in &#8220;law&#8221; had less to do with law (psak) than with the poetry of ceremonial performance (in my opinion). Or his rejection of civic Jewish law after the Hurban. Or his rejection of coercion and coercive religious authority (especially his rejection of the herem). Or his skepticism re: appeals to the authority of miracle as a foundation for Jewish law. Or the easy concourse with gentiles. Or the deep, deep immersion in classical and German culture.</p>
<p>If you prefer, perhaps &#8220;meta-halakhic&#8221; is the better term, as it is more current in recent discussions. And perhaps &#8220;post-traditional&#8221; would also be a better term. I certainly did not mean the term &#8220;post-halakhic&#8221; to put anyone&#8217;s teeth on edge since I don&#8217;t see a radical negation in it usage.</p>
<p>I hope this makes sense to you.<br />
Best,  &#8212; zjb</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Jon Baker		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/18/an-interview-with-michah-gottlieb-moses-mendelssohn-as-a-guide-for-orthodoxy/#comment-3547</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jon Baker]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2011 22:08:20 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4035#comment-3547</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[If Mendelssohn was regarded as a third link in &quot;From Moshe to Moshe&quot; in his own lifetime, it must be in part because he viewed himself as such a link.  His first published work was a commentary on Maimonides&#039; first work, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hebrewbooks.org/33752&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Milot haHigayon&lt;/a&gt;.  In R Kapach&#039;s edition, it&#039;s characterized as the best commentary available, although RK can&#039;t bring himself to alienate his Charedi readers by actually saying &quot;Mendelssohn&quot; - he calls him RM&quot;D, which, after a bit, I realized must be R&#039; Moshe Dessauer, or Mendelssohn.

Some editions of the Biur call him &lt;a href=&quot;http://thanbook.blogspot.com/2007/07/not-necessarily-r-akiva-eger.html&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Rambeman&lt;/a&gt; - R&#039; Moshe ben Menachem Mendel - another link to Rambam.

One calumny I often see online, starting with &lt;a href=&quot;http://thanbook.blogspot.com/2009/12/mendelssohn-in-lubavitch-eyes.html&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;the previous Lubavitcher rebbe&lt;/a&gt;, is attributing to him the statement/idea, &quot;Be a Jew in the home and a man in the street.&quot;  Which just goes to show that people don&#039;t know much about RM&quot;D - there&#039;s a widely-quoted letter where he makes a point about refusing to drink non-Jewish wine in the home of a nobleman.  Really that statement is due to YL Gordon, in the middle 19th century, and Stanislawski sees it as a call for TIDE, not for abandonment of public displays of Jewishness.

BTW, one of Sorkin&#039;s essay collections got me interested in Mendelssohn and his circle.  I now have a number of books by Mendelssohn and particularly Wessely, who wrote more in Hebrew than in German - I don&#039;t read German.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If Mendelssohn was regarded as a third link in &#8220;From Moshe to Moshe&#8221; in his own lifetime, it must be in part because he viewed himself as such a link.  His first published work was a commentary on Maimonides&#8217; first work, the <a href="http://www.hebrewbooks.org/33752" rel="nofollow">Milot haHigayon</a>.  In R Kapach&#8217;s edition, it&#8217;s characterized as the best commentary available, although RK can&#8217;t bring himself to alienate his Charedi readers by actually saying &#8220;Mendelssohn&#8221; &#8211; he calls him RM&#8221;D, which, after a bit, I realized must be R&#8217; Moshe Dessauer, or Mendelssohn.</p>
<p>Some editions of the Biur call him <a href="http://thanbook.blogspot.com/2007/07/not-necessarily-r-akiva-eger.html" rel="nofollow">Rambeman</a> &#8211; R&#8217; Moshe ben Menachem Mendel &#8211; another link to Rambam.</p>
<p>One calumny I often see online, starting with <a href="http://thanbook.blogspot.com/2009/12/mendelssohn-in-lubavitch-eyes.html" rel="nofollow">the previous Lubavitcher rebbe</a>, is attributing to him the statement/idea, &#8220;Be a Jew in the home and a man in the street.&#8221;  Which just goes to show that people don&#8217;t know much about RM&#8221;D &#8211; there&#8217;s a widely-quoted letter where he makes a point about refusing to drink non-Jewish wine in the home of a nobleman.  Really that statement is due to YL Gordon, in the middle 19th century, and Stanislawski sees it as a call for TIDE, not for abandonment of public displays of Jewishness.</p>
<p>BTW, one of Sorkin&#8217;s essay collections got me interested in Mendelssohn and his circle.  I now have a number of books by Mendelssohn and particularly Wessely, who wrote more in Hebrew than in German &#8211; I don&#8217;t read German.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: S.		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/18/an-interview-with-michah-gottlieb-moses-mendelssohn-as-a-guide-for-orthodoxy/#comment-3545</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[S.]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2011 17:50:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4035#comment-3545</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[zjb, how does revealed legislation (and observance) correspond with post-halakhic, even in the full range of his life and thought?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>zjb, how does revealed legislation (and observance) correspond with post-halakhic, even in the full range of his life and thought?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: zjb		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/18/an-interview-with-michah-gottlieb-moses-mendelssohn-as-a-guide-for-orthodoxy/#comment-3544</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[zjb]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2011 16:53:11 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4035#comment-3544</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Loved the interview with Michah and can&#039;t wait to read the book(s). I wonder thought what kind of orthodoxy Mendelssohn would model. I&#039;m not sure that &quot;traditionalist&quot; is the right word with which to describe him. While clearly loyal to the world of tradition in which his life and thought are profoundly and genuinely steeped, I&#039;d rather call him post-traditional and post-halakhic, given the full range of his life and thought. 

What strikes me about Mendelssohn for today is the rejection of ecclesiastical authority, and the fluid freedom and poetry and gentle heart with which he conceived Jewish life. As Michah notes, the way he balanced everything (secularism and religion, particularism and universalism, etc etc). By &quot;law,&quot; Mendellsohn clearly meant something that Strauss did not (&quot;obedience&quot;). 

For Reb Yudel, don&#039;t bother with the magnificent Altmann biography. It contains way too much information and I can&#039;t help but think it would bore you to tears. I&#039;d go straight to the second part of Jerusualem and its presentation of &quot;the cermonial law&quot; as &quot;living script&quot; (or what we today might call &quot;performance&quot;); and also the play of Psalms and his dramatic reading (presented in dialogue form) of the Golden Calf, the 13 attributes and the kindness of a forgiving God.
 
The question I guess I would ask is whether there is an *institutional*  place for this kind of liberalism in the firmament of modern orthodox Judaism.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Loved the interview with Michah and can&#8217;t wait to read the book(s). I wonder thought what kind of orthodoxy Mendelssohn would model. I&#8217;m not sure that &#8220;traditionalist&#8221; is the right word with which to describe him. While clearly loyal to the world of tradition in which his life and thought are profoundly and genuinely steeped, I&#8217;d rather call him post-traditional and post-halakhic, given the full range of his life and thought. </p>
<p>What strikes me about Mendelssohn for today is the rejection of ecclesiastical authority, and the fluid freedom and poetry and gentle heart with which he conceived Jewish life. As Michah notes, the way he balanced everything (secularism and religion, particularism and universalism, etc etc). By &#8220;law,&#8221; Mendellsohn clearly meant something that Strauss did not (&#8220;obedience&#8221;). </p>
<p>For Reb Yudel, don&#8217;t bother with the magnificent Altmann biography. It contains way too much information and I can&#8217;t help but think it would bore you to tears. I&#8217;d go straight to the second part of Jerusualem and its presentation of &#8220;the cermonial law&#8221; as &#8220;living script&#8221; (or what we today might call &#8220;performance&#8221;); and also the play of Psalms and his dramatic reading (presented in dialogue form) of the Golden Calf, the 13 attributes and the kindness of a forgiving God.</p>
<p>The question I guess I would ask is whether there is an *institutional*  place for this kind of liberalism in the firmament of modern orthodox Judaism.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: S.		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/18/an-interview-with-michah-gottlieb-moses-mendelssohn-as-a-guide-for-orthodoxy/#comment-3543</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[S.]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2011 15:22:46 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4035#comment-3543</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&#062;I think Gotlieb missed the reason Mendelssohn’s name is still villified by Haredim: The need for every idea to have a singular originator to whom it can be attributed. From the standpoint of history of ideas, it’s obviously ridiculous, but that’s the logic of the Mishna.

It&#039;s not just the Haredim. Until Smolenskin the Maskilim almost always were unstinting in their praise of Mendelssohn, and they too saw him as a singular originator. Zionists saw Ben Yehuda as the founder of modern Hebrew, etc.

As it happens, past the popular level of the masses, the Haredim &quot;remember&quot; Mendelssohn&#039;s contemporaries too and do not lack for discussions of them. Wessely, Satanow - they are all vilified in countless journals and books (except of course when selected maskilim are being rehabilitated for certain purposes).]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&gt;I think Gotlieb missed the reason Mendelssohn’s name is still villified by Haredim: The need for every idea to have a singular originator to whom it can be attributed. From the standpoint of history of ideas, it’s obviously ridiculous, but that’s the logic of the Mishna.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s not just the Haredim. Until Smolenskin the Maskilim almost always were unstinting in their praise of Mendelssohn, and they too saw him as a singular originator. Zionists saw Ben Yehuda as the founder of modern Hebrew, etc.</p>
<p>As it happens, past the popular level of the masses, the Haredim &#8220;remember&#8221; Mendelssohn&#8217;s contemporaries too and do not lack for discussions of them. Wessely, Satanow &#8211; they are all vilified in countless journals and books (except of course when selected maskilim are being rehabilitated for certain purposes).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Reb Yudel		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/18/an-interview-with-michah-gottlieb-moses-mendelssohn-as-a-guide-for-orthodoxy/#comment-3539</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Reb Yudel]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2011 07:18:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4035#comment-3539</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Feiner needs more friends: The only Amazon review of his book is from a Coulter-loving, Pat Buchanan follower who thinks the Englightenment -- and no doubt Vatican II -- is a bad idea.

I think Gotlieb missed the reason Mendelssohn&#039;s name is still villified by Haredim: The need for every idea to have a singular originator to whom it can be attributed. From the standpoint of history of ideas, it&#039;s obviously ridiculous, but that&#039;s the logic of the Mishna.

For those of us who don&#039;t have time to read the biography (four copies of which are in the Teaneck library system), could you share some excerpts of how Mendelssohn is important for today? That is to say, examples of Mendelssohn in action?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Feiner needs more friends: The only Amazon review of his book is from a Coulter-loving, Pat Buchanan follower who thinks the Englightenment &#8212; and no doubt Vatican II &#8212; is a bad idea.</p>
<p>I think Gotlieb missed the reason Mendelssohn&#8217;s name is still villified by Haredim: The need for every idea to have a singular originator to whom it can be attributed. From the standpoint of history of ideas, it&#8217;s obviously ridiculous, but that&#8217;s the logic of the Mishna.</p>
<p>For those of us who don&#8217;t have time to read the biography (four copies of which are in the Teaneck library system), could you share some excerpts of how Mendelssohn is important for today? That is to say, examples of Mendelssohn in action?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
