<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: “Contending Modernities: Catholic, Muslim, Secular.”	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/11/18/%e2%80%9ccontending-modernities-catholic-muslim-secular-%e2%80%9d/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/11/18/%e2%80%9ccontending-modernities-catholic-muslim-secular-%e2%80%9d/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2010 21:14:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/11/18/%e2%80%9ccontending-modernities-catholic-muslim-secular-%e2%80%9d/#comment-1997</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2010 21:14:32 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2412#comment-1997</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[EJ-
I think you put your finger on it. Very sharp. As I was typing, I was wondering, hmm this sounds a bit Marxist of the Ernesto Laclau or Talal Asad variety, and a little Muslim liberation theology thrown in. This is a similar group to the Fundamentalist Project, they noticed a change but got the interpretation completely wrong. If you never read Peter Berger&#039;s critique of the project, you should. We trust Christian Smith and Robert Wuthnow over the Fundamentalist Project. People are Evangelical, Centrist Orthodox or Engaged Yeshivsh not Fundamentalist. I get the same sense here. They do have their finger on a social change and there are things to learn from reading the papers. However, it may need a very different interpretation. 
I will keep my eyes open for the critiques from those not there. Anthony Giddens is solid, and should juxtaposed to Judaism. But there are other interpretations. 

The Caputo volume was from a great conference at Syracuse. I do have a Paul post or two when I get to those pages in something that I am writing. As Jews involved, lets not forget Taubes and Paula Fredrickson. 

I have been bookmarking material on Milbank. But since he is not part of my courses or something that I am working on, then he is ever receding.  There are already lots and lots of great blog posts on Zizek-Milbank, even a blogger who just wrote an intro book on the topic. If someone out there like you wants to write a few posts, then I will certainly add my two cents.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>EJ-<br />
I think you put your finger on it. Very sharp. As I was typing, I was wondering, hmm this sounds a bit Marxist of the Ernesto Laclau or Talal Asad variety, and a little Muslim liberation theology thrown in. This is a similar group to the Fundamentalist Project, they noticed a change but got the interpretation completely wrong. If you never read Peter Berger&#8217;s critique of the project, you should. We trust Christian Smith and Robert Wuthnow over the Fundamentalist Project. People are Evangelical, Centrist Orthodox or Engaged Yeshivsh not Fundamentalist. I get the same sense here. They do have their finger on a social change and there are things to learn from reading the papers. However, it may need a very different interpretation.<br />
I will keep my eyes open for the critiques from those not there. Anthony Giddens is solid, and should juxtaposed to Judaism. But there are other interpretations. </p>
<p>The Caputo volume was from a great conference at Syracuse. I do have a Paul post or two when I get to those pages in something that I am writing. As Jews involved, lets not forget Taubes and Paula Fredrickson. </p>
<p>I have been bookmarking material on Milbank. But since he is not part of my courses or something that I am working on, then he is ever receding.  There are already lots and lots of great blog posts on Zizek-Milbank, even a blogger who just wrote an intro book on the topic. If someone out there like you wants to write a few posts, then I will certainly add my two cents.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/11/18/%e2%80%9ccontending-modernities-catholic-muslim-secular-%e2%80%9d/#comment-1994</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2010 20:20:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2412#comment-1994</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I find it interesting how quickly everyone has changed in such a relatively short time. When Hitler, Mussolini and the Japanese rulers were on the ascendency, no one except fascists spoke of different paths to modernity, even though those countries were prime examples of modernity in terms of science, industrial development, sexual relations and aesthetics. When Stalin and Mao were transforming their countries all in the name of modernization, no one except diehard Stalinists spoke how we should not judge these societies on the basis of enlightenment values. But when it come to Islam, no matter if they  are  promoting Gulf brands of medieval intolerance or the Iranian Shiite version of messianism, we line up to do apologetics... You have to understand that democracy,  liberty, free markets, autonomy  are only one way amongst many ways, etc,. and in any case Protestant values are the ideological face of neo-liberalism, ie. capitalism run amuck... Everybody has become a cynic. 

So I smell a rat. I think in only inviting Catholics and Muslims and some &quot;modernism has nothing to do with secularism&quot; types, plus the ever affable Martin Marty, there is an implicit criticism of the Protestants and their way to a decent, tolerant society. We are going to hear talk from Catholics about the Muslim way to finding God which morphs into the Islamic path to Jesus. Both groups want global hegemony and have difficulty with exceptions, individualism and autonomy. There is more going on here than a pitch for communitarians, and it is a separate from the recent discussions about Paul. It&#039;s somehow the idea that only a Catholic worldview is sufficiently capacious and universal to find a way to coexist with Islamic universalism.  

(You should take a look at the Milbank-Zizek exchanges which is growing daily, and this book edited by Caputo, &quot;St. Paul among the Philosophers.&quot; This literature is confusing, what is the Maoist Badiou doing darshening St. Paul? One  person out there representing Jewish thinking is Boyarin, beginning with his book on Paul.  Maybe you can help by giving us a road map of the players and what values they represent. )]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I find it interesting how quickly everyone has changed in such a relatively short time. When Hitler, Mussolini and the Japanese rulers were on the ascendency, no one except fascists spoke of different paths to modernity, even though those countries were prime examples of modernity in terms of science, industrial development, sexual relations and aesthetics. When Stalin and Mao were transforming their countries all in the name of modernization, no one except diehard Stalinists spoke how we should not judge these societies on the basis of enlightenment values. But when it come to Islam, no matter if they  are  promoting Gulf brands of medieval intolerance or the Iranian Shiite version of messianism, we line up to do apologetics&#8230; You have to understand that democracy,  liberty, free markets, autonomy  are only one way amongst many ways, etc,. and in any case Protestant values are the ideological face of neo-liberalism, ie. capitalism run amuck&#8230; Everybody has become a cynic. </p>
<p>So I smell a rat. I think in only inviting Catholics and Muslims and some &#8220;modernism has nothing to do with secularism&#8221; types, plus the ever affable Martin Marty, there is an implicit criticism of the Protestants and their way to a decent, tolerant society. We are going to hear talk from Catholics about the Muslim way to finding God which morphs into the Islamic path to Jesus. Both groups want global hegemony and have difficulty with exceptions, individualism and autonomy. There is more going on here than a pitch for communitarians, and it is a separate from the recent discussions about Paul. It&#8217;s somehow the idea that only a Catholic worldview is sufficiently capacious and universal to find a way to coexist with Islamic universalism.  </p>
<p>(You should take a look at the Milbank-Zizek exchanges which is growing daily, and this book edited by Caputo, &#8220;St. Paul among the Philosophers.&#8221; This literature is confusing, what is the Maoist Badiou doing darshening St. Paul? One  person out there representing Jewish thinking is Boyarin, beginning with his book on Paul.  Maybe you can help by giving us a road map of the players and what values they represent. )</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
