<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Arthur Green responds to Daniel Landes	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/30/arthur-green-responds-to-daniel-landes/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/30/arthur-green-responds-to-daniel-landes/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Nov 2010 23:09:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Steg (dos iz nit der šteg)		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/30/arthur-green-responds-to-daniel-landes/#comment-1985</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Steg (dos iz nit der šteg)]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Nov 2010 23:09:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2272#comment-1985</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[AS:

Pardes does not claim to be pluralist.  Pardes only believes in one thing — &lt;b&gt;Jews should learn Torah&lt;/b&gt;.  Everything else is not their agenda, their issue or their problem.  Their dominant approach to Torah, though, comes from a traditional perspective.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>AS:</p>
<p>Pardes does not claim to be pluralist.  Pardes only believes in one thing — <b>Jews should learn Torah</b>.  Everything else is not their agenda, their issue or their problem.  Their dominant approach to Torah, though, comes from a traditional perspective.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Steve Brizel		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/30/arthur-green-responds-to-daniel-landes/#comment-1955</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Steve Brizel]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2010 17:54:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2272#comment-1955</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[R Daniel Landes deserves much praise for his critique of Arthur Green&#039;s latest book, which views Judaism as only of many religions with &quot;ethical truths&quot; and attempting to show that one can be a good Jewish Buddhist.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>R Daniel Landes deserves much praise for his critique of Arthur Green&#8217;s latest book, which views Judaism as only of many religions with &#8220;ethical truths&#8221; and attempting to show that one can be a good Jewish Buddhist.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Len Moskowitz		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/30/arthur-green-responds-to-daniel-landes/#comment-1917</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Len Moskowitz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2010 22:34:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2272#comment-1917</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/30/arthur-green-responds-to-daniel-landes/#comment-1851&quot;&gt;Len Moskowitz&lt;/a&gt;.

I wrote: &quot;The ones who “took them prisoner” might fall into another category. I don’t know — what do you think?&quot;

Since no one answered my question,  I asked a rosh yeshiva at RIETS (who shall remain unnamed).  He responded that the teachers and leaders in the non-Orthodox movements should also be considered tinokote sheh-nishbu, because they too did not have proper  Jewish educations from young ages.
]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/30/arthur-green-responds-to-daniel-landes/#comment-1851">Len Moskowitz</a>.</p>
<p>I wrote: &#8220;The ones who “took them prisoner” might fall into another category. I don’t know — what do you think?&#8221;</p>
<p>Since no one answered my question,  I asked a rosh yeshiva at RIETS (who shall remain unnamed).  He responded that the teachers and leaders in the non-Orthodox movements should also be considered tinokote sheh-nishbu, because they too did not have proper  Jewish educations from young ages.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/30/arthur-green-responds-to-daniel-landes/#comment-1912</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2010 19:50:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2272#comment-1912</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Perhaps someone should write a critique of the Pardes model of &#039;pluralism.&#039; If you compare it to Chabad&#039;s toleration of heterodoxy you see the basic parallels.

Chabad: it&#039;s OK if you drive to shul, just do more mitzvot and feel Jewish.

Pardes: it&#039;s OK if you drive to an egalitarian minyan, just engage with these texts and feel Jewish. 

In other words, It&#039;s good that Landes put this out there so that people who are not Orthodox will have a better idea of what they are getting if they choose to go to Pardes.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Perhaps someone should write a critique of the Pardes model of &#8216;pluralism.&#8217; If you compare it to Chabad&#8217;s toleration of heterodoxy you see the basic parallels.</p>
<p>Chabad: it&#8217;s OK if you drive to shul, just do more mitzvot and feel Jewish.</p>
<p>Pardes: it&#8217;s OK if you drive to an egalitarian minyan, just engage with these texts and feel Jewish. </p>
<p>In other words, It&#8217;s good that Landes put this out there so that people who are not Orthodox will have a better idea of what they are getting if they choose to go to Pardes.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Len Moskowitz		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/30/arthur-green-responds-to-daniel-landes/#comment-1898</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Len Moskowitz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 07 Nov 2010 00:13:40 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2272#comment-1898</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Art Green, Arnie Eisen and David Ellenson will be talking about Green&#039;s book at the Manhattan JCC on Monday November 8th at 8 PM.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Art Green, Arnie Eisen and David Ellenson will be talking about Green&#8217;s book at the Manhattan JCC on Monday November 8th at 8 PM.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Larry Yudelson		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/30/arthur-green-responds-to-daniel-landes/#comment-1868</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Larry Yudelson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 03 Nov 2010 02:37:50 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2272#comment-1868</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I don&#039;t understand what you&#039;re saying. How can someone who fails to offer korbanot and has only one wife claim to follow a &quot;Torah&quot; lifestyle? And is it a lifestyle or is it morality?

Rav Kook would argue that it is not just the conception of God, but the conception of morality that has evolved. L&#039;maaseh, however, contemporary Orthodox Judaism doesn&#039;t follow him in that regards.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I don&#8217;t understand what you&#8217;re saying. How can someone who fails to offer korbanot and has only one wife claim to follow a &#8220;Torah&#8221; lifestyle? And is it a lifestyle or is it morality?</p>
<p>Rav Kook would argue that it is not just the conception of God, but the conception of morality that has evolved. L&#8217;maaseh, however, contemporary Orthodox Judaism doesn&#8217;t follow him in that regards.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Eliyahu A.		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/30/arthur-green-responds-to-daniel-landes/#comment-1867</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eliyahu A.]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2010 22:05:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2272#comment-1867</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Daniel Landes&#039; critique took the words from my mouth when first reading Green&#039;s &quot;Seek My Face&quot; (Hebrew translation). Even more superb is his &quot;uncovering&quot; of the &quot;hidden master&quot;.
Green&#039;s response doesn&#039;t make thing better and unintentionally acknowledges  Landes&#039; case:

1. There is indeed an &quot;evolution&quot; of God in Judaism. However this God was always consistent with his moral demands of Humanity and Israel. Therefore, both the Chasidic masters and R. Kook who maintain a panentheistic outlook, never gave up a Torah lifestyle or the idea of Israel&#039;s uniqueness. Also, this &quot;God&quot; never tried to market Himself to the changing whims and fashions of the people - whether they were following Egyptian, Canaanite or Hellenic deities.  , Green boasts that he knows better then the previous generation what they believed in. In reality, they always  made an effort to reconcile their theology with the biblical and rabbinical one, and never saw a contradiction between the &quot;God&quot;s. 
The pantheistic religion a-la Green is a response to every new age trend in the market, and and justification of every almost every liberal fashion. If &quot;everything is God&quot; and therefore holy, there can be no true sense of right or wrong and real moral stand cannot be sought-after. The conscious attempt to revolutionize a completely new theology is Reconstructionism by definition.

2. Evolution presents a problem only for the Haredim, who are just straw-men for Green&#039;s arguments.  For R. Kook the theory&#039;s &quot;trueness&quot; was irrelevant; he just saw it as a means to explain some Kabbalistic ideas.  Green, it seems, adopts evolution because it&#039;s the current scientific paradigm, just as Kaplan adopted  trans-naturalism. (I believe he should be warned against the attempt of joining religion and science. Scientific theories have a tendency to change or to be dismissed altogether, rendering their &quot;spiritual&quot; counterpart as pseudoscience).

3. While Biblical criticism is a challenge for the Orthodox, I personally don&#039;t think it undermines &lt;i&gt; Torah mi-Shamyim &lt;/i&gt;. It may be claimed that the author(s) are divinely inspired (see Halivni&#039;s &quot;REVELATION RESTORED: DIVINE WRIT AND CRITICAL RESPONSES&quot; ). Green&#039;s dismissal of this possibility, is a definitive mark of Kaplan&#039;s teachings.

4. The Holocaust was not the first tragedy to befall the Jewish people, although it&#039;s by far the worst tragedy. In every generation Jews lost faith in God due to the difficulties of the exile.  For the faithful, the answers were either theodicy, or God hiding his face. Both of these are found in the Tanakh. (see Eliezer Berkovits: Faith after the Holocaust)

5. What&#039;s striking is that Green&#039;s response stops short with the Holocaust without mentioning the State of Israel which, according to the disciples of his beloved R. Kook, is God&#039;s return to the arena - no less!
For me, as a religious Zionist, one of his most disturbing ideas is the dismissal of  Israel&#039; s &lt;i&gt;true&lt;/i&gt;  significance for Judaism: It&#039;s not just a shelter, but the a chance for Judaism to shake of the anomaly of the Exile. It&#039;s the only place where Judaism can once again become a real &quot;religious civilization&quot;.  Furthermore, his dealing with the Israeli-Palestinian conflict is quite ad hoc and naive.  He advises the Israeli&#039;s to agree to the  Palestinians&#039; demands on pluralistic grounds, i.e. just because the Palestinians demand them...  It seems that according to him that by clinging to our outdated notions of nationalism we fail to see that the century long conflict is just a misunderstanding... in the end we are all One and same.

&lt;em&gt;(edited by site owner-please read rules for comments before commenting again)&lt;/em&gt;]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Daniel Landes&#8217; critique took the words from my mouth when first reading Green&#8217;s &#8220;Seek My Face&#8221; (Hebrew translation). Even more superb is his &#8220;uncovering&#8221; of the &#8220;hidden master&#8221;.<br />
Green&#8217;s response doesn&#8217;t make thing better and unintentionally acknowledges  Landes&#8217; case:</p>
<p>1. There is indeed an &#8220;evolution&#8221; of God in Judaism. However this God was always consistent with his moral demands of Humanity and Israel. Therefore, both the Chasidic masters and R. Kook who maintain a panentheistic outlook, never gave up a Torah lifestyle or the idea of Israel&#8217;s uniqueness. Also, this &#8220;God&#8221; never tried to market Himself to the changing whims and fashions of the people &#8211; whether they were following Egyptian, Canaanite or Hellenic deities.  , Green boasts that he knows better then the previous generation what they believed in. In reality, they always  made an effort to reconcile their theology with the biblical and rabbinical one, and never saw a contradiction between the &#8220;God&#8221;s.<br />
The pantheistic religion a-la Green is a response to every new age trend in the market, and and justification of every almost every liberal fashion. If &#8220;everything is God&#8221; and therefore holy, there can be no true sense of right or wrong and real moral stand cannot be sought-after. The conscious attempt to revolutionize a completely new theology is Reconstructionism by definition.</p>
<p>2. Evolution presents a problem only for the Haredim, who are just straw-men for Green&#8217;s arguments.  For R. Kook the theory&#8217;s &#8220;trueness&#8221; was irrelevant; he just saw it as a means to explain some Kabbalistic ideas.  Green, it seems, adopts evolution because it&#8217;s the current scientific paradigm, just as Kaplan adopted  trans-naturalism. (I believe he should be warned against the attempt of joining religion and science. Scientific theories have a tendency to change or to be dismissed altogether, rendering their &#8220;spiritual&#8221; counterpart as pseudoscience).</p>
<p>3. While Biblical criticism is a challenge for the Orthodox, I personally don&#8217;t think it undermines <i> Torah mi-Shamyim </i>. It may be claimed that the author(s) are divinely inspired (see Halivni&#8217;s &#8220;REVELATION RESTORED: DIVINE WRIT AND CRITICAL RESPONSES&#8221; ). Green&#8217;s dismissal of this possibility, is a definitive mark of Kaplan&#8217;s teachings.</p>
<p>4. The Holocaust was not the first tragedy to befall the Jewish people, although it&#8217;s by far the worst tragedy. In every generation Jews lost faith in God due to the difficulties of the exile.  For the faithful, the answers were either theodicy, or God hiding his face. Both of these are found in the Tanakh. (see Eliezer Berkovits: Faith after the Holocaust)</p>
<p>5. What&#8217;s striking is that Green&#8217;s response stops short with the Holocaust without mentioning the State of Israel which, according to the disciples of his beloved R. Kook, is God&#8217;s return to the arena &#8211; no less!<br />
For me, as a religious Zionist, one of his most disturbing ideas is the dismissal of  Israel&#8217; s <i>true</i>  significance for Judaism: It&#8217;s not just a shelter, but the a chance for Judaism to shake of the anomaly of the Exile. It&#8217;s the only place where Judaism can once again become a real &#8220;religious civilization&#8221;.  Furthermore, his dealing with the Israeli-Palestinian conflict is quite ad hoc and naive.  He advises the Israeli&#8217;s to agree to the  Palestinians&#8217; demands on pluralistic grounds, i.e. just because the Palestinians demand them&#8230;  It seems that according to him that by clinging to our outdated notions of nationalism we fail to see that the century long conflict is just a misunderstanding&#8230; in the end we are all One and same.</p>
<p><em>(edited by site owner-please read rules for comments before commenting again)</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Nathan Katz		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/30/arthur-green-responds-to-daniel-landes/#comment-1865</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nathan Katz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2010 19:59:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2272#comment-1865</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I have no wish to enter into the Landes-Green disputations, but I am flattered that Pierre wrote:
&quot;I&#039;d like to hear Dr.Nathan Katz’s take on some of this exchange, as he’s written extensively on intersections of faiths – as with R. Akiva Tatz’s dialogue with a Zen Buddhist Jew and the Jewish Renewal role in such things. I still snicker when much “inter-faith dialogue” from those realms is Jewish Jews talking with Jewish buddhists; can any other religious dialogue crew say that? I remember reading a bit from a “Hebrew Catholic” who attended some of the BC Jewish/Catholic conferences, but NOT as a speaker…&quot;
Pierre gets my point perfectly. If we care about interreligious dialogue, then a conversation between a Jew and and JuBu simple doesn&#039;t pass muster (as Tatz&#039;s book). I once read a book by Hans Kung on interreligious dialogue wherein every participant was between Christians and Christians representing other religions. Utterly inauthentic.
Genuine dialogue is always surprising; new insights emerge when one makes the effort to step outside of one&#039;s usual framework. To do this, we have to get to know real, flesh-and-blood Buddhists (or Hindus, or whatever). Dialogue must be between and among real people, not our own projections. And what else are JuBus but Jewish projections onto Buddhism? (Pace, friends.)]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have no wish to enter into the Landes-Green disputations, but I am flattered that Pierre wrote:<br />
&#8220;I&#8217;d like to hear Dr.Nathan Katz’s take on some of this exchange, as he’s written extensively on intersections of faiths – as with R. Akiva Tatz’s dialogue with a Zen Buddhist Jew and the Jewish Renewal role in such things. I still snicker when much “inter-faith dialogue” from those realms is Jewish Jews talking with Jewish buddhists; can any other religious dialogue crew say that? I remember reading a bit from a “Hebrew Catholic” who attended some of the BC Jewish/Catholic conferences, but NOT as a speaker…&#8221;<br />
Pierre gets my point perfectly. If we care about interreligious dialogue, then a conversation between a Jew and and JuBu simple doesn&#8217;t pass muster (as Tatz&#8217;s book). I once read a book by Hans Kung on interreligious dialogue wherein every participant was between Christians and Christians representing other religions. Utterly inauthentic.<br />
Genuine dialogue is always surprising; new insights emerge when one makes the effort to step outside of one&#8217;s usual framework. To do this, we have to get to know real, flesh-and-blood Buddhists (or Hindus, or whatever). Dialogue must be between and among real people, not our own projections. And what else are JuBus but Jewish projections onto Buddhism? (Pace, friends.)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/30/arthur-green-responds-to-daniel-landes/#comment-1864</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2010 18:24:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2272#comment-1864</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Prof Yaakov Bildstein has an article on the problematical nature of using the term tinok shnishba in our era. Rav Yoel bin Nun has an article in Akdamot seeking to replace it with a new category. And Rav Shagar has at least two articles on the subject seeking to create a new category. I don&#039;t have the references at hand, and my photocopies are at home.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Prof Yaakov Bildstein has an article on the problematical nature of using the term tinok shnishba in our era. Rav Yoel bin Nun has an article in Akdamot seeking to replace it with a new category. And Rav Shagar has at least two articles on the subject seeking to create a new category. I don&#8217;t have the references at hand, and my photocopies are at home.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Len Moskowitz		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/30/arthur-green-responds-to-daniel-landes/#comment-1863</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Len Moskowitz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2010 18:04:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2272#comment-1863</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[ej wrote:

&quot;This tinok shenisbah idea is a halachic but not an empirical category.  ...&quot;

There are limits to what traditional Jewish theology can say about institutions that purposely and knowingly uproot the fundamentals of Judaism.

Tinoke Sheh-nishba allows traditionally observant Jewry to respond favorably to individual traditionally non-observant Jews without endorsing heretic institutions and their leaders.

Someone who was disposed to judge others for the good might consider the Tinoke Sheh-nishba response as the most compassionate response that traditional Jewry could make to widespread institutional heresy, and accept it for what it is.  

In some ways, it could be seen as similar to the response that the Catholic Church made with Vatican II&#039;s Nostra Aetate.  It&#039;s not ideal, but anyone familiar with the Church and the limits their theology imposes on them, can see it (despite its obvious shortcomings) as an act of great courage and an attempt at a compassionate response towards Jewry.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ej wrote:</p>
<p>&#8220;This tinok shenisbah idea is a halachic but not an empirical category.  &#8230;&#8221;</p>
<p>There are limits to what traditional Jewish theology can say about institutions that purposely and knowingly uproot the fundamentals of Judaism.</p>
<p>Tinoke Sheh-nishba allows traditionally observant Jewry to respond favorably to individual traditionally non-observant Jews without endorsing heretic institutions and their leaders.</p>
<p>Someone who was disposed to judge others for the good might consider the Tinoke Sheh-nishba response as the most compassionate response that traditional Jewry could make to widespread institutional heresy, and accept it for what it is.  </p>
<p>In some ways, it could be seen as similar to the response that the Catholic Church made with Vatican II&#8217;s Nostra Aetate.  It&#8217;s not ideal, but anyone familiar with the Church and the limits their theology imposes on them, can see it (despite its obvious shortcomings) as an act of great courage and an attempt at a compassionate response towards Jewry.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: David S		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/30/arthur-green-responds-to-daniel-landes/#comment-1862</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[David S]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2010 14:27:22 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2272#comment-1862</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[EJ, dead on.  I remember when I was in biz school that we had a class in industrial marketing where rather than learning from a book, we played an elaborate game for the entire semester.  We were to try and determine customer preferences and spend R&#038;D money to develop products that fit the customers needs.  The problem is that the customer preferences were always moving around so if you designed the product to fit the last set of preferences you never quite made it.  The key was to figure out somehow where the customer was GOING TO BE and not just where they were.  In other words, the valid thing to recognize was that things were in motion and not static.  I think the same thing underlying dynamic informs the schism that EJ mentions above.  Within the Orthodox worldview, there are incredible lengths taken to prove that what exists now at this moment was always in place and that there is an unbroken chain of transmission of the same basic way of life.  To people used to a critical analysis of history, there are incredible lengths taken to prove that what exists at this moment is the result of a historical process that included inputs generated internal to the Jewish people and externally by other societies and cultures.  These two views cannot avoid being in conflict.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>EJ, dead on.  I remember when I was in biz school that we had a class in industrial marketing where rather than learning from a book, we played an elaborate game for the entire semester.  We were to try and determine customer preferences and spend R&amp;D money to develop products that fit the customers needs.  The problem is that the customer preferences were always moving around so if you designed the product to fit the last set of preferences you never quite made it.  The key was to figure out somehow where the customer was GOING TO BE and not just where they were.  In other words, the valid thing to recognize was that things were in motion and not static.  I think the same thing underlying dynamic informs the schism that EJ mentions above.  Within the Orthodox worldview, there are incredible lengths taken to prove that what exists now at this moment was always in place and that there is an unbroken chain of transmission of the same basic way of life.  To people used to a critical analysis of history, there are incredible lengths taken to prove that what exists at this moment is the result of a historical process that included inputs generated internal to the Jewish people and externally by other societies and cultures.  These two views cannot avoid being in conflict.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/30/arthur-green-responds-to-daniel-landes/#comment-1858</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2010 01:14:31 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2272#comment-1858</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I think what is important for Green are three considerations. He wants a theology that ends up on the progressive side of issues. He wants a Judaism that is passionate about the planet and its future,  is pluralist and tolerant, has some conception of global justice, doesn’t demonize non Jews, is on the side of enlightened science and so on. It makes little difference if this is the Torah’s views or not. Even if not, he will darshen so that these new values seem to have a Jewish connection, or he will say straight out the Torah is wrong. Arthur Green is not shy, as befits a major Jewish leader. Second he wants his theology to reflect his taste palette. He’s not a Talmud guy or a Rambam guy. We all know his enthusiasms. Third he wants his theology to be of interest to his demographic. God outside is pretty much a non-starter, so he has nowhere else to go but inward. 

Let’s face it, the Jewish people are in schism. Depending on how you count, they have at least two religions. Orthodoxy and its satellites, and Reform (or unaffiliated) and its satellites. The unaffiliated camp doesn’t care much what they are called, Judaism 2.0 would do. I feel the primary goal is to hold Jews together as a global community, even if the unity is somewhat artificial. The  conceptual confusion that  is involved when two distinct religions use the same names is well worth the price. The point that Orthodoxy is the closest successor of traditional Judaism is granted by everyone. Whether or not this closeness is a virtue or not is not solved by saying “But this wasn’t/isn’t Judaism.”

This tinok shenisbah idea is a halachic but not an empirical category. Go tell a group of non Orthodox Jews that Moshe kibail Torah miSinai. How many will say, &quot;OMG, who knew?&quot; It&#039;s the Orthodox way of never recognizing other Jewish groups, except as potential kiruv material. No one but Orthodoxy  knows  how to help Jews lead a moral and spiritual life.  Eleven million Jews are children, mamish children , captured and raised by pirates while at sea.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think what is important for Green are three considerations. He wants a theology that ends up on the progressive side of issues. He wants a Judaism that is passionate about the planet and its future,  is pluralist and tolerant, has some conception of global justice, doesn’t demonize non Jews, is on the side of enlightened science and so on. It makes little difference if this is the Torah’s views or not. Even if not, he will darshen so that these new values seem to have a Jewish connection, or he will say straight out the Torah is wrong. Arthur Green is not shy, as befits a major Jewish leader. Second he wants his theology to reflect his taste palette. He’s not a Talmud guy or a Rambam guy. We all know his enthusiasms. Third he wants his theology to be of interest to his demographic. God outside is pretty much a non-starter, so he has nowhere else to go but inward. </p>
<p>Let’s face it, the Jewish people are in schism. Depending on how you count, they have at least two religions. Orthodoxy and its satellites, and Reform (or unaffiliated) and its satellites. The unaffiliated camp doesn’t care much what they are called, Judaism 2.0 would do. I feel the primary goal is to hold Jews together as a global community, even if the unity is somewhat artificial. The  conceptual confusion that  is involved when two distinct religions use the same names is well worth the price. The point that Orthodoxy is the closest successor of traditional Judaism is granted by everyone. Whether or not this closeness is a virtue or not is not solved by saying “But this wasn’t/isn’t Judaism.”</p>
<p>This tinok shenisbah idea is a halachic but not an empirical category. Go tell a group of non Orthodox Jews that Moshe kibail Torah miSinai. How many will say, &#8220;OMG, who knew?&#8221; It&#8217;s the Orthodox way of never recognizing other Jewish groups, except as potential kiruv material. No one but Orthodoxy  knows  how to help Jews lead a moral and spiritual life.  Eleven million Jews are children, mamish children , captured and raised by pirates while at sea.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: David S		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/30/arthur-green-responds-to-daniel-landes/#comment-1856</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[David S]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2010 22:07:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2272#comment-1856</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/30/arthur-green-responds-to-daniel-landes/#comment-1835&quot;&gt;Larry Yudelson&lt;/a&gt;.

A river is never the same as you look at it from moment to moment although it may appear to be the same.  Nothing is the same in fact from moment to moment.   Judaism is not static if only because the people living it are different people and perceive it differently by dint of their God given uniqueness.  There are threads that tie things back to the source, eternal golden braids in time.  Everyone is trying to weave their thoughts and ideas to the strand. Posterity alone will define which strands are braided into the whole.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/30/arthur-green-responds-to-daniel-landes/#comment-1835">Larry Yudelson</a>.</p>
<p>A river is never the same as you look at it from moment to moment although it may appear to be the same.  Nothing is the same in fact from moment to moment.   Judaism is not static if only because the people living it are different people and perceive it differently by dint of their God given uniqueness.  There are threads that tie things back to the source, eternal golden braids in time.  Everyone is trying to weave their thoughts and ideas to the strand. Posterity alone will define which strands are braided into the whole.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
