<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>education &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/category/education/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 May 2010 03:13:57 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='kavvanah.wordpress.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/c9f111237f93750b6b994fc5185d49c3?s=96&#038;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>education &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>Peter Beinart on Day Schools</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/25/peter-beinart-on-day-schools/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/25/peter-beinart-on-day-schools/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2010 03:13:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[avi chai]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[day schools]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[peter beinart]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1364</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Back in 1999, Beinart framed the rise of day schools as a rejection of the original acceptance of public school. The growth of Jewish Day Schools is an abandonment of the American public square. Beinart pointed out that the rise &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/25/peter-beinart-on-day-schools/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Back in 1999, Beinart framed the rise of day schools as a rejection of the original acceptance of public school. The growth of Jewish Day Schools is an abandonment of the American public square.</p>
<p>Beinart pointed out that the rise of day school had other factors than the obvious religious commitment.  Even though day schools were originally for ideologically driven Orthodox who have not totally integrated into America, Day Schools became a form of private school for those moving up the latter. </p>
<p>Now, it seems the drive for day schools is the ideological need to create an enclave, in many classes an upper middle class Orthodox enclave.  In this type of school, what counts? the education or the creation of the enclave?  Some families are clearly still interested in creating private schools better than the public schools while others no longer ask if the day school if better than the public school in social studies, English, arts, or college preparation.  Beinart reminds us to account for the role of the school in social mobility,class and caste. At the end of the twentieth century, day schools were “in” but the word “day school” may have had three different meanings- <strong>a prep school for Jews, a community school for identity, and a day school to create an enclave. </strong><a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/11/peripheral-vision/"> Studies done by Avi Chai</a> do not differentiate types of schools or factor in class and caste. (<a href="http://www.peje.org/docs/GrowthToronto.pdf">One of the decent studies available on the web</a>, which was done privately by Alex Pomson, shows that in Toronto day schools are not growing relative to population increase.)</p>
<p>Jews supported public school because it helped enforce the separation of Church and State.  Jews did   encourage Christian kids to go to pre-Vatican II Catholic and Protestant schools because it would not have helped their integration. In those days, thinking of America as a Christian country would have meant Jews are excluded. Now, Jews do not worry about the possibility if there are Christian schools that do not offer an American secular narrative  Jews do not worry about being outsiders. Nor do American Orthodox Jews currently worry about the possibility of Afrocentric, Muslim, Hindu, and Sikh private schools.</p>
<p>What  do day school parents feel about the melting pot? I would suspect that many are oblivious or against. Or it is only useful for everyone else. Do some of the parents see that if you exclude yourself from the socialization of the rest of the country then you start to look sectarian? Or if you accept the melting pot for viewing sports and listening to Lady Gaga, but not for social science thinking and historical narrative  then you create a hybridization that may not work in all contexts.  (In the full article, Beinhart cheers for the creation of the New-Jew HS in Boston as outside the box.)</p>
<p><a href="http:// http://www.theatlantic.com/past/issues/99oct/9910jewishschools.htm">Read full version of Beinart on Jewish schools here.</a></p>
<blockquote><p>Preparing children for &#8220;the general American environment&#8221; meant public education as both practice and ideology. &#8220;The public school,&#8221; says Alvin I. Schiff, the Irving I. Stone Distinguished Professor of Education at Yeshiva University, in New York, &#8220;was considered sacred, holy. It was the method and setting by which Jews could become Americans.&#8221;<br />
All the talk about Jewish identity may also obscure a less high-minded reason for the Jewish-school boom: as Jews have moved up the economic ladder, their commitment to public education has waned.<br />
&#8220;As the public schools have eroded,&#8221; Miller says, &#8220;we are no longer being compared so much to public schools as to other independents.&#8221; Jewish leaders argue that because Jews make up such a small proportion of the U.S. population, the growth of Jewish schools has no real impact on the overall health of American public education. But public schools rely more heavily on Jewish support than the numbers would suggest, in part because Jewish organizations, fearful of any breakdown of the wall between Church and State, have traditionally lobbied hard against school vouchers and other government aid to private schools. As awareness grows that voucher programs might benefit financially strapped Jewish schools, that opposition may diminish.<br />
Yet such parents, by choosing Jewish schools, are preparing their children to lead more observant, less assimilated lives than they do. Some even describe the phenomenon as an inversion of a practice in nineteenth-century Europe whereby parents would remain Jewish but baptize their children.<br />
Why a growing number of relatively secular Jewish parents are abandoning the education model of their youth is a topic of considerable debate within the organized Jewish world</p>
<p>THERE is another, even more sensitive issue lurking behind the Jewish-school phenomenon. Earlier generations of Jews, according to Eduardo Rauch, of the Jewish Theological Seminary, in New York, sent their children to public school not simply as a means of ascending into the middle class but as a show of national loyalty. Today, in contrast, parents are willing to consider Jewish schools in part because they no longer fear being viewed as outsiders. They take their integration into mainstream America as a given. But what if earlier generations were correct &#8212; that full equality in an overwhelmingly Christian country is, in fact, reliant on Jewish willingness to participate in a common system of education?<br />
In fact, when discussing issues like Afrocentrism and bilingual education, American Jewish leaders sometimes bemoan the demise of the melting-pot ideal in this country. Yet separate religious schools both rely on that demise and exacerbate it. The Orthodox community, for its part, has rarely celebrated the melting pot, and generally worries less about total acceptance by the broader culture. </p></blockquote>
<p>For our last discussion about day schools, see here- <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/11/catholic-schools-and-jewish-day-schools/">Catholic Schools and Jewish Day Schools.</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/25/peter-beinart-on-day-schools/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>History – the Orthodox Way: Without Causality and with Presentism</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/22/history-%e2%80%93-the-orthodox-way-without-causality-and-with-presentism/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/22/history-%e2%80%93-the-orthodox-way-without-causality-and-with-presentism/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2010 02:46:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[holidays]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[holocaust]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Holocaust history]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jewish history]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Simone Schweber]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=837</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Here is a good article that I missed when it came out and it does not seem to have gained notice of the Jewish education circles.  The article is about a Lubavitch girls school, but most of the observations that &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/22/history-%e2%80%93-the-orthodox-way-without-causality-and-with-presentism/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here is a good article that I missed when it came out and it does not seem to have gained notice of the Jewish education circles.  The article is about a Lubavitch girls school, but most of the observations that I excerpted apply equally well to Modern Orthodox students on both college and graduate level.  In addition, the article is on the Holocaust but can apply equally well to most other issues in Jewish history.  I have found students unable to apply any causality to the Middle East, to modern religious movements, or anti-Semitism.  I have also found students who treat theological statement of Rabbis or Rabbis working out theology as if it was real history. Theological statements about halakhah are used as causality for events. The lack of social science thinking about Judaism is wide spread despite the required Jewish history in high school. Absurd forms of presentism are acceptable for debate. This article harshly calls this accepted orthodox approach narcissistic, social isolationism, moral arrogance and religious triumphalism. Any thoughts?</p>
<p>Simone Schweber, &#8220;Here there is no why&#8221;: Holocaust education at a Lubavitch girls&#8217; yeshivah. Jewish Social Studies Volume 14, Number 2, (Winter 2008) 156-185</p>
<p><em>Numerous authors have elaborated the discourse of the Holocaust&#8217;s unintelligibility, expounding on the Shoah&#8217;s unspeakability, unimaginability, and fundamental unknowability… Few, however, have considered the disciplinary limitations of such a theoretical position. The stance of unintelligibility may work for literary theorists and cultural critics, but it hardly aids educators. What might it mean, for example, to teach </em><em>toward</em> unintelligibility? Can one teach despite, through, or with a Warumverbot? [Asking why is forbidden]</p>
<p><em>When I set out to study the teaching of the Holocaust at a Lubavitch girls&#8217; yeshivah in the Midwestern United States, I was not aware, naïvely perhaps, that a Warumverbot could serve as a pedagogical platform. How might students who believed in divinely driven history, for example, understand human perpetrators? When would contingency trump eschatology and vice versa?</em></p>
<p><em>First, as a result of the culture of argumentation, the students&#8217; presentist orientations toward history surfaced. Because they thought of their religious dictates as being ahistorical or transhistorical, they could argue over whether it was &#8220;okay&#8221; for Jews in hiding to recite Catholic prayers; their investment in prayer and religious obligations trumped historical circumstances in their understandings of the Holocaust. Second, because some of the girls thought of Jewish teenagers as being basically the same across time and space, they could argue over why European Jewish teens would return to their homes. The girls&#8217; assumptions about Jews, in other words, were personally based (and similarly presentist). In most public or Christian school contexts where the Holocaust is taught, Jews are easily exoticized, but for these Hasidic girls, Jews were noticeably normalized.</em></p>
<p><em>Rather than blaming assimilation, secular Jews, the advent of Reform Judaism, Zionism, Zionists, or the lack of or dedication to a Jewish homeland—all of which are common refrains in Israeli haredi materials—these girls located the root of persecution in envy. In response to the interview question &#8220;Why were Jews persecuted?,&#8221; each of the other four focus students supplied an answer that involved jealousy or difference… Because chosenness bounded the girls&#8217; historical meaning-making, other victim groups fell out of their Holocaust narratives…. Hashem used the Holocaust as testament to both the endurance and enduring nature of the Jewish people…. By contrast, later in the unit, when they read about Japanese-Americans being interned in camps, a student asked, &#8220;What did they do to deserve that?&#8221;</em></p>
<p><em>Although Mrs. Glickman taught about the Holocaust during her secular studies block, she taught about it as a religious event. She did not include miraculous stories that so frequently populate Hasidic sources, but her course relied on the miraculous as explanation; for much of her Holocaust curriculum, rational explanations for events were not proffered.</em></p>
<p><em>The special status of the Holocaust in their classroom deprived them of basic historical understandings. None of the girls at the end of their unit knew about the history of antisemitism,<sup> </sup>the reasons Germans voted for Hitler, or the ways perpetrators were socialized. None could answer even basic historical questions like why the Holocaust occurred without resorting to all-encompassing theological rationales.</em></p>
<p><em>As I see it, Mrs. Glickman taught toward fundamentally narcissistic ends: she did not expand the girls&#8217; notions of others, of otherness, or even of Jewishness itself</em></p>
<p><em>Moreover, in considering Nazi behavior to be abnormal, unknowable, and unable to be investigated, Mrs. Glickman fed the girls&#8217; moral arrogance and religious triumphalism. Not only did the girls believe themselves to be incapable of compromising behavior, but they could not deign to discuss it even in others. The starkness of the moral divide… reified the girls&#8217; righteousness and supported their narrow-mindedness. In the process, the contingencies, complexities, and even overly simplistic explanations that sometimes masquerade as history were occluded, rendered invisible to these girls.</em></p>
<p><em>Mrs. Glickman&#8217;s Holocaust education thus did not serve to complicate the girls&#8217; worldviews but rather to narrow their world&#8217;s vistas and support its moral simplicity, religious clarity, and, ultimately, social insularity. Rather than opening up moral questions, Mrs. Glickman&#8217;s pedagogy closed them down.</em></p>
<p>Simone Schweber is the Goodman Associate Professor of Education and Jewish Studies at the University of Wisconsin-Madison. She is the author of <em>Making Sense of the Holocaust: Lessons from Classroom Practice</em> (2004) and, with Debbie Findling, <em>Teaching the Holocaust</em> (2007).</p>
<p>Copyright © 2010 Alan Brill • All Rights Reserved</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/22/history-%e2%80%93-the-orthodox-way-without-causality-and-with-presentism/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>7</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Moshe Kline and the Structured Mishnah</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/18/moshe-kline-and-the-structured-mishnah/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/18/moshe-kline-and-the-structured-mishnah/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2010 16:17:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[literary studies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[midrash]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[leo strauss]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Maharal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mishnah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[moshe kline]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=586</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The 1980&#8217;s and 1990&#8217;s attracted many original minds to Jerusalem. One of them, Moshe Kline, part-time real estate developer, devoted himself to a Torah lishmah quest for the structure of Mishnah. I was always intrigued by anyone who can discuss &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/18/moshe-kline-and-the-structured-mishnah/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The 1980&#8217;s and 1990&#8217;s attracted many original minds to Jerusalem. One of them, Moshe Kline, part-time real estate developer, devoted himself to a Torah lishmah quest for the structure of Mishnah. I was always intrigued by anyone who can discuss Leo Strauss, Maharal, and Mishnah in one sentence. My interest was originally the Maharal angle. But, I have had many colleagues who use Kline&#8217;s structured approach to the Mishnah in teaching HS or adult education.</p>
<p>An introductory lecture presenting his discovery and method as delivered to <a href="http://chaver.com/Mishnah-New/English/Articles/Introduction to the Structured Mishnah.htm">Talmoodists is available here.</a> <a href="http://moshekline.com/General/Color Codes/English Color Code.htm"><br />
</a><a href="http://chaver.com/General/Color%20Codes/English%20Color%20Code.htm">Having this chart</a> in front of you will help  in understanding the lecture.<br />
An article capturing his original insight <a href="http://chaver.com/Mishnah-New/English/Articles/TheArt-H.htm">based on Maharal is available here.</a><br />
The website has his articles on Bible and his complete printable color-coded Mishnah. If you want to discuss the method then please read the above articles first. <a href="http://chaver.com/">Here is the home page </a>of the website with tabs for articles on Torah and Mishnah.</p>
<p>He recently stopped by on a cold wintry NY day and answered a few questions.</p>
<p>1] <strong>What was your discovery about the Mishnah? </strong></p>
<p>The original goal of my Mishnah project was to determine the principles according to which chapters of Mishnah were organized. In order to uncover these rules, it was first necessary to identify the components of chapters. The differing divisions into mishnayot (Bavli, Yerushalmi, various printings of the Mishnah) are all late and extraneous to the text. So I began going through the Mishnah dividing the chapters into components according to literary indicators.<br />
Early on, I realized that the chapters were actually composed with two levels of division, a fact which is totally disguised by the common division into linearly-divided mishnayot. This was the key to the discovery that the chapters were composed as non-linear texts which could be visualized and understood as tables.<br />
The chapters of the Mishnah were formatted according to a paradigm that resembles a table. I then set out each chapter in a visual format consistent with its inner literary structure. The discovery of the literary structure of the chapter leads to an approach to the study of the chapter as a coherent construct rather that a collection of loosely connected laws.</p>
<p>2] <strong>Who has supported it? </strong></p>
<p>My edition of the Mishnah was accepted for publication by BGU Press on recommendation of Shamma Friedman and Daniel Boyarin. I have also received encouragement from David Weiss Halivni and Shlomo Zalman Havlin. Since I made it available online (chaver.com) about ten years ago, I have lost track of how many people actually use it. Currently people are downloading about 20-30 copies of the full text per day. In addition, several hundred individual chapters are accessed every day. So I guess a lot of people are using it.</p>
<p>3] <strong>What did you learn from Leo Strauss about reading a text?</strong></p>
<p>Although I cite <em>Persecution and the Art of Writing</em>, and see the Mishnah as an exoteric/esoteric text, I learned how to read during four years of the great-books program at St. John’s College. (Strauss retired to St. John’s as scholar in residence.) The most important element of this education, relevant to my research, is the requirement to read primary texts without commentary. This made me uncomfortable with the traditional Jewish approach to its foundational texts, i.e. that they could not be approached without commentaries. I was also influenced by the fact that the historical approach was anathema at St. John’s. Consequently, my work is neither “traditional” nor academic/historical.</p>
<p>4] <strong>What did you gain from Maharal?</strong></p>
<p>The Maharal opened the door for me to see the Mishnah as a coherent composition, primarily through his exposition of the pairs in the first chapter of Avot. He made it clear that this structure was to be read as a philosophic composition rather than a loose compilation of aphorisms.</p>
<p>5] <strong>What did you learn from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leon_Ashkenazi_(Manitou)">Rabbi Yehuda Leon Ashkenazi (Manitou)</a>?</strong></p>
<p>From Manitou I learned first and foremost to trust in myself and my St. John’s training. After we studied Maharal together for a period of several months, I began to see other parts of Avot as literary constructs, in addition to the pairs in the first chapter. Manitou then told me that he had received a tradition that the whole of the Mishnah used to be studied in the way that I was beginning to read Avot. However, several generations ago this knowledge had been lost. He asked me to restore this knowledge by identifying the literary structure of the Mishnah. He was sure that the “kabbala” was embedded in the formal structure, or in his words, that the Mishnah was constructed according to the “kabbala”. However, he instructed me to avoid reference to this in my work, and limit myself to literary analysis. Monitou gave me my life’s work, which has now gone farther than he envisioned.</p>
<p>6] <strong>What are you current Bible projects?</strong></p>
<p>I am preparing a structured edition of the Torah which is similar to my edition of the Mishnah. In the meantime, I have published articles on Leviticus. Jacob Milgrom has become my mentor in biblical studies. I am also finishing an article on the link between the structure of the Torah and the structure of the Mishnah. In it, I demonstrate that Rabbi had an esoteric tradition regarding the literary formatting of the Torah which he applied to the composition of the Mishnah.</p>
<p>The paradigm can be seen in the first chapter of the Torah through the six days of creation. We all are familiar with the parallels between days 1 and 4, 2 and 5, 3 and 6. These parallels actually divide the days into two parallel cycles of three days each, 1-3 and 4-6. What is less known, is that the cycles differ from each other in a fixed manner. The days of the first cycle contain creations that are unique, separated, named and motionless (Straus). The days of the second cycle contain groups of multiple, unnamed, moving creations: stars, fish, etc. By arranging the six days in a table containing two columns, the two cycles, and three rows, the paired days, you get a visual representation of the structure underlying the six days of creation. Each individual day is a function of the intersection of two planning lines, its column and its row. “Reading” the text according to this structure reveals the underlying metaphysics of the creation.</p>
<p>7] <strong>How does your approach differ from the literary approaches to Bible and Mishnah that are being produced by Machon Herzog? </strong><br />
My specific focus is on the division into the structural literary units and the additional meanings that are made available by the identification of these larger units.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/18/moshe-kline-and-the-structured-mishnah/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Elie Wiesel&#8217;s Rashi</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/05/elie-wiesels-rashi/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/05/elie-wiesels-rashi/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2009 01:35:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Adam Kirsch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Camus]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Crusades]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[elie Wiesel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hasidic stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rashi]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=118</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I used to receive many phone calls from people looking for the source of some of Elie Wiesel’s Hasidic stories. Usually the source was Dostoevsky, Camus or some other French existentialist authors. I was also asked: “where does the Baal &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/05/elie-wiesels-rashi/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I used to receive many phone calls from people looking for the source of some of Elie Wiesel’s Hasidic stories. Usually the source was Dostoevsky, Camus or some other French existentialist authors. I was also asked: “where does the Baal Shem Tov tell us to always remember the past?” The answer is that the Besht said to “<strong>always remember God”</strong>, in all your ways think of God. This becomes shortened to “Always remember” and then translated as <strong>always remember the past</strong>. I am working on an academic article on the: topic.</p>
<p>But now we have a new book from <a href="http://www.nextbookpress.com/bookseries/9066/rashi/" target="_self">Wiesel Rashi,</a> basically on on how Rashi survived the Holocaust. The answer is that he provides memory, wrote literature, provided solidarity, and offered hope. Once again Camus is offered as the Jewish tradition. For some reason, it bothers me less when done to Hasidic tales than when done to Rashi.</p>
<p>Most mid twentieth century scholars wanting to fit the models of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henri_Pirenne" target="_self">Henri Pirenne</a> on medieval cities, and depicted Rashi’s life as building community and democracy through self reliance and pragmatism. Here for Wiesel, Rashi bleeds history and suffering. Rashi is celebration of commentary, a celebration of memory, and of brotherhood too</p>
<p>Memory in Rashi is usually that one has to keep a memory of ones sins before one memory is sin, or one has to remember the mighty hand of God. Wiesel offers us the memory of his own study of Rashi from his youth where there used to be solidarity in the heder.</p>
<p>In chapter one, we have stories of Rashi’s life interspersed with Wiesel’s nostalgia and memories of his own childhood.  We have legends and miracle tales of Rashi, with the message that the actual events do not matter, only the legends.</p>
<p>In Wiesels’ hands, Rashi, which was taught in cheder as reading the Rashi and then teitch into Yiddish, taught him how to craft literature.</p>
<blockquote><p>He [Rashi] said to me, as if confidentially: look, my child; fear nothing, everything must be grasped and conveyed with simplicity. Strange words stand in the way like obstacles? Start all over again with me. It happened to me too. I started all over again. You just have to break through the shell of a word, a sentence, an expression. Everything is inside them. Everything is waiting for you.</p></blockquote>
<p>Chapter 2 offers selections from Rashi’s Biblical commentary. In the chapter, we are told that he stove for truth and reaching for the exact meaning of the verse (I can except that), but also examples of where Rashi must have let his inability to face evil directly to overcome his approach.</p>
<p>Chapter 3 on Israel, the people and the land shows that Rashi’s moral dualism of Esau and goyim as bad and Jews as good shows that he understood Camus’ idea of solidarity.</p>
<p>Chapter 4  is on sadness and memory, where Rashi confronts the fear and hope of the Crusader period. It does not matter to Wiesel that almost all Rashi scholars do not see any influence of the crusades on his commentaries, only on his elegies.</p>
<p>To hedge his bets and to foreshadow contemporary politics of existential fear of Iran, we are reminded that when Rashi lived the crusaders were fighting the Shiites “where suicidal and murderous fanaticism is still alive today.”Crusaders and Shiites glorified death , while Rashi remains a celebration of human life. Or as Wiesel closed his recent speech at Buchenwald condemning Iran</p>
<blockquote><p>A great man, Camus, wrote at the end of his marvelous novel, The Plague: &#8220;After all,&#8221; he said, &#8220;after the tragedy, never the rest&#8230;there is more in the human being to celebrate than to denigrate.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>As his own explanation of the volume: “This book, therefore, is a story for present and future exiles, but also a moving prayer in their memory to bring them closer to redemption.”</p>
<p>As the wrong complaint to end with, there is an old joke about two elderly Jews discussing a restaurant, one says “the food was terrible and OY! there was so little of it. The book is very short, at best the length of a single chapter in most of this other books. In seems he just added a little verbal padding to his Rashi chapter from a prior book to earn his Nextbook money.</p>
<p>So I will end with noting that the ever clueless <a href="http://www.tabletmag.com/arts-and-culture/books/11014/a-nation-of-commentators/" target="_self">Adam Kirsch used his review of Wiesel’s Rashi </a>to discuss if Jews such as Lionel Trilling and Irving Howe are such good literary critics due to the culture of commentary created by Rashi.</p>
<p>(If any journal or newspaper wants an edited and more book review version of this, then let me know. I also have many more sedate paragraphs which I left out.)</p>
<p>Update The Forward also disliked the book: <a href="http://www.forward.com/articles/116227/">Rashi, Wiesel: Why, Why, Why?</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/05/elie-wiesels-rashi/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sacred Attunments &#8212;part 1</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/21/sacred-attunments-part-1/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/21/sacred-attunments-part-1/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Sep 2009 17:46:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[michael fishbane]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[revelation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sacred attunments]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=49</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Prof Michael Fishbane spoke in our minyan one of the mornings of Rosh Hashanah. Fishbane’s talk was based on his book Sacred Attunements, which came out one year ago. He opened with the idea that we are awakened from below &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/21/sacred-attunments-part-1/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Prof Michael Fishbane spoke in our minyan one of the mornings of Rosh Hashanah.</p>
<p>Fishbane’s talk was based on his book Sacred Attunements, which came out one year ago.</p>
<blockquote><p>He opened with the idea that we are awakened from below through the significant events of our lives.</p>
<p>Then the talk had three parts.</p>
<p>The need to find our sense of self, our groundedness.</p>
<p>The need to hear the call of the moment and the uniqueness of the mitzvah we are called to do.</p>
<p>The need to develop a God consciousness in our lives.</p>
<p>The conclusion was the idea that in Hasidic thought the Shofar is God speaking through us.</p></blockquote>
<p>I read Fishbane’s book a year ago which was billed as the first major theological work in a generation. In the year, it has not generated much review except for pre-publication review by David Novak in First Things, which focused on Novak’s pet themes “why didn’t he engage Christianity and particularism more?” What not more the pure monotheism of Herman Cohen and how to avoid polytheism?” And to his chagrin Novak had to conclude that Fishbane is about God-Talk and awakening people to theology.</p>
<p>Since God talk and theology is my thing. I may write a review and this may help determine if I do.</p>
<p>As some first thoughts:</p>
<p>1] Fishbane seems to return the technical Kabbalah to Buber and Heschel. He assumes that his reader/listener knows the terms awakening from below (itaruta delitata) inner light (or penimi), Pardes, devekut, hokhmah, binah. He assumes that the current cannon includes required academic courses in an intro to the Zohar and an intro to Hasidut.</p>
<p>2] The minyan has gotten used to his talks. But the first times he spoke the questions afterwards reflected a more Lutheran inspired modern Orthodoxy. “We confront God and then recoil.” “We follow the law and do not have God directly in our lives”.We cannot trust the self”  “The experience of God can only be know though the normative law.“ Fishbane is comfortable with direct God talk and as a once born optimist he does not have the dark side of the twice born.</p>
<p>3] He assumes that everyone is looking to get in touch with themselves. Most people are not. He also assumes that his audience is transparent and psychologically aware in their religious lives. For Fishbane, the problem is habit not lack of reflection, denial, or placing the onus on the community.</p>
<p>4]  Fishbane calls Halacha as &#8220;the gestures of the generations,&#8221;  and thinks we need to avoid &#8220;spiritual plagiarism.&#8221;</p>
<p>He develops Scholem’s idea of Torah as organism into <strong>Torah kelulah</strong>: God&#8217;s ongoing presence. We have an opening to receive God’s word in everything if we are &#8220;attuned&#8221; to it.  The fullness of Torah Kelulah is unsayable.  What he calls the &#8220;Torah Kelulah&#8221; is a caesural opening in which God&#8217;s creative power issues forth into a manifest universe that includes a system of natural law and the moral reality of human existence. It is the &#8220;kiss of divine truth on the vastness of world-being.&#8221;</p>
<p>The Written Torah. Scripture. Is the &#8220;unsayable.”.<br />
<strong>Torah she-be&#8217;al peh</strong>: the Oral Torah. This is the ongoing expression and development of the Written Torah  Religious life is not prayer or interpersonal relations as it was for Heschel and Buber, but religious life is in Torah study as reflected, imbibed, and present in the self. This process includes interiorization, centering, and silence</p>
<p>This seems to be a Heidegger influenced view of revelation. (It needs to be compared to Rahner’s mystical use of Heidegger.) Heidegger wites:</p>
<blockquote><p>[T]o exist as Da-sein means to hold open a domain through its capacity to receive-perceive the significance of things that are given to it and that address it by virtue of its own &#8220;clearing&#8221;. <em>Zollikon Seminars</em>, 4/H4.<strong> </strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p>One of Fishbane’s students has already used a pre-publication draft to apply the theory &#8220;to<strong> </strong>Jewish education, particularly with respect to the characterization, development, and reinforcement of theological dispositions.&#8221; Daniel <em><em>Marom</em></em> Journal of Jewish Education, Volume 74, Issue s1 2008 , pages 29 &#8211; 51 I have not read the article yet.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/21/sacred-attunments-part-1/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
