<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Paul Griffiths on Death	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/08/paul-griffiths-on-death/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/08/paul-griffiths-on-death/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Jun 2010 23:21:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: rabbichaplain		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/08/paul-griffiths-on-death/#comment-1163</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[rabbichaplain]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 13 Jun 2010 23:21:54 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1491#comment-1163</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I think people are ready to hear these thoughts of Paul Griffiths and in the current cultural climate of debating health care spending, perhaps his words are crucial.  We need to always remember that it is a tricky balance between embracing life and embracing death. We all want to live as long as possible, but wish and hope that our current physical lives are qualitatively good as well.  

In terms of a Jewish art of dying, I think we are challenged to reexplore the texts you make mention of in your post.  Most Jewish people are unfamiliar with works like Maavar Yaaboq and of those who are familiar, there is still the challenge of incorporating a 16th century mystical death journey into our 21st century consciousness.  

Having said that, working in the field of chaplaincy, it is the works of our mystics that often get lost and when it comes time to people dying, there is little that can be said about the journey of the soul for most were never even brought up to believe in an afterlife.  I think we need people to bring to the forefront these issues in the Jewish community for it gives people a hope for something more than life itself.  Sure, much of the descriptions of a Jewish afterlife include punishment and suffering along the way, but I think even that people would be willing to hear.  I cannot begin to count the number of times I have heard from Jewish people who are dying &quot;do we believe in an afterlife?&quot;  My favorite of those was the words of one surviving family member who said, &quot;I envy Catholics for they have an afterlife.&quot;  It is very disheartening.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think people are ready to hear these thoughts of Paul Griffiths and in the current cultural climate of debating health care spending, perhaps his words are crucial.  We need to always remember that it is a tricky balance between embracing life and embracing death. We all want to live as long as possible, but wish and hope that our current physical lives are qualitatively good as well.  </p>
<p>In terms of a Jewish art of dying, I think we are challenged to reexplore the texts you make mention of in your post.  Most Jewish people are unfamiliar with works like Maavar Yaaboq and of those who are familiar, there is still the challenge of incorporating a 16th century mystical death journey into our 21st century consciousness.  </p>
<p>Having said that, working in the field of chaplaincy, it is the works of our mystics that often get lost and when it comes time to people dying, there is little that can be said about the journey of the soul for most were never even brought up to believe in an afterlife.  I think we need people to bring to the forefront these issues in the Jewish community for it gives people a hope for something more than life itself.  Sure, much of the descriptions of a Jewish afterlife include punishment and suffering along the way, but I think even that people would be willing to hear.  I cannot begin to count the number of times I have heard from Jewish people who are dying &#8220;do we believe in an afterlife?&#8221;  My favorite of those was the words of one surviving family member who said, &#8220;I envy Catholics for they have an afterlife.&#8221;  It is very disheartening.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: H Sragow		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/08/paul-griffiths-on-death/#comment-1147</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[H Sragow]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Jun 2010 11:57:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1491#comment-1147</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The world may not yet be ready for these thoughts.  

Awareness of our lack of control  over death supports the human ability (or perhaps, necessity) to confront it.  Refinement of medical practices and technology over the last century or so, however, has produced steady advances in our ability to avoid death.  The physician, rather than the clergyman, has become the expert consulted at the time of death.  And that expert is usually saying &quot;we can control death if we try a little harder&quot; (at least in the long  term).

As medical progress slows, it is becoming more obvious what medicine can cure, and what it cannot (e.g., pancreatic cancer is rarely curable).  This enables the medical expert to feel more comfortable saying &quot;Death is coming,&quot; and stepping aside so that other practices can begin.  Perhaps this is why hospice care has started growing, but hospice is still the exception rather than the norm.

I suspect several more decades of medical stagnation and frustration will be necessary before we become more comfortable institutionally confronting death, and creating useful ceremony for it (rather than just cleaning up the mess afterward).]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The world may not yet be ready for these thoughts.  </p>
<p>Awareness of our lack of control  over death supports the human ability (or perhaps, necessity) to confront it.  Refinement of medical practices and technology over the last century or so, however, has produced steady advances in our ability to avoid death.  The physician, rather than the clergyman, has become the expert consulted at the time of death.  And that expert is usually saying &#8220;we can control death if we try a little harder&#8221; (at least in the long  term).</p>
<p>As medical progress slows, it is becoming more obvious what medicine can cure, and what it cannot (e.g., pancreatic cancer is rarely curable).  This enables the medical expert to feel more comfortable saying &#8220;Death is coming,&#8221; and stepping aside so that other practices can begin.  Perhaps this is why hospice care has started growing, but hospice is still the exception rather than the norm.</p>
<p>I suspect several more decades of medical stagnation and frustration will be necessary before we become more comfortable institutionally confronting death, and creating useful ceremony for it (rather than just cleaning up the mess afterward).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Mordechai Y. Scher		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/08/paul-griffiths-on-death/#comment-1143</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mordechai Y. Scher]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Jun 2010 03:50:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1491#comment-1143</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Seems comparable to the narrative about Rebi&#039;s death.  Nicely put.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Seems comparable to the narrative about Rebi&#8217;s death.  Nicely put.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
