<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Dictatorship of Relativism	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/13/dictatorship-of-relativism/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/13/dictatorship-of-relativism/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Jul 2010 22:08:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/13/dictatorship-of-relativism/#comment-1331</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 16 Jul 2010 22:08:14 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1671#comment-1331</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&lt;em&gt;And what does it say about us that we tolerate them,&lt;/em&gt;

The circular answer may be that we crave absolutes, truths, God given-ness, and solutions.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>And what does it say about us that we tolerate them,</em></p>
<p>The circular answer may be that we crave absolutes, truths, God given-ness, and solutions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Larry Yudelson		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/13/dictatorship-of-relativism/#comment-1330</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Larry Yudelson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 16 Jul 2010 21:32:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1671#comment-1330</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Was the Catholic Church&#039;s preference of Naziism over Communism an absolute moral choice, or a relative moral choice?

Ratzinger uses the language of absolutism to convince his &lt;strike&gt;shills&lt;/strike&gt; followers that he represents some absolute, God-given truth... when in fact, the Church has shifted in the moral winds as much as any other institution.

What is it with these traditionalists and their desire for man-on-man action, anyway? Why catholic priests and orthodox rabbis so convinced that God hates ordaining women but tolerates molesting little boys? And what does it say about us that we tolerate them, and allow them to sully our discourse with their perverted and depraved desires?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Was the Catholic Church&#8217;s preference of Naziism over Communism an absolute moral choice, or a relative moral choice?</p>
<p>Ratzinger uses the language of absolutism to convince his <strike>shills</strike> followers that he represents some absolute, God-given truth&#8230; when in fact, the Church has shifted in the moral winds as much as any other institution.</p>
<p>What is it with these traditionalists and their desire for man-on-man action, anyway? Why catholic priests and orthodox rabbis so convinced that God hates ordaining women but tolerates molesting little boys? And what does it say about us that we tolerate them, and allow them to sully our discourse with their perverted and depraved desires?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Kevin Rothman		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/13/dictatorship-of-relativism/#comment-1328</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kevin Rothman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 16 Jul 2010 01:41:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1671#comment-1328</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I just don&#039;t see it that way.  You quoted:

&quot;Sadly, to my way of thinking, since there’s so much that’s rich and important in Catholic moral theology, the Church has transformed itself into a
kind of fertility cult, so that what it really cares about now is making sure that you know men aren’t having sex with men and nobody’s having abortions and there are no condoms in the JCR around the corner here and that there aren’t any divorce&quot;

I see this as less of a &quot;why do you guys find our moral instinct lacking&quot;, i.e. something fundamentally defensive in nature and more of an indictment of the church itself, an offensive... its degeneration into the very sort of moral bankruptcy you agree an exclusive focus on ritual concerns over human (ritual) ones entails.  

 It may be that as an individual Green, despite the larger implications of his argument, believes simply as you interpret him (though i think he intended more).  This, however, would then be a rather petty complaint and dealing with it on this level only shares therein.  I think it wiser to take him up as having offered a meaningful critique of (a) contemporary religious institution(s) that warrants self-accounting... this way the debate remains productive]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I just don&#8217;t see it that way.  You quoted:</p>
<p>&#8220;Sadly, to my way of thinking, since there’s so much that’s rich and important in Catholic moral theology, the Church has transformed itself into a<br />
kind of fertility cult, so that what it really cares about now is making sure that you know men aren’t having sex with men and nobody’s having abortions and there are no condoms in the JCR around the corner here and that there aren’t any divorce&#8221;</p>
<p>I see this as less of a &#8220;why do you guys find our moral instinct lacking&#8221;, i.e. something fundamentally defensive in nature and more of an indictment of the church itself, an offensive&#8230; its degeneration into the very sort of moral bankruptcy you agree an exclusive focus on ritual concerns over human (ritual) ones entails.  </p>
<p> It may be that as an individual Green, despite the larger implications of his argument, believes simply as you interpret him (though i think he intended more).  This, however, would then be a rather petty complaint and dealing with it on this level only shares therein.  I think it wiser to take him up as having offered a meaningful critique of (a) contemporary religious institution(s) that warrants self-accounting&#8230; this way the debate remains productive</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Arie Folger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/13/dictatorship-of-relativism/#comment-1327</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arie Folger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Jul 2010 23:11:51 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1671#comment-1327</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/13/dictatorship-of-relativism/#comment-1326&quot;&gt;Kevin Rothman&lt;/a&gt;.

I agree. The lack of differentiation between ethics and morals in Judaism indeed elevates the interpersonal to be ritual, as well, and sometimes more. But I don&#039;t see Green criticizing the church for failing to take human rights seriously. He rather lambasted it for taking issue with the moral relativism of the modern West, hence my comment. I don&#039;t think Green was asking &quot;how worthy are the exhortations to sexual purity uttered with eyes closed to suffering.&quot; I rather think he was asking, very much like a Reform rabbi may do to an Orthodox Jew, &quot;why do you guys find our moral instinct lacking, after all, we have morals, too.&quot;]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/13/dictatorship-of-relativism/#comment-1326">Kevin Rothman</a>.</p>
<p>I agree. The lack of differentiation between ethics and morals in Judaism indeed elevates the interpersonal to be ritual, as well, and sometimes more. But I don&#8217;t see Green criticizing the church for failing to take human rights seriously. He rather lambasted it for taking issue with the moral relativism of the modern West, hence my comment. I don&#8217;t think Green was asking &#8220;how worthy are the exhortations to sexual purity uttered with eyes closed to suffering.&#8221; I rather think he was asking, very much like a Reform rabbi may do to an Orthodox Jew, &#8220;why do you guys find our moral instinct lacking, after all, we have morals, too.&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Kevin Rothman		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/13/dictatorship-of-relativism/#comment-1326</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kevin Rothman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Jul 2010 23:03:29 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1671#comment-1326</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Mr. (Rabbi?) Folger - 

I think you are correct that Judaism does not necessarily distinguish between morality and ethics in the sense of a difference between ritual crime and interpersonal crime (though, in refraining from making such a decision, I suppose interpersonal crime would take on a ritual status) would not this very lack of differentiation constitute a call for as much vigilance with respect to matters of human rights as with respect to matters of sexual morals?  If the Church or Judaism or Islam were then to devote near exclusive attention to the latter would this not denote a certain moral bankruptcy (not only in having ignored the former but, in having done so, within the latter itself)?  I think it is less a matter of condoning the breakdown of sexual, or any other, taboo and more a matter of a legitimate critique: how worthy are the exhortations to sexual purity uttered with eyes closed to suffering?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Mr. (Rabbi?) Folger &#8211; </p>
<p>I think you are correct that Judaism does not necessarily distinguish between morality and ethics in the sense of a difference between ritual crime and interpersonal crime (though, in refraining from making such a decision, I suppose interpersonal crime would take on a ritual status) would not this very lack of differentiation constitute a call for as much vigilance with respect to matters of human rights as with respect to matters of sexual morals?  If the Church or Judaism or Islam were then to devote near exclusive attention to the latter would this not denote a certain moral bankruptcy (not only in having ignored the former but, in having done so, within the latter itself)?  I think it is less a matter of condoning the breakdown of sexual, or any other, taboo and more a matter of a legitimate critique: how worthy are the exhortations to sexual purity uttered with eyes closed to suffering?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Arie Folger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/13/dictatorship-of-relativism/#comment-1323</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arie Folger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Jul 2010 05:22:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1671#comment-1323</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/13/dictatorship-of-relativism/#comment-1317&quot;&gt;AS&lt;/a&gt;.

The difference between ethics and morals is not a religious difference, but a modern one. Religiously, one cannot claim that theft or armed robbery is really bad, but regarding idol worship or adultery live and let live. Judaism doesn&#039;t argue for such a position, Christianity doesn&#039;t, and I believe Islam doesn&#039;t either. However, Green argues:
&lt;blockquote&gt;Sadly, to my way of thinking, since there’s so much that’s rich and important in Catholic moral theology, the Church has transformed itself into a
kind of fertility cult, so that what it really cares about now is making sure that you know men aren’t having sex with men and nobody’s having abortions and there are no condoms in the JCR around the corner here and that there aren’t any divorces.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Green argues against sexual taboos. Then he does a double take and reminds us that even very liberal societies have sexual taboos, but only musters an example where violence is a major factor. That is as much as saying that as long as consenting peers are not hurting anyone without consent, their sexual behavior should be condoned, a typical libertarian position. By inference, Green is really arguing against all sexual taboos. And in the process, he also implies a differentiation between ethics and morals, because he has no use for morals, i.e. for taboos where no one gets physically, financially or emotionally hurt (to the exclusion of spiritual damage, which he does not seem to recognize).

You are right that the existence of laws against non-reproductive consensual incest shows that societies do maintain taboos, but that only shows that society doesn&#039;t follow Green&#039;s line. Ditto for laws against polygamy. Had Green argued for maintaining those laws, now then you would have had an argument.

PS: in all fairness, statutory rape and bestiality do not belong in this list. Bestiality is seen by some as being unconscionable because the animal didn&#039;t consent (not my view, but libertarians who argue against bestiality do make this argument), and statutory rape is a legal curiosity, a bug, not a feature, which results from the legislator&#039;s desire to protect minors who are still vulnerable, easily taken advantage of and not always consenting.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/13/dictatorship-of-relativism/#comment-1317">AS</a>.</p>
<p>The difference between ethics and morals is not a religious difference, but a modern one. Religiously, one cannot claim that theft or armed robbery is really bad, but regarding idol worship or adultery live and let live. Judaism doesn&#8217;t argue for such a position, Christianity doesn&#8217;t, and I believe Islam doesn&#8217;t either. However, Green argues:</p>
<blockquote><p>Sadly, to my way of thinking, since there’s so much that’s rich and important in Catholic moral theology, the Church has transformed itself into a<br />
kind of fertility cult, so that what it really cares about now is making sure that you know men aren’t having sex with men and nobody’s having abortions and there are no condoms in the JCR around the corner here and that there aren’t any divorces.</p></blockquote>
<p>Green argues against sexual taboos. Then he does a double take and reminds us that even very liberal societies have sexual taboos, but only musters an example where violence is a major factor. That is as much as saying that as long as consenting peers are not hurting anyone without consent, their sexual behavior should be condoned, a typical libertarian position. By inference, Green is really arguing against all sexual taboos. And in the process, he also implies a differentiation between ethics and morals, because he has no use for morals, i.e. for taboos where no one gets physically, financially or emotionally hurt (to the exclusion of spiritual damage, which he does not seem to recognize).</p>
<p>You are right that the existence of laws against non-reproductive consensual incest shows that societies do maintain taboos, but that only shows that society doesn&#8217;t follow Green&#8217;s line. Ditto for laws against polygamy. Had Green argued for maintaining those laws, now then you would have had an argument.</p>
<p>PS: in all fairness, statutory rape and bestiality do not belong in this list. Bestiality is seen by some as being unconscionable because the animal didn&#8217;t consent (not my view, but libertarians who argue against bestiality do make this argument), and statutory rape is a legal curiosity, a bug, not a feature, which results from the legislator&#8217;s desire to protect minors who are still vulnerable, easily taken advantage of and not always consenting.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/13/dictatorship-of-relativism/#comment-1317</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2010 17:17:20 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1671#comment-1317</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/13/dictatorship-of-relativism/#comment-1315&quot;&gt;Arie Folger&lt;/a&gt;.

Green says that in Western culture it is not the case that everything goes and then proceeds to use the example of rape. You calim that this example is fallacious because rape is only wrong because it forces someone to do something that &quot;she&quot; (are only women raped?) abhors.

First, you have not identified any fallacy becasue Green&#039;s point is that &quot;not everything goes&quot; and that there are universally recognized ethical norms. Second, the distinction between ethics and morals perhaps relies on a quasi antiquated usage of the terms, but is not used today, so I&#039;m not sure what you are trying to convey. The idea of &quot;sexual morality&quot; is not confined to &quot;moralizing about sexuality&quot;, which appears to be what you mean.   Finally, there certainly are &quot;taboos&quot; that are alive and well today. Incest is illegal, even between consenting adult siblings who are not going to procreate, and generally abhorred, as is polygamy, bestiality, and statutory rape among others.  Green does not appear opposed to these taboos so I&#039;m not sure how your claim that he, and secular society in general are opposed to taboos is supported by anything he wrote.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/13/dictatorship-of-relativism/#comment-1315">Arie Folger</a>.</p>
<p>Green says that in Western culture it is not the case that everything goes and then proceeds to use the example of rape. You calim that this example is fallacious because rape is only wrong because it forces someone to do something that &#8220;she&#8221; (are only women raped?) abhors.</p>
<p>First, you have not identified any fallacy becasue Green&#8217;s point is that &#8220;not everything goes&#8221; and that there are universally recognized ethical norms. Second, the distinction between ethics and morals perhaps relies on a quasi antiquated usage of the terms, but is not used today, so I&#8217;m not sure what you are trying to convey. The idea of &#8220;sexual morality&#8221; is not confined to &#8220;moralizing about sexuality&#8221;, which appears to be what you mean.   Finally, there certainly are &#8220;taboos&#8221; that are alive and well today. Incest is illegal, even between consenting adult siblings who are not going to procreate, and generally abhorred, as is polygamy, bestiality, and statutory rape among others.  Green does not appear opposed to these taboos so I&#8217;m not sure how your claim that he, and secular society in general are opposed to taboos is supported by anything he wrote.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Kevin Rothman		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/13/dictatorship-of-relativism/#comment-1316</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kevin Rothman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2010 13:12:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1671#comment-1316</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[i agree with AS that the question of relativism extends both to the right and to the left.  ultimately one, and more importantly to the discussion, society, must take a stance if only for pragmatic purposes.  The standard of measure being public welfare.  The problem, as I see it, is that the church is in the business not of fighting moral relativism, but of fighting a very specific sort of moral relativism.  That is, the ritual aspects of its morality (eg. opposition to homosexuality) that have no bearing on public welfare.  This type of concern is the church&#039;s overwhelming concern.  There was recently an article in the NY Times on the Pope describing his career: though he was in a position to take an active and positive role in the pedophilia scandals when they first began emerging, he, instead, whiled away his time and energy opposing liberation theology in south america... a theology aimed at protecting the rights of the poor and disempowered... i.e. a theology that concerns itself with resolving much larger moral and ethical problems.  This is also moral relativism, just of a sort that favors the narrow concerns of the church.  

I think the real challenge for religious people today is in the retaking of human rights as a properly religious interest... instead of remaining indifferent to them by regarding religion in purely ritual/ritualistic terms.  Is this not the constant message of the neviim?  I am not saying ritual or ritualistic morality is worthless, but I am saying that focusing on this to the exclusion of those concerns that secular society has taken up is, in my opinion, a grave mistake, and, quite a blatant and problematic form of relativism.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>i agree with AS that the question of relativism extends both to the right and to the left.  ultimately one, and more importantly to the discussion, society, must take a stance if only for pragmatic purposes.  The standard of measure being public welfare.  The problem, as I see it, is that the church is in the business not of fighting moral relativism, but of fighting a very specific sort of moral relativism.  That is, the ritual aspects of its morality (eg. opposition to homosexuality) that have no bearing on public welfare.  This type of concern is the church&#8217;s overwhelming concern.  There was recently an article in the NY Times on the Pope describing his career: though he was in a position to take an active and positive role in the pedophilia scandals when they first began emerging, he, instead, whiled away his time and energy opposing liberation theology in south america&#8230; a theology aimed at protecting the rights of the poor and disempowered&#8230; i.e. a theology that concerns itself with resolving much larger moral and ethical problems.  This is also moral relativism, just of a sort that favors the narrow concerns of the church.  </p>
<p>I think the real challenge for religious people today is in the retaking of human rights as a properly religious interest&#8230; instead of remaining indifferent to them by regarding religion in purely ritual/ritualistic terms.  Is this not the constant message of the neviim?  I am not saying ritual or ritualistic morality is worthless, but I am saying that focusing on this to the exclusion of those concerns that secular society has taken up is, in my opinion, a grave mistake, and, quite a blatant and problematic form of relativism.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Arie Folger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/13/dictatorship-of-relativism/#comment-1315</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arie Folger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2010 11:36:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1671#comment-1315</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Green is every bit as intolerant as whoever he tries to criticize.

And his statement that even in the secular West it is not true that anything goes, is a fallacy, as his example of a sexuality taboo in Western society, rape, is not really a sexual taboo. The reason why he is wrong is that rape isn&#039;t about sexual morality, per se, but about forcing another human being into an act she utterly abhors. That is rather a matter of ethics, not morals.

IOW, Green confirms that relativistic secular society is opposed to any taboos. The measure in which actual societies are not as permissive as Green may like reflects the fact that not all citizens buy into secular relativism.

And what would be wrong about sacrificing a ram every month? How about suggesting doing it at the new moon, rather than the full moon? In Jerusalem, you know, on the sacred esplanade?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Green is every bit as intolerant as whoever he tries to criticize.</p>
<p>And his statement that even in the secular West it is not true that anything goes, is a fallacy, as his example of a sexuality taboo in Western society, rape, is not really a sexual taboo. The reason why he is wrong is that rape isn&#8217;t about sexual morality, per se, but about forcing another human being into an act she utterly abhors. That is rather a matter of ethics, not morals.</p>
<p>IOW, Green confirms that relativistic secular society is opposed to any taboos. The measure in which actual societies are not as permissive as Green may like reflects the fact that not all citizens buy into secular relativism.</p>
<p>And what would be wrong about sacrificing a ram every month? How about suggesting doing it at the new moon, rather than the full moon? In Jerusalem, you know, on the sacred esplanade?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/13/dictatorship-of-relativism/#comment-1313</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2010 11:00:14 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1671#comment-1313</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It&#039;s definitely true that the term &#039;relativism&#039; is thrown around by those who have some notion of divine-command morality (or a theological conception of natural law) as shorthand for &quot;what inevitably happens to morality in the absence of faith.&quot; However, if you think about it, if that is the real fear, then the term that they should be using is moral anarchism, not relativism. Relativism is the belief that different groups functioning autonomously from one another can adopt different moral norms, and that neither group is justified (within certain bounds) in critiquing the others&#039; norms. 

The misuse of the term relativism may reflect their own insecurity in the midt of democratic majoritarian societies that sometimes do and sometimes do not allow individual minority communities to adopt practices that are out of line with mainstream social practices. The beneficiaries of relativism then are really the religious and ethnic groups that deviate from the norms of the majority. But depending on the political context, their security in this dispensation can be precarious. 

Fear of relativism is then the fear that liberals have in allowing minority groups to function in part with non-democratic and non-egalitarian norms.

So everyone it seems is afraid of &#039;relativism&#039;, they just mean different things.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It&#8217;s definitely true that the term &#8216;relativism&#8217; is thrown around by those who have some notion of divine-command morality (or a theological conception of natural law) as shorthand for &#8220;what inevitably happens to morality in the absence of faith.&#8221; However, if you think about it, if that is the real fear, then the term that they should be using is moral anarchism, not relativism. Relativism is the belief that different groups functioning autonomously from one another can adopt different moral norms, and that neither group is justified (within certain bounds) in critiquing the others&#8217; norms. </p>
<p>The misuse of the term relativism may reflect their own insecurity in the midt of democratic majoritarian societies that sometimes do and sometimes do not allow individual minority communities to adopt practices that are out of line with mainstream social practices. The beneficiaries of relativism then are really the religious and ethnic groups that deviate from the norms of the majority. But depending on the political context, their security in this dispensation can be precarious. </p>
<p>Fear of relativism is then the fear that liberals have in allowing minority groups to function in part with non-democratic and non-egalitarian norms.</p>
<p>So everyone it seems is afraid of &#8216;relativism&#8217;, they just mean different things.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
