<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: An interview with Prof Zachary J. Braiterman	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/13/an-interview-with-prof-zachary-j-braiterman/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/13/an-interview-with-prof-zachary-j-braiterman/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2011 03:42:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: zachary braiterman		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/13/an-interview-with-prof-zachary-j-braiterman/#comment-2969</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[zachary braiterman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2011 03:42:54 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3441#comment-2969</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/13/an-interview-with-prof-zachary-j-braiterman/#comment-2966&quot;&gt;Alan Brill&lt;/a&gt;.

Without wanting to turn this into a private conversation, let me say that I agree almost 100% with Alan against the Buber-Rosenzweig conception of religious revelation. 

A not so quick caveat: the Buber-Rosenzweig conception of revelation would include as well Benjamin&#039;s conception of revolution --the way in which new art (for Benjamin, this was surrealism and film) serves to shock consciousness out of received encrusted habits and into new revolutionary directions. It would also include Adorno&#039;s conception of abstract art as a kind of otherworldy form of sensation that doubles back to secure criticism of the established social order. 

But yes, Alan is right. Instead of revelation ala Buber-Rosenzweig and Rudolf Otto, Alan&#039;s desciption of Passover preparations in his neighborhood has a Geertzian feel of a &quot;thick description.&quot; It is one that resonates with Marx and Gramsci on ideology, hegemony, and fetishism. This to me sounds more correct in terms of getting at lived quotidian forms of religious experience.

Somewhere, though, I would still want to argue that the Buber-Rosenzweig-Benjaminian notion of revelation and revolution as profound, demanding spiritual realization and reorientation still counts for something and makes sense for some people at some moment in their lives. I can only speak for myself.

Look, maybe I&#039;m old fashioned. I really don&#039;t know. I&#039;m just about to turn 48. I grew up in Habonim in the mid to late 1970s, still under the star that old modernist paradigm filtered through the Grateful Dead, Jefferson Airplane and all that; not to mention Spinoza, Nietzsche, and I.B. Singer. So no, I don&#039;t fully trust myself and neither should anyone else. I am what I am. 

I just wonder how these things play out for younger people whose experience of things (be they secular or frum) is more seamless and integrated; or for even younger people who may soon be entering into a much less settled, less secure, and more disjointed social environment.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/13/an-interview-with-prof-zachary-j-braiterman/#comment-2966">Alan Brill</a>.</p>
<p>Without wanting to turn this into a private conversation, let me say that I agree almost 100% with Alan against the Buber-Rosenzweig conception of religious revelation. </p>
<p>A not so quick caveat: the Buber-Rosenzweig conception of revelation would include as well Benjamin&#8217;s conception of revolution &#8211;the way in which new art (for Benjamin, this was surrealism and film) serves to shock consciousness out of received encrusted habits and into new revolutionary directions. It would also include Adorno&#8217;s conception of abstract art as a kind of otherworldy form of sensation that doubles back to secure criticism of the established social order. </p>
<p>But yes, Alan is right. Instead of revelation ala Buber-Rosenzweig and Rudolf Otto, Alan&#8217;s desciption of Passover preparations in his neighborhood has a Geertzian feel of a &#8220;thick description.&#8221; It is one that resonates with Marx and Gramsci on ideology, hegemony, and fetishism. This to me sounds more correct in terms of getting at lived quotidian forms of religious experience.</p>
<p>Somewhere, though, I would still want to argue that the Buber-Rosenzweig-Benjaminian notion of revelation and revolution as profound, demanding spiritual realization and reorientation still counts for something and makes sense for some people at some moment in their lives. I can only speak for myself.</p>
<p>Look, maybe I&#8217;m old fashioned. I really don&#8217;t know. I&#8217;m just about to turn 48. I grew up in Habonim in the mid to late 1970s, still under the star that old modernist paradigm filtered through the Grateful Dead, Jefferson Airplane and all that; not to mention Spinoza, Nietzsche, and I.B. Singer. So no, I don&#8217;t fully trust myself and neither should anyone else. I am what I am. </p>
<p>I just wonder how these things play out for younger people whose experience of things (be they secular or frum) is more seamless and integrated; or for even younger people who may soon be entering into a much less settled, less secure, and more disjointed social environment.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/13/an-interview-with-prof-zachary-j-braiterman/#comment-2966</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 17 Apr 2011 02:22:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3441#comment-2966</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[ZJB- I think that EJ is onto something with his Benjamin-Adorno comment. 
As I watch my enclave prepare for the holiday, I get a sense that it would be perfect for a Walter Benjamin Archives Project. Much of Orthodoxy makes itself know in the desires of the market, the political, the interpellation, and the culture of production.  I go into the take out store on Friday and the owner frames passover in terms of Israeli politics, I go to other stores and see the selling of mass produced reproductions- even a &quot;Jerusalem stone&quot; store. Orthodoxy may have more to do with culture in the Benjamin sense than religious experience in the Buber-Rosenzweig sense. To be part of orthodox relgion is to buy into a set of desires and attitudes and thereby commercial products.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ZJB- I think that EJ is onto something with his Benjamin-Adorno comment.<br />
As I watch my enclave prepare for the holiday, I get a sense that it would be perfect for a Walter Benjamin Archives Project. Much of Orthodoxy makes itself know in the desires of the market, the political, the interpellation, and the culture of production.  I go into the take out store on Friday and the owner frames passover in terms of Israeli politics, I go to other stores and see the selling of mass produced reproductions- even a &#8220;Jerusalem stone&#8221; store. Orthodoxy may have more to do with culture in the Benjamin sense than religious experience in the Buber-Rosenzweig sense. To be part of orthodox relgion is to buy into a set of desires and attitudes and thereby commercial products.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ZJB		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/13/an-interview-with-prof-zachary-j-braiterman/#comment-2962</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ZJB]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2011 04:32:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3441#comment-2962</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I’ll try to provide something of an answer to the probing questions by AS, Alan Brill, and ej. I’m hope I can do them justice. . My responses are introduced by my intitials &quot;ZJB.&quot;

1) AS &#124; April 14, 2011 at 12:15 pm &#124; Reply 
ZJB: I think AS is right, but this is going to get complicated. [1] I would submit that a lot of high art,  seeks to find its place in the everyday world (Cubism, Dada, American straight photography, Bauhaus, Pop Art, Conceptual Art, etc.). So high art tries to take its stance in the real world of objects and social relations. Sometimes it works, sometimes it doesn’t. In general, there is always the danger that high art will tend to drown out more everyday aesthetic experience. Avant-garde art always seeks to break down the line separating high art and everyday life, always by means of...more art. This is why I find myself un-persuaded by avant-gardist criticism (Peter Burger, Hal Foster, Slavoy Zizek). I prefer and find much less pretentious the old art-for-art’s sake notion of art, because it proponents understood that art is something in particular and that not everything is art. 

AS is therefore also right to say that [2] the concepts tend to get dull when everything is reduced to “aesthetics.” (I’d say the same thing about ethics.) This is where the Venn diagram comes in handy. There are vast areas of overlap between aesthetics, art, and religion, without them actually constituting each other. But having recognized that in theory, we run the danger that in practice we will have done precisely just that. I run this risk in my own thinking. About this I can only trust my judgment, understanding that legal, political, and ethical phenomena do not easily lend themselves to reductionist aesthetic analysis. The mundane realia of political life and law and the experience of catastrophic suffering are two good examples. As a general rule, theorists of whatever stripe (law, ethics, art)  always need to rely on the criticism of others to call them out as to their own overreaching. This should not be too complicated. Take for example my own work. If a critic like AS reads it and finds it interesting, then perhaps I have done my job responsibly. 

2) Alan Brill &#124; April 14, 2011 at 12:30 pm &#124; Reply 
ZJB: To be honest, I never understood God, Man, and History in the sense that I was never able to get a critical handle on it. I think the passage cited by Alan is both overwritten and underwhelming. Buber made the same point much more succinctly in I and Thou (something along the lines of  “I am nothing/everything depends on me”). Much of it sounds like Buber-Rosenzweig. In With God in Hell, Berkovits even mentions the God-human relation as an I-Thou. So there is definitely an influence. But it seems all too vaguely “sublime” in the technical sense intended by Kant. First the moment which shatters the human person and human understanding, and then the second moment in which human subjectivity is recouped. It’s also, perhaps not “interesting” in the sense intended by AS in his critique above. Is there anything specifically orthodox here? Probably not. So maybe that’s the interesting point. An orthodox conception of revelation that is, in the end, not too terribly orthodox.

3) ej &#124; April 14, 2011 at 5:38 pm &#124; Reply 

ZJB: I don’t think the Buber-Rosenzweig project was as individualistic as the romantic-Emersonian-Nietzschean one. While I think both Buber and Rosenzweig were both egotists of the highest order, they actually wrote very little about cultivating their own sense of personhood. This is a modernist sensibility perhaps, this anti-subjectivist impulse. The subject that Buber-Rosenzeweig wanted to cultivate and deepen was “Judaism,” which they viewed in the light of revelation, not as a one-time event, but as God’s ongoing presence in the world. Rosenzweig was drawn to mitzvot, Buber to other types of living Jewish form. 

As for religious life in a secular society with many different ends and with AS’s comment in mind, I’d only say that religious ends remain religious ends. There is at least one end in religion that I think is unique to western religion: closeness to God, cleaving to God, being with God.  While this end is correlate to other ends (political, ethical, aesthetic), they are not substitutable with these other ends. That’s why I think the Buber-Rosenzweig legacy is the supreme legacy of German Judaism...for understanding Judaism and for religion, not for understanding political theory. If Lukacs, Benjamin, and Adorno help us think about religion, they do so from the side. In an ideal world, all these different ends (political, religious, aesthetic) would sustain and deepen each other; and maybe they sometimes do, even in our own imperfect world.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’ll try to provide something of an answer to the probing questions by AS, Alan Brill, and ej. I’m hope I can do them justice. . My responses are introduced by my intitials &#8220;ZJB.&#8221;</p>
<p>1) AS | April 14, 2011 at 12:15 pm | Reply<br />
ZJB: I think AS is right, but this is going to get complicated. [1] I would submit that a lot of high art,  seeks to find its place in the everyday world (Cubism, Dada, American straight photography, Bauhaus, Pop Art, Conceptual Art, etc.). So high art tries to take its stance in the real world of objects and social relations. Sometimes it works, sometimes it doesn’t. In general, there is always the danger that high art will tend to drown out more everyday aesthetic experience. Avant-garde art always seeks to break down the line separating high art and everyday life, always by means of&#8230;more art. This is why I find myself un-persuaded by avant-gardist criticism (Peter Burger, Hal Foster, Slavoy Zizek). I prefer and find much less pretentious the old art-for-art’s sake notion of art, because it proponents understood that art is something in particular and that not everything is art. </p>
<p>AS is therefore also right to say that [2] the concepts tend to get dull when everything is reduced to “aesthetics.” (I’d say the same thing about ethics.) This is where the Venn diagram comes in handy. There are vast areas of overlap between aesthetics, art, and religion, without them actually constituting each other. But having recognized that in theory, we run the danger that in practice we will have done precisely just that. I run this risk in my own thinking. About this I can only trust my judgment, understanding that legal, political, and ethical phenomena do not easily lend themselves to reductionist aesthetic analysis. The mundane realia of political life and law and the experience of catastrophic suffering are two good examples. As a general rule, theorists of whatever stripe (law, ethics, art)  always need to rely on the criticism of others to call them out as to their own overreaching. This should not be too complicated. Take for example my own work. If a critic like AS reads it and finds it interesting, then perhaps I have done my job responsibly. </p>
<p>2) Alan Brill | April 14, 2011 at 12:30 pm | Reply<br />
ZJB: To be honest, I never understood God, Man, and History in the sense that I was never able to get a critical handle on it. I think the passage cited by Alan is both overwritten and underwhelming. Buber made the same point much more succinctly in I and Thou (something along the lines of  “I am nothing/everything depends on me”). Much of it sounds like Buber-Rosenzweig. In With God in Hell, Berkovits even mentions the God-human relation as an I-Thou. So there is definitely an influence. But it seems all too vaguely “sublime” in the technical sense intended by Kant. First the moment which shatters the human person and human understanding, and then the second moment in which human subjectivity is recouped. It’s also, perhaps not “interesting” in the sense intended by AS in his critique above. Is there anything specifically orthodox here? Probably not. So maybe that’s the interesting point. An orthodox conception of revelation that is, in the end, not too terribly orthodox.</p>
<p>3) ej | April 14, 2011 at 5:38 pm | Reply </p>
<p>ZJB: I don’t think the Buber-Rosenzweig project was as individualistic as the romantic-Emersonian-Nietzschean one. While I think both Buber and Rosenzweig were both egotists of the highest order, they actually wrote very little about cultivating their own sense of personhood. This is a modernist sensibility perhaps, this anti-subjectivist impulse. The subject that Buber-Rosenzeweig wanted to cultivate and deepen was “Judaism,” which they viewed in the light of revelation, not as a one-time event, but as God’s ongoing presence in the world. Rosenzweig was drawn to mitzvot, Buber to other types of living Jewish form. </p>
<p>As for religious life in a secular society with many different ends and with AS’s comment in mind, I’d only say that religious ends remain religious ends. There is at least one end in religion that I think is unique to western religion: closeness to God, cleaving to God, being with God.  While this end is correlate to other ends (political, ethical, aesthetic), they are not substitutable with these other ends. That’s why I think the Buber-Rosenzweig legacy is the supreme legacy of German Judaism&#8230;for understanding Judaism and for religion, not for understanding political theory. If Lukacs, Benjamin, and Adorno help us think about religion, they do so from the side. In an ideal world, all these different ends (political, religious, aesthetic) would sustain and deepen each other; and maybe they sometimes do, even in our own imperfect world.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/13/an-interview-with-prof-zachary-j-braiterman/#comment-2960</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 22:38:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3441#comment-2960</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[There is a well know tradition of overthrowing the Gods in the name of not just liberty and autonomy but as part of becoming an individual and developing/creating one’s own vision or voice. This view in essence was promoted by Shelly, Emerson, Whitman, Wilde, Nietzsche and many others , each saying over this thesis in a slightly different way. How does this idea relate to the Buber/Rosenzweig understanding of redemption and revelation? Is the latter more of a one time being touched by an angel experience which in turn leads to a deeper acceptance of God either as a presence or as source of mitzvot? And how do you see religious Jewish life in the context of a liberal society that includes many ends? Do you value having an active religious life against the background of a larger humane and liberal culture because you feel such a culture would be progressive and of aesthetic value, or is such a culture a prolegomena of sorts to other deeper religious values?

Since asking such questions is a rare treat, I’ll ask one more question, mostly out of curiosity. Why do you thing Buber Rosenzweig is the primary legacy of German Jewry, and not the Lukacs, Benjamin, Frankfort School of secular criticism?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There is a well know tradition of overthrowing the Gods in the name of not just liberty and autonomy but as part of becoming an individual and developing/creating one’s own vision or voice. This view in essence was promoted by Shelly, Emerson, Whitman, Wilde, Nietzsche and many others , each saying over this thesis in a slightly different way. How does this idea relate to the Buber/Rosenzweig understanding of redemption and revelation? Is the latter more of a one time being touched by an angel experience which in turn leads to a deeper acceptance of God either as a presence or as source of mitzvot? And how do you see religious Jewish life in the context of a liberal society that includes many ends? Do you value having an active religious life against the background of a larger humane and liberal culture because you feel such a culture would be progressive and of aesthetic value, or is such a culture a prolegomena of sorts to other deeper religious values?</p>
<p>Since asking such questions is a rare treat, I’ll ask one more question, mostly out of curiosity. Why do you thing Buber Rosenzweig is the primary legacy of German Jewry, and not the Lukacs, Benjamin, Frankfort School of secular criticism?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/13/an-interview-with-prof-zachary-j-braiterman/#comment-2959</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 17:30:31 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3441#comment-2959</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I have a question about Berkovits on revelation for one of the few people who specialize in both Buber and Berkovits. In the passage below from Berkovits, where do you see this the same as Buber/Rosenzweig? And where do you see Berkovits going off in his dialectic theology or Orthodox perspective?

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;The Paradox of the Encounter&quot; in &lt;strong&gt;God, Man, and History&lt;/strong&gt; (1965):
 God&#039;s presence seems to be threatening; it imperils the life of the person to whom it wishes to communicate itself... Standing at the mountain of Sinai, the children of Israel trembled with fear at the voice of God, which yet was conferring on them their greatest distinction... The peril that emanates from &quot;contact&quot; with the Divine Presence, has nothing to do either with the sinfulness of man or with the judgment of the Almighty. It is something quite &quot;natural&quot;, almost &quot;physical&quot;, if one may say so. A man wilts in the heat of the midday sun, or dies of exhaustion if he is exposed too long to cold weather. Often mere lightning and thunder or the tempest of the elements frighten him. How, then, dare he hope to stand in the presence of the ultimate source of all energy and all power in the cosmos; how dare he approach it and survive!... Thus we are faced with a strange paradox. The God of religion, we have found must be a living one. And a living God is one who stands in relationship to the world, i.e., a God who not only is but is also for man, as it were, who is concerned about man... Now we find that the encounter threatens the very existence of man.., there can be no religion without some active relationship between man and God; in the relationship, however, man cannot survive.

 The paradox is resolved by God, when He &quot;shows&quot; Himself to man. God, who reveals His &quot;unbearable&quot; Presence to the helpless creature, also sustains man in the act of revelation... Man is threatened and affirmed at the same time. Through the peril that confronts him, he is bound to recognize his nothingness before God; yet, in the divine affirmation, the highest conceivable dignity is bestowed upon him: he is allowed into fellowship with God... The dual nature of man, which emerges in the basic religious experience, found its classical formulation in the words of the Psalmist, when he explained: &quot;What is man, that thou are mindful of him? And the son of man, that Thou thinkest of him? Yet Thou hast made him but lower than the angels, and hast crowned him with glory and honor.&quot; Man, who is &quot;dust and ashes&quot; and is yet &quot;crowned with glory and honor&#039; is the corollary to God, whose throne is the heaven and footstool is the earth and who yet looks on him who is &quot;poor and of a contrite spirit&quot;... Through the encounter Judaism first learned of God, who is almighty and yet cares for man, Supreme Lord and yet a friend.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have a question about Berkovits on revelation for one of the few people who specialize in both Buber and Berkovits. In the passage below from Berkovits, where do you see this the same as Buber/Rosenzweig? And where do you see Berkovits going off in his dialectic theology or Orthodox perspective?</p>
<blockquote><p>&#8220;The Paradox of the Encounter&#8221; in <strong>God, Man, and History</strong> (1965):<br />
 God&#8217;s presence seems to be threatening; it imperils the life of the person to whom it wishes to communicate itself&#8230; Standing at the mountain of Sinai, the children of Israel trembled with fear at the voice of God, which yet was conferring on them their greatest distinction&#8230; The peril that emanates from &#8220;contact&#8221; with the Divine Presence, has nothing to do either with the sinfulness of man or with the judgment of the Almighty. It is something quite &#8220;natural&#8221;, almost &#8220;physical&#8221;, if one may say so. A man wilts in the heat of the midday sun, or dies of exhaustion if he is exposed too long to cold weather. Often mere lightning and thunder or the tempest of the elements frighten him. How, then, dare he hope to stand in the presence of the ultimate source of all energy and all power in the cosmos; how dare he approach it and survive!&#8230; Thus we are faced with a strange paradox. The God of religion, we have found must be a living one. And a living God is one who stands in relationship to the world, i.e., a God who not only is but is also for man, as it were, who is concerned about man&#8230; Now we find that the encounter threatens the very existence of man.., there can be no religion without some active relationship between man and God; in the relationship, however, man cannot survive.</p>
<p> The paradox is resolved by God, when He &#8220;shows&#8221; Himself to man. God, who reveals His &#8220;unbearable&#8221; Presence to the helpless creature, also sustains man in the act of revelation&#8230; Man is threatened and affirmed at the same time. Through the peril that confronts him, he is bound to recognize his nothingness before God; yet, in the divine affirmation, the highest conceivable dignity is bestowed upon him: he is allowed into fellowship with God&#8230; The dual nature of man, which emerges in the basic religious experience, found its classical formulation in the words of the Psalmist, when he explained: &#8220;What is man, that thou are mindful of him? And the son of man, that Thou thinkest of him? Yet Thou hast made him but lower than the angels, and hast crowned him with glory and honor.&#8221; Man, who is &#8220;dust and ashes&#8221; and is yet &#8220;crowned with glory and honor&#8217; is the corollary to God, whose throne is the heaven and footstool is the earth and who yet looks on him who is &#8220;poor and of a contrite spirit&#8221;&#8230; Through the encounter Judaism first learned of God, who is almighty and yet cares for man, Supreme Lord and yet a friend.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/13/an-interview-with-prof-zachary-j-braiterman/#comment-2958</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 17:15:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3441#comment-2958</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I&#039;ve noticed that theorists often try to talk about aesthetics more broadly, but once talk of art enters the discussion it dominates and drowns out  everyday aesthetic experience. But when everything becomes aesthetic and it is no longer an interesting category. I&#039;m not sure exactly how this relates to Braiterman&#039;s work, but his claim to explore aesthetics as “the science of perception&quot; to me is in tension with a sustained engagement with high art, so I wonder if he could clarify what he is doing.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ve noticed that theorists often try to talk about aesthetics more broadly, but once talk of art enters the discussion it dominates and drowns out  everyday aesthetic experience. But when everything becomes aesthetic and it is no longer an interesting category. I&#8217;m not sure exactly how this relates to Braiterman&#8217;s work, but his claim to explore aesthetics as “the science of perception&#8221; to me is in tension with a sustained engagement with high art, so I wonder if he could clarify what he is doing.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
