<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>God &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/tag/god/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Jan 2011 21:04:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='kavvanah.wordpress.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/c9f111237f93750b6b994fc5185d49c3?s=96&#038;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>God &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>Arthur Green – Radical Judaism #5</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/22/arthur-green-%e2%80%93-radical-judaism-5/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/22/arthur-green-%e2%80%93-radical-judaism-5/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 23 May 2010 01:44:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Abraham joshua heschel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AJ Heschel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[arthur Green]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[God]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1317</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Time for the final chapter. Continued from here and here. Green asks: What Does God want you to do? or as Green puts it Who are you? What does it mean to be human? For Green, the answer must come &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/22/arthur-green-%e2%80%93-radical-judaism-5/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Time for the final chapter.  Continued from <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/01/arthur-green-–-radical-judaism-3/">here</a> and <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/08/green-radical-judaism-4/">here.</a></p>
<p>Green asks: What Does God want you to do? or as Green puts it Who are you?  What does it mean to be human?</p>
<p>For Green, the answer must come from our sense of Creation that includes all of humanity, we need to internalize a universalist concept that man is the image of God.  (We don’t get an ethicist&#8217;s or jurist&#8217;s list of ethical principles.) There is an evolutionary human development toward greater universalism. So rather than giving us a theory of justice, we get a discussion of how can we still use the kabbalistic language of soul as a basis for universalism. Green strength is his personal honesty to state that he is hesitant to use the word metaphysical word soul but then turns it around to preserve the holy language of the soul by stating that the soul is the recognition that we are a holy being enjoined to remember to respect and rejoin the pantheistic source of all being. Immortality is the acknowledgment of the circle of life. There are new babies and new flowers and eternal renewal. (What I get is a sensibility more than universal values.)</p>
<p>Green places the current debate among Israeli Religious Zionists about universalism in a footnote but does not enter the fray. What did Hazal do with the universal principles of image of God and Love thy neighbor? Alon Goshen-Gottstein sees these ideas as too universal for Hazal while Yair Lorberbaum shows how Maimonides and Nahmanides retained aspects of these ideas to create metaphysics. [As a contrast to Green, when Rav Cherlow asks this question of what God wants from you– he responds with a compassionate Jewish law of values.] </p>
<p>Green states that he is not worried over who is a Jew, and other discredited nineteenth century ideas like race and peoplehood. He feels that there is too much emphasis in Jewish life on the insecurity of our existence and not enough on our status as seekers. Choosing of Israel does not mean rejection of other people. The Six-Day War and the Yom Kippur War created a lasting impression on Jews. But Israel and the law of return is still bound to the Nuremburg laws.  Jews are seekers, not a race.  (echoes of  Avraham Burg, but the later advocates ethics.) For Green, between the universal seeker and tribal Jew is the Jewish seeker.  </p>
<p>Green does not consider the way the Jewish seeker plays itself out in real life. Two common forms of the Jewish seeker are (1) the tribal seeker, who has a universal Judaism and hates other faiths or commitments. he Bu-Jew with a hatred of Christianity and Islam. (2)Or those so tribal that they say anything she touches is Jewish. This second Jewish seeker is adamant that any fragment of Buddhism or Yoga that they like is a fulfillment of Judaism </p>
<p>Green describes himself as a religious Jew and secular Zionist. There is no religious or messianic status to the land of Israel. But essentially he remains a diasporist.</p>
<p>Green has a nice section on his differences from Heschel. For Heschel, one actually gives to God when performing a mizvah- there is real theurgy. Heschel had a Biblical personalist image of with mystical overtones, and Green admits that he is a pantheist with personalist overtones A pantheistic God as energy that offers blessing – meaning an energy that adds value and meaning to the world. Heschel was God’s partner- he translated prophetic and kabbalistic language into  personalist language.Heschel has traditional views of God, Torah, Israel.  Heschel  approach to the law was apologetic combined with a plea for more compassion and decency. Green approach is heterodoxy. Green acknowledges that Heschel  has both a progressive approach, which Green likes, but also a strong conservative trend. </p>
<p>Well was this book a vision for the 21st century future of Judaism or was it just the spiritual autobiography of a baby-boomer?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/22/arthur-green-%e2%80%93-radical-judaism-5/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Spirituality at B’nai Jeshurun</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/13/spirituality-at-b%e2%80%99nai-jeshurun/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/13/spirituality-at-b%e2%80%99nai-jeshurun/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2009 05:32:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[popular religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sociology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[arthur Green]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[B’nai Jeshurun]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[God]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[s3k]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[spirituality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Synagouge 3000]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=245</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[There is a new study from Synagogue 3000&#8212; The New Jewish Spirituality and Prayer: Take BJ, For Instance  Ayala Fader &#38; Mark Kligman S3K Synagogue Studies Institute. This one looks at the success of BJ in NYC. I have picked &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/13/spirituality-at-b%e2%80%99nai-jeshurun/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There is a new study from Synagogue 3000&#8212; The New Jewish Spirituality and Prayer: Take BJ, For Instanc<em>e  Ayala Fader &amp; Mark Kligman</em> S3K Synagogue Studies Institute. This one looks at the success of BJ in NYC. I have picked out the theological sections.  BJ preaches a spirituality of finding God in one&#8217;s own life through an emotional religious experience. Their deity is a therapeutic deism with psychological elements- it seems the true fulfillment of Arthur Green&#8217;s theology in <em>Seek My Face, Speak My Name: A Contemporary Jewish Theology</em> (1992) or the undated pop version Ehyeh: A Kabbalah for Tomorrow (2002).</p>
<blockquote><p>Central to BJ is the claim by members and rabbis alike that in order to experience God, individuals must “let go”  of rationalism and the intellect. The goal is to access an emotional part of the self which opens the individual to experience the “energy” of God, something which is found within each person. When it comes to prayer, comprehension of Hebrew (<em>loshn kodesh</em>), Jewish ritual or traditional Jewish music is less important than <em>kavanah </em>(“sincere intention”). By privileg­ing <em>kavanah</em>, the emphasis of prayer shifts from “obligation” (the <em>mitzvah</em>) to what congregants describe as the “freedom” to choose those aspects of Judaism that best speak to each individual’s experience of God.</p>
<p>[The] aim is to have religious practice create opportunities for what they call “spiritual experi­ence,” meaning the experience of God; but God must be re-concep­tualized in order to be relevant in the contemporary world. Marcelo explains: “We have to change the paradigm from the idea of God to the experience of God.” The paradigm for today’s Jews requires what the rabbis describe as a “God of love.” Jews today, suggest the rabbis, need a “reason of love” or they will abandon God. [Their ] “God of love” is not necessarily a supernatural figure. As an entity found inside the self, God is, in effect, human.</p>
<p>To find God, each person must search inside the self. This concept of God echoes humanistic beliefs, but is clearly distinct from secularism. The rabbis elaborate a post- rationalistic God, located in the emotional interior of each individual, not the intellect. The point of the commandments (<em>mitzvot</em>), claim the rabbis, is not to force us to “give up things” but to “open us up and purify us for God.” Jew­ish ritual practice, particularly prayer, is an individual choice one makes in order to experience the divine.</p>
<p>Self-exploration is often expressed in therapeutic language, but with the goal of personal transcen­dence. When there is closeness to, and individual experience of, God, an individual can become more holy in the sense of ascending to a higher level of humanity. As the rabbinic intern said: &#8220;It’s not separating the two, God and psychology. We’re not going to pass it over to the therapists&#8230;it’s about finding out where God is in your life… It’s about how you can grow holy in this thing… It’s co-opting psychology and lacing it in spiritual terms.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>Now the contextualization in studies on Spirituality and Evangelical Churches. It confirms that much of the Neo-Hasidism of liberal Jews shares much in style with Conservative Evangelicals.</p>
<blockquote><p>Embodied religious practice comes also through the use in services of practices from a range of minority religions. A number of people talked about the use of “breath” and meditation techniques. Others adopt meta­phors of “healing and wholeness” drawn from therapeutic contexts. This kind of combinative religious practice is a com­mon feature of New Age spirituality (Rothenberg and Vallely, 2008). Individualized picking and choosing from world religions in order to satisfy personal needs is a feature of postmodern religiosity, a “tradition” favored by Jewish baby boomers (Cohen and Eisen, 2000). But at BJ, combinative religious practice is institutionalized, not left to individual personal spiritual journeys; it is part and parcel of the synagogue, modeled publicly by authoritative spiritual leaders, and framed as the revitalization of Juda­ism’s authentic and shared religious heritage.</p>
<p>BJ shares many goals and practices with North Ameri­can megachurches and evangelical seeker churches. These churches focus on Christian spirituality in large settings where members can be part of a growing, successful and innovative ministry (Thumma and Travis, 2007:158). Like so many at BJ also, evangelical seekers, predominant­ly baby boomers, decidedly depart from the denomina­tion of their upbringing, searching out religious fulfill­ment through individual choice and a therapeutic ethos with an anti-institutional bias (Sargeant, 2000:163-4).</p>
<p>However, BJ has a distinctive definition of what indi­vidual fulfillment means. Seeker churches satisfy thera­peutic concerns for self-fulfillment through an evangelical understanding of Christ’s salvation (Sargeant, 2000). At BJ, individuals encounter God through individualized and, often, embodied expression of affect. Concep­tions of God, too, differ of course. Anthropologist Tanya Luhrman’s description of a “new paradigm” church (2004), for example, describes how congregants learn to conceptualize Jesus as a “buddy.” BJ members, by con­trast, find God inside themselves. However, God only enters the emotional, non-rational, vulnerable aspect of the self.</p>
<p>Regardless, what makes BJ seem modern to so many is the way that the traditional liturgy is made to engage modern forms of self-construction, including introspection, self-cultivation, and personal freedom as the path to happiness.</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="http://synagogue3000.org/files/S3KReportBJNovember2009.pdf"> Full Article Here</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/13/spirituality-at-b%e2%80%99nai-jeshurun/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>John T. Elson, Editor Who Asked ‘Is God Dead?’ at Time, Dies at 78</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/29/john-t-elson-editor-who-asked-%e2%80%98is-god-dead%e2%80%99-at-time-dies-at-78/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/29/john-t-elson-editor-who-asked-%e2%80%98is-god-dead%e2%80%99-at-time-dies-at-78/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2009 19:25:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[popular religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Berkovits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[God]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Is God dead?]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[secularization]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=101</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Elson died last week and this is a good vantage point to look at the changes of religion in the last half century.  Even though many proclaimed the end of God in the late 1960&#8217;s and early 1970&#8217;s, God returned &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/29/john-t-elson-editor-who-asked-%e2%80%98is-god-dead%e2%80%99-at-time-dies-at-78/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Elson died last week and this is a good vantage point to look at the changes of religion in the last half century.  Even though many proclaimed the end of God in the late 1960&#8217;s and early 1970&#8217;s, God returned with a vengeance to show his public face in the public sphere in the 1980&#8217;s and 1990&#8217;s. But the story is not so simple:</p>
<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/09/18/business/media/18elson.html?_r=2" target="_self">The New York Times Obit </a>notes that the cover of Time magazine posed a question: “Is God dead?” But “the article’s actual headline was ‘Toward a Hidden God,’ and it was a scholarly, careful look at how secularism, urbanism, and all the other ‘isms were changing people’s ideas about God.” “Secularization, science, urbanization — all have made it comparatively easy for the modern man to ask where God is and hard for the man of faith to give a convincing answer, even to himself,” Mr. Elson wrote.</p>
<p>Quotes from the original Tine magazine article: Friday, Oct. 22, 1965 <a href="http://www.time.com/time/printout/0,8816,941410,00.html" target="_self">Theology: The God Is Dead Movement</a></p>
<blockquote><p>They say that it is no longer possible to think about or believe in a transcendent God who acts in human history,</p>
<p>Buddhism &amp; Blake. There is a strong streak of mysticism&#8230; whose eclectic theology borrows from such diverse sources as Buddhism and William Blake</p>
<p>Paul van Buren is an advocate of linguistic analysis, which attempts to clarify language by examining the way words are used and denies the objective truth of statements that cannot be verified empirically.</p>
<p>// </p>
<p> Harvard&#8217;s Harvey Cox&#8230; whose book The Secular City concludes with the idea that Christianity may have to stop talking about God for a while, complains about the writers&#8217; imprecise language. &#8220;Is it the loss of the experience of God, the loss of the existence of God in Christianity, or the lack of adequate language to express God today?&#8221; he asks.</p></blockquote>
<p>Yet we indeed do have a more hidden limited deity.  Eliezer Berkovits is the author to be credited for the idea that we no longer have direct contact with a theistic God and now we follow halakhah without a direct presence. His lines about halakhah as substituting for a living presence are now associated with almost any modern pan-halachic approach.  But Berkovits was the one to respond to the hidden God by saying we now have halakhah.</p>
<p>Mysticism and Kabblah which were not in vouge in the first half of the twentieth century are useful in diverse ways. We have the symbolic realm of the Kabbalah to deflect from a personal deity onto more benign, God is sefirot. Even those who read Ramhal to be Haredi have deflected their God away from a person to a closed mechanism of sefirot and inner divine drive. We also have the spirituality version of Kabbalah and Neo-hasidism where God is functional to provide human happiness and religious experience. We also now have the Elie Wiesel Hasidic deity whom humans argue with. We have the tzimzum deity whom we can no longer know through doctrine.</p>
<p>And finally we have a variety of Jewish based kitchen deities, where one prays for everyday miracles, prosperity, and that the kugel comes out OK There is one recent semi-yeshivish popular book on Jewish prayer that encourages one to pray for one&#8217;s daily concerns. Even as God has come back in the public sphere, the deity is more therapeutic than theistic.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/29/john-t-elson-editor-who-asked-%e2%80%98is-god-dead%e2%80%99-at-time-dies-at-78/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
