<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Shai Held on Abraham Joshua Heschel: The Call of Transcendence	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/17/shai-held-on-abraham-joshua-heschel-the-call-of-transcendence/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/17/shai-held-on-abraham-joshua-heschel-the-call-of-transcendence/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2013 12:52:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Shai Held		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/17/shai-held-on-abraham-joshua-heschel-the-call-of-transcendence/#comment-9148</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shai Held]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2013 12:52:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6379#comment-9148</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thanks for the question, Hayyim.  You&#039;re right.  The issue here was simply space.  In the book, I do talk about what panentheism is, and about why Heschel is not a panentheist.  For a more sustained argument than mine for why Heschel is not a panentheist, see this article by John Merkle: http://ejournals.bc.edu/ojs/index.php/scjr/article/view/1420

Sorry I can&#039;t write more at the moment.  Thanks again for your important question.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thanks for the question, Hayyim.  You&#8217;re right.  The issue here was simply space.  In the book, I do talk about what panentheism is, and about why Heschel is not a panentheist.  For a more sustained argument than mine for why Heschel is not a panentheist, see this article by John Merkle: <a href="http://ejournals.bc.edu/ojs/index.php/scjr/article/view/1420" rel="nofollow ugc">http://ejournals.bc.edu/ojs/index.php/scjr/article/view/1420</a></p>
<p>Sorry I can&#8217;t write more at the moment.  Thanks again for your important question.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Hayyim		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/17/shai-held-on-abraham-joshua-heschel-the-call-of-transcendence/#comment-9145</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Hayyim]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2013 02:59:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6379#comment-9145</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Shai, your response to Question #3 (immanence/transcendence) seems to me not to adequately cover the theological options, the perspective(s) found within Jewish mysticism (especially Chassidus), or the views of Rabbi Heschel, a&quot;h.  Alongside pantheism and monism, why do you not consider panentheism?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Shai, your response to Question #3 (immanence/transcendence) seems to me not to adequately cover the theological options, the perspective(s) found within Jewish mysticism (especially Chassidus), or the views of Rabbi Heschel, a&#8221;h.  Alongside pantheism and monism, why do you not consider panentheism?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Pinchos Chalk		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/17/shai-held-on-abraham-joshua-heschel-the-call-of-transcendence/#comment-9144</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pinchos Chalk]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2013 00:41:22 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6379#comment-9144</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Without being subsumed by another society or system it is impossible to know if your effort is real because internal consistency cannot be measured in a comfortable environment.

As Viktor Frenkel said (I normally spell that wrong) - something can only give light if it can endure being burnt (which I assume is a reference to the burning bush).

Finding God in America will always be difficult exactly because the Jews have created a multi-dimensional society in the new world. Which is maybe why if you move from the old world to the new one, you may be construed as not having achieved your earlier potential.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Without being subsumed by another society or system it is impossible to know if your effort is real because internal consistency cannot be measured in a comfortable environment.</p>
<p>As Viktor Frenkel said (I normally spell that wrong) &#8211; something can only give light if it can endure being burnt (which I assume is a reference to the burning bush).</p>
<p>Finding God in America will always be difficult exactly because the Jews have created a multi-dimensional society in the new world. Which is maybe why if you move from the old world to the new one, you may be construed as not having achieved your earlier potential.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Jeff Eyges		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/17/shai-held-on-abraham-joshua-heschel-the-call-of-transcendence/#comment-9136</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jeff Eyges]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2013 14:24:51 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6379#comment-9136</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/17/shai-held-on-abraham-joshua-heschel-the-call-of-transcendence/#comment-9134&quot;&gt;YM Goldstein&lt;/a&gt;.

The entire Haredi world confuses its gedolim with Hashem, and that amounts to the same thing.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/17/shai-held-on-abraham-joshua-heschel-the-call-of-transcendence/#comment-9134">YM Goldstein</a>.</p>
<p>The entire Haredi world confuses its gedolim with Hashem, and that amounts to the same thing.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: YM Goldstein		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/17/shai-held-on-abraham-joshua-heschel-the-call-of-transcendence/#comment-9134</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[YM Goldstein]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2013 13:38:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6379#comment-9134</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/17/shai-held-on-abraham-joshua-heschel-the-call-of-transcendence/#comment-9122&quot;&gt;Shai Held&lt;/a&gt;.

Even for those for whom halacha is &quot;an exclusive preoccupation&quot;, they may not be missing the boat since it is the way that they are able to get beyond themselves and fully devote their effort to fulfilling Hashem&#039;s will.  I don&#039;t believe I have ever met anyone who confuses halacha with Hashem; it is &quot;you&quot; who perhaps is making assumptions about their motivation or philosophy.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/17/shai-held-on-abraham-joshua-heschel-the-call-of-transcendence/#comment-9122">Shai Held</a>.</p>
<p>Even for those for whom halacha is &#8220;an exclusive preoccupation&#8221;, they may not be missing the boat since it is the way that they are able to get beyond themselves and fully devote their effort to fulfilling Hashem&#8217;s will.  I don&#8217;t believe I have ever met anyone who confuses halacha with Hashem; it is &#8220;you&#8221; who perhaps is making assumptions about their motivation or philosophy.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: H Handler		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/17/shai-held-on-abraham-joshua-heschel-the-call-of-transcendence/#comment-9132</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[H Handler]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2013 13:24:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6379#comment-9132</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I wonder if anyone has thought to compare Heschel to the Catholic thinker, Louis Dupre, especially in his book, &quot;Transcendent Selfhod&quot;.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I wonder if anyone has thought to compare Heschel to the Catholic thinker, Louis Dupre, especially in his book, &#8220;Transcendent Selfhod&#8221;.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Shai Held		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/17/shai-held-on-abraham-joshua-heschel-the-call-of-transcendence/#comment-9131</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shai Held]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2013 12:59:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6379#comment-9131</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I should have added: self-transcendence is not just about ethics, but ethics is arguable its highest manifestation.  There is also the crucial spiritual (and psychological) work of realizing that my ego and my consciousness are not the center of the universe.  In Heschel&#039;s image, they are spokes, but not the bub, of the universe.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I should have added: self-transcendence is not just about ethics, but ethics is arguable its highest manifestation.  There is also the crucial spiritual (and psychological) work of realizing that my ego and my consciousness are not the center of the universe.  In Heschel&#8217;s image, they are spokes, but not the bub, of the universe.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Shai Held		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/17/shai-held-on-abraham-joshua-heschel-the-call-of-transcendence/#comment-9130</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shai Held]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2013 11:27:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6379#comment-9130</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[EJ, thanks for your comments.  First, it seems like you simply equate Heschel&#039;s views with my own.  They are not fully overlapping.

Heschel unfortunately does not offer a developed theory of what self-transcendence does and doesn&#039;t mean and of what it doesn&#039;t require or entail (this is true of many philosophers who use the term).  One thing that is clear is that he doesn&#039;t think it means not having a self at all (an ideal which is neither desirable nor possible)-- the focus is more on transcending selfishness than on moving beyond having a self at all.  More positively, it&#039;s about cultivating &quot;transitive concern,&quot; concern for the welfare of others.

You write of the need to see certain commitments as supererogatory.  I think Heschel would agree with you, but with one huge caveat:  &quot;Even if you&#039;re right,&quot; I imagine him saying, &quot;that I place too little in the real of supererogation, most people place far too much there.  Caring about the poor and downtrodden and acting to ameliorate their suffering is din, not lifnim mishurat hadin.  And I have Isaiah and Amos and Moshe Rabbenu on my side.&quot;  (Tikkun Olam is not a term he uses at all, and I suspect he&#039;d have regarded it as vague and amorphous and a tiny bit trite.)

On another note, I have been toying with the idea of writing something about the role of laughter and play in theology and spirituality because I think they can often get completely neglected in religious writing.  Just how and why that is would itself make for an interesting conversation.

There is more to say here, obviously.  Thanks again for your comments..]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>EJ, thanks for your comments.  First, it seems like you simply equate Heschel&#8217;s views with my own.  They are not fully overlapping.</p>
<p>Heschel unfortunately does not offer a developed theory of what self-transcendence does and doesn&#8217;t mean and of what it doesn&#8217;t require or entail (this is true of many philosophers who use the term).  One thing that is clear is that he doesn&#8217;t think it means not having a self at all (an ideal which is neither desirable nor possible)&#8211; the focus is more on transcending selfishness than on moving beyond having a self at all.  More positively, it&#8217;s about cultivating &#8220;transitive concern,&#8221; concern for the welfare of others.</p>
<p>You write of the need to see certain commitments as supererogatory.  I think Heschel would agree with you, but with one huge caveat:  &#8220;Even if you&#8217;re right,&#8221; I imagine him saying, &#8220;that I place too little in the real of supererogation, most people place far too much there.  Caring about the poor and downtrodden and acting to ameliorate their suffering is din, not lifnim mishurat hadin.  And I have Isaiah and Amos and Moshe Rabbenu on my side.&#8221;  (Tikkun Olam is not a term he uses at all, and I suspect he&#8217;d have regarded it as vague and amorphous and a tiny bit trite.)</p>
<p>On another note, I have been toying with the idea of writing something about the role of laughter and play in theology and spirituality because I think they can often get completely neglected in religious writing.  Just how and why that is would itself make for an interesting conversation.</p>
<p>There is more to say here, obviously.  Thanks again for your comments..</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/17/shai-held-on-abraham-joshua-heschel-the-call-of-transcendence/#comment-9124</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2013 21:11:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6379#comment-9124</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The idea that we ought to transcend our ego, or  self in current psychoanalytic jargon, depends what is included in the ego/self. Rabbi Held  seems to include desires and ambitions plus self regarding ideals. Following Kohut and other self-psychologists we can think of the self as being driven by desires and ambitions, and pulled by our ideals, including other regarding ideals. When a person has the virtues of benevolence and sympathy as his ideal, there is no need to overcome or transcend the self. Rather once these ideals are internalized, helping others, concern for the poor and downtrodden becomes an intrinsic part of a life plan. Socialists and others who worked a lifetime on behalf of the poor were not known for their God centeredness. Their efforts were part of who they were.

Even if working for others is understood as outside the ego, the leap to projecting the feeling for the other onto God, and then re-internalizing this projection as a norm, needs some extra justification. Even if God were indifferent to the cries of the sick and the hungry, we might still feel that it is a virtue if not an outright duty to help others at least in part. And conversely if God is benevolent, why must we be the same? He can afford to care, He is God, but we humans perhaps ought to take care of our self, since if we don’t who will?  The grounding of sympathy and the other attitudes that lead to doing good are best seen as part of our moral education.

Tikun haolam and other such grandiose projects are best understood as supererogatory. Not all of us must be preoccupied all the time with helping others. There must be some room for bourgeois pleasures and the study of Torah lishma. On Rabbi Held’s views it is not clear why after a certain point, helping others is supererogatory.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The idea that we ought to transcend our ego, or  self in current psychoanalytic jargon, depends what is included in the ego/self. Rabbi Held  seems to include desires and ambitions plus self regarding ideals. Following Kohut and other self-psychologists we can think of the self as being driven by desires and ambitions, and pulled by our ideals, including other regarding ideals. When a person has the virtues of benevolence and sympathy as his ideal, there is no need to overcome or transcend the self. Rather once these ideals are internalized, helping others, concern for the poor and downtrodden becomes an intrinsic part of a life plan. Socialists and others who worked a lifetime on behalf of the poor were not known for their God centeredness. Their efforts were part of who they were.</p>
<p>Even if working for others is understood as outside the ego, the leap to projecting the feeling for the other onto God, and then re-internalizing this projection as a norm, needs some extra justification. Even if God were indifferent to the cries of the sick and the hungry, we might still feel that it is a virtue if not an outright duty to help others at least in part. And conversely if God is benevolent, why must we be the same? He can afford to care, He is God, but we humans perhaps ought to take care of our self, since if we don’t who will?  The grounding of sympathy and the other attitudes that lead to doing good are best seen as part of our moral education.</p>
<p>Tikun haolam and other such grandiose projects are best understood as supererogatory. Not all of us must be preoccupied all the time with helping others. There must be some room for bourgeois pleasures and the study of Torah lishma. On Rabbi Held’s views it is not clear why after a certain point, helping others is supererogatory.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Shai Held		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/17/shai-held-on-abraham-joshua-heschel-the-call-of-transcendence/#comment-9122</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shai Held]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2013 18:06:22 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6379#comment-9122</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I am not attacking the Orthodox.  I am responding to a problem with which Jews have struggled for centuries: what happens when Halakha becomes an exclusive preoccupation, as it has in certain circles?  Rabbenu Bahya felt this every bit as strongly as Heschel did.  And I agree with you, as I state in the interview: on this point, there is no great chiddush in Heschel on this point.  He is merely the most recent in a line of eloquent protesters against one of Judaism&#039;s yetzer haras.  (But don&#039;t underestimate the Leibowitzian strand in contemporary frum culture.  I have taught young adults from Orthodox backgrounds, American and Israeli, for almost two decades now, and the criticisms I hear along these lines are very common.)  

On this blog, I was asked to talk about what Heschel would say to the Modern Orthodox community; somewhere else I&#039;d be glad to talk about what he&#039;d say to Reform and Conservative Jews, or to secular ones, for that matter.

It always makes me sad when either he or (lehavdil) I am accused of being anti-Orthodox.  Like him, I don&#039;t identify denominationally, and never mean to be attacking one group or grinding some sort of ideological axe. I really believe than when we encounter a true gadol, like Heschel, all communities wanting to inherit the masorah with integrity have what to learn.   I hope this clarifies my intentions at least a bit.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I am not attacking the Orthodox.  I am responding to a problem with which Jews have struggled for centuries: what happens when Halakha becomes an exclusive preoccupation, as it has in certain circles?  Rabbenu Bahya felt this every bit as strongly as Heschel did.  And I agree with you, as I state in the interview: on this point, there is no great chiddush in Heschel on this point.  He is merely the most recent in a line of eloquent protesters against one of Judaism&#8217;s yetzer haras.  (But don&#8217;t underestimate the Leibowitzian strand in contemporary frum culture.  I have taught young adults from Orthodox backgrounds, American and Israeli, for almost two decades now, and the criticisms I hear along these lines are very common.)  </p>
<p>On this blog, I was asked to talk about what Heschel would say to the Modern Orthodox community; somewhere else I&#8217;d be glad to talk about what he&#8217;d say to Reform and Conservative Jews, or to secular ones, for that matter.</p>
<p>It always makes me sad when either he or (lehavdil) I am accused of being anti-Orthodox.  Like him, I don&#8217;t identify denominationally, and never mean to be attacking one group or grinding some sort of ideological axe. I really believe than when we encounter a true gadol, like Heschel, all communities wanting to inherit the masorah with integrity have what to learn.   I hope this clarifies my intentions at least a bit.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: YM Goldstein		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/17/shai-held-on-abraham-joshua-heschel-the-call-of-transcendence/#comment-9120</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[YM Goldstein]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2013 17:38:46 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6379#comment-9120</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&quot;For Heschel, as we have seen, the goal of the spiritual life is to overcome selfishness and self-preoccupation.&quot;  This is true in the teachings of Rabbi Shlomo Wolbe and other mussar greats; it seems pretty obvious and I believe most Orthodox Jews are aware that Halacha is the way or path, but not the goal.  Why attack the Orthodox?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&#8220;For Heschel, as we have seen, the goal of the spiritual life is to overcome selfishness and self-preoccupation.&#8221;  This is true in the teachings of Rabbi Shlomo Wolbe and other mussar greats; it seems pretty obvious and I believe most Orthodox Jews are aware that Halacha is the way or path, but not the goal.  Why attack the Orthodox?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Shai Held		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/17/shai-held-on-abraham-joshua-heschel-the-call-of-transcendence/#comment-9119</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shai Held]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2013 17:25:32 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6379#comment-9119</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Todd, thanks so much for your interest in my book.  I don&#039;t deal with whatever R. Soloveitchik&#039;s or R. Hutner&#039;s criticisms might have been, because all we have is hearsay, and I didn&#039;t want to get into that. 

I will say this: I think the notion that theology needs to be grounded in Halakha has been a common trope in Orthodox discourse since Soloveitchik said as much in The Halakhic Mind.  But I often feel that that notion is used very lazily, and that people don&#039;t take the trouble to figure out what Soloveitchik may have meant by it.  For example, it&#039;s true that R. Soloveitchik says that theology should be grounded in Halakhic sources (I don&#039;t have the actual passage in front of me, so I hope I&#039;m remembering it right) , but he also says emphatically in Ish HaHalakha that  Genesis 1 is a Halakhic text.  So it&#039;s just not clear what the slogan means, or what it could mean. Is the theology of man as creator in HM, II, really more grounded in Halakha than Part 1 of God in Search of Man?  I&#039;m not sure, because I am not sure I (we) know quite what Soloveitchik meant, but I am skeptical. I once raised this question on an interdenominational listserve and people got very nervous, as if even asking that question was beyond the pale. 

As far as respect from JTS Talmud professors, that&#039;s really beyond the scope of my book, which is about philosophy and theology and not really about Heschel&#039;s life.  You might look at Ed Kaplan&#039;s biography for some of that.
 .]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Todd, thanks so much for your interest in my book.  I don&#8217;t deal with whatever R. Soloveitchik&#8217;s or R. Hutner&#8217;s criticisms might have been, because all we have is hearsay, and I didn&#8217;t want to get into that. </p>
<p>I will say this: I think the notion that theology needs to be grounded in Halakha has been a common trope in Orthodox discourse since Soloveitchik said as much in The Halakhic Mind.  But I often feel that that notion is used very lazily, and that people don&#8217;t take the trouble to figure out what Soloveitchik may have meant by it.  For example, it&#8217;s true that R. Soloveitchik says that theology should be grounded in Halakhic sources (I don&#8217;t have the actual passage in front of me, so I hope I&#8217;m remembering it right) , but he also says emphatically in Ish HaHalakha that  Genesis 1 is a Halakhic text.  So it&#8217;s just not clear what the slogan means, or what it could mean. Is the theology of man as creator in HM, II, really more grounded in Halakha than Part 1 of God in Search of Man?  I&#8217;m not sure, because I am not sure I (we) know quite what Soloveitchik meant, but I am skeptical. I once raised this question on an interdenominational listserve and people got very nervous, as if even asking that question was beyond the pale. </p>
<p>As far as respect from JTS Talmud professors, that&#8217;s really beyond the scope of my book, which is about philosophy and theology and not really about Heschel&#8217;s life.  You might look at Ed Kaplan&#8217;s biography for some of that.<br />
 .</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Todd Berman		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/17/shai-held-on-abraham-joshua-heschel-the-call-of-transcendence/#comment-9116</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Todd Berman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2013 15:27:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6379#comment-9116</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Shai, I can&#039;t wait to read your book. Do you deal with the criticism of traditionalist like the Rav or from what I have heard from Rav Hutner of Heschel not grounding Jewish Theology in Halacha (I guess a kin to Eliezer Berkowitz.)  Also, they say that he didn&#039;t really get the respect he deserved from the powers that be -- aka the Talmudists -- at JTS in his day. I don&#039;t know the truth of the above. I am curious if you relate to the above.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Shai, I can&#8217;t wait to read your book. Do you deal with the criticism of traditionalist like the Rav or from what I have heard from Rav Hutner of Heschel not grounding Jewish Theology in Halacha (I guess a kin to Eliezer Berkowitz.)  Also, they say that he didn&#8217;t really get the respect he deserved from the powers that be &#8212; aka the Talmudists &#8212; at JTS in his day. I don&#8217;t know the truth of the above. I am curious if you relate to the above.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
