<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: God is Back &#8212;-Part II&#8212;-Religious Conclusions and Orthodox implications	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/05/god-is-back-part-ii-religious-conclusions-and-orthodox-implications/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/05/god-is-back-part-ii-religious-conclusions-and-orthodox-implications/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2010 15:08:47 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Yonatan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/05/god-is-back-part-ii-religious-conclusions-and-orthodox-implications/#comment-1301</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Yonatan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2010 15:08:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1596#comment-1301</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[1) Responding to both Brill &#038; Chinn, even if their are Orthodox Jewish biker groups and Orthodox Jewish 12 step groups, then tend to be not integrated into the Orthodox Jewish communities. 

Individuals will go out and have their 12 step weekend or artist event and then go back into their community without a real integration. 

For example most 12 step meetings take place in Churches rather than in synagogues presumably by the decision of those in the fellowships.

Though interestingly enough, one of the few areas of integration is the professionals integrating their professions (Doctors, Lawyers &#038; Academics, in particular) into the Jewish communities.

Chinn, a major problem with the YU model is that, in practice, it only works for those already part of its systems. It&#039;s hard for most outsiders to assimilate into their communities. Unlike evangelical churches.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>1) Responding to both Brill &amp; Chinn, even if their are Orthodox Jewish biker groups and Orthodox Jewish 12 step groups, then tend to be not integrated into the Orthodox Jewish communities. </p>
<p>Individuals will go out and have their 12 step weekend or artist event and then go back into their community without a real integration. </p>
<p>For example most 12 step meetings take place in Churches rather than in synagogues presumably by the decision of those in the fellowships.</p>
<p>Though interestingly enough, one of the few areas of integration is the professionals integrating their professions (Doctors, Lawyers &amp; Academics, in particular) into the Jewish communities.</p>
<p>Chinn, a major problem with the YU model is that, in practice, it only works for those already part of its systems. It&#8217;s hard for most outsiders to assimilate into their communities. Unlike evangelical churches.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: tomerpersico		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/05/god-is-back-part-ii-religious-conclusions-and-orthodox-implications/#comment-1262</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tomerpersico]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 06 Jul 2010 04:23:03 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1596#comment-1262</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[You write that the authors are &quot;content to simply describe what it sees, without ever attempting to pass judgment&quot;. I haven&#039;t read the book, but from your two (very informative, thank you) posts here I think it&#039;s clear that the authors do, in a way, pass judgment on the religious life in the US. I think they approve of evangelicalism, and that&#039;s simply because of its success. As you wrote in the earlier post,

&quot;[T]he authors argue that the lack of strong State supported churches created an opening for niche churches and the sort of religious innovation necessary to thrive in the open climate of modernity. A religious free market forced clergymen to actively seek congregants to fill their pews by catering to popular needs. As the authors openly admit, this thesis comes from Tocqueville; they are merely updating it for the twenty-first century.&quot;

This sounds like what is called &quot;the religious market model&quot; for explaining secularization, meaning that unless religion be free from state interference and able to compete in a liberal public sphere – and thus need to change and upgrade itself vis a vis competing religious forms – it will fail to draw costumers and go bankrupt (excuse me, fail to draw believers and disappear).

I am willing to guess this is why the authors are positive toward evangelism: simply because it has succeeded. In an open market, laissez-faire kind of view on religion, that means it&#039;s GOOD. It may be no accident that the two authors are the editors of The Economist.

On another note, I think you emphasize the importance of intellectualism a bit too much. Evangelism isn&#039;t the most rapidly growing (or simply the only growing) Christian denomination because it&#039;s intellectual, but because it s stress on feeling, on the direct experience of the Holy Spirit. I think that&#039;s what is in demand today, will be  more and more  in demand in the future, and it&#039;s with that that Jewish Orthodoxy will have to struggle.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>You write that the authors are &#8220;content to simply describe what it sees, without ever attempting to pass judgment&#8221;. I haven&#8217;t read the book, but from your two (very informative, thank you) posts here I think it&#8217;s clear that the authors do, in a way, pass judgment on the religious life in the US. I think they approve of evangelicalism, and that&#8217;s simply because of its success. As you wrote in the earlier post,</p>
<p>&#8220;[T]he authors argue that the lack of strong State supported churches created an opening for niche churches and the sort of religious innovation necessary to thrive in the open climate of modernity. A religious free market forced clergymen to actively seek congregants to fill their pews by catering to popular needs. As the authors openly admit, this thesis comes from Tocqueville; they are merely updating it for the twenty-first century.&#8221;</p>
<p>This sounds like what is called &#8220;the religious market model&#8221; for explaining secularization, meaning that unless religion be free from state interference and able to compete in a liberal public sphere – and thus need to change and upgrade itself vis a vis competing religious forms – it will fail to draw costumers and go bankrupt (excuse me, fail to draw believers and disappear).</p>
<p>I am willing to guess this is why the authors are positive toward evangelism: simply because it has succeeded. In an open market, laissez-faire kind of view on religion, that means it&#8217;s GOOD. It may be no accident that the two authors are the editors of The Economist.</p>
<p>On another note, I think you emphasize the importance of intellectualism a bit too much. Evangelism isn&#8217;t the most rapidly growing (or simply the only growing) Christian denomination because it&#8217;s intellectual, but because it s stress on feeling, on the direct experience of the Holy Spirit. I think that&#8217;s what is in demand today, will be  more and more  in demand in the future, and it&#8217;s with that that Jewish Orthodoxy will have to struggle.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Izgad		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/05/god-is-back-part-ii-religious-conclusions-and-orthodox-implications/#comment-1254</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Izgad]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Jul 2010 20:52:39 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1596#comment-1254</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[What I would define as the YU model is a clean cut personality and personal observance mixed with a certain intellectual worldliness. Now this fits very well into the American model. But just as the American model struggles with intellectualism, it also (and this I did not discuss in the review) struggles with a dialectic of being in the system and being outside of it. Evangelical Christianity has handled this dialectic very well since the 1970s (far better than they did in the 50s and 60s). They are able to be both clean cut suburban family values and the “edgy” challenge the system. In this they have been helped by this perception of a “liberal establishment” taking over the media and the university system during the 1960s. 
  
One of the ways I think we need to be more like the Evangelicals is in our ability to cultivate a counter-culture element in addition to our establishment. I do not see this as talking out of both sides of one’s mouth; rather it is having the baseline stability to experiment with diversity. I personally have no interest in joining an Orthodox biker gang, but I believe we need to get to a place where such a thing would be acceptable. So I think we are on the same side here. I would challenge the YU model as to where do they intend to fit in non-establishment people with their non-clean cut personalities.  There are a lot of Jews out there who consider themselves Orthodox or at least would like to be accepted by Orthodoxy, but do not fit into the obvious categories. The Orthodox establishments needs to come to terms with this fact.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What I would define as the YU model is a clean cut personality and personal observance mixed with a certain intellectual worldliness. Now this fits very well into the American model. But just as the American model struggles with intellectualism, it also (and this I did not discuss in the review) struggles with a dialectic of being in the system and being outside of it. Evangelical Christianity has handled this dialectic very well since the 1970s (far better than they did in the 50s and 60s). They are able to be both clean cut suburban family values and the “edgy” challenge the system. In this they have been helped by this perception of a “liberal establishment” taking over the media and the university system during the 1960s. </p>
<p>One of the ways I think we need to be more like the Evangelicals is in our ability to cultivate a counter-culture element in addition to our establishment. I do not see this as talking out of both sides of one’s mouth; rather it is having the baseline stability to experiment with diversity. I personally have no interest in joining an Orthodox biker gang, but I believe we need to get to a place where such a thing would be acceptable. So I think we are on the same side here. I would challenge the YU model as to where do they intend to fit in non-establishment people with their non-clean cut personalities.  There are a lot of Jews out there who consider themselves Orthodox or at least would like to be accepted by Orthodoxy, but do not fit into the obvious categories. The Orthodox establishments needs to come to terms with this fact.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
