<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Synagouge 3000 &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/tag/synagouge-3000/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2009 08:15:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='kavvanah.wordpress.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/c9f111237f93750b6b994fc5185d49c3?s=96&#038;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>Synagouge 3000 &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>Spirituality at B’nai Jeshurun</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/13/spirituality-at-b%e2%80%99nai-jeshurun/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/13/spirituality-at-b%e2%80%99nai-jeshurun/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2009 05:32:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[popular religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sociology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[arthur Green]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[B’nai Jeshurun]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[God]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[s3k]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[spirituality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Synagouge 3000]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=245</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[There is a new study from Synagogue 3000&#8212; The New Jewish Spirituality and Prayer: Take BJ, For Instance  Ayala Fader &#38; Mark Kligman S3K Synagogue Studies Institute. This one looks at the success of BJ in NYC. I have picked &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/13/spirituality-at-b%e2%80%99nai-jeshurun/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There is a new study from Synagogue 3000&#8212; The New Jewish Spirituality and Prayer: Take BJ, For Instanc<em>e  Ayala Fader &amp; Mark Kligman</em> S3K Synagogue Studies Institute. This one looks at the success of BJ in NYC. I have picked out the theological sections.  BJ preaches a spirituality of finding God in one&#8217;s own life through an emotional religious experience. Their deity is a therapeutic deism with psychological elements- it seems the true fulfillment of Arthur Green&#8217;s theology in <em>Seek My Face, Speak My Name: A Contemporary Jewish Theology</em> (1992) or the undated pop version Ehyeh: A Kabbalah for Tomorrow (2002).</p>
<blockquote><p>Central to BJ is the claim by members and rabbis alike that in order to experience God, individuals must “let go”  of rationalism and the intellect. The goal is to access an emotional part of the self which opens the individual to experience the “energy” of God, something which is found within each person. When it comes to prayer, comprehension of Hebrew (<em>loshn kodesh</em>), Jewish ritual or traditional Jewish music is less important than <em>kavanah </em>(“sincere intention”). By privileg­ing <em>kavanah</em>, the emphasis of prayer shifts from “obligation” (the <em>mitzvah</em>) to what congregants describe as the “freedom” to choose those aspects of Judaism that best speak to each individual’s experience of God.</p>
<p>[The] aim is to have religious practice create opportunities for what they call “spiritual experi­ence,” meaning the experience of God; but God must be re-concep­tualized in order to be relevant in the contemporary world. Marcelo explains: “We have to change the paradigm from the idea of God to the experience of God.” The paradigm for today’s Jews requires what the rabbis describe as a “God of love.” Jews today, suggest the rabbis, need a “reason of love” or they will abandon God. [Their ] “God of love” is not necessarily a supernatural figure. As an entity found inside the self, God is, in effect, human.</p>
<p>To find God, each person must search inside the self. This concept of God echoes humanistic beliefs, but is clearly distinct from secularism. The rabbis elaborate a post- rationalistic God, located in the emotional interior of each individual, not the intellect. The point of the commandments (<em>mitzvot</em>), claim the rabbis, is not to force us to “give up things” but to “open us up and purify us for God.” Jew­ish ritual practice, particularly prayer, is an individual choice one makes in order to experience the divine.</p>
<p>Self-exploration is often expressed in therapeutic language, but with the goal of personal transcen­dence. When there is closeness to, and individual experience of, God, an individual can become more holy in the sense of ascending to a higher level of humanity. As the rabbinic intern said: &#8220;It’s not separating the two, God and psychology. We’re not going to pass it over to the therapists&#8230;it’s about finding out where God is in your life… It’s about how you can grow holy in this thing… It’s co-opting psychology and lacing it in spiritual terms.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>Now the contextualization in studies on Spirituality and Evangelical Churches. It confirms that much of the Neo-Hasidism of liberal Jews shares much in style with Conservative Evangelicals.</p>
<blockquote><p>Embodied religious practice comes also through the use in services of practices from a range of minority religions. A number of people talked about the use of “breath” and meditation techniques. Others adopt meta­phors of “healing and wholeness” drawn from therapeutic contexts. This kind of combinative religious practice is a com­mon feature of New Age spirituality (Rothenberg and Vallely, 2008). Individualized picking and choosing from world religions in order to satisfy personal needs is a feature of postmodern religiosity, a “tradition” favored by Jewish baby boomers (Cohen and Eisen, 2000). But at BJ, combinative religious practice is institutionalized, not left to individual personal spiritual journeys; it is part and parcel of the synagogue, modeled publicly by authoritative spiritual leaders, and framed as the revitalization of Juda­ism’s authentic and shared religious heritage.</p>
<p>BJ shares many goals and practices with North Ameri­can megachurches and evangelical seeker churches. These churches focus on Christian spirituality in large settings where members can be part of a growing, successful and innovative ministry (Thumma and Travis, 2007:158). Like so many at BJ also, evangelical seekers, predominant­ly baby boomers, decidedly depart from the denomina­tion of their upbringing, searching out religious fulfill­ment through individual choice and a therapeutic ethos with an anti-institutional bias (Sargeant, 2000:163-4).</p>
<p>However, BJ has a distinctive definition of what indi­vidual fulfillment means. Seeker churches satisfy thera­peutic concerns for self-fulfillment through an evangelical understanding of Christ’s salvation (Sargeant, 2000). At BJ, individuals encounter God through individualized and, often, embodied expression of affect. Concep­tions of God, too, differ of course. Anthropologist Tanya Luhrman’s description of a “new paradigm” church (2004), for example, describes how congregants learn to conceptualize Jesus as a “buddy.” BJ members, by con­trast, find God inside themselves. However, God only enters the emotional, non-rational, vulnerable aspect of the self.</p>
<p>Regardless, what makes BJ seem modern to so many is the way that the traditional liturgy is made to engage modern forms of self-construction, including introspection, self-cultivation, and personal freedom as the path to happiness.</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="http://synagogue3000.org/files/S3KReportBJNovember2009.pdf"> Full Article Here</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/13/spirituality-at-b%e2%80%99nai-jeshurun/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>On Spiritual Choice</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/24/on-spiritual-choice/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/24/on-spiritual-choice/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2009 21:06:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[sociology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[A secular age]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[alan brill]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Alban Institute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Charles Taylor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[durkheim]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[peoplehood]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[spirituality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[synablog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Synagouge 3000]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wuthnow]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=91</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Over at Synagogue 3000, there is a post and my rsponse. I have been told there will likely be 2 more responses. Beyond Spiritual Consumerism. . . Or Not Rabbi Michael Wasserman, The New Shul, Scottsdale, AZ He wrote in &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/24/on-spiritual-choice/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Over at Synagogue 3000, there is a post and my rsponse. I have been told there will likely be 2 more responses.</p>
<p><a href="http://synagogue3000.org/synablog/?p=157"><strong>Beyond Spiritual Consumerism. . . Or Not</strong></a></p>
<p><strong><em>Rabbi Michael Wasserman</em>, The New Shul, Scottsdale, AZ</strong></p>
<p>He wrote in his opinion piece:</p>
<blockquote><p>Lawrence Hoffman &#8230;  envisions people taking advantage of a wide menu of synagogue offerings according to their individual tastes, much as they shop for clothes (<em>Rethinking Synagogues</em>, pp. 174-175).  If we ask for no sense of shared responsibility, then aren’t we treating people, in essence, as spiritual consumers? Aren’t we inviting them, in effect, to “buy” spiritual experiences?</p></blockquote>
<p>I commented:</p>
<p><a href="http://synagogue3000.org/synablog/?p=157"><strong>Choice Does Not Always Mean Consumer Choice</strong></a></p>
<p>On Sunday nights, I am glued to my TV watching the hit show Mad Men The show ostensively focuses on an ad agency in 1962 portraying the rise of advertising and consumer culture in America. But the real story is the sense of falling and anxiety that occurred when the certainties of the nineteen fifties gave way to the individualism of the 1960’s. I find that this post “ <span style="color:windowtext;text-decoration:none;">Beyond Spiritual Consumerism. . . Or Not</span>” confuses the plot with the real story.</p>
<div style="margin:0;"><strong> </strong></div>
<div style="margin:0;">In the 1950’s people learned to accept culturally constructed institutions and model ideal attitudes whose expectations might not have been experienced privately. In the 1960’s people started to seek their own individual directions and overcome the split between the institutional and the personal. They moved from dwelling to seeking. By the 1980’s and 1990’s this individualism became the norm.</div>
<div style="margin:0;">Jews aspired to a collective idea of peoplehood and accepted institutional attitudes toward Judaism, family life, and society. Mordechai Kaplan’s important re-evaluation of Judaism was based on the descriptive ideas of Durkheim in which individuals express themselves in collectives. But what comes after Durkheim, and the evident decline in self-definition through Jewish institutions?</div>
<div style="margin:0;">Charles Taylor in his recent work <em>A Secular Age</em> points out that Durkheim’s approach — in which individuals expressed themselves in collectives and institutions — no longer holds true in its original meaning. Religion today, Taylor argues, can be found in “the continuing multiplication of new options, religious, spiritual, and anti-religious, which individuals seize on in order to make sense of their lives.” Taylor stresses the complex ways in which religion is now even more a part of our daily lives, and the importance of a multiplicity of practices and interpretations to deal with this variety.</div>
<div style="margin:0;">In the post –Durkheim reality described by Taylor, we need to reframe the issue away from peoplehood to individual meanings and smaller social units, in short, religion in the human life.  We need to think in terms of changes based on the small changes of meanings and moral orders.</div>
<div style="margin:0;">Take, for example, the variety of religious experiences and moral orders that could be found among the pews in a single congregation on Yom Kippur 2009. We will find people from whom Judaism is of varying importance in their daily lives, but for whom the content of that Judaism is different and varying. There will be those who adhere to old-time theology, those for whom Judaism is about being a politically conservative ADL supporter, those who are progressive, another who stresses social action, another who understands reality using 12-step language, and another who eclectically combines Chabad, <em>feng shui</em>, and Buddhist spirituality, those who are uplifted through art, and even moral majority Jews who embrace Judaism for its strong “family values.” There are dozens of other Jewish moral orders, no congregation has even half of them. People choose to obligate themselves to these diverse meanings because they help make sense of their lives.</div>
<div style="margin:0;">Recently, many analysts of the Jewish community have picked up the phrase “spiritual marketplace” (first used a generation ago) and proceed to compare the Jewish choices made by today’s Jew to the choice of a “grande soy latte” in Starbucks – a simile implying a degree of pampering and meaningless luxuries. Viewing Jews making life decisions as Starbucks customers, their policy proposals emphasize the need to reach younger Jews through better marketing. However, religious choices, as Robert Wuthnow has stressed, reflect an attempt to create meaningful lives and a structure of moral orders. Multiple choices do not lead to the banal market pluralism, but to a variety of constructed finite religious identities.</div>
<div style="margin:0;">When entering the contemporary spiritual landscape, the contemporary Jew experiences not three or four denominations, but dozens of flavors. Synagogues and Jewish organization become specialized into single products for specialized audiences. So of course, people enjoy the Synaplex model because it gives them a possibility, a chance, to experience what they find meaningful. If they are lucky, they can find their personal vision validated.</div>
<div style="margin:0;">To return to the original issue of equating choice with consumer choice, we need to look at moral orders and meanings created.</div>
<div style="margin:0;">Seekers, as Wuthnow categorized them, are not a single category but are many approaches and many moral orders. While some still seek naturalism, other seekers embrace traditional concepts of God. The literature in the field of spirituality divides spirituality into anywhere between four to ten different types. Many of the books from Alban Institute place the number at four.</div>
<div style="margin:0;">Rabbis need to know that these different types of spirituality are not interchangeable and that congregants are not choosing them just for consumerist variety. Some congregants seeking certain forms of spirituality are actually repelled by some of the others. No one congregation can attempt all of the current varieties of spirituality. No Rabbi can offer all of them. But there is shopping because there in fact several different unique types of spirituality, each with their own sense of meaning, not because they have internalized the marketplace values.</div>
<div style="margin:0;">The blog post asked “If we ask for no sense of shared responsibility, then aren’t we treating people, in essence, as spiritual consumers?”</div>
<div style="margin:0;">The answer is no!  Judaism is capacious and has the possibility of many meanings constructed and many moral orders formed. That is, unless, the vision is to return the community to the 1950’s. We watch Mad Men to remind ourselves how much we have changed.</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/24/on-spiritual-choice/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Israel as an Educational Text</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/23/israel-as-an-educational-text/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/23/israel-as-an-educational-text/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2009 00:48:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[israel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Synagouge 3000]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=61</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I just received by email the latest report from Synagogue 3000&#8217;s Synagogue Studies Institute &#8220;Bringing Conversations about Israel into the Life of American Congregations.&#8221; Authors Alex Sinclair and Esti Moskovitz-Kalman It seems the goal after 2000 years and the return &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/23/israel-as-an-educational-text/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I just received by email the latest report from Synagogue 3000&#8217;s Synagogue Studies Institute &#8220;Bringing Conversations about Israel into the Life of American Congregations.&#8221; Authors Alex Sinclair and Esti Moskovitz-Kalman</p>
<p>It seems the goal after 2000 years and the return to the land of Israel is to go back to treating Israel as a symbol- or a text, an idea, a midrash. Not to treat Israel as a flesh and blood realpolitic middle eastern country, at least on the synagogue level. Israel is something to understand from a distance through the lens of one’s personal life. Birthright is successful since it takes place in Israel but is an American experience, as are many of the “year in Israel” programs. It does not let Israeli reality interfere with eduction.  These programs allow American to understand Israel though the lens of their American suburban lives.</p>
<p>They study  refers to another  recent study that shows that American Jews are not emotionally  distant from Israel, just lost in the self-absorption of their pleasure seeking lives.</p>
<p>What of AIPAC and <em>CPMAJO a<em>nd their advocacy activities? </em>ANS: They collide with<em> Jewish education. </em></em></p>
<p><em>Here are some quotes:<em><br />
</em></em></p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Israel is a Jewish Text</strong><strong></strong></p>
<p>We begin with an audacious claim: <em>Israel</em><em> is a Jewish text like all other Jewish texts. </em>And we Jews know a thing or two about how to read, discuss, teach, learn and draw mean­ing from texts.</p>
<p>We know how to grapple with a text we find problematic. We know how to incorporate the ideas of texts into our own lives….</p>
<p>The “distancing from Israel” hypothesis has been challenged empiri­cally (Sasson, Kadushin, and Saxe 2008).Nevertheless, from a value perspective, both schools of thought agree that it is absolutely critical that Israel engagement become a vehicle for personal meaning-making  Without a deep level of personal meaning, the American Jew will not engage with Israel. <em>Our claim is that conversation is a significant educa­tional means and end to lead to that personal meaning-makin</em>g, even, and indeed especially, for those Jews who have weak prior commitments to Israel.</p>
<p>Sasson, T., Kadushin, C., and Saxe, L. (2008). <em>American Jewish Attach­ment to Israel: an assessment of the “distancing” hypothesis. </em>Boston: Maurice and Marilyn  Cohen Center for Modern Jewish Studies</p>
<p>A congregant I am working with right now says “I have no interest in going to Israel; there are a thousand other places in the world where I would rather go.” I don’t think we have yet answered these questions for the vast majority of people.</p>
<p><strong>The Israel Advocacy Agenda — Friend or Foe?</strong></p>
<p>However, notwithstanding its value in the political sphere, Israel advo­cacy can collide with Israel education. The advocacy agenda may alienate those who don’t like politics in general. It certainly repels congregants who question the very Israeli policies that the advocates espouse. It frustrates those who reject being told that contrary to the ethos of the democracy in which they live, they may not voice their doubts about Israel’s policies openly and honestly.</p>
<p><a href="http:// http://synagogue3000.org/files/IsraelConversations.pdf"> </a><a href="http://synagogue3000.org/files/IsraelConversations.pdf" target="_self">Article</a></p></blockquote>
<p>I am not sure what to think about this. I do think they are correct educationally. They are correct about the way American students  project on Israel and I do think education need to be separated from advocacy. (i dont want to discuss politics)  But it means that Israel has to become part of the construction of an American life, a projection onto a silent land It is like the ideal in Graham Green novels novels of marrying someone who does not speak your language in order to have an ideal marriage, since one can project onto the silent spouse anything one wants. The longing of Yehudah Halevi and the heavenly Jerusalem of a Hasidic text is more inspiring than actual Israeli society.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/23/israel-as-an-educational-text/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
