<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Remember Always- First Thought&#8217;s on Miroslav Volf&#8217;s The End of Memory	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/04/19/remember-always-first-thoughts-on-miroslav-volfs-the-end-of-memory/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/04/19/remember-always-first-thoughts-on-miroslav-volfs-the-end-of-memory/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Apr 2012 23:27:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Josh		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/04/19/remember-always-first-thoughts-on-miroslav-volfs-the-end-of-memory/#comment-4400</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 22 Apr 2012 23:27:40 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/04/19/remember-always-first-thoughts-on-miroslav-volfs-the-end-of-memory/#comment-4400</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This posts shifts from book review to normative stuff really fast. Thus it ends up conflating at least three kinds of memory. Liturgical memory is what Levinas seems to be addressing in terms of the Exodus and Tisha BeAv. Then there&#039;s the weird survivor memories that aren&#039;t or can&#039;t be totally true because they&#039;re exaggerated, self serving, or just misunderstandings. A third category called Elie Wiesel memory, which draws on the patois of the first kind of memory and the inaccuracies of the second to create a literary genre of memory. There are different normative pitfalls to each of the three memories. This is true even though all of them can be contrasted with &quot;History.&quot; Without being exhaustive of all normative issues, I think the normative pitfalls are distinct in each case. 
Liturgy suffers from the problem of ossification and translation. Its not readily assimilable to normative purposes without translation. This is why we don&#039;t get really bloodthirsty around parshas Zachor. Because we need to transpose Amalek from one idiom to another to get Amalek= Ahmidinejad. And that work of transposition is also a work of mistranslation. If Amalek is Ahmi, then Amalek is Ahmidinejad outside of the rhythms of liturgical time in which Amalek is Amalek. Sadly, Ahmi never fully mythologizes himself into a live Amalek in the Torah.  So we could have a Holocaustian liturgy of kinnot which are eventually as alive as the kinnot for the Jews of the Crusades. This is not to say that liturgical memory has no positive contributions to make to a normative project. But its not really the way to get people to do stuff. It might build group cohesion or help coordinate people&#039;s actions (eg we all meet at shul on shavout and hatch a plan to kill Ahmi) but its not going to be a simple thing. 
(I am assuming prayer has no perlocutionary effects-- however if it does its possible that reading  the 13 attributes of mercy may lead to the deaths of the enemies of Israel or something. Which would be interesting to see.)
The delicate and ever passing memories of survivors are harder for me to criticize. Its hard to say these lead to hate. After all, rational listeners can contextualize survivors words and realize that they are traumatized by terrible persecutions. I do not think the Manichean worldview which twinges the apocalyptic fringes of some Jews today comes from survivors at all. In fact, one could argue that the current obsession with 1939 comes from the children emigre writers who dodged the bullet of the Holocaust. Subsequently, they decided that they could have prevented it. There&#039;s something like a fetishization of history that leads to its hypostatization in this move, where if only the right people would&#039;ve been empowered at some cinematic and utterly decisive juncture, the whole thing would&#039;ve happened differently. It reminds me of the ability to get a &quot;do over&quot; which was common to nintendo games of my youth. I guess the underpinnings of this fetishization of decisive historical moments stem from some ability to separate history into two discrete substances: the phenomenon of history itself, and the failed Labor party hacks who actually enacted that history, and then substitute the latter with heroic and farsighted experts in hindsight. 
Whatever the case may be, it seems like survivors testimonies form a living memory which is contextualized and domesticated by historians with utter regularity but which still has some power (often overrated) to connect people in mystical ways with past things. So what&#039;s wrong with that? It doesn&#039;t prevent genocide in Cambodia? OK. That&#039;s because survivors were busy working in NJ real estate and didn&#039;t have time to prevent genocide in Cambodia. Is the normative upshot of this that people who suffered genocide need to take the time and effort to prevent it in far flung corners of the world? That sounds like an awful lot of trouble for people who lost years of their lives fleeing genocide!
I will not comment on the third genre of memory except to note that it seems to bear the brunt of the criticism here. Its unfortunate that one literary genre, through whatever accidental circumstances, became so popular. But again, its hard to see why this contains special normative value. The hunger games is about economic exploitation, but no one goes out to prevent economic exploitation or gladiator contests based on the hunger games. Similarly, the books of Wiesel deal with the holocaust. Sadly, they aren&#039;t a panacea for preventing future holocausts.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This posts shifts from book review to normative stuff really fast. Thus it ends up conflating at least three kinds of memory. Liturgical memory is what Levinas seems to be addressing in terms of the Exodus and Tisha BeAv. Then there&#8217;s the weird survivor memories that aren&#8217;t or can&#8217;t be totally true because they&#8217;re exaggerated, self serving, or just misunderstandings. A third category called Elie Wiesel memory, which draws on the patois of the first kind of memory and the inaccuracies of the second to create a literary genre of memory. There are different normative pitfalls to each of the three memories. This is true even though all of them can be contrasted with &#8220;History.&#8221; Without being exhaustive of all normative issues, I think the normative pitfalls are distinct in each case.<br />
Liturgy suffers from the problem of ossification and translation. Its not readily assimilable to normative purposes without translation. This is why we don&#8217;t get really bloodthirsty around parshas Zachor. Because we need to transpose Amalek from one idiom to another to get Amalek= Ahmidinejad. And that work of transposition is also a work of mistranslation. If Amalek is Ahmi, then Amalek is Ahmidinejad outside of the rhythms of liturgical time in which Amalek is Amalek. Sadly, Ahmi never fully mythologizes himself into a live Amalek in the Torah.  So we could have a Holocaustian liturgy of kinnot which are eventually as alive as the kinnot for the Jews of the Crusades. This is not to say that liturgical memory has no positive contributions to make to a normative project. But its not really the way to get people to do stuff. It might build group cohesion or help coordinate people&#8217;s actions (eg we all meet at shul on shavout and hatch a plan to kill Ahmi) but its not going to be a simple thing.<br />
(I am assuming prayer has no perlocutionary effects&#8211; however if it does its possible that reading  the 13 attributes of mercy may lead to the deaths of the enemies of Israel or something. Which would be interesting to see.)<br />
The delicate and ever passing memories of survivors are harder for me to criticize. Its hard to say these lead to hate. After all, rational listeners can contextualize survivors words and realize that they are traumatized by terrible persecutions. I do not think the Manichean worldview which twinges the apocalyptic fringes of some Jews today comes from survivors at all. In fact, one could argue that the current obsession with 1939 comes from the children emigre writers who dodged the bullet of the Holocaust. Subsequently, they decided that they could have prevented it. There&#8217;s something like a fetishization of history that leads to its hypostatization in this move, where if only the right people would&#8217;ve been empowered at some cinematic and utterly decisive juncture, the whole thing would&#8217;ve happened differently. It reminds me of the ability to get a &#8220;do over&#8221; which was common to nintendo games of my youth. I guess the underpinnings of this fetishization of decisive historical moments stem from some ability to separate history into two discrete substances: the phenomenon of history itself, and the failed Labor party hacks who actually enacted that history, and then substitute the latter with heroic and farsighted experts in hindsight.<br />
Whatever the case may be, it seems like survivors testimonies form a living memory which is contextualized and domesticated by historians with utter regularity but which still has some power (often overrated) to connect people in mystical ways with past things. So what&#8217;s wrong with that? It doesn&#8217;t prevent genocide in Cambodia? OK. That&#8217;s because survivors were busy working in NJ real estate and didn&#8217;t have time to prevent genocide in Cambodia. Is the normative upshot of this that people who suffered genocide need to take the time and effort to prevent it in far flung corners of the world? That sounds like an awful lot of trouble for people who lost years of their lives fleeing genocide!<br />
I will not comment on the third genre of memory except to note that it seems to bear the brunt of the criticism here. Its unfortunate that one literary genre, through whatever accidental circumstances, became so popular. But again, its hard to see why this contains special normative value. The hunger games is about economic exploitation, but no one goes out to prevent economic exploitation or gladiator contests based on the hunger games. Similarly, the books of Wiesel deal with the holocaust. Sadly, they aren&#8217;t a panacea for preventing future holocausts.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/04/19/remember-always-first-thoughts-on-miroslav-volfs-the-end-of-memory/#comment-4399</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 22 Apr 2012 23:26:03 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/04/19/remember-always-first-thoughts-on-miroslav-volfs-the-end-of-memory/#comment-4399</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[C&#039;v...all I said is if it is 1939, then Jews should leave. But I think saying it&#039;s 1939 is false, and Netanyahu is politicizing the Holocaust. A  good way of seeing the many ways Jerusalem is not Vilna is to read Prof. Timothy Snyder&#039;s  &quot;Bloodlands: Europe Between Hitler and Stalin.&quot; 

Speaking of Beinart, why not a post on the acceptance and rejection of his book. I am sure you saw the piece in Jewish Ideas Daily on how the Evangelicals are beginning to rething their position on the Palestinians.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>C&#8217;v&#8230;all I said is if it is 1939, then Jews should leave. But I think saying it&#8217;s 1939 is false, and Netanyahu is politicizing the Holocaust. A  good way of seeing the many ways Jerusalem is not Vilna is to read Prof. Timothy Snyder&#8217;s  &#8220;Bloodlands: Europe Between Hitler and Stalin.&#8221; </p>
<p>Speaking of Beinart, why not a post on the acceptance and rejection of his book. I am sure you saw the piece in Jewish Ideas Daily on how the Evangelicals are beginning to rething their position on the Palestinians.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/04/19/remember-always-first-thoughts-on-miroslav-volfs-the-end-of-memory/#comment-4398</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 22 Apr 2012 22:06:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/04/19/remember-always-first-thoughts-on-miroslav-volfs-the-end-of-memory/#comment-4398</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Avi- Many of those who call to remember do not care about actual facts or historic causality. It is not about weighing evil, which cannot be measured. But the goal is not confuse the role of subjective memory in the synagogue or survivor family with the need for objective memory in the textbook. Much of the subjective memory is wildly incorrect.
You want to see my prior post on Miller&#039;s book on Hirsch&#039;s years in Moravia, https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/02/29/rabbis-and-revolution-michael-l-miller/
EJ- Maybe you should write a response to Beinart- that everyone should move out of Israel for safety?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Avi- Many of those who call to remember do not care about actual facts or historic causality. It is not about weighing evil, which cannot be measured. But the goal is not confuse the role of subjective memory in the synagogue or survivor family with the need for objective memory in the textbook. Much of the subjective memory is wildly incorrect.<br />
You want to see my prior post on Miller&#8217;s book on Hirsch&#8217;s years in Moravia, <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/02/29/rabbis-and-revolution-michael-l-miller/" rel="nofollow ugc">https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/02/29/rabbis-and-revolution-michael-l-miller/</a><br />
EJ- Maybe you should write a response to Beinart- that everyone should move out of Israel for safety?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Avi		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/04/19/remember-always-first-thoughts-on-miroslav-volfs-the-end-of-memory/#comment-4397</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Avi]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 22 Apr 2012 18:56:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/04/19/remember-always-first-thoughts-on-miroslav-volfs-the-end-of-memory/#comment-4397</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Another compelling post.

I appreciate the need to pursue objective accuracy over subjective memory--in general. But would the slight uptick or downtick on the evil meter that better accuracy would bring really be meaningful in the context of the mind-blowing evil of the Holocaust? (Or am I misunderstanding the post?)]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Another compelling post.</p>
<p>I appreciate the need to pursue objective accuracy over subjective memory&#8211;in general. But would the slight uptick or downtick on the evil meter that better accuracy would bring really be meaningful in the context of the mind-blowing evil of the Holocaust? (Or am I misunderstanding the post?)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/04/19/remember-always-first-thoughts-on-miroslav-volfs-the-end-of-memory/#comment-4396</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 22 Apr 2012 18:44:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/04/19/remember-always-first-thoughts-on-miroslav-volfs-the-end-of-memory/#comment-4396</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Two comments: 1)I have problems with universalizing the Holocaust so that we the Jewish people have a special need or obligation to prevent future genocides. There have been more than a few genocides since WW2. In none of these situations did Jews or the State of Israel play a prominent or even significant role in stopping  the murders and rapes. Mao caused the death of 40-70 million people during his reign. The estimate is that 5 million were murdered in the Congo, close to a million in Rwanda, up to 3 million in Cambodia. East Timor,Bosnia, Darfur, the Sudan, Ivory Coast…the list goes on.  My point is simple…it is not a good idea to suggest we have a special role to play in preventing genocides when we have a 65 year record of doing nothing. When Jews do get worked up, as was the case with the Jewish Neo-Conservatives in Iraq and now Iran, there were articles and lobbying that did influence American policy. 2) I once met a man who was in the city where my father was born when the Nazis invaded. All the Jews there were murdered with a few exceptions. He ran away into the forests and survived  to become a real estate mogul. I asked him what lesson he learnt from his experience. He answered with a big smile on his face “Location, location, location!”  For me the lesson of the Holocaust is to run away before it’s too late. If it is now 1939 as Netanyahu keeps on saying, Jews should leave Israel for safer places.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Two comments: 1)I have problems with universalizing the Holocaust so that we the Jewish people have a special need or obligation to prevent future genocides. There have been more than a few genocides since WW2. In none of these situations did Jews or the State of Israel play a prominent or even significant role in stopping  the murders and rapes. Mao caused the death of 40-70 million people during his reign. The estimate is that 5 million were murdered in the Congo, close to a million in Rwanda, up to 3 million in Cambodia. East Timor,Bosnia, Darfur, the Sudan, Ivory Coast…the list goes on.  My point is simple…it is not a good idea to suggest we have a special role to play in preventing genocides when we have a 65 year record of doing nothing. When Jews do get worked up, as was the case with the Jewish Neo-Conservatives in Iraq and now Iran, there were articles and lobbying that did influence American policy. 2) I once met a man who was in the city where my father was born when the Nazis invaded. All the Jews there were murdered with a few exceptions. He ran away into the forests and survived  to become a real estate mogul. I asked him what lesson he learnt from his experience. He answered with a big smile on his face “Location, location, location!”  For me the lesson of the Holocaust is to run away before it’s too late. If it is now 1939 as Netanyahu keeps on saying, Jews should leave Israel for safer places.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
