<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Why Maimonides Matters &#8212;Kenneth Hart Green-Part II	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/22/why-maimonides-matters-kenneth-hart-green-part-ii/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/22/why-maimonides-matters-kenneth-hart-green-part-ii/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2013 14:23:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Yonatan Kaganoff		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/22/why-maimonides-matters-kenneth-hart-green-part-ii/#comment-8049</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Yonatan Kaganoff]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2013 14:23:40 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6113#comment-8049</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I would like to question Professor Green&#039;s presentation of Maimonides&#039; as a model of moderation. 
Clearly in the cultivation of virtues, Maimonides seeks the golden mean and the aschews extremism. However, I suspect that many in the audience will understanding moderation as validating their Middle Class bourgeois lifestyle. 

In the Shemonah Perakim, Maimonides clearly and strongly states that all of ones activities should be dedicated to the service of God. Eating, drinking, leisure above the minimum is condemned by Maimonides. Even if one maintains a healthy moderate lifestyle but for the wrong reasons, that too is incorrect. 

Please respond to this aspect of Maimonidean thought and spiritual practices, which appear to be out of sync with Western Middle Class lifestyles.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I would like to question Professor Green&#8217;s presentation of Maimonides&#8217; as a model of moderation.<br />
Clearly in the cultivation of virtues, Maimonides seeks the golden mean and the aschews extremism. However, I suspect that many in the audience will understanding moderation as validating their Middle Class bourgeois lifestyle. </p>
<p>In the Shemonah Perakim, Maimonides clearly and strongly states that all of ones activities should be dedicated to the service of God. Eating, drinking, leisure above the minimum is condemned by Maimonides. Even if one maintains a healthy moderate lifestyle but for the wrong reasons, that too is incorrect. </p>
<p>Please respond to this aspect of Maimonidean thought and spiritual practices, which appear to be out of sync with Western Middle Class lifestyles.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Ira Rohde		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/22/why-maimonides-matters-kenneth-hart-green-part-ii/#comment-8048</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ira Rohde]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2013 00:20:51 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6113#comment-8048</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/22/why-maimonides-matters-kenneth-hart-green-part-ii/#comment-8044&quot;&gt;Eric&lt;/a&gt;.

Thanks, Eric, for your help. I am seriously behind the times. 
The postscript is translated in the new expanded English addition of TaPQ, and although you are correct that he says the book is aimed against Leibowitz, Strauss as well as Husik were also major foils. It&#039;s great to see him admit more sympathy for the &quot;dualistic&quot; Straussians, although he still evidently feels that Strauss&#039; views are dismissive of the central role Halakhah plays in Maimonides&#039; philosophic world view. And my impression is that despite his &quot;sympathy,&quot; Hartman still finds such &quot;dualistic&quot; views psychologically inauthentic and hence, for him, due to his own predilection for analyzing ancient and medieval authors based upon modern psychology (which as a Straussian I find highly objectionable) - intolerable. 
Upon my re-reading, I admit that Strauss&#039; collaborator in issuing the Guide&#039;s translation, Prof. Pines, in his forward to TaPQ, said something similar to what I am in pointing out the limitation of positive human knowledge beyond the sub-lunar sphere in the Guide and in some understandings of one of Maimonides&#039; major philosophic sources, Al-Farabi. Thanks for the interview as well as the Drazin &#038; Klingenstein articles. Bloom seems to imply that there was an evolution in Strauss&#039; views of Maimonides.
I&#039;m open to a younger Strauss writing to Glatzer and other former Lehrhaus associates of having felt that Maimonides was more purely inclined to philosophic truth.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/22/why-maimonides-matters-kenneth-hart-green-part-ii/#comment-8044">Eric</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks, Eric, for your help. I am seriously behind the times.<br />
The postscript is translated in the new expanded English addition of TaPQ, and although you are correct that he says the book is aimed against Leibowitz, Strauss as well as Husik were also major foils. It&#8217;s great to see him admit more sympathy for the &#8220;dualistic&#8221; Straussians, although he still evidently feels that Strauss&#8217; views are dismissive of the central role Halakhah plays in Maimonides&#8217; philosophic world view. And my impression is that despite his &#8220;sympathy,&#8221; Hartman still finds such &#8220;dualistic&#8221; views psychologically inauthentic and hence, for him, due to his own predilection for analyzing ancient and medieval authors based upon modern psychology (which as a Straussian I find highly objectionable) &#8211; intolerable.<br />
Upon my re-reading, I admit that Strauss&#8217; collaborator in issuing the Guide&#8217;s translation, Prof. Pines, in his forward to TaPQ, said something similar to what I am in pointing out the limitation of positive human knowledge beyond the sub-lunar sphere in the Guide and in some understandings of one of Maimonides&#8217; major philosophic sources, Al-Farabi. Thanks for the interview as well as the Drazin &amp; Klingenstein articles. Bloom seems to imply that there was an evolution in Strauss&#8217; views of Maimonides.<br />
I&#8217;m open to a younger Strauss writing to Glatzer and other former Lehrhaus associates of having felt that Maimonides was more purely inclined to philosophic truth.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Eric		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/22/why-maimonides-matters-kenneth-hart-green-part-ii/#comment-8044</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eric]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2013 15:30:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6113#comment-8044</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/22/why-maimonides-matters-kenneth-hart-green-part-ii/#comment-8039&quot;&gt;Ira Rohde&lt;/a&gt;.

Ira,

I know it wasn&#039;t the major thrust of your comment, but see Rabbi Hartman&#039;s postscript to the 2009 Hebrew edition of TaPQ - he admits that he came to the realization that although not in accord with his understanding of Maimonides, a Straussian reading of Maimonides is plausible, and that his true foil in the book is . . . Yeshayahu Leibovitz.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/22/why-maimonides-matters-kenneth-hart-green-part-ii/#comment-8039">Ira Rohde</a>.</p>
<p>Ira,</p>
<p>I know it wasn&#8217;t the major thrust of your comment, but see Rabbi Hartman&#8217;s postscript to the 2009 Hebrew edition of TaPQ &#8211; he admits that he came to the realization that although not in accord with his understanding of Maimonides, a Straussian reading of Maimonides is plausible, and that his true foil in the book is . . . Yeshayahu Leibovitz.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Lawrence Kaplan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/22/why-maimonides-matters-kenneth-hart-green-part-ii/#comment-8042</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lawrence Kaplan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2013 12:44:13 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6113#comment-8042</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Ranak was aware of an esoteric dimension to the Guide. See the end of Chapter 4 of MNZ.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ranak was aware of an esoteric dimension to the Guide. See the end of Chapter 4 of MNZ.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: moti		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/22/why-maimonides-matters-kenneth-hart-green-part-ii/#comment-8040</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[moti]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2013 02:33:15 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6113#comment-8040</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I want to thank Professor Green for his thoughtful response to my comment. I&#039;ve just purchased the book LS and the Rediscovery and Maimonides and look forward to reading it.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I want to thank Professor Green for his thoughtful response to my comment. I&#8217;ve just purchased the book LS and the Rediscovery and Maimonides and look forward to reading it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Ira Rohde		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/22/why-maimonides-matters-kenneth-hart-green-part-ii/#comment-8039</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ira Rohde]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2013 20:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6113#comment-8039</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I don&#039;t see in Professor Green&#039;s comments the greatest defense of Leo Strauss&#039; esotericist view of Maimonides, a view which could also be called &quot;dualistic&quot; or &quot;Averroistic&quot; (in the sense of &quot;double-truthed&quot;), from virulent attacks such as David Hartman&#039;s (which is clearly against Leo Strauss&#039; views even where Hartman doesn&#039;t mention Strauss by name) in his introduction to &quot;Maimonides: Torah and Philosophic Quest, &quot; p. 9-13, where he says: &quot;This dishonest separation may still be tolerated because of an awareness that submission to social and political virtue is the only way of living in a crude world of mass ignorance. One is then condemned to live in this social and political world as a philosophic Marrano.&quot; 

My own defense of Strauss I would borrow from my reading of Straussian Alan Bloom: Yes, Strauss feels Maimonides accepts and justifies much of the halakhic system within political categories. Yes, there is real truth in the world above, outside the cave, which one could theoretically get to apart from knowledge of things in the cave, and it is important to reach that as a goal in the end. But it is exactly the political/religious world we live in, the world within the cave, the world of shadows, which is the more important one. 

A Maimonidean Platonism (which Strauss explicitly points to) would see the construction of the Republic of halakha as the supreme task it is for the philosopher. It is in the world formed by halakha that the philosopher and the proto-philosopher will be protected and enabled as he discretely pursues the investigation of truth. Hartman writes tellingly, in the same section: &quot;Socrates was the fool who confused philosophy with ethics and politics.&quot; Well, we all know what Bloom, and, in his view, presumably, Strauss, would say to that: Socrates was no fool. Socrates drank the cup completely willingly, fully conceding Athen&#039;s ethical right and duty to execute him. And Maimonides fully endorsed the limiting of philosophical and religious speculation publicly. 

Halakhah, the world of Torah, does point to truth. The truth it points to are the &quot;ideas,&quot; which are, after all, only the shadows on the wall of the cave. But in our world, it is primarily by inferring from those shadows that we know about the &quot;truth&quot; beyond the cave. Hence the philosopher who has seen the light above the cave must conceal some and only selectively reveal if he is to be effective in his mission of return to the cave to enlighten the inhabitants. 

That&#039;s the way I, as an Orthodox Jew, would defend a Straussian view of Maimonides&#039; esotericism, The problem I have with Strauss and his followers is why didn&#039;t they say something like that themselves? I&#039;m going through Bauman&#039;s translation of Leo Strauss&#039; &quot;Philosophy and Law,&quot; finding reference after reference to Enlightenment thinkers versus Jewish &quot;Orthodoxy,&quot; without Strauss ever defining what a Jewish Orthodoxy would truly be in his view. Perhaps his own Jewish knowledge, he felt, was inadequate. How well did Strauss really know the rest of the Maimonidean ouevre, aside from the Guide? But Strauss seems to just assume &quot;Orthodoxy&quot; will always be there for him and stayed aloof from us practicing Orthodox Jews in our struggle to define what Orthodoxy means.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I don&#8217;t see in Professor Green&#8217;s comments the greatest defense of Leo Strauss&#8217; esotericist view of Maimonides, a view which could also be called &#8220;dualistic&#8221; or &#8220;Averroistic&#8221; (in the sense of &#8220;double-truthed&#8221;), from virulent attacks such as David Hartman&#8217;s (which is clearly against Leo Strauss&#8217; views even where Hartman doesn&#8217;t mention Strauss by name) in his introduction to &#8220;Maimonides: Torah and Philosophic Quest, &#8221; p. 9-13, where he says: &#8220;This dishonest separation may still be tolerated because of an awareness that submission to social and political virtue is the only way of living in a crude world of mass ignorance. One is then condemned to live in this social and political world as a philosophic Marrano.&#8221; </p>
<p>My own defense of Strauss I would borrow from my reading of Straussian Alan Bloom: Yes, Strauss feels Maimonides accepts and justifies much of the halakhic system within political categories. Yes, there is real truth in the world above, outside the cave, which one could theoretically get to apart from knowledge of things in the cave, and it is important to reach that as a goal in the end. But it is exactly the political/religious world we live in, the world within the cave, the world of shadows, which is the more important one. </p>
<p>A Maimonidean Platonism (which Strauss explicitly points to) would see the construction of the Republic of halakha as the supreme task it is for the philosopher. It is in the world formed by halakha that the philosopher and the proto-philosopher will be protected and enabled as he discretely pursues the investigation of truth. Hartman writes tellingly, in the same section: &#8220;Socrates was the fool who confused philosophy with ethics and politics.&#8221; Well, we all know what Bloom, and, in his view, presumably, Strauss, would say to that: Socrates was no fool. Socrates drank the cup completely willingly, fully conceding Athen&#8217;s ethical right and duty to execute him. And Maimonides fully endorsed the limiting of philosophical and religious speculation publicly. </p>
<p>Halakhah, the world of Torah, does point to truth. The truth it points to are the &#8220;ideas,&#8221; which are, after all, only the shadows on the wall of the cave. But in our world, it is primarily by inferring from those shadows that we know about the &#8220;truth&#8221; beyond the cave. Hence the philosopher who has seen the light above the cave must conceal some and only selectively reveal if he is to be effective in his mission of return to the cave to enlighten the inhabitants. </p>
<p>That&#8217;s the way I, as an Orthodox Jew, would defend a Straussian view of Maimonides&#8217; esotericism, The problem I have with Strauss and his followers is why didn&#8217;t they say something like that themselves? I&#8217;m going through Bauman&#8217;s translation of Leo Strauss&#8217; &#8220;Philosophy and Law,&#8221; finding reference after reference to Enlightenment thinkers versus Jewish &#8220;Orthodoxy,&#8221; without Strauss ever defining what a Jewish Orthodoxy would truly be in his view. Perhaps his own Jewish knowledge, he felt, was inadequate. How well did Strauss really know the rest of the Maimonidean ouevre, aside from the Guide? But Strauss seems to just assume &#8220;Orthodoxy&#8221; will always be there for him and stayed aloof from us practicing Orthodox Jews in our struggle to define what Orthodoxy means.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
