<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>israel &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/category/israel/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2010 21:18:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='kavvanah.wordpress.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/c9f111237f93750b6b994fc5185d49c3?s=96&#038;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>israel &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>David Shasha on Kellner, Idel, and Nationalism</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/08/david-shasha-on-kellner-idel-and-nationalism/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/08/david-shasha-on-kellner-idel-and-nationalism/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2010 21:16:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[israel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[david shasha]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[menachem Kellner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Moshe idel]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1643</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[David Shasha is a proponent of all things Sefardi and a radical follower of Jose Faur who envisions a Levantine synthesis of Jewish and Arabic humanism. Shasha offers a critique of Kellner, Idel and others as destroying the humanistic foundations &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/08/david-shasha-on-kellner-idel-and-nationalism/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>David Shasha is a proponent of  all things Sefardi and a radical follower of Jose Faur who envisions a Levantine synthesis of Jewish and Arabic humanism. Shasha offers a critique of Kellner, Idel and others as destroying the humanistic foundations of Judaism. He claims that they destroy the foundation of Maimonidean humanism even if they accept Maimonides. Kellner advocates for the rationalism of Maimonides but back-handedly considers the Maimonideans as too demanding for the common person, as rejecting folk religion, and as not the Jewish tradition. Shasha demands that Maimonides be considered the tradition or else Maimonideans would always be in a defensive position. If one does not live in a rational world then all the power is in the magical hand of the rabbis. </p>
<p>Shasha places blame at the feet of Moshe Idel who explores the magical, irrational, and mythic forces in Judaism but who also maintains that this theurgic world is the world of the Talmudic Rabbis. For Idel, the Rabbinic tradition is magical. Kabbalah is not a Gnostic intruder into Judaism but the very meaning of the commandments for the Rabbis. Once Jews studied Saadyah, Ibn Ezra, Maimonides, Gersonides as the traditon, now they read Abulafia and Zohar. For Shasha, this is tantamount to a return to idolatry and the source of militant nationalism. <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/david-shasha/dangerous-mystic-motifs-i_b_637535.html">Full Version here.</a></p>
<p>Shasha writes:<br />
<em>At the center of this controversy is the vexing question of Jewish authenticity.<br />
In his 2006 study &#8220;Maimonides&#8217; Confrontation with Mysticism,&#8221; Menachem Kellner adopts an approach that has become standard in most Jewish circles, writing:</p>
<blockquote><p>&#8220;The Jewish world in which Maimonides lived was uncongenial to the austere, abstract, demanding vision of Torah which he preached. Evidence from a wide variety of sources shows that Jews in Maimonides&#8217; day &#8211; common folk and scholars alike &#8211; accepted astrology, the magical use of divine names, appeals to angels, etc.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p></em><em> In a noble attempt to elevate the thinking of Maimonides, Kellner&#8217;s arguments bizarrely lend credence to the positions of the anti-Maimonideans.</em><br />
<em>In the book&#8217;s conclusion he states:</em></p>
<blockquote><p>The world favored by Maimonides&#8217; opponents, on the other hand, is an &#8220;enchanted&#8221; world. Many of Maimonides&#8217; opponents, in his day and ours, do indeed accept the efficacy of charms and amulets, and fear the harm of demons and the evil eye. But it is not in that sense that I maintain that they live in an enchanted world. Theirs is not a world which can be explained in terms of the unvarying workings of divinely ordered laws of nature; it is not a world which can be rationally understood. It is a world in which the notion of miracle loses all meaning, since everything that happens is a miracle. In such a world instructions from God, and contact with the divine in general, must be mediated by a religious elite who alone can see the true reality masked by nature. This is the opposite of an empowering religion, since it takes their fate out of the hands of Jews, and, in effect, puts it into the hands of the rabbis.</p></blockquote>
<p><em>We can see the tension at the heart of Kellner&#8217;s argument, a tension that forces his hand in accepting the absolute authenticity of the mystical-occult tradition of the Kabbalah and rejecting the Jewish validity of Maimonidean rationalism.</p>
<p>Kellner&#8217;s book contains a forward by Hebrew University professor Moshe Idel, perhaps the single most influential academic in the world of Judaica, a winner of the prestigious Israel Prize and a ubiquitous presence in the world of Jewish studies. Idel has relentlessly promoted the pro-magic, neo-pagan, anti-rational strain of Jewish tradition also called Kabbalah. </p>
<p>Idel&#8217;s scholarly project has been designed to affirm the authenticity of the mystical-occult Kabbalah and undermine the validity of the rational standards of Religious Humanism. As we see in a representative passage in his seminal 1988 work &#8220;Kabbalah: New Perspectives&#8221;:</em></p>
<blockquote><p>Kabbalah can be viewed as part of a restructuring of those aspects of rabbinic thought that were denied authenticity by Maimonides&#8217; system. Far from being a total innovation, historical Kabbalah represented an ongoing effort to systematize existing elements of Jewish theurgy, myth, and mysticism into a full-fledged response to the rationalistic challenge.<br />
It is, however, possible to assume that, if the motifs transmitted in those unknown [Kabbalistic] circles formed part of an ancient weltanschauung, their affinities to the rabbinic mentality would be more organic and easily absorbed into the mystic cast of Judaism.<br />
According to this hypothesis, we do not need to account for why ancient Jews took over Gnostic doctrines, why they transmitted them, and, finally, how this &#8216;Gnostic&#8217; Judaism was revived in the Middle Ages by conservative Jewish authorities. </p></blockquote>
<p>Shasha concludes:</p>
<p><em>This has led to the rejection of Sephardic Jewish Humanism as formulated by Maimonides and an affirmation of an ethnocentric Jewish chauvinism based on the magical mysticism of Kabbalistic theurgy. It is a Judaism that rejects the tenets of a critical reading of the Jewish past and has led us to the sort of ideological purity and militant nationalism that has become characteristic of the intractable impasse in the Middle East. Though this occult process has been secularized by Zionism, it is apparent that the ideological values of the mystical continue to animate the Jewish self-perception in a nationalistic sense.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/08/david-shasha-on-kellner-idel-and-nationalism/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>10</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Ben-Gurion, Bergman and Aurobindo in Israel</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/30/ben-gurion-bergman-and-aurobindo-in-israel/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/30/ben-gurion-bergman-and-aurobindo-in-israel/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2010 15:59:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[hinduism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[israel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ben-gurion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hugo Bergman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sri Aurobindo]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1417</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Here is a found nugget from Tusar N. Mohapatra I read Sri Aurobindo to find some light in our difficult days Professor Samuel Hugo Bergman (1883-1975) Prithwindra Mukherjee In a recent conversation[1], I mentioned that in 1972, as a guest &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/30/ben-gurion-bergman-and-aurobindo-in-israel/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here is a found nugget from <a href="http://feelphilosophy.blogspot.com/2010/05/i-read-sri-aurobindo-to-find-some-light.html">Tusar N. Mohapatra</a></p>
<p><strong>I read Sri Aurobindo to find some light in our difficult days</strong></p>
<p><strong>Professor Samuel Hugo Bergman  (1883-1975)<br />
Prithwindra Mukherjee</strong></p>
<p>In a recent conversation[1], I mentioned that in 1972, as a guest of the Hebrew University for lecturing on Savitri, I made the acquaintance of Yehuda Hanegby, editor of the monthly Ariel. During this visit, Madame Themanlys, commissioned to interview me for Kol Israel, the official radio, revealed her identity as the daughter-in-law of a personal friend that the Mother had in Paris, belonging to Max Théon’s group.  I would like to speak of a third interesting personality whom I met in Jerusalem : Professor Schmuel Hugo Bergman, commonly known as Samuel Bergman.</p>
<p>On the eve of my talk, during a dinner, Dr Poznanski, the Rector of the University, informed me that  Professor Bergman, Dean of the University, was hoping to listening to me but, owing to his health (running 89), he could not be present at my lecture; he would appreciate if I went to have breakfast with him on the next morning.</p>
<p>I was staying with my friend, Professor Joseph Sadan, and had my meals with his parents at the picturesque Hayim Nahman Bialik Street : Joseph&#8217;s father Dov Sadan was a well-known scholar in Ladino, and his mother treated me with refined traditional dishes from Central Europe. Yehuda came to pick me up for going to see Bergman. Yehuda knew him pretty well and informed that Bergman had been a school-mate of Franz Kafka in Prague, and  a zealous friend and translator of Rudolf Steiner (1861-1925). In 1920, Bergman along with Martin Buber (1878-1965) had founded in Palestine a &#8220;dual national&#8221; area to house peacefully Jews and Arabs, before joining the Hebrew University.</p>
<p>On entering the impressive library where sat the venerable scholar, I discovered rows of books by Sri Aurobindo. Amused by my reaction, he asked me to take the seat in front of him and commented on showing me the set : &#8220;This was our food for thought; David and I read Sri Aurobindo to find some light in our difficult days.&#8221;</p>
<p>Yehuda whispered : &#8220;By David, he means Ben Gurion !&#8221;</p>
<p>[1] &#8220;Meeting Prithwindra Mukherjee&#8221;, Article and Interview by Sunayana Panda, The Golden Chain, August 2009, p.13</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/30/ben-gurion-bergman-and-aurobindo-in-israel/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>4</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tzvia Greenfield: Israel&#8217;s first female Haredi MK- Meretz Activist</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/17/tzvia-greenfield-peace-activist-leftist-israels-first-female-haredi-mk/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/17/tzvia-greenfield-peace-activist-leftist-israels-first-female-haredi-mk/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 18 Apr 2010 02:51:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[israel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[religious zionism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Meretz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tzvia Greenfield]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1146</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[From Haaretz- full version here Tzvia Greenfield. Israel&#8217;s first Haredi female to be elected to the Knesset, she is a fierce critic of her own community&#8217;s attitudes to the peace process and modernity; describing the Haredi community as being &#8220;incapable &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/17/tzvia-greenfield-peace-activist-leftist-israels-first-female-haredi-mk/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1163329.html">From Haaretz- full version here</a></p>
<p>Tzvia Greenfield. Israel&#8217;s first Haredi female to be elected to the Knesset, she is a fierce critic of her own community&#8217;s attitudes to the peace process and modernity; describing the Haredi community as being &#8220;incapable of compromise.&#8221; Yet she still lives in it, a resident of the Jerusalem suburb of Har Nof.</p>
<p>Of course, her horizons are far broader than the narrow vista of ultra-Orthodoxy. The 62-year-old, who has a doctorate in political philosophy from the Hebrew University, was elected on behalf of Meretz last November. She advocates a two-State solution based closely on the pre-1967 War borders; a self-proclaimed egalitarian, she’s in favour of women rabbis and religious pluralism.</p>
<p>The mother-of-five, who sent her children to national religious high-schools and both her sons to the army, arrives as expected wearing a sheitel (one that looks like a sheitel) and a long dress.</p>
<p>She then speaks candidly about her prospects of influencing change: she is unsure that Israel&#8217;s left can be revived &#8211; she&#8217;s not sure they can awake secular Israel from its &#8220;slumber&#8221;- and feels compelled to channel change in her own back-yard, despite disillusionment about the trenchant positions of the Haredi world, which her Austrian &#8220;ultra-Orthodox Zionist parents&#8221; brought her into.</p>
<p>She describes the &#8220;haredization&#8221; of parts of Jerusalem and Beit Shemesh as &#8220;killing&#8221; those places: &#8220;Once they take over a community no one else can live in &#8211; like in some parts of Jerusalem and Beit Shemesh &#8211; that&#8217;s unacceptable. That is something people won&#8217;t tolerate because they want to live their lives. One neighbour cannot impinge on the other&#8217;s rights; it&#8217;s true the Haredi community doesn&#8217;t understand its task in a democracy. It believes when its population grows in a territory, the whole area should be governed by its rules.</p>
<p>She added: &#8220;An essential part of adjustment is in being a minority; the problem is when they become a majority. They are already driving people out of Jerusalem and not just the secular &#8211; but the modern Orthodox; because they cannot tolerate this. If the Haredi community gets large enough we won&#8217;t see nice developments.&#8221;</p>
<p>Her non-interventionist liberal instincts means she defends its right to promote a school curriculum that bares little resemblance to the national model: she believes a &#8220;balanced&#8221; approach is necessary in seeking to bring the Haredi world into the modern age, without assaulting its delicate nuances. &#8220;Interfering in questions of education is particularly sensitive and fragile,&#8221; she argues. &#8220;Thinking from all sides, I think society has to ensure Haredim aren&#8217;t poor. Despite Israeli society’s investment it&#8217;s a very poor community.&#8221;</p>
<p>Can Meretz deliver change? &#8220;I&#8217;m not sure. I think the left all over Europe and particularly Israel has severely failed on many assignments and I think the left should profoundly reconsider its goals and how it goes about them. To me after years of being a peace activist it&#8217;s a shameful situation and I think it&#8217;s unacceptable not to look at ourselves.</p>
<p>Q and A</p>
<p><strong>Bearing in mind you say some religious people have difficulty with compromise how would you like to see change stemming from the religious world?</strong></p>
<p>Religious people have difficulty grasping essential ideas like peace, compromise and accepting others. These are difficult issues and they&#8217;ve got to be worked out.</p>
<p>I&#8217;m writing a book on the subject. I decided I had to write down what I think and that would be the best way to explain how one could retain ones religiosity and faithfulness to ones position and yet encourage profound changes.</p>
<p>I have one answer to your question. I think a religion ought to be concerned with human beings and not objects. Too often traditional religions have a great interest in objects and not enough in human beings. That has to be shifted completely. The emphasis and the concern should be entirely different and there are ways to do it.</p>
<p><strong>Do you think the demonstration of the human side of the Judaism has been lost?</strong></p>
<p>I think there is not enough concern about human beings, and I mean human beings in general, including non-Jews. As a religious person I believe that all human beings were created in the image of God.</p>
<p>What we&#8217;ve seen in Israel in the last thirty or forty years ever since the &#8217;67 War is a concern with land. That&#8217;s an object. It&#8217;s become the centre of attention for religious people and I think that&#8217;s a major mistake and I think that should be changed.</p>
<p><strong>Where do you stand on issues of religious pluralism and the rights of all sects of Judaism to have equal funding with regards to conversion programs and education?</strong></p>
<p>Of course I support pluralism. People have to make their choices and decide what&#8217;s for them. There&#8217;s no way the state should direct on what or how they should do things. Every citizen should be a free subject to make his or her decisions without any input by the state whatsoever.</p>
<p><strong>How would you, as a progressive Haredi, advocate it modernises its approach to self- governance?</strong></p>
<p>Education. Education is the answer to everything, The fact that it blocks general education to its community is part of the problem because they never really understand what is going on and make their own decision. I would try and allow these people to get education without breaking down the system altogether, without enforcing education on them in a way which cannot acceptable, not only for them, but even for me. I don?t believe in enforcing it brutally; it has to be done carefully.</p>
<p>The very fact it&#8217;s living in the modern world, is affecting it. We are talking about the younger generation that will make decisions about what they are doing. In both America and Israel.  They are re-evaluating the world that their parents have brought them into. We&#8217;re probably going to see changes in the next 20-30 years. After all, they do not want to be poor.</p>
<p>You hope that the secular and Haredi worlds can live side by side but at the moment even the modern Orthodox are getting annoyed with the Haredim as the recent riots in Beit Shemesh prove.</p>
<p>Once they take over a community no one else can live in &#8211; like in some parts of Jerusalem and Beit Shemesh &#8211; that&#8217;s unacceptable. That is something people won’t tolerate because they want to live their lives. One neighbor cannot impinge on the other&#8217;s rights; it&#8217;s true the Haredi community doesn&#8217;t understand its task in a democracy. It believes when its population grows in a territory the whole area should be governed by its rules.</p>
<p><strong>The Haredization of Jerusalem is already here &#8211; how can this situation be clawed back?</strong></p>
<p>The community is poor, uneducated and very militant &#8211; the combination is lethal. It will kill Jerusalem.</p>
<p><strong>How can the Haredi leadership recognise the need to modernise?</strong></p>
<p>There is one factor in favour of modernisation- poverty. Some of the leadership recognizes and is concerned by this. Although the politicians would recommend poverty should be paid for, the leaders have a deeper approach. Certain changes must occur. First women join professions. Later on some men join. Things will change. Young men will be encouraged to join colleges. Already now there are a couple of colleges where Haredi girls are accepted to law or commerce school.</p>
<p><strong>What do you think about the status of women in the Haredi world?</strong></p>
<p>The big issue here is a very delicate one. That is children. Large families thirty years ago was six children; now there&#8217;s 13 or 14 &#8211; from one wife. I believes the glorification of bringing as many children as possible is a definite way of ensuring women can&#8217;t bring their advantages into effect &#8211; subjugation.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s inconceivable for a woman to say to her husband, &#8220;I won&#8217;t have more than three children&#8221; &#8211; a cause for divorce. Inconceivable and non-existent.</p>
<p><strong>Do you think there should be Orthodox female rabbis?</strong></p>
<p>I&#8217;m all for it. I think if women want to serve as rabbis in religious function they should be given the right to do so. The issue of depriving women a religious position is part of deprivation of women from positions of power. Women don’t have equal rights in Judaism because they never had them in any field of life- a general result of subjugation.</p>
<p><strong>Why is there a lack of state involvement in social issues?</strong></p>
<p>The state has been run by conservatives who don&#8217;t want equal rights for women, Arabs, anyone; any progressive left issues. They want to sabotage these things.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/17/tzvia-greenfield-peace-activist-leftist-israels-first-female-haredi-mk/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>7</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>On the Economy and on Sustenance: Judaism, Society, and Economics [Hebrew]</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/09/on-the-economy-and-on-sustenance-judaism-society-and-economics-hebrew/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/09/on-the-economy-and-on-sustenance-judaism-society-and-economics-hebrew/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2010 02:55:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[israel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[religious zionism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[aharon lavi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economic judaism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Itamar brenner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Menachem froman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[shagar]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=509</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Al haKalkalah ve-al haMihyah eds Itamar Brenner and Aharon Ariel Lavi 2008 I just got around to reading another volume in the “Jewish Thought and Cultural Criticism” series, they reflect the thinking going around Religious Zionist circles Below are short &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/09/on-the-economy-and-on-sustenance-judaism-society-and-economics-hebrew/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/310375091&amp;referer=brief_results">Al haKalkalah ve-al haMihyah eds Itamar Brenner and Aharon Ariel Lavi 2008</a></p>
<p>I just got around to reading another volume in the “Jewish Thought and Cultural Criticism” series, they reflect the thinking going around Religious Zionist circles Below are short summaries of the articles  without the details to give you a sense of the volume. I will focus more on the ones that deal with Jewish thought.</p>
<p>Section One<br />
The opening essay by Rav Shagar Z”l presents two understandings of the Sabbatical Year Shmita- a functional one and a spiritual return to harmony with nature and the Divine. He presents an ambivalence of inner and outer views of society. Hazal were ambivalent on carrying on Sabbath- it is one of the 39 prime categories but also a melakhah gerua but one can make eruv. He says that Hazal were more concerned with outer bounderies with the natural order than internal ones with the camp. He applies that back to the Sabbatical year. But along the ride, he discusses Midrash, Zohar, Heschel, and Mordechai Breuer, He concludes “Shimita is a catharsis, a disengagement and a purification from acquisition and civilization.</p>
<p>Dov Berkovits offers a nice analysis of the agricultural laws as showing wealth as the blessing of God and we partake of God’s blessing. He compares this to John Locke where wealth is human initiative. For Locke, God mandates government and human are left free, while for Hazal there is an interaction of the Divine and the human.</p>
<p>Roni Bar-Lev, who is working for a PHD under Avi Sagi discussed wealth in the writings of Rav Nahman of Breslov.He shows how for Rav Nahman, a kosher Jews should be far away from money or acquisition. Money is vile. In the story “master of prayer” the wealthy are so delusional that they organize themselves into angelic ranks based on their wealth. Yet, it is needed in the world. Greed is the only vice that cannot be transmuted to good, but desire itself can be transmuted.</p>
<p>Motti bar-Or of Kolot also offers the distinction in zedakah between the functional and the getting closer to the Divine.</p>
<p>Aharon Lavi, an editor of the volume doing a PHD in economic gives us a long article that is a gold mine of playing Jewish thought off of economic concerns. He major thesis is that Jewish thought offers a model of giving and receiving (mashbia, mekabel) , a connected societal model which he contrasts with Utilitarianism. He cites Chabad, early Hasidut, Zohar, Rav Nahman to create his model, more Chabad than others. For him, the Torah is pro Keynes and against Milton Freidman He also explores other images of tikkun, from above and from below. He concludes by rejecting Naomi Klein’s ideas of NO LOGO because she does not get the cultural elements.</p>
<p>Section two<br />
Israel Auman, the noble prize winner offers a Hebrew translation of his English articles on Risk Aversion. Yaakov Rosenberg offers a Richard Posner analysis of hilkhot nezikin.Julian Sinclair offers a translation of his English article on climate change and Judaism. The political Kabbalist Yitzhak Ginzburgh creates a kabbblah of management. And Yossi Zuriah (I am not sure if this is how he spells his name) ponders applying ideas of Shimitah to the high tech industry- “shareware” “open source” and why this would still keep the company afloat.</p>
<p>Section three</p>
<p>Articles from a current Israeli halakhic debate on not relying on heter iska today. Rav Shlomo Zalman Auerbach was against using it today. Some say we should use Arab banks. So this volume has Rabbis Yaakov Ariel and Yoel Bin Nun on the topic on minimizing the use of heter iska as much as possible.  This is a  <a href="http://www.vbm-torah.org/archive/halak65/14halak.htm">VBM shiur by Daniel Wolf </a>that gives the background. Some of these arguments could use a review of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Money_supply">Money Supply </a>before writing<br />
The same section has an out of place article by Yael Wilfed presenting part of her Duke PHd comparing Roman and rabbinic concepts in philanthropy. Conclusion – Romans were concerned with the collective state and gave out bread, the sages were concerned on a personal level.<br />
There is an article by Yosef Yitzahak Lifshitz presenting his libertarian anti-socialist views, seems a translation from Azure. (It should have been in part II). And an article of Meir Tamari and an article by Edo Rechnitz, from the Beth Din for money, on targeting Zedakah</p>
<p>Little prepared me for the afterword by Rabbi Menachem Froman Of Tekoa<br />
He start off by discussing how people found Religious Zionism from decades ago as all socialism and secular at its core but observant only on top of that. He turns to hasidut to discuss how we have to do things leshem yehud, to unify God, to sanctify the everyday. Then he moves to Rav Nahman to discuss how everyday life and money is the evil side and that God wants us to enter the evil side to redeem it. We then get a homily on the Zohar in which there is a disjunctive inserted between Lo (DO NOT) and KILL (Tirzah) meaning that sometimes you have to do what is normally forbidden. We then move to the importance of making an offering to the evil side as shown by the scapegoat offered to the evil side, but Froman’s question is why the second goat? Answer- we need to return to the non-spiritual, the mundane. We need to bring the spiritual work into the mundane into the evil side of dealing with money.<br />
Then he discusses Camus’s myth of Sisyphus and the Plague and concludes that Torah teaches us not to ask about the outcome; we need to do things lishmah. He concludes with a discussion weaving together the Zohar, that the world is the evil side and Doug Adams – Hitchhikers Guide to the Galaxy.<br />
I read the Rav Froman piece last Shabbat and right after Shabbat I read a great article on Rav Froman in<a href="http://www.nrg.co.il/online/1/ART2/013/267.html"> the religious section of MAARIV/NRG.</a></p>
<p>If you do comment, please comment on ideas, not people. And please  do not arrive to offer scatter shot citations of articles on economics and Judaism from the RJJ and TUM journal and the like.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/09/on-the-economy-and-on-sustenance-judaism-society-and-economics-hebrew/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Islam as the relgion of Hesed</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/11/islam-as-the-relgion-of-hesed/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/11/islam-as-the-relgion-of-hesed/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 11 Dec 2009 07:57:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[israel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Abraham maimuni]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avraham elqayam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[clash of civilizations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[deot]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Judeo-Islamic synthesis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Shabbatai Zevi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yishmael]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=349</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Dr Avraham Elqayam is head of the Shlomo Moussaieff Center for Kabbalah Research and professor of Kabbalah at Bar Ilan University. A number of years ago he wrote an article in the journal of the Torah veAvodah movement called “The &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/11/islam-as-the-relgion-of-hesed/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dr Avraham Elqayam is head of the Shlomo Moussaieff Center for Kabbalah Research and professor of Kabbalah at Bar Ilan University. A number of years ago he wrote an article in the journal of the Torah veAvodah movement called “The Religion of Mercy: Encounters with Islam” <em>Deot </em>19, (2004) 6-8 (It is a late night freehand translation). I am not sure of his current opinion but it is a very interesting three page article. He does not draw broader implications than those presented here.</p>
<p>In the article, he discusses the clash of civilization that puts Jews on the side of Western civilization. He demurs:</p>
<blockquote><p>But are Jews part of the flesh of the flesh of Western Civilization? I am astonished! My family lived under the Muslim world in Spain and afterward in a small community in Gaza City. They lived submersed in the midst the Arabic Muslim civilization.</p></blockquote>
<p>On the identification of Judaism and the West:</p>
<blockquote><p>The question is – do we have to continue in this direction until we reach opposition or do we need to go in another direction? The Torah recounts how Isaac and Ishmael went together to bury Abraham. It is valid to ask on the role of Yishmael in the Jewish spiritual tradition. Our modern philosophers, especially [Franz] Rosenzweig betrayed us. I will turn, therefore, from the world of philosophy to the world of mysticism and Kabbalah. Perhaps there we will find a path and a direction.</p></blockquote>
<p>Elqayam finds three approaches in Jewish mysticism to Islam. Kabbalah, Jewish Sufism, and Sabbatianism.</p>
<p>In Kabbalah- the world is all symbolic of the divine realm, therefore</p>
<blockquote><p>When you contemplate about Islam, think about Ishmael in the parashah [Hayai Sarah] Ask what is being symbolized, what is the allusion in the world of divinity. It is surprising to reveal that the Spanish kabbalists saw the essence of Islam as connected to the power of the sefirah hesed. Abraham our patriarch represented hesed and Ishmael comes from Abraham, therefore Islam represents hesed.</p>
<p>In its inwardness, Islam is a religion of hesed  This is the self-consciousness of the Muslims themselves. Muslims are called in Arabic a religion of tolerance. This opinion appears in the writings of Yosef Gikitilla….The destiny of the Islamic nation amidst the humanity is to represent Divine hesed.”</p></blockquote>
<p>Rabbi Abraham Maimoni was influenced by the Sufi mystical schools. He quoted the learning of Sufis, and praised their use of music, body posture, and prostrations.</p>
<blockquote><p>Rabbi Abraham Maimuni saw Sufism as a form of meta-religion that bridged between Islamic spirituality and prophetic spirituality. His intention was understandably to imitate the prophets and not the Muslims, except according to his opinion, only the Muslims preserved the path of prophecy. We have seen in him the spiritual possibility within Judaism that preserves the Jewish identity but which expresses the spiritual world of Islam- the Jew lived in the culture of Islam, drawing leaven from the Muslim world yet making a synthesis between the worlds as a Jew.</p></blockquote>
<p>Shabbatai Zevi converted to Islam and his followers created a synthesis that mixed both religions, they were Muslims who also kept Jewish practices including the Jewish holidays. [He gives several examples of the syncretism]</p>
<p>He conlcudes:</p>
<blockquote><p>We need to reconnect the fine threads and the gleanings– that bring us to our brothers Ishmael, that are almost lost to us. It is possible that the time has already passed but we are required at least to try. It is incumbent upon us to begin afresh to build a spiritual bridge between Judaism and Islam, to this I desire.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/11/islam-as-the-relgion-of-hesed/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rabbi Hirschenson&#8217;s Malki Bakodesh</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/06/rabbi-hirschensons-malki-bakodesh/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/06/rabbi-hirschensons-malki-bakodesh/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 06 Dec 2009 17:21:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[holidays]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[israel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[religious zionism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[abarbanel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[abraham lincoln]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hagadah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hayyim Hirschenson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[malci bakodesh]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[malki bakodesh]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mishpat ivri]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rabbi reines]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SPinoza]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=342</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I was given a copy of the 2006 reprint of Rabbi Hayyim Hirschenson’s Malki baKodesh on my last journey. I have read the older Hebrew edition. But as I pack for the next journey, I took it out to read &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/06/rabbi-hirschensons-malki-bakodesh/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I was given a copy of the 2006 reprint of Rabbi Hayyim Hirschenson’s <em>Malki baKodesh</em> on my last journey. I have read the older Hebrew edition. But as I pack for the next journey, I took it out to read for Shabbat.and looked at the new edition, He writes as 1929 Zionist. who attended the early Zionist congresses and wants to deal with the political problems that will arrive. He wants to assure that Religious Jews would not require a king and would not require the institution of sacrifices. He wants to allow people on to the Temple mount but as house of prayer for all people. It is permitted to join the Jewish legion even if it is a non-obligatory war- yet was are not in a messianic age. Finally, he accepts the concept of a high court of appeals- something that Rav Kook vehemently objected to its institution.Along the way and unlike most Rabbinic works are discussions of Horace Kalen, Louis Brandeis, and Jabotinsky. He supports the creation of legal boards and mishpat ivri to avoid Rabbinic courts. And finds the Balfour declaration a major event that should reorient Judaism. No law of the Torah can be against true civilization</p>
<p>In the original 1929 edition there was already an English preface which encouraged the role of the populous, and the need to make sure the halakhah does not perish. &#8221; They deal with considerations of primary importance for every Jew who is interested in the organic continuation of Jewish life in the line of historical development of Jewish teaching on the basis of Halacha.&#8221; The editor of the new edition notes the influence of Abraham Lincoln’s  “that this nation, under God, shall have a new birth of freedom—and that government: of the people, by the people, for the people, shall not perish from the earth.”.</p>
<p>He is anti Kingship based on the Abrabanel. And his approach seems to solve problems by making things problematic. The Bavli says this but the midreshei halakhah say other things and our questions cannot be answered so we can have a removal of a Rabbinic category. So unlike Maimonides who creates an ideal messianic halakhah- Hirschenson shows there is no ideal and there the laws are inoperative. He also used the technical questions of the Vilna Gaon, R. Akiva Eier and the Torah Temimah, to remove closure. As a said in my YUTorah class on Hirschenson- he is not just creating liberal position but works through Horayot and Sanhedrin and undoing them. Unlike others who try and make him Maimonidean, philosophic, or intellectual modernist. He is more historic oriented, a strong defense of popularism, and is more about removal of law than the construction of new law. (cf, the volume’s introduction that compares him to David Hartman).</p>
<p>A few theological points:</p>
<p>He writes that he was witness to WWI and the slaughter of the Armenians and decides that there is a need to write a new Zohar style apocalypse, like the Nistarot of Rabbi Shimon or Zohar Shemot 6-7, which he wrote and called “Tikkune Hamalkhut”</p>
<p>He wrote and analysis of Spinoza’s ethics and what we can learn from it in Spinoza’s work,  contained in his Musagei Shav veha-Emet. He can use Spinoza because he is not trying to create rationality, rather he is seeking to create opening for a broader life, like Rabbi Reines.</p>
<p>Coincidently, I had Hirschenson’s hagadah at hand, literally, someone recently sent me a copy.</p>
<p>Here are a few ideas from it:</p>
<p>“Maimonides did not intend that there would be only 13 principles of faith; there are many other principles in the Torah. Maimonides needed to explain only those principles that the masses would not understand because of their philosophic depth… There are many halakhot that are also principles such as those of “kill and do not violate.” And in the case of the Hagadah, the wicked son writes himself out of Judaism.</p>
<p>He translates “pereshut- zu derekh eretz” as one of the class system, perishut means class and the Jews who were originally upper class were treated as lower class and that is a major afflication.</p>
<p>The hagadah states that Jews are free in many countries due to minority rights but they are not spiritually free yet because are feeling the oppression of the majority culture and therefore do not have love of Torah and fear of heaven.  He also notes that until he cme to the US, he never knew why both phrases are needed and now he sees that one can have a sense of heaven and be totally removed from [the laws of] Shabbat and Torah.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/06/rabbi-hirschensons-malki-bakodesh/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>6</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Restoring Sacrifice viewed from Nepal</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/02/restoring-sacrifice-viewed-from-nepal/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/02/restoring-sacrifice-viewed-from-nepal/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2009 22:50:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[israel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[popular religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[religious zionism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ritual]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[animal sacrifice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hinduism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kodshim]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kook sacrifice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[korbanot]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sacrifice]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=330</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[There are many who look forward to re-instituting sacrifice in Judiasm. Notice the reaction that it gets in Hinduism. Would we get the same reaction? Would Judiasm and Hinduism now be linked, with pejorative intent, in peoples minds as the &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/02/restoring-sacrifice-viewed-from-nepal/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There are many who look forward to re-instituting sacrifice in Judiasm. Notice the reaction that it gets in Hinduism. Would we get the same reaction? Would Judiasm and Hinduism now be linked, with pejorative intent, in peoples minds as the two religions of sacrifice?Christianity, Islam, and Buddhism do not have sacrifice of animals as part of a regular order &#8211; Jews and Hindus do.</p>
<p>Mumbling something about Rav Kook writing that the restored sacrifices will be vegtable does not seem to have much clout when Kooks current followers are assiduously studying Kodshin and growing their nails long as they long for the Temple mount.</p>
<p>Now if I gave out this article to eighth graders while teaching Leviticus they would probably be appalled but what of 11th graders? How about kids after a year in Israel?Is there a way to create a modernist or contemporary approach to kodshim? What would be a contemporary approach seeing that since it is our sacred texts, we will witness a return of the repressed.  How seriously is everyone taking kodshim? I like the study of kodshin, whether Griz or Chofetz Chaim, and especially Mishnayot. But are we heading back to actual practice? As you read this, think of how different Jews will react and is this the Judiasm of the future?</p>
<p>Here is a conflated account from two versions</p>
<blockquote><p><a href="http://www.buddhistchannel.tv/index.php?id=39,8730,0,0,1,0"><strong>&#8220;Animal slaughter fest&#8221; begins despite protests in Nepal</strong></a> November 24, 2009</p>
<p><strong>Kathmandu</strong><strong>, Nepal</strong> &#8212; Despite appeals to halt the centuries-old custom of animal sacrifice, Gadhimai festival on Tuesday started in southern Nepal with millions of devotees flocking from various parts of the country and India. It is estimated that some 35,000 to 40,000 buffaloes, which are brought mostly from India, for the world&#8217;s largest ritual sacrifice at the temple.</p>
<p>India&#8217;s noted animal right activist Maneka Gandhi had also written a letter to Prime Minister Madhav Kumar Nepal appealing him to stop the sacrifice. Meanwhile, Animal Welfare Network Nepal and Anti-Animal Sacrifice Alliance has written to head priest Mangal Chaudhary and organising committee chief Shiva Chandra Kushwaha to stop the mass sacrifice.&#8221;We beg you to consider our plea. As the two important persons you have the ability to show wisdom, compassion and courage by doing everything to stop the killing of innocent creatures in the name of the God,&#8221; the letter said.</p>
<p>The government has, however, remained non-committal on its role in ending the custom. We will not interfere in the centuries-old tradition of the people, an official said.</p>
<p>Around five million people, 80 per cent from India, will arrive to observe the festival this time. Some 3,00,000 to 5,00,000 animals will be sacrificed during the two-day festival.</p>
<p>Hindus in Nepal routinely offer animals for sacrifice to appease deities, Especially power goddesses, for good luck and prosperity. But the festival held every five years at the Gadhimai temple in southern Nepal was condemned this year by animal rights activists.</p>
<p>Scores of butchers carrying big curved knives killed the animals in an open field as thousands of devotees stood by, witnesses reached by phone said. More than 80 percent of Nepal&#8217;s 27 million people are Hindus.</p>
<p>&#8220;It is a tradition and people&#8217;s faith. How can any protests stop that,&#8221; asked Mangal Chaudhary, chief priest of the temple, adding there were no protests.Some devotees said they were offering animals for sacrifice in the hope of being blessed with a son, preferred by many parents in Nepal and India.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/02/restoring-sacrifice-viewed-from-nepal/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>This is How Redemption Looks- Chayuta Deutsch</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/26/this-is-how-redemption-looks-chayuta-deutsch/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/26/this-is-how-redemption-looks-chayuta-deutsch/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 26 Oct 2009 03:56:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[israel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[religious zionism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[chayuta deutsch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ככה נראית גאולה]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=190</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Chayuta (also spelled Hayuta) Deutsch is the editor of the Akdamot Journal, published by Beit Morasha of Jerusalem, and the author of Nechama: The Biography of Nechama Leibovitz, published by Yedioth Ahronot Press. She was the literay editor for Ha-Zofeh &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/26/this-is-how-redemption-looks-chayuta-deutsch/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Chayuta (also spelled Hayuta) Deutsch is the editor of the Akdamot Journal, published by Beit Morasha of Jerusalem, and the author of Nechama: The Biography of Nechama Leibovitz, published by Yedioth Ahronot Press. She was the literay editor for Ha-Zofeh during its sensationalist decade.<br />
She has a new book out &#8220;ככה נראית גאולה&#8221; This is how Redemption Looks. Something for me to get next trip to Israel.<br />
&#8220;ככה נראית גאולה&#8221;, מאת חיותה דויטש, הוצאת &#8220;ידיעות ספרים&#8221;. 239 עמודים. The book is short stories about the Relgious Zionist world&#8211;Think &#8220;Serugim&#8221;<br />
<a href="http://www.ynet.co.il/articles/0,7340,L-3793315,00.html">Here is an excerpt.</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.facebook.com/people/Chayuta-Deutsch/825864249#/pages/-/159840826946">Facebook for book</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/26/this-is-how-redemption-looks-chayuta-deutsch/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Israel as an Educational Text</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/23/israel-as-an-educational-text/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/23/israel-as-an-educational-text/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2009 00:48:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[israel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Synagouge 3000]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=61</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I just received by email the latest report from Synagogue 3000&#8217;s Synagogue Studies Institute &#8220;Bringing Conversations about Israel into the Life of American Congregations.&#8221; Authors Alex Sinclair and Esti Moskovitz-Kalman It seems the goal after 2000 years and the return &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/23/israel-as-an-educational-text/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I just received by email the latest report from Synagogue 3000&#8217;s Synagogue Studies Institute &#8220;Bringing Conversations about Israel into the Life of American Congregations.&#8221; Authors Alex Sinclair and Esti Moskovitz-Kalman</p>
<p>It seems the goal after 2000 years and the return to the land of Israel is to go back to treating Israel as a symbol- or a text, an idea, a midrash. Not to treat Israel as a flesh and blood realpolitic middle eastern country, at least on the synagogue level. Israel is something to understand from a distance through the lens of one’s personal life. Birthright is successful since it takes place in Israel but is an American experience, as are many of the “year in Israel” programs. It does not let Israeli reality interfere with eduction.  These programs allow American to understand Israel though the lens of their American suburban lives.</p>
<p>They study  refers to another  recent study that shows that American Jews are not emotionally  distant from Israel, just lost in the self-absorption of their pleasure seeking lives.</p>
<p>What of AIPAC and <em>CPMAJO a<em>nd their advocacy activities? </em>ANS: They collide with<em> Jewish education. </em></em></p>
<p><em>Here are some quotes:<em><br />
</em></em></p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Israel is a Jewish Text</strong><strong></strong></p>
<p>We begin with an audacious claim: <em>Israel</em><em> is a Jewish text like all other Jewish texts. </em>And we Jews know a thing or two about how to read, discuss, teach, learn and draw mean­ing from texts.</p>
<p>We know how to grapple with a text we find problematic. We know how to incorporate the ideas of texts into our own lives….</p>
<p>The “distancing from Israel” hypothesis has been challenged empiri­cally (Sasson, Kadushin, and Saxe 2008).Nevertheless, from a value perspective, both schools of thought agree that it is absolutely critical that Israel engagement become a vehicle for personal meaning-making  Without a deep level of personal meaning, the American Jew will not engage with Israel. <em>Our claim is that conversation is a significant educa­tional means and end to lead to that personal meaning-makin</em>g, even, and indeed especially, for those Jews who have weak prior commitments to Israel.</p>
<p>Sasson, T., Kadushin, C., and Saxe, L. (2008). <em>American Jewish Attach­ment to Israel: an assessment of the “distancing” hypothesis. </em>Boston: Maurice and Marilyn  Cohen Center for Modern Jewish Studies</p>
<p>A congregant I am working with right now says “I have no interest in going to Israel; there are a thousand other places in the world where I would rather go.” I don’t think we have yet answered these questions for the vast majority of people.</p>
<p><strong>The Israel Advocacy Agenda — Friend or Foe?</strong></p>
<p>However, notwithstanding its value in the political sphere, Israel advo­cacy can collide with Israel education. The advocacy agenda may alienate those who don’t like politics in general. It certainly repels congregants who question the very Israeli policies that the advocates espouse. It frustrates those who reject being told that contrary to the ethos of the democracy in which they live, they may not voice their doubts about Israel’s policies openly and honestly.</p>
<p><a href="http:// http://synagogue3000.org/files/IsraelConversations.pdf"> </a><a href="http://synagogue3000.org/files/IsraelConversations.pdf" target="_self">Article</a></p></blockquote>
<p>I am not sure what to think about this. I do think they are correct educationally. They are correct about the way American students  project on Israel and I do think education need to be separated from advocacy. (i dont want to discuss politics)  But it means that Israel has to become part of the construction of an American life, a projection onto a silent land It is like the ideal in Graham Green novels novels of marrying someone who does not speak your language in order to have an ideal marriage, since one can project onto the silent spouse anything one wants. The longing of Yehudah Halevi and the heavenly Jerusalem of a Hasidic text is more inspiring than actual Israeli society.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/23/israel-as-an-educational-text/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
