<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Is this Beit Midrash on a Razors Edge or in a Tower: Danny Landes in Tikkun	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/31/is-this-beit-midrash-on-a-razors-edge-or-in-a-tower-danny-landes-in-tikkun/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/31/is-this-beit-midrash-on-a-razors-edge-or-in-a-tower-danny-landes-in-tikkun/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2011 09:41:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Mark E.D.		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/31/is-this-beit-midrash-on-a-razors-edge-or-in-a-tower-danny-landes-in-tikkun/#comment-2518</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mark E.D.]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2011 09:41:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2944#comment-2518</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I can&#039;t help but think when reading this article that Landes is less concerned with changing the practices of traditional yeshivot than he is with giving non-Orthodox Jews access to Orthodoxy.  His concern with the &quot;chosen irrelevancy&quot;of the &quot;classic beit midrash&quot; only rings true to one for whom the Orthodox yeshivot seem irrelevant; they obviously seems relevant in the communities that engender them.  Here we have a program for Jews who feel alienated by traditional Judaism (an admittedly large percentage), but who wish to engage in it.  The second half of the article reads to me like a sales pitch to the Jew who longs for a (consumer-ready?) spiritual education.

EJ&#039;s comments above will remain true for Jews who see Mishnah as the key to a just life.  Meanwhile, Jews who interpret Judaism/Yiddishkeit in non-Orthodox ways continue to search for potent expressions of their religious selves.  P.S. I&#039;m still mad at Landes for his complete dismissal of &quot;Radical Judaism&quot; and the bizarre accusation that Art Green has a &quot;secret master&quot; in Mordecai Kaplan.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I can&#8217;t help but think when reading this article that Landes is less concerned with changing the practices of traditional yeshivot than he is with giving non-Orthodox Jews access to Orthodoxy.  His concern with the &#8220;chosen irrelevancy&#8221;of the &#8220;classic beit midrash&#8221; only rings true to one for whom the Orthodox yeshivot seem irrelevant; they obviously seems relevant in the communities that engender them.  Here we have a program for Jews who feel alienated by traditional Judaism (an admittedly large percentage), but who wish to engage in it.  The second half of the article reads to me like a sales pitch to the Jew who longs for a (consumer-ready?) spiritual education.</p>
<p>EJ&#8217;s comments above will remain true for Jews who see Mishnah as the key to a just life.  Meanwhile, Jews who interpret Judaism/Yiddishkeit in non-Orthodox ways continue to search for potent expressions of their religious selves.  P.S. I&#8217;m still mad at Landes for his complete dismissal of &#8220;Radical Judaism&#8221; and the bizarre accusation that Art Green has a &#8220;secret master&#8221; in Mordecai Kaplan.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/31/is-this-beit-midrash-on-a-razors-edge-or-in-a-tower-danny-landes-in-tikkun/#comment-2517</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2011 04:36:54 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2944#comment-2517</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[EJ- I think that is the point, they are not talking about curriculum or even method of study. They are talking about process, Jewish identity, and new forms of cultural identity.  As David points out, it is not the substitution of Kabbalah for Talmud but some very different change that is showing up wherever we look. It is not hasmada, iyyun, or bekiut- it is &quot;cusp of a new landscape.&quot; Here are some of your Shema articles, non of them are about learning in the old sense.
Stephanie Ives on teaching text with a sense of mission; Charlie Schwartz and Russel Neiss, as well as Judd Kruger Levingston write about technology and new ways to &quot;remix&quot; learning; and Lisa Grant explores the lifelong pursuit of learning through narrative restorying of our lives.
My questions in the original post were intended to decipher the new horizon from my old-fashioned horizon.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>EJ- I think that is the point, they are not talking about curriculum or even method of study. They are talking about process, Jewish identity, and new forms of cultural identity.  As David points out, it is not the substitution of Kabbalah for Talmud but some very different change that is showing up wherever we look. It is not hasmada, iyyun, or bekiut- it is &#8220;cusp of a new landscape.&#8221; Here are some of your Shema articles, non of them are about learning in the old sense.<br />
Stephanie Ives on teaching text with a sense of mission; Charlie Schwartz and Russel Neiss, as well as Judd Kruger Levingston write about technology and new ways to &#8220;remix&#8221; learning; and Lisa Grant explores the lifelong pursuit of learning through narrative restorying of our lives.<br />
My questions in the original post were intended to decipher the new horizon from my old-fashioned horizon.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: David S		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/31/is-this-beit-midrash-on-a-razors-edge-or-in-a-tower-danny-landes-in-tikkun/#comment-2516</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[David S]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2011 03:42:54 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2944#comment-2516</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Perhaps the answer to your perplexity dear EJ lies in the invention of the airplane.  Before that invention we say the world with limited perspective.  In Judaism, breaking ones teeth on the Talmud represents a portion but not the whole length and breadth of the Jewish experience.  It seems to be everything but if you look back you realize that there is much more.  I think we are in a time and place where many different traditions are now viewable from above as it were.  The chain of transmission does not come from one source but from many.  As such it is hard to suggest that we should not drink from all of the waters and choose a path.  If you are brought up in an absolutely traditional way, there is only one path, the path of your father.  However, there are more things in the Jewish heaven and earth than are dreamt of in our philosophy.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Perhaps the answer to your perplexity dear EJ lies in the invention of the airplane.  Before that invention we say the world with limited perspective.  In Judaism, breaking ones teeth on the Talmud represents a portion but not the whole length and breadth of the Jewish experience.  It seems to be everything but if you look back you realize that there is much more.  I think we are in a time and place where many different traditions are now viewable from above as it were.  The chain of transmission does not come from one source but from many.  As such it is hard to suggest that we should not drink from all of the waters and choose a path.  If you are brought up in an absolutely traditional way, there is only one path, the path of your father.  However, there are more things in the Jewish heaven and earth than are dreamt of in our philosophy.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/31/is-this-beit-midrash-on-a-razors-edge-or-in-a-tower-danny-landes-in-tikkun/#comment-2515</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2011 00:36:05 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2944#comment-2515</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I am beginning to become  confused what is the topic and what are the issues. I felt the same when you posted the announcement on the lamdanus conference. I received an email this afternood from Sh&#039;ma about their new issue...&quot;Most would agree that we&#039;re on the cusp of a new landscape of Jewish learning.&quot; Maybe that&#039;s true, but this cusp is proving difficult for me to understand. Here&#039;s what&#039;s bothering me. I can understand a desire to change the standard, historical Jewish curriculum. But why not just come out and say it....less Talmud, more Jewish culture, less chumash more kabbalah, whatever.  Each of these can be looked at, accepted or rejected at the personal or institutional level. But if are talking knowing the Talmud, there are no ways around learning at a certain pace, day after day, year after year until one acheives the desired level of proficiency. No one has discovered analytical insights that substitute knowing the plain meaning of the sugya plus the views of the main  rishonim. It is madness to think we should start with source criticism or the historical context or the hundreds of academic articles on the Talmud if the goal is to know the Talmud. I fail to see how anything has changed. You want to know tractate Yevamos you must jump in and you don&#039;t get to emerge from this difficult place until you master the material. Yes, we have a Schottenstein translation, and yes some clever guys have written out flow charts how you can be your own grandfather, and yes there are some stimulating yeshivish  shiurim,  all very helpful, but not different in kind than the old Jastrow and the Bais Yehuda chumushim and the classic achronim. 
If Landes wants to call the standard ways Jews became baki in Shas  &quot;systemic parochialism, chosen irrelevancy, and sought-after faux elitism,&quot; I don&#039;t quite know what to say other than it seems to me a foolish quip. Yevamos is for the most part irrelevant as is Zevachim, and thank God it is about itself and not Yevamos and the Jewish Question or Yevamos in the light of Ugarit. 
I once had a neighbor, an otherwise ordinary man,  who learnt daf hayomi beiyun bechavrusa his whole life. He told me &quot;The fifth, sixth time around it gets a little easier, you have a little better idea of the whole.&quot; The elitism Landes mocks is an elitism that wants nothing more than to to sit and be a student all one&#039;s life. It seems to me if one also works for a living and is not dependent on Jewish charity, the goal of learning forever is indeed noble, with or without cartwheels.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I am beginning to become  confused what is the topic and what are the issues. I felt the same when you posted the announcement on the lamdanus conference. I received an email this afternood from Sh&#8217;ma about their new issue&#8230;&#8221;Most would agree that we&#8217;re on the cusp of a new landscape of Jewish learning.&#8221; Maybe that&#8217;s true, but this cusp is proving difficult for me to understand. Here&#8217;s what&#8217;s bothering me. I can understand a desire to change the standard, historical Jewish curriculum. But why not just come out and say it&#8230;.less Talmud, more Jewish culture, less chumash more kabbalah, whatever.  Each of these can be looked at, accepted or rejected at the personal or institutional level. But if are talking knowing the Talmud, there are no ways around learning at a certain pace, day after day, year after year until one acheives the desired level of proficiency. No one has discovered analytical insights that substitute knowing the plain meaning of the sugya plus the views of the main  rishonim. It is madness to think we should start with source criticism or the historical context or the hundreds of academic articles on the Talmud if the goal is to know the Talmud. I fail to see how anything has changed. You want to know tractate Yevamos you must jump in and you don&#8217;t get to emerge from this difficult place until you master the material. Yes, we have a Schottenstein translation, and yes some clever guys have written out flow charts how you can be your own grandfather, and yes there are some stimulating yeshivish  shiurim,  all very helpful, but not different in kind than the old Jastrow and the Bais Yehuda chumushim and the classic achronim.<br />
If Landes wants to call the standard ways Jews became baki in Shas  &#8220;systemic parochialism, chosen irrelevancy, and sought-after faux elitism,&#8221; I don&#8217;t quite know what to say other than it seems to me a foolish quip. Yevamos is for the most part irrelevant as is Zevachim, and thank God it is about itself and not Yevamos and the Jewish Question or Yevamos in the light of Ugarit.<br />
I once had a neighbor, an otherwise ordinary man,  who learnt daf hayomi beiyun bechavrusa his whole life. He told me &#8220;The fifth, sixth time around it gets a little easier, you have a little better idea of the whole.&#8221; The elitism Landes mocks is an elitism that wants nothing more than to to sit and be a student all one&#8217;s life. It seems to me if one also works for a living and is not dependent on Jewish charity, the goal of learning forever is indeed noble, with or without cartwheels.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Jon		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/31/is-this-beit-midrash-on-a-razors-edge-or-in-a-tower-danny-landes-in-tikkun/#comment-2511</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jon]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2011 04:46:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2944#comment-2511</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&quot;No real criticism here. Just some first thoughts and reactions.&quot;

I&#039;d hate to be on the receiving end of real criticisms then...]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&#8220;No real criticism here. Just some first thoughts and reactions.&#8221;</p>
<p>I&#8217;d hate to be on the receiving end of real criticisms then&#8230;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
