<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Interview with Yoel Glick &#8211; Part 2	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/10/19/interview-with-yoel-glick-part-2/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/10/19/interview-with-yoel-glick-part-2/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2015 04:42:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: HRtsFan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/10/19/interview-with-yoel-glick-part-2/#comment-12962</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[HRtsFan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2015 04:42:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6726#comment-12962</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[[ January 21, 2015 / 2 Shevat 5775 ]
    I like your explanation about prophecy.  But: If after perceiving a truth that a person doesn&#039;t yet have a &#039;vessel&#039; for [or a &#039;capacity-for-deciphering&#039;]:
    If the &quot;candidate-revelatory-experience&quot; is somehow recorded within one&#039;s memory - perhaps in some primitive, or raw form, Then: what if future experiences enable, or would enable, that &quot;experience&quot; to newly gain &#039;translation&#039;, to belatedly have a fathomable meaning/message?
    Since you are a well practiced meditator, perhaps personally? have you [or practitioners you know of]  attempted to:  preserve a &#039;raw form&#039; memory of a candidate-revelatory-experience [and making effort:  to avoid editing our &#039;memories&#039; of what we thought the experience was - trying to preserve authentic pieces of the candidate-revelatory-experience], and then, weeks, months, or years, later, succeeded to &#039;find something belatedly&#039; from the candidate-revelatory-experience [which, wow, showed itself to be, yes, a revelatory-experience]?
    And, even if we have &#039;a&#039; vessel for a revelatory experience, maybe, or inferably??, we should value, ?revere?, the experience itself enough that we would want to expend effort to attempt to preserve it in some primitive, or raw form?  [And maybe the vessels which are &#039;at the ready&#039; are even falsely applicable vessels, or are too basic-of-shape to hold a more subtle or nuanced meaning.]]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>[ January 21, 2015 / 2 Shevat 5775 ]<br />
    I like your explanation about prophecy.  But: If after perceiving a truth that a person doesn&#8217;t yet have a &#8216;vessel&#8217; for [or a &#8216;capacity-for-deciphering&#8217;]:<br />
    If the &#8220;candidate-revelatory-experience&#8221; is somehow recorded within one&#8217;s memory &#8211; perhaps in some primitive, or raw form, Then: what if future experiences enable, or would enable, that &#8220;experience&#8221; to newly gain &#8216;translation&#8217;, to belatedly have a fathomable meaning/message?<br />
    Since you are a well practiced meditator, perhaps personally? have you [or practitioners you know of]  attempted to:  preserve a &#8216;raw form&#8217; memory of a candidate-revelatory-experience [and making effort:  to avoid editing our &#8216;memories&#8217; of what we thought the experience was &#8211; trying to preserve authentic pieces of the candidate-revelatory-experience], and then, weeks, months, or years, later, succeeded to &#8216;find something belatedly&#8217; from the candidate-revelatory-experience [which, wow, showed itself to be, yes, a revelatory-experience]?<br />
    And, even if we have &#8216;a&#8217; vessel for a revelatory experience, maybe, or inferably??, we should value, ?revere?, the experience itself enough that we would want to expend effort to attempt to preserve it in some primitive, or raw form?  [And maybe the vessels which are &#8216;at the ready&#8217; are even falsely applicable vessels, or are too basic-of-shape to hold a more subtle or nuanced meaning.]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Rabbi Yoel Glick		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/10/19/interview-with-yoel-glick-part-2/#comment-12325</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rabbi Yoel Glick]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2014 11:31:52 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6726#comment-12325</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The search for God is an integral part of religious experience. Our search for the One and for Oneness began with the first Jew, Avraham. He looked around at the world and could not accept the fragmentation of reality. “Mi bara eleh”? he asked  Avraham was seeking the unity behind the diversity. 
The Zohar tells us that God created humanity so we might know Him. The Baal Shem speaks at length of the centrality of the Divine exhortation “vebo tedbak” – you shall join and bind yourself to God. The search for Oneness is at the core of the mystical dimension of Judaism.
On one hand, it is true that our world is a world of duality. The very essence of being a human is that we have a separate individual consciousness and can recognize the “other”. But this capacity to recognize the other is there so we might form relationships – so that we will see the unity behind the diversity and recognize it as ourselves. This is the unique opportunity we have as humans: to know God as a separate conscious individual, and from that place become One. The rest of the creation is part of the Oneness without any conscious awareness of the fact. We alone can seek out the Other and join with Him.
There is no opposition between the observance of the mitzvot and the search for God union. They are two parts of one whole. The Hasidic Masters saw Torah study, prayer and the fulfillment of the mitzvot as our means of joining with God. They are the basis of our relationship with God, the vehicle we use to reach the Ein Sof. Our inner work is the fuel that propels that spiritual vehicle – the power that takes it toward our destination.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The search for God is an integral part of religious experience. Our search for the One and for Oneness began with the first Jew, Avraham. He looked around at the world and could not accept the fragmentation of reality. “Mi bara eleh”? he asked  Avraham was seeking the unity behind the diversity.<br />
The Zohar tells us that God created humanity so we might know Him. The Baal Shem speaks at length of the centrality of the Divine exhortation “vebo tedbak” – you shall join and bind yourself to God. The search for Oneness is at the core of the mystical dimension of Judaism.<br />
On one hand, it is true that our world is a world of duality. The very essence of being a human is that we have a separate individual consciousness and can recognize the “other”. But this capacity to recognize the other is there so we might form relationships – so that we will see the unity behind the diversity and recognize it as ourselves. This is the unique opportunity we have as humans: to know God as a separate conscious individual, and from that place become One. The rest of the creation is part of the Oneness without any conscious awareness of the fact. We alone can seek out the Other and join with Him.<br />
There is no opposition between the observance of the mitzvot and the search for God union. They are two parts of one whole. The Hasidic Masters saw Torah study, prayer and the fulfillment of the mitzvot as our means of joining with God. They are the basis of our relationship with God, the vehicle we use to reach the Ein Sof. Our inner work is the fuel that propels that spiritual vehicle – the power that takes it toward our destination.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Rabbi Yoel Glick		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/10/19/interview-with-yoel-glick-part-2/#comment-12317</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rabbi Yoel Glick]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2014 21:12:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6726#comment-12317</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I wouls also add that though people alwyas speak of joy and devotion in relaton to Hasidut, Hasidut also has a strong jnana side to it. Rebbe Nachman of Breslov and Rav Kook are both good examples of Hasidic teachers who were both strong bhaktis and jnanis. In that vein, it occurs to me that it would be a wonderful exercise to go through the great Hasidic Masters and decide if they were bhaktis or jnanis or both, and which was their outer character and which their inner one. For example, perhaps we can say that the Baal Shem Tov was a bhakti on the outside and a jnani on the inside, while the Maggid of Mezertich was a jnani on the outside and a bhakti within.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I wouls also add that though people alwyas speak of joy and devotion in relaton to Hasidut, Hasidut also has a strong jnana side to it. Rebbe Nachman of Breslov and Rav Kook are both good examples of Hasidic teachers who were both strong bhaktis and jnanis. In that vein, it occurs to me that it would be a wonderful exercise to go through the great Hasidic Masters and decide if they were bhaktis or jnanis or both, and which was their outer character and which their inner one. For example, perhaps we can say that the Baal Shem Tov was a bhakti on the outside and a jnani on the inside, while the Maggid of Mezertich was a jnani on the outside and a bhakti within.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Rabbi Yoel Glick		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/10/19/interview-with-yoel-glick-part-2/#comment-12315</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rabbi Yoel Glick]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2014 20:20:50 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6726#comment-12315</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Howie Katz I certainly agree with you about Hasidut being primarily a bhakti path. And it is certainly true that there is no contradiction between jnana and bhakti, as we see from the lives of many great spiritual teachers and saints. In fact, there is a saying in the Ramakrishna Order that Sri Ramakrishna was a bhakti on the outside and a jnani within, while Swami Vivekananda was a bhakti within and a jnani on the outside. This is also certainly true of the teachings in my book. Though there is a Vedantic non-dual line that runs through my book, many of the sources from Hinduism and Hasidut are about the bhakti path, about kavanah and hitlahavut. Joy and devotion have an important role to play the inner life I outline in the book. 
I would also add that I am not so much making comparisons between Judaism and Hinduism in the book, as drawing on the mystical traditions of both religions to illuminate various issues in the spiritual life. I find that the manner in which the two religions address these issues often provides interesting perspective and fresh insight into the major questions of the spiritual path. Sometimes the insights come by looking at the similarities between the two religions, and sometimes it occurs by observing the contrasts in their approaches. For me, at least, the interaction between the two religions has been stimulating, enriching and instructive. And crucially, it has enhanced my appreciation of the profundity and wisdom in both religions.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Howie Katz I certainly agree with you about Hasidut being primarily a bhakti path. And it is certainly true that there is no contradiction between jnana and bhakti, as we see from the lives of many great spiritual teachers and saints. In fact, there is a saying in the Ramakrishna Order that Sri Ramakrishna was a bhakti on the outside and a jnani within, while Swami Vivekananda was a bhakti within and a jnani on the outside. This is also certainly true of the teachings in my book. Though there is a Vedantic non-dual line that runs through my book, many of the sources from Hinduism and Hasidut are about the bhakti path, about kavanah and hitlahavut. Joy and devotion have an important role to play the inner life I outline in the book.<br />
I would also add that I am not so much making comparisons between Judaism and Hinduism in the book, as drawing on the mystical traditions of both religions to illuminate various issues in the spiritual life. I find that the manner in which the two religions address these issues often provides interesting perspective and fresh insight into the major questions of the spiritual path. Sometimes the insights come by looking at the similarities between the two religions, and sometimes it occurs by observing the contrasts in their approaches. For me, at least, the interaction between the two religions has been stimulating, enriching and instructive. And crucially, it has enhanced my appreciation of the profundity and wisdom in both religions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Len Moskowitz		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/10/19/interview-with-yoel-glick-part-2/#comment-12314</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Len Moskowitz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2014 14:43:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6726#comment-12314</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/10/19/interview-with-yoel-glick-part-2/#comment-12312&quot;&gt;Howie Katz&lt;/a&gt;.

Howie writes:

&quot;If the goal is to achieve a non-dual state, in which all that exists is seen as a manifestation of one Divine Consciouness, then how is this furthered by following a system which reinforces, at every turn, the notion of “Us and Them”?&quot;

and 

&quot;A thought on this – Halacha may serve, as does Hatha Yoga, as a preliminary system of purification which prepares the practitioner for the later(deeper?) practices that lead to the non-dual state. (Just a thought).&quot;

Rav Chaim Volozhiner deals with this directly in the Neffesh Ha-chaim (Shaar 3, end of Perek 3). He says that although it&#039;s ultimately true that there is nothing other than the One, it&#039;s a terrible mistake to base our actions on the one-ness, and that this specific mistake has the potential to demolish some of the foundations of Torah . For Jews, the focus must be the world of duality. Talmud Torah, t&#039;fila and mitzvote must be the focus of our actions, speech and thoughts.

Bottom line: according to Chaim Volozhiner the world as not-One is why we&#039;re here, while the non-dual state is optional. Non-duality is a pleasant sideshow for those who can get there (and may be useful), but we shouldn&#039;t mistake it for the main event.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/10/19/interview-with-yoel-glick-part-2/#comment-12312">Howie Katz</a>.</p>
<p>Howie writes:</p>
<p>&#8220;If the goal is to achieve a non-dual state, in which all that exists is seen as a manifestation of one Divine Consciouness, then how is this furthered by following a system which reinforces, at every turn, the notion of “Us and Them”?&#8221;</p>
<p>and </p>
<p>&#8220;A thought on this – Halacha may serve, as does Hatha Yoga, as a preliminary system of purification which prepares the practitioner for the later(deeper?) practices that lead to the non-dual state. (Just a thought).&#8221;</p>
<p>Rav Chaim Volozhiner deals with this directly in the Neffesh Ha-chaim (Shaar 3, end of Perek 3). He says that although it&#8217;s ultimately true that there is nothing other than the One, it&#8217;s a terrible mistake to base our actions on the one-ness, and that this specific mistake has the potential to demolish some of the foundations of Torah . For Jews, the focus must be the world of duality. Talmud Torah, t&#8217;fila and mitzvote must be the focus of our actions, speech and thoughts.</p>
<p>Bottom line: according to Chaim Volozhiner the world as not-One is why we&#8217;re here, while the non-dual state is optional. Non-duality is a pleasant sideshow for those who can get there (and may be useful), but we shouldn&#8217;t mistake it for the main event.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Howie Katz		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2014/10/19/interview-with-yoel-glick-part-2/#comment-12312</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Howie Katz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2014 12:42:58 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6726#comment-12312</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thanks for posting this. A few comments/questions:

1 – The comparison between Hasidut and Jnana Yoga/Vedanta, though plausible, is not the most obvious comparison. To my mind, Hasidut is most similar to Bhakti Yoga, rather than Vedanta. The devotional focus of Hasidut and its’ emphasis on joy(at least in its’ formative years) make the comparison with similar elements in the devotional path of Bhakti Yoga the more obvious one.  Of course,  Bhakti Yoga itself, though usually seen as a dualistic spiritual path as it  implies a devotee’s separation from the divine(i.e. Sri Ramamkrishna’s “It is better to taste sugar than to be sugar”) will also, if followed with devotion, “open” onto the non-dual state as well. Though there is a history of some tension between Bhakti and Jnana Yoga/ Vedanta (the Jnanis, as the Litvaks of Indian spirituality, have always had more than a little disdain for Bhaktas) , there utlitmately is no contradiction  between them and some of the greatest Indian adepts have practiced both. See, for example, Sri Ramakrishna and, especially, Sri Adi Shankara, whose devotional hymns to the Divine Mother  are well known and moving. The Hasidut-Vedanta comparison can certainly be maintained, as Rabbi Glick does, but to be complete the comparison should include the devotional side(s) of yoga as well. It seems to me that the Hasidic “bittul Ha-Yesh”  is achieved in great measure via devotion.

2 – Rabbi Glick mentions Sri Ramana’s initial awakening experience as having been precipitated by a simulated death experience(at the age of 16!). This is true – however, Sri Ramana did not teach death-simulation as a means of reaching the non-dual state. Rather he taught Atma Vichara (“Self Inquiry) in which the practitioner constantly asks “Who am I?” in a meditative state, without expecting a rational answer and while tracing the “I” back to its’ source. I am not sure either why Sri Ramana abandoned death-simulation as a practice or if there is a Hasidic equivalent to Atma Vichara.     

3 – The discussion of content-less revelation is quite interesting. It does, however, lead, at some point, to a discussion of a rather large elephant(Ganesh?) in the room  - namely, what is the role of halacha or shemirat hamitzvot in any this. If the goal is to achieve a non-dual state, in which all that exists is seen as a manifestation of one Divine Consciouness, then how is this furthered by following a system which reinforces, at every turn, the notion of “Us and Them”?  I have not yet read Rabbi Glick’s book (just ordered it) and I imagine he deals with it. (Arthur Green deals with this as well in his biography of Rebbe Nachman, not very satisfactorily, in my opinion). A thought on this – Halacha may serve, as does Hatha Yoga, as a preliminary system of purification which prepares the practitioner for the later(deeper?) practices that lead to the non-dual state. (Just a thought).]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thanks for posting this. A few comments/questions:</p>
<p>1 – The comparison between Hasidut and Jnana Yoga/Vedanta, though plausible, is not the most obvious comparison. To my mind, Hasidut is most similar to Bhakti Yoga, rather than Vedanta. The devotional focus of Hasidut and its’ emphasis on joy(at least in its’ formative years) make the comparison with similar elements in the devotional path of Bhakti Yoga the more obvious one.  Of course,  Bhakti Yoga itself, though usually seen as a dualistic spiritual path as it  implies a devotee’s separation from the divine(i.e. Sri Ramamkrishna’s “It is better to taste sugar than to be sugar”) will also, if followed with devotion, “open” onto the non-dual state as well. Though there is a history of some tension between Bhakti and Jnana Yoga/ Vedanta (the Jnanis, as the Litvaks of Indian spirituality, have always had more than a little disdain for Bhaktas) , there utlitmately is no contradiction  between them and some of the greatest Indian adepts have practiced both. See, for example, Sri Ramakrishna and, especially, Sri Adi Shankara, whose devotional hymns to the Divine Mother  are well known and moving. The Hasidut-Vedanta comparison can certainly be maintained, as Rabbi Glick does, but to be complete the comparison should include the devotional side(s) of yoga as well. It seems to me that the Hasidic “bittul Ha-Yesh”  is achieved in great measure via devotion.</p>
<p>2 – Rabbi Glick mentions Sri Ramana’s initial awakening experience as having been precipitated by a simulated death experience(at the age of 16!). This is true – however, Sri Ramana did not teach death-simulation as a means of reaching the non-dual state. Rather he taught Atma Vichara (“Self Inquiry) in which the practitioner constantly asks “Who am I?” in a meditative state, without expecting a rational answer and while tracing the “I” back to its’ source. I am not sure either why Sri Ramana abandoned death-simulation as a practice or if there is a Hasidic equivalent to Atma Vichara.     </p>
<p>3 – The discussion of content-less revelation is quite interesting. It does, however, lead, at some point, to a discussion of a rather large elephant(Ganesh?) in the room  &#8211; namely, what is the role of halacha or shemirat hamitzvot in any this. If the goal is to achieve a non-dual state, in which all that exists is seen as a manifestation of one Divine Consciouness, then how is this furthered by following a system which reinforces, at every turn, the notion of “Us and Them”?  I have not yet read Rabbi Glick’s book (just ordered it) and I imagine he deals with it. (Arthur Green deals with this as well in his biography of Rebbe Nachman, not very satisfactorily, in my opinion). A thought on this – Halacha may serve, as does Hatha Yoga, as a preliminary system of purification which prepares the practitioner for the later(deeper?) practices that lead to the non-dual state. (Just a thought).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
