<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>jewish thought &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/category/jewish-thought/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Jan 2011 21:14:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='kavvanah.wordpress.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/c9f111237f93750b6b994fc5185d49c3?s=96&#038;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>jewish thought &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>David Shasha on Kellner, Idel, and Nationalism</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/08/david-shasha-on-kellner-idel-and-nationalism/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/08/david-shasha-on-kellner-idel-and-nationalism/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2010 21:16:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[israel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[david shasha]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[menachem Kellner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Moshe idel]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1643</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[David Shasha is a proponent of all things Sefardi and a radical follower of Jose Faur who envisions a Levantine synthesis of Jewish and Arabic humanism. Shasha offers a critique of Kellner, Idel and others as destroying the humanistic foundations &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/08/david-shasha-on-kellner-idel-and-nationalism/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>David Shasha is a proponent of  all things Sefardi and a radical follower of Jose Faur who envisions a Levantine synthesis of Jewish and Arabic humanism. Shasha offers a critique of Kellner, Idel and others as destroying the humanistic foundations of Judaism. He claims that they destroy the foundation of Maimonidean humanism even if they accept Maimonides. Kellner advocates for the rationalism of Maimonides but back-handedly considers the Maimonideans as too demanding for the common person, as rejecting folk religion, and as not the Jewish tradition. Shasha demands that Maimonides be considered the tradition or else Maimonideans would always be in a defensive position. If one does not live in a rational world then all the power is in the magical hand of the rabbis. </p>
<p>Shasha places blame at the feet of Moshe Idel who explores the magical, irrational, and mythic forces in Judaism but who also maintains that this theurgic world is the world of the Talmudic Rabbis. For Idel, the Rabbinic tradition is magical. Kabbalah is not a Gnostic intruder into Judaism but the very meaning of the commandments for the Rabbis. Once Jews studied Saadyah, Ibn Ezra, Maimonides, Gersonides as the traditon, now they read Abulafia and Zohar. For Shasha, this is tantamount to a return to idolatry and the source of militant nationalism. <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/david-shasha/dangerous-mystic-motifs-i_b_637535.html">Full Version here.</a></p>
<p>Shasha writes:<br />
<em>At the center of this controversy is the vexing question of Jewish authenticity.<br />
In his 2006 study &#8220;Maimonides&#8217; Confrontation with Mysticism,&#8221; Menachem Kellner adopts an approach that has become standard in most Jewish circles, writing:</p>
<blockquote><p>&#8220;The Jewish world in which Maimonides lived was uncongenial to the austere, abstract, demanding vision of Torah which he preached. Evidence from a wide variety of sources shows that Jews in Maimonides&#8217; day &#8211; common folk and scholars alike &#8211; accepted astrology, the magical use of divine names, appeals to angels, etc.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p></em><em> In a noble attempt to elevate the thinking of Maimonides, Kellner&#8217;s arguments bizarrely lend credence to the positions of the anti-Maimonideans.</em><br />
<em>In the book&#8217;s conclusion he states:</em></p>
<blockquote><p>The world favored by Maimonides&#8217; opponents, on the other hand, is an &#8220;enchanted&#8221; world. Many of Maimonides&#8217; opponents, in his day and ours, do indeed accept the efficacy of charms and amulets, and fear the harm of demons and the evil eye. But it is not in that sense that I maintain that they live in an enchanted world. Theirs is not a world which can be explained in terms of the unvarying workings of divinely ordered laws of nature; it is not a world which can be rationally understood. It is a world in which the notion of miracle loses all meaning, since everything that happens is a miracle. In such a world instructions from God, and contact with the divine in general, must be mediated by a religious elite who alone can see the true reality masked by nature. This is the opposite of an empowering religion, since it takes their fate out of the hands of Jews, and, in effect, puts it into the hands of the rabbis.</p></blockquote>
<p><em>We can see the tension at the heart of Kellner&#8217;s argument, a tension that forces his hand in accepting the absolute authenticity of the mystical-occult tradition of the Kabbalah and rejecting the Jewish validity of Maimonidean rationalism.</p>
<p>Kellner&#8217;s book contains a forward by Hebrew University professor Moshe Idel, perhaps the single most influential academic in the world of Judaica, a winner of the prestigious Israel Prize and a ubiquitous presence in the world of Jewish studies. Idel has relentlessly promoted the pro-magic, neo-pagan, anti-rational strain of Jewish tradition also called Kabbalah. </p>
<p>Idel&#8217;s scholarly project has been designed to affirm the authenticity of the mystical-occult Kabbalah and undermine the validity of the rational standards of Religious Humanism. As we see in a representative passage in his seminal 1988 work &#8220;Kabbalah: New Perspectives&#8221;:</em></p>
<blockquote><p>Kabbalah can be viewed as part of a restructuring of those aspects of rabbinic thought that were denied authenticity by Maimonides&#8217; system. Far from being a total innovation, historical Kabbalah represented an ongoing effort to systematize existing elements of Jewish theurgy, myth, and mysticism into a full-fledged response to the rationalistic challenge.<br />
It is, however, possible to assume that, if the motifs transmitted in those unknown [Kabbalistic] circles formed part of an ancient weltanschauung, their affinities to the rabbinic mentality would be more organic and easily absorbed into the mystic cast of Judaism.<br />
According to this hypothesis, we do not need to account for why ancient Jews took over Gnostic doctrines, why they transmitted them, and, finally, how this &#8216;Gnostic&#8217; Judaism was revived in the Middle Ages by conservative Jewish authorities. </p></blockquote>
<p>Shasha concludes:</p>
<p><em>This has led to the rejection of Sephardic Jewish Humanism as formulated by Maimonides and an affirmation of an ethnocentric Jewish chauvinism based on the magical mysticism of Kabbalistic theurgy. It is a Judaism that rejects the tenets of a critical reading of the Jewish past and has led us to the sort of ideological purity and militant nationalism that has become characteristic of the intractable impasse in the Middle East. Though this occult process has been secularized by Zionism, it is apparent that the ideological values of the mystical continue to animate the Jewish self-perception in a nationalistic sense.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/08/david-shasha-on-kellner-idel-and-nationalism/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>10</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>New unpublished Rav Kook</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/28/new-unpublished-rav-kook/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/28/new-unpublished-rav-kook/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 28 May 2010 05:52:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[religious zionism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rav Kook]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1396</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[My reader Paul Shaviv showed up earlier this week and left the blogging equivalent of a baby in a basket in a comment on my About page. He posted a link to a pdf of one of the new Rav &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/28/new-unpublished-rav-kook/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My reader Paul Shaviv showed up earlier this week and left the blogging equivalent of a baby in a basket in a comment on my About page. He posted a link to a pdf of one of the new Rav Kook works that have been recently transcribed.  I had assumed that this was already discussed and linked elsewhere.</p>
<p>Rav Kook left behind scores of notebooks of his thoughts. Many of those notebooks were used by the Nazir  to create Orot Hakodesh as an editor’s synthesis.  Others were used by R Zvi Yehudah to produce a different voice for Rav Kook. Recently, some of these notebooks have been published  as Shemonah Kevatzim. In the last few years, even more material has come forth from the archives creating a serious academic and Merkaz haRav world debate on   why were they hidden until now? what was edited out? Does it change our view of Rav Kook?</p>
<p>For those of us in the field, none of this is new. It is the bread and butter of academic conferences.  Back in summer 2009 at the World Congress for Jewish Studies in Jerusalem when others were heading home already, I attended session 352 held in the evening in the Senate room located away from the other sessions .  The session was dedicated to the editorial changes and changes over time in rav Kook’s thought. The speakers were Neriah Gutel, Yehudah Mrsky, Udi Avramovitch  and Bitty Yehudah. And the audience was the entire cabal of Rav Kook experts (<a href="http://www.nrg.co.il/online/1/ART2/112/240.html">minus a few for specific personal reasons.</a>) Their papers and the discussion afterwards discussed all the debated issues of what do we learn from these new volumes? How was Rav Kook’s vision different at the beginning? And what was consciously changed and censored? </p>
<p>Everyone had already read Avinoam Rozenak’s Hidden Diaries and New Discoveries: The Life and Thought of Rabbi A. I. Kook Shofar: An Interdisciplinary Journal of Jewish Studies &#8211; Volume 25, Number 3, Spring 2007, pp. 111-147, which first appeared in Hebrew. Rozenak showed that some of these writing had a more antinomian element to them and that the editors were more conservative. </p>
<p>So here is the 250 page pdf of one new books, <a href='https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2010/05/kook-nevuchai.pdf'>Harav Kook- leNevuchai Hazeman</a> The work starts off following the Guide of the Perplexed for content but then veers off course.  Very little of it is new, we have seen almost all  of the paragraphs or at least the ideas before in his other works.  What we gain is a turn a phrase here, a named interlocutor there, and an alternative organization illuminating Rav Kook’s thought pattern.</p>
<p>We also have two recent articles in Kipa [in Hebrew]. <a href="http://www.kipa.co.il/jew/show.asp?id=38570">One used the aforementioned Udi Avramovitch </a>as its expert source. Udi finds the volume more radical than the printed version and he finds a greater identity of God’s will and the will of the people. He also claims that in this work Rav Kook claims a value for other religions and that they worship the one true God. <a href="http://www.kipa.co.il/jew/show.asp?id=38613">The second article</a> quotes the army and settlement Rabbi Yosef Kellner that the book is essential to read but they are confining distribution, and <a href="http://bhol-forums.co.il/topic.asp?whichpage=2&amp;topic_id=2789611&amp;forum_id=1364">here is a letter by Rav Kellner about the book.</a></p>
<p>Rav Kook started the volume while still in Europe and finished it in Jaffa. The book starts off discussing the image of God as volition- will. Human have a will to make manifest as creativity in the world. Yes, Schopenhauer’s definition of man as the guide for our generation.  (Along the way Spinoza is deftly defeated by the volition of R. Moses Hayyim Luzatto)The second chapter tells me that Saadayah and Maimonides saw that books of sectarians (minim) multiplied so they were compelled to write philosophic works.  That does not inspire me in its understanding of the medieval but tells me more about Rav Kook. In a later chapter, he tells me that “all revolutions are good for clearing away the small minded people and narrow visions” with a later in the paragraph phrase that “they all follow the pure knowledge of God” Holy Hegelian Marxist! What do I do with these grapplings with the sectarian writings of German Idealists for a Torah for the 21st century?</p>
<p>Can we use this as a guide for social revolution now? Well, let look at what he said about the problem of favoritism, corruption and cronyism in rabbinic courts. Rav Kook was against any change to the institutional fabric and rejected secular oversight or higher courts to oversee lower batai din, threatening to return to the R. Hayyim Sonnenfeld camp. What of women in modern world? He did not think women should vote or study Torah. What of secular studies? The new diaries show that he encouraged his inner circle to avoid the wisdom of the gentiles and stick to the prophetic Torah.</p>
<p>Furthermore, we tend to read Rav Kook as if he is the one pushing the envelope on the potential diffusion of God’s light in a new age. Rather than responding to forgotten correspondents who were more radical than he was like R Shmuel Alexandrov or R. Moshe Seidel.  These newly released versions, at first reading, will make it easier to find the original dialogue partner.  As you read through it, let me know if you find any especially unique passages or if you can detect changes from the beginning to the end of the writing process.</p>
<p>For the meaning of these writings, I await the series of new scholarly articles that will be written in the next few years. The one thing these writings do show is his concern with making a new passionate Jew beyond cognitive focus of the Eastern European beit midrash. A new Jew concerned with volition, inner voice, volkgeist,  a new age, love, and seeking a new knowledge of God.   </p>
<p><strong>Immediate Update</strong>&#8211; both the article in Kipa and the file of Rav Kook have been take down, the link wont work. I can understand the removal of the unpublished book, but what benign or nefarious power took down a current news article. If anyone knows then please let me know. The article in Kipah is cached and one can still get to the Headline but not the article. Friends in Israel, what&#8217;s the story?<br />
<strong>Next Update</strong>&#8211; I just posted the pdf from my saved copy and the articles reappeared with minor changes.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/28/new-unpublished-rav-kook/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>5</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Arthur Green- Radical Judaism #2 of 5 parts</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/26/arthur-green-radical-judaism-2/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/26/arthur-green-radical-judaism-2/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Apr 2010 03:43:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neo-Hasidism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rabbis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[spirituality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[arthur Green]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[radical judaism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1176</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The first chapter is on Green’s quest for God. Continued from part 1- here. Continue to part 3 &#8211; here. Continue to part 4 here. part 5 here Green writes that he is a Jewish seeker looking for a lone &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/26/arthur-green-radical-judaism-2/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The first chapter is on Green’s quest for God.</p>
<p><a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/06/arthur-green-radical-judaism-1/">Continued from part 1- here. </a>     </p>
<p> <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/01/arthur-green-–-radical-judaism-3/">Continue to part 3 &#8211; here.</a> <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/08/green-radical-judaism-4/">Continue to part 4 here. </a><br />
<a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/22/arthur-green-–-radical-judaism-5/">part 5 here</a></p>
<p>Green writes that he is a Jewish seeker looking for a lone path. He discusses his atheist upbringing and that he is seeking a middle path between atheism and theism, which he finds in his poetic pantheistic reading of Hasidism.</p>
<p>Green wants to be both a seeker and the spiritual leader of our age. His calling himself a seeker is a bit much at this point when Green sets himself up  as an exemplar and leader of our age.  Someone who is seeking does not write an article called “On Being Arthur Green” implying that one should learn from his wisdom &#8211; it was published when he first got to Hebrew College. One can only write an article like that at a pinnacle to share your wisdom. In addition, Green has been in the public eye and noted in the newspapers his whole life.</p>
<p>As a spiritual autobiography of someone who was in all the important places, there was little on his teachers at JTS or Brandeis. Nor on his classmates David Novak, Reuven Kimmelman, and  Byron Sherwin. Nothing as doctoral adviser at Penn or his being President of RRC. Nor a mention of being invited as a young academic to Peter Berger’s &#8220;other side of God&#8221; retreats or being one of the youngest involved in the Classics of Spirituality and World Spirituality series. Nothing on founding Shefa quarterly with Jonathan Omar-Man and Adin Steinsatz. And most surprisingly nothing on the founding of the first havurah while in grad school Havurat Shalom in Somerville, where along with his buddies Danny Matt, Michael Fishbane, James Kugel and Michael Strassfeld they set out to create a new Judaism for a new age. As a seeker he can claim to “still haven’t found what I am looking for” and not need to survey the past. But if he is offering wisdom that he holds as truth then the disestablishmentarianism is a bit jarring.</p>
<p>Green himself attributes his title <em>Radical Judaism</em> to the radical &#8220;God is dead&#8221; theology of the 1960’s. He claims that the holocaust and historical criticism ruptured his faith. He found his way back through the non-personal pantheistic hiding God of Hasidism and Kabbalah. He attributes his salvation in the writings of  Hilell Zeitlin (H”YD) who went from freethinking journalist to fervent Hasid and was uniquely able to interpret Hasidism through the eyes of Nietzsche, Schopenhauer, and Tolstoy. Zeitlin created an urbane Hasidism for his urban newspaper readers.</p>
<p>As a side point, Green’s <em>Tormented Master</em> followed the interpretive lines of Zeitlin and portrayed Rav Nahman as struggling with doubt and freethinking.  When Mendel Pierkaz gave a negative review of Green as “Hasidism for a new world” since it was based on Zeitlin, everyone was furious and even more furious when Piekarz reprinted his review.  The sacrilege was that Green was considered in America as the true university interpretation of Rav Nahman. Now Zvi Mark is the regnant academic work on Rav Nahman and has a different reading of Rav Nahman than Greens, and more people follow the interpretation of Rav Nahman by Rabbis Kenig, Schick, Arush and Schechter et al than academic works.</p>
<p>Green accepts his involvement in the psychedelic age and quaintly defines post-modernism as the rejection of modernity by the counter culture of the 1960’s  They sought to transcend the rational into the realm of myth, drugs, pantheism, and poetry. (Go read Art Green&#8217;s early psychedelic works under the pseudonym Itzhak Lodzer.) </p>
<p>Green accepts as another side to his thought that of religious humanism- Kafka, Buber, and Hebrew literature.</p>
<p>After almost 40 years, Green is not claiming identity of his thought with Heschel anymore. He does claim affinity to Tom Berry (d 2009) visionary advocate of evolutionary ecological development of human consciousness, human lifestyle, and our life on the planet. Berry is the near forgotten theologian of the Age of Aquarius and moon landing, who barely got obituaries last summer when he died. Green reminds people of Berry’s positions on our sitting on the edge of a new evolutionary moment where religion will no longer be literal. Like in 2001 Space Odyssey, the world is being thrust into the future and mankind needs to evolve with it.  Religion will now be a mystical pantheism of energy flow that God providentially directs. Yes, he believes this but just not literal the way fundamentalists or orthodox believe. This God is not the theistic God of the Protestant era but “God” – the force of the astro, geo, bio, psych, realms.</p>
<p>Many years ago, Green wrote an article in<em> Shefa Quarterly </em>on the need for a new Jewish theology deserves reprinting for its quest for remytholization over rationalism. Not shattered myths but learning to make the myths of Pesikta, Zohar, and Rav Nahman come live again. For a sense of what this new volume lacks in its discussion of myth compared to older Green writings, here are some excerpts from a <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/1989/02/19/us/reconstructionist-jews-turn-to-the-supernatural.html">NYT interview from 1989 </a>about the new RRC prayer book. They give a sense of the kernel of the birth his rejection of rational for myth and learning to see religion as a progressive force.</p>
<blockquote><p>While the notion of a &#8221;chosen people&#8221; is still excluded from the new liturgy, the mention of miracles, like the splitting of the Red Sea, have been restored. Dr. Arthur Green, president of the Reconstructionist Rabbinical College and one of the editors of the new volume, said the &#8221;language of myth&#8221; speaks powerfully to many people, even if they do not believe in the literal details. &#8221;As myth, the ancient tale of wonder underscores the sense of daily miracle in our lives,&#8221; he said.</p>
<p>Dr. Green, the president of the college, said the prayer book was molded by events that began unfolding in the 1960&#8217;s, and &#8221;our view of religion and its place in society have drastically changed&#8221; since then. The nation, he said, went from debates over &#8221;Is God Dead?&#8221; to seeing the power of religion in the civil rights movement and in the movement to end the Vietnam War. &#8221;We learned from the 60&#8217;s that religion can be a progressive social force for change,&#8221; he added.</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/01/arthur-green-–-radical-judaism-3/">Continue to part 3 &#8211; here.</a><br />
<a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/08/green-radical-judaism-4/">Continue to part Four here </a><br />
<a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/22/arthur-green-–-radical-judaism-5/">Continue to part 5 here.</a></p>
<p>Copyright © 2010 Alan Brill • All Rights Reserved </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/26/arthur-green-radical-judaism-2/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>6</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Arthur Green- Radical Judaism #1 of 5 posts</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/06/arthur-green-radical-judaism-1/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/06/arthur-green-radical-judaism-1/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2010 01:15:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Hasidism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neo-Hasidism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[A Plausible God]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[arthur Green]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[david wolpe]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[radical judaism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1084</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[There is a new book from Arthur Green that is his mature vision for a Neo-Hasidic Renewal Judaism. I received a review copy as soon as it came out and have been grappling about whether this will be a short &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/06/arthur-green-radical-judaism-1/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There is a new book from Arthur Green that is his mature vision for a Neo-Hasidic Renewal Judaism. I received a review copy as soon as it came out and have been grappling about whether this will be a short quickly review or a very long full study. In his introduction, Green quotes Arnold Eisen as telling Green that he should put out a definite scholarly version of his theology. The actual product is a version that is actually less scholarly and more personal than the prior versions and can serve as an eminently readable introduction to his thought.</p>
<p>In the interim as I continue to write up my own reflections, David Wolpe has put out a very concise and insightful review.  Wolpe puts his finger on the pulse of the book as having a renegade provocative 1960’s tone. He also catches how a technical academic scholarly approach glides in Green’s hands into New Age mysticism. Green’s work rejects Biblical theism into a minimal theology of mystical metaphors. Wolpe calls it pantheist and animist but I think there is much more going on. Green’s God would feel comfortable on the shelf with Eliade as a myth and symbol, sacred cyclical time deity.</p>
<p>The view of God of Arthur Green, Michael Lerner, and others has been given a quite cogent philosophic and theological analysis by Michael Silver, <em>A Plausible God: Secular Reflections on Liberal Jewish Theology</em> (New York: Fordham University Press, 2006)</p>
<p>Those of us interested in Kabbalah and Hasidism have a much more complex relationship with Green’s work than does Wolpe because Green’s <em>Tormented Master</em> was one of the first works available in English. Green has had a presence in both the academic and theological use of Hasidism, and the field consists of his students. Nevertheless, many of the original readers of <em>Tormented Master </em>have either moved on to the works by the Breslov Research Institute and no longer turn to academic works or the readers turned to charismatic teachers by Aleph –Alliance for Jewish Renewal. </p>
<p>Those of us who teach Polish Hasidism, when dealing with Green’s works have to grapple with when Green is modernizing in a natural way, when he transforms it into his own renewal view, and when he just truncates away an essential element such as Torah study or halakhah.<br />
<a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/26/arthur-green-radical-judaism-2/">Continue to post 2 of 5 posts on Arthur Green &#8211; here.</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.jewishjournal.com/ books/article/rethinking_judaism_20100331">March 30, 2010 Rethinking Judaism By Rabbi David Wolpe</a></p>
<blockquote><p>Arthur Green, author of “Radical Judaism: Rethinking God and Tradition” (Yale University Press, $26), has been working to reimagine Judaism since his early days as a renegade scholar and theologian. The book under review is filled with interesting observations and sources. They are knit together in a neo-Chasidic, kabbalistically infused ’60s activist Judaism that claims Green as one of its pioneers and preeminent spokesmen. To rework a Divine self-description, this book will be persuasive for those to whom it is persuasive. Some will find it a bracing tonic; for others it will be Jewish learning sprinkled with heresy. Can “radical Judaism” speak to people outside the envisioned circle?<br />
Most of Green’s book (a capstone to the trilogy, “Seek My Face, Speak My Name” and “Ehyeh: A Kabbalah for Tomorrow”), is deliberately provocative. “Radical Judaism” should not be the title of a book that soothes. It is accessibly written, although occasionally with a kind of academic-cum-New Age mistiness that some will cherish and others will not: “Just as Y-H-W-H is not a ‘thing’ but refers to the transcendent wholeness of Being that both surpasses and embraces all beings, so is the soul to be seen as the transcendent wholeness of the person, a mysterious essence that is more than the sum of all the characteristics of that person we could ever name.”<br />
Green’s approach is panentheist. God is not a separate Being who created and superintends the world. Rather God is in all things, shot through the fabric of life, but because the system as a whole is greater than its parts, God is also more than the sum of life. If this smacks of a kind of “Avatar”-ish paganism, that charge is one kabbalists have always had to combat. Green insists it is not pagan, as his predecessors always did. He is right; it is not worship of nature; it is rather a deification of the totality of all that is. For moderns, such a theology may be the only possible piety. To a classical taste, while this may not be paganism, it is at least in the animist suburbs.<br />
Green wrests from this premise some very beautiful and inspiring imagery. Speaking of faith, he wisely says, “We can only testify, never prove. Our strength lies in grandeur of vision, in an ability to transport the conversation about existence and origins to a deeper plane of thinking.” This he seeks to do by insisting that we have to reconceive of God and the world. Everything is interdependent, connected and organismic — and together this vast, pulsing reality is what we can augment or diminish by our actions. In the modern world we have learned to look at systems, and his is a sort of systems theology.<br />
For Green, our great task is awareness. The book is divided into classical categories — God, Torah, Israel. Within each, he struggles with the particularity and universality of the tradition. He struggles as well with the need, given a modern audience, to explain traditional concepts before he can offer a revisioning of them.<br />
As one would expect of a leading light of the chavurah and renewal movements, Green’s book is also a call for Jews to be politically activist. Environmentalism, anti-war activities and other traditional causes of the left are seen not as political choices, but as spiritual imperatives. To criticize the book for this is foolish: One can agree or disagree with convictions and still esteem the courage to have them. For Green, a religious position that does not embrace his politics contradicts the heart of his theology of interdependence: As we are all bound together, universalism, environmentalism, radical activism in many areas is a concomitant of theological understanding.<br />
Green writes several times that he hopes non-Jews will take up this book as well. Certainly much of his theology is not “specifically” Jewish: There is no chosenness, for there is no Chooser. Jews have special responsibilities arising from their history; yet other groups do as well. Green reads his beliefs from the sources of Judaism, and does so with deep knowledge and skill, but they are surely not the predominant reading. Other religious traditions can be read to endorse the same conclusions, as he readily acknowledges. Indeed, Green repeatedly encourages Jews to turn to other traditions, East and West, for insights absent or unacknowledged in our own.<br />
In a pluralistic age, readers will have different feelings about such ecumenicism. Some will see it as a great strength; others as a disqualifying weakness. As one whose belief in God is more traditional than Green’s, I remain enlightened and provoked, but ultimately unpersuaded. </p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/06/arthur-green-radical-judaism-1/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>4</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Eleven Maskilim</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/01/eleven-maskilim/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/01/eleven-maskilim/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2010 05:46:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[religious zionism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[haskalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[haskole]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mizrahi]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1042</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In the Haaretz Passover supplement there is a nice introduction to the important maskilim of the end of the 19th century. In their time, they were the intellectuals who were read by everyone who wanted to sustain the Jewish community. &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/01/eleven-maskilim/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the Haaretz Passover supplement there is a nice introduction to the important maskilim of the end of the 19th century. In their time, they were the intellectuals who were read by everyone who wanted to sustain the Jewish community. </p>
<p>Some of these Russian haskole figures are the banes of the 1890- 1940 Yeshiva world and one finds many allusions and refutations  to the writings of the mussar movement or the writings of the Yeshiva world. (Anyone have any favorite citations? Let see who has the best one. Bear in mind that Schulman was the translator  of Graetz and that Hasidic tales are based on the model of Zweifel.)  </p>
<p>The Mizrahi movement of Reines and his followers Zev Yaavetz and A. M. Lifshitz incorporated the changes to Jewish education advocated by these maskilim. Modern Orthodoxy does not really come from Rabbi S.R. Hirsch and Germany but from the hundreds of Russian rabbis who moved to the US and turned to the Maskilim and the Mizrahi rabbis to help create a Hebrew education system. Between the two wars most of the Mizrahi movement lived in the US and only made aliyah in the early 1950’s. Figures in US Orthodoxy like Pinchas Churgin, Moshe Seidel, Wolf Gold, Shimon Federbush, Meir Bar-Ilan are the forgotten creators of our elementary school system of Hebrew, navi, maps, charts, and “mi amar le-mi.”  These Russian born Mizrahi educators are nearly forgotten in American Jewish memory. Day school curriculum is based on these Mizrahi movement figures and their use of the haskole works.<br />
High Schools used to present many of these haskole figures as if they were all observant, some were and some were not. </p>
<p><em>Lights on in the park  By Haim Cohen<br />
Along with shady paths and playgrounds, Tel Aviv&#8217;s Haskalah Park offers a history lesson on the Jewish enlightenment</p>
<p>Like the names of 11 streets in the adjacent neighborhood, Bitzaron, the park commemorates the Jewish Enlightenment movement (the Haskalah). Portraits of 11 Enlightenment thinkers (maskilim) adorn the shelter in the south of the park, </p>
<p>The maskilim called for education, tolerance, love of mankind and morality, the spread of knowledge and the valorization of the Hebrew language. They expressed their ideas through journals, newspapers and books. Among the key maskilim were the philosopher Moses Mendelssohn, who is considered the father of the Jewish Enlightenment, and Isaac Eichel, its founder; Isaac Baer Levinsohn, one of the first maskilim in Russia; Samuel David Luzzatto, from Padua in Italy; philosopher and historian Reb Nachman Krochmal; the poet Y.L. Gordon and many more. </p>
<p>Leading lights </p>
<p>Each of the 11 maskilim represented in the park was given an appropriate nickname. There are The Linguist (Yehuda Leib Ben-Zeev), The Satirist (Isaac Erter), The Itinerant Maskil (Abraham Baer Gottlober), The Translator (Kalman Schulman), The Reconciler (Eliezer Zvi Hacohen Zweifel), The Scientist (Chaim Zelig Slonimski), The Scholar of Jewish Studies (Solomon Rubin), The Concordance Compiler (Salomon Mandelkern), The Bibliographer (Yitzhak Isaac Ben-Yaakov) The Teacher (Israel Haim Tavyov) and The Typical Maskil (Mordecai Aaron Guenzburg). </p>
<p>The Concordance Compiler </p>
<p>Salomon Mandelkern (1846-1902) established the impressive project of the Hebrew-Latin Bible concordance &#8220;Heikhal Hakodesh&#8221; (Leipzig, 1896), the exhausting distribution of which cost him his mental health. Mandelkern was a Hebrew poet, a Bible scholar and a philologist. He translated German and Russian masterpieces into Hebrew, served as a government rabbi in Odessa and was active in the promulgation of the Haskalah.<br />
At the southern edge of the park is a table with his Hebrew translation of Lord Byron&#8217;s poem &#8220;So We&#8217;ll Go No More A-roving&#8221; (Leipzig, 1890). </p>
<p>The Scientist </p>
<p>Chaim Zelig Slonimski (1810-1904) wrote and published many scientific texts in Hebrew on mathematics, astronomy, optics, engineering and more, and reported to Hebrew readers on innovations in science in his newspaper Hatsfira (the first Hebrew newspaper published in Poland). Slonimski invented many things, including a calculator in 1844, and served as the head of the Zhitomir rabbinical seminary and as censor of Hebrew and Yiddish books for the Russian government.<br />
Etched on one of the handsome tables in the park is the title page of his work on astronomy, &#8220;Sefer Kokhava Deshavita,&#8221; which was published in Vilna in 1835, along with an illustration of the solar system from the book&#8217;s appendix. </p>
<p>The Teacher </p>
<p>Israel Haim Tavyov (1858-1920) ran an &#8220;improved heder&#8221; (traditional primary school), wrote textbooks in Hebrew and briefly (1908-10) published a vowel-pointed daily newspaper for children, Hehaver. He was also a playwright, author, translator and researcher of language and folklore who earned his living as an accountant and teacher. </p>
<p>The Satirist </p>
<p>Isaac Erter (1791-1851) was one of the key figures in the Hebrew literature of the 19th century (as well as a teacher and physician). In his works, he criticized the ways of the Hasidim, describing Jewish life in Galicia in a sarcastic and amusing way. </p>
<p>The Reconciler </p>
<p>Eliezer Zvi Hacohen Zweifel (1815-1888) criticized the way in which the Haskalah&#8217;s bitter enemy, Hasidism, had developed, but in his work &#8220;Peace on Israel&#8221; (1868-73, in four volumes), he described the early days of Hasidism in a positive light. His moderate and tolerant approach was a source of tension with his fellow maskilim. He was also a historian and wrote essays and fictional works, but earned his living as a preacher and teacher of young children, and as a teacher of Talmud at the Zhitomir rabbinical seminary. On a table in the park there is a quotation from his &#8220;Peace on Israel&#8221; about the exhausting work of a maskil: </p>
<p>For nigh 30 years I&#8217;ve been writing this and I&#8217;m fatigued.<br />
For whom? And why? It&#8217;s a mystery even to me.<br />
For my sake? For heaven&#8217;s sake? No! On different grounds<br />
On grounds embracing all the wheels of reality and life<br />
Grounds that keep species, persons and health alive<br />
Grounds obvious to some and to others unfound. </p>
<p>(from &#8220;Peace on Israel,&#8221; by E.Z. Zweifel, Volume III, Vilna, 1873). </p>
<p>The Linguist<br />
Yehuda Leib Ben-Zeev (1764-1811) published pioneering, widely distributed books of grammar and syntax, textbooks and dictionaries, such as &#8220;Talmud Lashon Ivri&#8221; (1796) and &#8220;Otzar Hashorashim&#8221; (1807-1808). </p>
<p>The Typical Maskil </p>
<p>Mordecai Aaron Guenzburg (1795-1846) was one of the earliest maskilim, and an outstanding figure in the Jewish Enlightenment in Lithuania in the first half of the 19th century. He translated many books into Hebrew and Yiddish, aiming to expand the horizons of the Jewish public, and wrote books on Russian history and the Napoleonic wars. His autobiographical work &#8220;Aviezer&#8221; was published posthumously. This is a rare book for its time, written in the 1840s, in which he frankly described his life and childhood and touched upon fundamental problems of the traditional society. </p>
<p>The Translator<br />
Kalman Schulman (1819-1899) translated modern literature into Hebrew, as well as books on history and geography that were published in many editions. The most outstanding of his translations is that of the French writer Eugene Sue&#8217;s &#8220;The Mysteries of Paris&#8221; which is considered the first modern novel to have been translated into Hebrew. He taught Hebrew literature at the rabbinical and teachers seminary in Vilna, and was active in the Society for the Promotion of Culture among the Jews of Russia. </p>
<p>The Scholar of Jewish Studies </p>
<p>Solomon Rubin (1823-1910?) was one of the most prolific of the Haskalah writers. His research covered many areas of Jewish studies, including history, Hebrew literature and folklore, linguistics, Jewish philosophy religions of the ancient East. He also translated books and plays into Hebrew. He wrote a doctorate at Goettingen University in Germany (1868) and earned his living, inter alia, as an accountant and teacher.<br />
The Itinerant Maskil </p>
<p>Abraham Baer Gottlober (1811-1899) is known mainly for his autobiographical memoirs of his wanderings, in which he described Jewish life in Eastern Europe, Hasidism and the Haskalah. Gottlober was a writer and poet in Hebrew and Yiddish, a translator, a teacher of Talmud and a historian. In the last years of his life, he was a member of Hovevei Zion, an organization that promoted Jewish settlement in the land of Israel. </p>
<p>The Bibliographer </p>
<p>Yitzhak Isaac Ben-Yaakov (1801-1863) was a publisher of ancient Hebrew manuscripts and a book trader. His greatest bibliographic project, &#8220;Otzar Haseforim&#8221; (1877-80), listed about 17,000 Hebrew books in print and manuscript. He published a special edition of the Hebrew Bible in 17 volumes with Rashi&#8217;s commentary, new notes and a translation into German in Hebrew letters from Mendelssohn&#8217;s commentary (the Biur) on the Pentateuch.</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1159877.html">Full Version</a><br />
Copyright © 2010 Alan Brill • All Rights Reserved </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/01/eleven-maskilim/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Levinas: Mature Jewish faith and Conference on Difficult Freedom</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/27/levinas-mature-jewish-faith-and-conference-on-difficult-freedom/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/27/levinas-mature-jewish-faith-and-conference-on-difficult-freedom/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 28 Mar 2010 01:20:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ethics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Difficile Liberté]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Difficult Freedom]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Levinas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mature faith]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1014</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This week I had the opportunity to teach this wonderful passage of Levinas again. Levinas exhorts his reader to have a mature faith and get rid of one’s primitive and childish views of God. A person needs to understand that &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/27/levinas-mature-jewish-faith-and-conference-on-difficult-freedom/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This week I had the opportunity to teach this wonderful passage of Levinas again. Levinas exhorts his reader to have a mature faith and get rid of one’s primitive and childish views of God. A person needs to understand that God does not promise anything or follow one&#8217;s magical thinking about God. He asks: “What kind of strange magician did you project as the inhabitant of your heaven.” Only an empty heaven allows one to take on the responsibilities of justice in this world. Only a heaven empty of childish perceptions allow an adult’s God can have an inner sense to fight evil and seek good. The eternal covenant is a Divine demand for goodness and justice, the deepest significance of the covenant between God and Israel.</p>
<blockquote><p>What is the meaning of the suffering of the innocent? Does it not witness to a world without God, to an earth where only man determines the measure of good and evil?  The simplest, most ordinary response would indeed be to draw the conclusion that there is no God.  This would also be the healthiest response for all those who until now have believed in a rather primitive God who awards prizes, imposes sanctions, or pardons mistakes, and who, in His goodness, treats people like perpetual children.  But what kind of limited spirit, what kind of strange magician did you project as the inhabitant of your heaven – you who today state that heaven is deserted? And why are you still looking, beneath an empty heaven, for a world that makes sense and is good?</p>
<p>Yossel son of Yossel experiences, with renewed vigor, beneath an empty heaven, certainty about God.  For his finding himself thus alone allows him to feel, on his shoulders, all of God&#8217;s responsibilities.  On the road that leads to the one and only God, there is a way station without God.  True monotheism must frame answers to the legitimate demands of atheism.  An adult&#8217;s God reveals Himself precisely in the emptiness of the child&#8217;s heaven.  That is the moment when God withdraws Himself from the world and veils His countenance.  “He has sacrificed humankind to its wild instincts,” says our text.  “And because those instincts dominate the world, it is natural that those who preserve the divine and the pure should be the first victims of this domination.”</p>
<p>But by the same token, this God who veils His countenance and abandons the just person, un-victorious, to his own justice – this faraway God – comes from inside.  That is the intimacy that coincides, in one&#8217;s conscience, with the pride of being Jewish, of being concretely, historically, altogether mindlessly, a part of the Jewish people.  “To be a Jew means… to be an everlasting swimmer against the turbulent, criminal human current… I am happy to belong to the unhappiest people in the world, to the people whose Torah represents the loftiest and most beautiful of all laws and moralities.”  Intimacy with this virile God is attained in passing an ultimate test.  Because I belong to the suffering Jewish people, the faraway God becomes my God.  “Now I know that you are truly my God, for you cannot possibly be the God of those whose deeds are the most horrible expression of a militant absence of God.” The just person&#8217;s suffering for the sake of a justice that fails to triumph is concretely lived out in the form of Judaism.</p></blockquote>
<p>Translation from the VBM shiur of  Tamir Granot-<a href="http://vbm-torah.org/archive/shoah/26b-shoah.htm"> Read full Version Here</a></p>
<p>This coincided with the web announcement of a great conference on <em>Difficult Freedom,</em> Levinas’ early Jewish writings. <em>First published in 1963, with a second edition appearing in 1976, Difficile Liberté is considered Levinas&#8217; most accessible book and constitutes an excellent introduction to his work: philosophy, Biblical and Talmudic commentary, a traditional yet new approach to Judaism, and an educational mission.<br />
<strong>« Readings of Difficult Freedom»</strong> is the largest international conference ever devoted to Levinas and his work. For an entire week, more than 180 speakers from 41 countries will present and discuss the ideas presented in Difficult Freedom. In addition, during the entire conference week there will be lectures and debates in a number of cultural centers in Toulouse as well as screenings of movies and documentaries. The conference and events are all open to the public.</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.sirel-levinas.org/dotclear/public/reading-DL-program-general-plenary-15-03-2010.pdf">Here are the plenary sessions.</a><br />
<a href="http://www.sirel-levinas.org/dotclear/public/readings-DL-parallel-17-03-2010.pdf">Here are the concurrent sessions.</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/27/levinas-mature-jewish-faith-and-conference-on-difficult-freedom/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Jewish respect and admiration for Muslim religiosity</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/15/jewish-respect-and-admiration-for-muslim-religiosity/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/15/jewish-respect-and-admiration-for-muslim-religiosity/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2010 18:27:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mysticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[popular religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rabbis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[islam and judaism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[yitzhak farhi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[zvi Zohar]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=944</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Here is something from last week by Zvi Zohar, Jewish respect and admiration for Muslim religiosity A full English translation of the original account is here. The original Hebrew article, with extensive footnotes was &#8220;An Awesome Event in the City &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/15/jewish-respect-and-admiration-for-muslim-religiosity/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here is something from last week by Zvi Zohar, Jewish respect and admiration for Muslim religiosity </p>
<p><a href="http://www.ihsis.org/Uploads/admin/Lisbon2009-Rabbi-Sheikh.pdf">A full English translation of the original account is here.</a> The original Hebrew article, with extensive footnotes was &#8220;An Awesome Event in the City of Damascus&#8221; in Tolerance in Religious Traditions (Shlomo Fisher ed., 2008). </p>
<p><em>Here I consider one such source, found in the writings of Rabbi Yitzhak Farhi of Jerusalem (1782-1853). It tells of a relationship between two outstanding men in late 18th century Damascus: a great Sufi sheikh and the Chief Rabbi of Damascus.<br />
One of the two heroes of Farhi’s tale, the Sufi sheikh, attained great mastery of the Seven Wisdoms, i.e., the body of universal human knowledge. Since a person’s perfection is contingent upon mastery of these wisdoms, the sheikh was more perfect than all the Jews of his generation, with the exception of the rabbi of Damascus, who was his equal and even slightly his superior in the realm of universal wisdom. </p>
<p>But the Seven Wisdoms are of course only one aspect of religious perfection: the highest form of religious accomplishment is the encounter with God and closeness to Him. In this realm, the realm of religious-mystical experience, it emerges quite clearly from Rabbi Farhi’s account that the sheikh was on a higher level than the rabbi. In that account, it was the sheikh who guided the rabbi along the paths of mystical experience, by way of the garden and the pool, until their joint entry into the Holy of Holies to encounter the Divine Reality reflected in the holy name YHVH. The words on the golden tablet they gazed upon were: “I envision YHWH before me always”. This formula is to be found in every synagogue. Yet as related by Farhi, the one who actualised the promise born by this verse, the person who was indeed able to envision in his consciousness “He Who Spoke and the universe was created”, was not the Jewish rabbi but the Muslim sheikh.</p>
<p>At the end of their joint journey, the rabbi shed copious tears, acknowledged the sheikh’s advantage in this crucial realm, and concluded: “It is becoming upon us to do even more than that”. </p>
<p>Rabbi Yitzhak Farhi, addressing his audience in Jerusalem and the Ottoman Empire in the fourth decade of the 19th century, presented the Sufi sheikh as an ideal spiritual figure reaching the greatest heights of awe of God.<br />
And above all else, there are shared elements and a partnership in the mystical experience itself—and in the joint focus of this experience: “He Who Spoke and the universe was created”. Not a Muslim God, and not a Jewish God, but the God of all existence, the Creator of all. </em></p>
<p>* Zvi Zohar is a professor of Sephardic Law and Ethics at Bar Ilan University, a Senior Research Fellow at the Shalom Hartman Institute of Advanced Judaic Studies in Jerusalem. A full translation, analysis and discussion of Rabbi Farhi’s account will soon be published in Jewish Studies Quarterly under the title “The Rabbi and the Sheikh”.<br />
<a href="http://www.commongroundnews.org/article.php?id=27423">Read Full op-ed Version here.</a></p>
<p>Update: I received a comment of Islamaphobia with an IP number from the Israel Tel Aviv Ministry-of-finance. Dont they at least tell people not to make such statements from work? Or at least not in English?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/15/jewish-respect-and-admiration-for-muslim-religiosity/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Kugel responds to his critics again</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/12/kugel-responds-to-his-critics-again/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/12/kugel-responds-to-his-critics-again/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 12 Mar 2010 16:03:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[bible]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[benjamin Sommer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[james Kugel]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=930</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I am surprised that this is not generating discussion The current issue of JQR has a critique of Kugel by Benjamin Sommer, “Two Introductions to Scripture: James Kugel and the Possibility of Biblical Theology,” Sommer advocates an approach like Moshe &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/12/kugel-responds-to-his-critics-again/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I am surprised that this is not generating discussion</p>
<p>The current issue of JQR has a critique of Kugel by Benjamin Sommer, “Two Introductions to Scripture: James Kugel and the<br />
Possibility of Biblical Theology,” Sommer advocates an approach like Moshe Greenberg, AJ Heschel, Michael Fishbane, or Jon Levenson and he has sympathies for Mordechai Breuer&#8217;s position.<br />
However, Kugel wrote an online response to Sommer, where all the ambiguities about Kugel&#8217;s position are finally cleared up. Kugel rejects all of the aforementioned names. Biblical study does not contribute to Judaism or religion. For Kugel, the Bible has no moral lessons or theological ideals.  There are no grand ideals or religious claims. Contradiction and parallel texts in the text do not teach anything. And there is a clear disjunctive between the Bible and the Scribes-Oral Law.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.jameskugel.com/kugel-jqr.pdf">Here is the response. </a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/12/kugel-responds-to-his-critics-again/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Shlomo Pines and Yoga</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/11/shlomo-pines-and-yoga/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/11/shlomo-pines-and-yoga/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 12 Mar 2010 01:42:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Buddhism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[al-Biruni]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jean-Luc Marion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kalam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[shlomo pines]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[yoga sutras]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=920</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I just discovered that there is a website and society dedicated to the memory of Professor Shlomo Pines of The Hebrew University. Pines is popularly associated with his translation of Maimonides’ Guide of the Perplexed, but for scholars he is &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/11/shlomo-pines-and-yoga/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I just discovered that there is a <a href="http://www.shlomopines.org.il/len/">website and society dedicated to the memory of Professor Shlomo Pines</a> of The Hebrew University. Pines is popularly associated with his translation of Maimonides’ Guide of the Perplexed, but for scholars he is known for his seminal articles on almost everything. As a polyglot he had an  uncanny ability to find kabbalah in Church Fathers, show that Judeo-Christians lasted for many more centuries than we thought, explain the atominism in Gaonic writings, find Ismaeli and Shiite influence on Halevi, contextualize Maimonides in the thought of Farabi and Ibn Bajja, find Hinduism in Arabic texts, and show how scholastics used Jewish thought. </p>
<p>Ever year they have a guest speaker in his honor. This year’s lecture in his honor is  Prof. Jean-Luc Marion (of the French Academy, The University of Paris-Sorbonne and the University of Chicago) will be our next lecturer for the Shlomo Pines annual lecture at the Israel Academy of Sciences and Humanities. He will speak on &#8220;Saint-Augustine and the Naming of God &#8211; idipsum&#8221;<br />
The lecture will be held on March 11, 2010 at 18:30 at the Israel Academy of Sciences and Humanities.<br />
It will be followed by a seminar on Friday, 12 March from 10:00 to 12:00 at the Belgium House, Givat Ram, the Hebrew University.<br />
You missed the lecture but try and catch the seminar. Marion is known for bringing God back into phenomenology.</p>
<p>The website has <a href="http://www.shlomopines.org.il/len/apage/40911.php">four articles about the life and thought of Shlomo Pines</a> well worth reading</p>
<p>It also has a <a href="http://www.shlomopines.org.il/len/apage/40908.php">few articles of the dozens that Pines wrote available as pdf’s. </a>It seems they started this project and then left off. But the articles that the web site does have up are his four articles that contain transcriptions and analysis of Patanjali’s Yoga Sutras as available in their Arabic translation.  Also available are articles on the use of Indian and Buddhist thought in the Kalam </p>
<p>These articles show that Jews in Muslim lands knew about various aspects of Indian religions through the Arabic (and Persian) mediators. The earliest Muslim scholar to show sustained interest in Indian religious and philosophical texts was the great scientist and philosopher al-Biruni (973-1048). He translated a number of Sanskrit works into Arabic (including selections from Patañjali&#8217;s Yogasūtras and the Bhagavad-Gita) in connection with his encyclopedic treatise on India. Al-Biruni did not translate the names of foreign deities, nor did he incorporate other gods  into his own theology. Like those who translated polytheistic Greek texts into Arabic, al-Biruni rendered the Sanskrit gods (deva) with the Arabic terms for angels (malā&#8217;ikah) or spiritual beings (rūhāniyyāt), a theological shift aiding in the acceptance of Indian texts.  Well- versed Jewish readers would have been acquainted with these translations and would have been thereby shielded from the foreign god implications of the original texts. These texts created a universal commonality since they understood Indian religions as monotheistic. In a similar manner, Jakata tales and the life of the Buddha tales became the various Hebrew collections of tales we know as the King and the Ascetic.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/11/shlomo-pines-and-yoga/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Further Adventures in new Zohar scholarship</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/06/further-adventures-in-new-zohar-scholarship/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/06/further-adventures-in-new-zohar-scholarship/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2010 01:40:20 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gerald Blidstein]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[honoring parents]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[oded yisraeli]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sefirot]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[yehudah liebes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[zohar]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=903</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[We have previously looked at the Zohar scholarship of Daniel Abrams, and Melila Hellner-Eshed, Now we look at Oded Yisraeli in a new article “Honoring Father and Mother in Early Kabbalah: From Ethos to Mythos” JQR 99/3 Summer 2009 396-415 &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/06/further-adventures-in-new-zohar-scholarship/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We have previously looked at the Zohar scholarship of <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/22/was-the-zohar-ever-a-book/">Daniel Abrams,</a> and <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/13/why-read-the-zohar/">Melila Hellner-Eshed,</a> Now we look at Oded Yisraeli in a new article “Honoring Father and Mother in Early Kabbalah: From Ethos to Mythos” JQR 99/3 Summer 2009 396-415</p>
<p>Yisraeli looks at a piece of Zohar where R. Hiyya identifies the father with binah, R. Abba identifies it with hokhmah, but R. Yossi identifies it with tiferet. Why does R. Yossi lower the identity of Father? Ans: to be more like Rabbinic texts.</p>
<p>Others have noted (Fishbane, Liebes, Heller-Eshed) that the names in the Zohar each portray different sources. Usually the names reflect a procession from Midrash to Gerona Kabbalah to Castillian Kabblah. But this case offer insight into the relationship of Zohar with Rabbinics. </p>
<p>Mother and Father are portrayed as the higher sefirot is everywhere before the Zohar, including Bahir and Gerona. The source is a variety of Logos theories and personification of the Nous and the highest levels.But starting with the Zohar Mother and Father are lowered to Tiferet and Malkhut.  Yisraeli claims that the shift in this case reflects a return to Rabbinics, especially the Mekhilta also cited in the Talmud, and Philo.<br />
The Talmud states that one honors one’s parents because it is honoring the Holy One, Blessed be He. Alternately in Philo, “parents are the created Gods”</p>
<p>Gerald Blidstein in his classic work <em>Honor Thy Father and Mother</em>, shows the prevalence of this idea in Stoic sources. But Blidstein sharply differentiates the rabbis from the Hellenistic sources because the Rabbis do not essentialize, and in fact treat God using a parent metaphor. In contrast, Yisraeli claims, that even without denying some difference between the Hellenistic sources and the Rabbinic, the later readers of the rabbinic tradition in later midrash and then in Kabbalah, in fact did essentialize. Kabblah presents an essentialist reading of Hazal.<br />
The Kabblaists were drawing the connection between the earthly father and the divine father of HKBH, creating a tight parallel.</p>
<p>Yehudah Liebes (1994) already noted the reading of the live images of rabbinics into a “stiff” kabbalistic framework.<br />
Yisraeli claims that nevertheless many of these live images were repressed and not used in the later rabbinic texts and they return afresh in kabbalah. He also claims that the new sefirot symbol makes a stronger case for the ethical imperative.</p>
<p>He finds a similar process in how “the land of Israel” is identified with malkhut. A repressed live myth of the land of Israel as divine realm returns as a need to cleave to malkhut. Before the 13th century when the goal was a restored Divine name, it did not have the same ethical import.<br />
He has studies on the process of moving from midrash to Zohar of the images of Eliyahu, Avrham, Esau, the land of Israel, and has forthcoming book on Tree of Life by Magnes Press. I look forward to reading it.</p>
<p>His forthcoming book will deal with the theme of the Tree of Life and show that the tree as essentialized in certain [Biblical and ] rabbinic passages, then the entire Divine realm is a tree (Bahir) and finally only Tiferet is a tree, but one can join to it, creating a stronger symbol.</p>
<p>Are you essential? Well, Hazal are essential according to the early kabbalah.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/06/further-adventures-in-new-zohar-scholarship/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>My New Book Just Came Out-Judaism and Other Religions</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/13/my-new-book-just-came-out-judaism-and-other-religions/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/13/my-new-book-just-came-out-judaism-and-other-religions/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 14 Feb 2010 00:43:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Buddhism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[spirituality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[alan brill]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr Brill]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jewish interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Judaism and other religions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[nathan Katz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rabbi Brill]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rabbi David Rosen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ruth Langer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=785</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[My book Judaism and Other Religions is to be officially released on March 2nd by Palgrave-Macmillan. But it is already available in the warehouse and available for purchase, Be the first one on your block to own one. Buy it &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/13/my-new-book-just-came-out-judaism-and-other-religions/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My book <strong>Judaism and Other Religions</strong> is to be officially released on March 2nd by Palgrave-Macmillan. But it is already available in the warehouse and available for purchase, Be the first one on your block to own one. Buy it now:</p>
<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Judaism-Other-Religions-Models-Understanding/dp/0230622267/ref=ntt_at_ep_dpt_2">Click here to buy it at Amazon </a></strong></p>
<p><a href="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="165" data-permalink="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/about/brill0230622267-2/" data-orig-file="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg" data-orig-size="396,594" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;}" data-image-title="Brill0230622267" data-image-description="" data-medium-file="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg?w=200" data-large-file="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg?w=396" class="alignleft size-medium wp-image-165" title="Brill0230622267" src="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg?w=200&#038;h=300" alt="" width="200" height="300" srcset="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg?w=200&amp;h=300 200w, https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg?w=100&amp;h=150 100w, https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg 396w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /></a></p>
<p><strong>Editorial Reviews</strong></p>
<p>“This wide-ranging but carefully organized collection of Jewish thought about other religions constitutes an indispensable resource for Jews and non-Jews engaged in interreligious relations today and for Jews seeking to develop a text-based contemporary Jewish theology of religions for our global world. Brill accompanies his lucid presentations of each approach with insightful critiques that will help guide their contemporary applications.”—Ruth Langer, Associate Professor of Jewish Studies, Theology Department Associate Director, Center for Christian-Jewish Learning, Boston College</p>
<p>“Serious Jewish engagement with other religions has substantially deepened and widened in recent years, both stimulating and responding to an increasing interest in Judaism from within the other world religions. Brill’s book provides essential access to the classical sources within the Jewish tradition relevant to this encounter.”—Rabbi Dr. David Rosen, International Director of Interreligious Affairs, AJC</p>
<p>“This is an excellent work: reflective, engaging, well-written, and perhaps most important—timely. Brill knows both the theoretical foundations for interreligious dialogue and rabbinic approaches to ‘other religions.’ It is a fine piece of scholarship, and it is also creative in bringing together three fields of discourse in a way they have not before been aligned. It blends both traditional and modern thinking about interreligious dialogue, and it analyzes these materials convincingly.”—Nathan Katz, Professor of Religious Studies, Florida International University</p>
<p><strong>Product Description</strong></p>
<p>With insight and scholarship, Alan Brill crisply outlines the traditional Jewish approaches to other religions for an age of globalization. He provides a fresh perspective on Biblical and Rabbinic texts, offering new ways of thinking about other faiths. In the majority of volume, he develops the categories of theology of religions for Jewish texts. He arranges the texts according classification widely used in interfaith work: inclusivist, exclusivist, universalist, and pluralist.</p>
<p>Judaism and Other Religions is essential for a Jewish theological understanding of the various issues in encounters with other religions. With passion and clarity, Brill argues that in today’s world of strong religious passions and intolerance, it is necessary to go beyond secular tolerance toward moderate and mediating religious positions.</p>
<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Judaism-Other-Religions-Models-Understanding/dp/0230622267/ref=ntt_at_ep_dpt_2">Click here to buy it at Amazon </a></strong></p>
<p>There is a forthcoming sequel volume <strong>Judaism and World Religions,</strong> which will be available at the end of 2010.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/13/my-new-book-just-came-out-judaism-and-other-religions/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>10</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg?w=200" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">Brill0230622267</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Levinas&#8217;s Wartime Notebooks</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/11/levinass-wartime-notebooks/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/11/levinass-wartime-notebooks/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Feb 2010 13:44:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[literary studies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Levinas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[notebooks in Captivity]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=771</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Summer Reading- Levinas&#8217;s Wartime notebooks. From the brief excerpts in the review in this week&#8217;s Forward, it seems that the content is steps on the way to his “Existence and Existents.” It also shows the early interest of Levinas in &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/11/levinass-wartime-notebooks/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Summer Reading- Levinas&#8217;s Wartime notebooks. From the brief excerpts in the review in <a href="http://www.forward.com/articles/125385/">this week&#8217;s Forward,</a> it seems that the content is steps on the way to his  “Existence and Existents.” It also shows the early interest of Levinas in fiction and human nature. The short quotes seem to have a Nietzsche quality or a Thomas Mann pessimism. </p>
<p><em>The Obi-Wan Kenobi of 20th-century Jewish philosophy, Lithuanian-born French philosopher Emmanuel Levinas, has grown in fame and stature since his death in 1995. </p>
<p>This spring, a flood of admiring new books on Levinas will appear: “Levinas and the Cinema of Redemption” from Columbia University Press; “Other Others: Levinas, Literature, Transcultural Studies” from SUNY Press; “Levinasian Meditations” from Duquesne University Press; and “A Covenant of Creatures: Levinas’s Philosophy of Judaism” from Stanford University Press. </p>
<p>Yet none is as startlingly, indeed stunningly, revelatory as a new book… Levinas’s previously unpublished “Notebooks in Captivity” the first volume of a planned series of his complete writings.<br />
The notebooks were written mostly during the Second World War (some uncollected postwar jottings and essays are also included). Levinas, a French citizen since 1930, had served in the army, and after the Nazi victory he became a prisoner of war in various French camps and finally, from 1942 to 1945, at Stalag XI-B at Fallingbostel, Germany, near Bergen-Belsen… Levinas was assigned to one of the all-Jewish commandos, doing hard labor for long hours under brutal conditions. He mostly worked in harshly treated forestry brigades, </p>
<p> Fascinatingly, the notebooks reveal for the first time that Levinas long planned to write novels, even though these would remain unfinished, surviving in the form of outlines and fragmentary drafts. One, titled “Sad Opulence” (Triste Opulence) and later retitled “Eros,” tells the story of an army interpreter who becomes a prisoner of war. A second novel, “The Lady From Wepler’s” (“La Dame de Chez Wepler”), also set in wartime, is about a protagonist’s obsession with a prostitute glimpsed, but never approached, because of the “chasm which separates respect from sexuality.”<br />
Levinas notes: “Sexual love — the only one which may be fulfilled, in which caresses may culminate. Other loves (even filial or paternal) are impotent. Impotent because inexpressible, incapable of being fulfilled.”</p>
<p>Excerpts from Emmanuel Levinas’s nine small wartime notebooks:</p>
<p>Appearance of prisoners in Germany. Monastic or moral life. Even old men have something innocent and pure about them. </p>
<p>In the room with the little dormer window, men like clouds which hide the sun. </p>
<p>In Tolstoy the main thing is not truth about human nature but the emotion of someone who suddenly discovers all of life’s falseness, lying, complacency. </p>
<p>Winter sun, like a dead man’s kiss. </p>
<p>The only human perfection — beauty. Like a miraculous branch on a rotten tree trunk. The only miracle. </p>
<p>Tree — the most arrogant vertical of living nature. Its majesty — vertical majesty. </em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/11/levinass-wartime-notebooks/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Heschel&#8217;s Heavenly Torah- Lost in Translation</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/27/heschels-heavenly-torah-lost-in-translation/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/27/heschels-heavenly-torah-lost-in-translation/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 27 Jan 2010 19:44:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[aggadah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[a j heschel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[abraham Heschel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[alan brill]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gedalia Haber]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gordon Tucker]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Heavenly Torah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rabbi Akiva]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=658</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In the Fall issue of Modern Judaism 29/3 October 2009, there is a devastating review of Gordon Tucker’s translation of Heschel’s Heavenly Torah in which he claims the original meaning of Heschel is lost in translation. He seems to be &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/27/heschels-heavenly-torah-lost-in-translation/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the Fall issue of Modern Judaism 29/3 October 2009, there is a devastating review of Gordon Tucker’s translation of Heschel’s <em>Heavenly Torah</em> in which he claims the original meaning of Heschel is lost in translation. He seems to be bending over backwards not to be scathing,but his bottom line is that Tucker omitted paragraphs essential for arguments, manipulated the material to make Heschel seem like a pluralist, and even worse, he inserted his own pluralist editorial comments into the text of Heschel without any indication that these are not Heschel’s words.</p>
<p>Haber also claims that Heschel sought to determine a correct position in Aggadah, that he uses traditional phrases like &#8220;principles of faith,&#8221; that he often follows Rabbi Akiva and Tucker will present Heschel as following Rabbi Yishmael when he really was following Rabbi Akiva.. The worst is that in the crucial section on Maimonides position on Torah from Sinai, Tucker added his own explanation at the expanse of Heschel’s own words. Therefore, I must correct <a href="http://www.edah.org/backend/journalarticle/aggadic%20man%20brill-final.pdf">what I wrote in my own review of Heschel,</a> based on the English translation, that the discussion of Maimonides was “not theology or halakhic,” what I need to say is that Tucker’s additions are the problem.</p>
<blockquote><p><a href="http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/modern_judaism/summary/v029/29.3.haber.html">Lost In Translation: Abraham Joshua Heschel&#8217;s &#8220;Heavenly Torah&#8221;—A Review Essay-</a> Gedalia Haber</p>
<p>Although Heschel is aware of the plurality of opinions shared by the Sages, I found that he nevertheless strives to determine which opinion is correct, according to its compatibility with the simple meaning of the biblical text (<em>Peshuto shel Mikra</em>).However, when I compared certain words and phrases in Tucker&#8217;s translation to Heschel&#8217;s original text, to my surprise, I discovered that Heschel&#8217;s intent was often obscured or omitted entirely.</p>
<p>In the pages that follow I shall demonstrate a few basic differences between &#8220;my Heschel&#8221; and &#8220;Tucker&#8217;s Heschel.&#8221; … This juxtaposition will reveal critical areas where Heschel&#8217;s intent has been altered, and will retrieve &#8220;lost&#8221; ideas that were omitted or adapted in Tucker&#8217;s work. This will help to reconsider the question of Heschel&#8217;s views regarding religious pluralism and the diversity of opinions characteristic of Aggadah.</p>
<p>Heschel&#8217;s explicit parallel between Jewish law and Jewish thought is omitted in Tucker&#8217;s translation, and all that remains is the dichotomy between Halacha and matters beyond Halacha….Tucker does not translate this passage, although it seems that Heschel is stating a fundamental principle.</p>
<p>Tucker&#8217;s translation undermines Heschel&#8217;s certainty, and while it may render Heschel&#8217;s ambitious claim more digestible, at the same time it reverses Heschel&#8217;s opinion completely.</p>
<p>Another example of Heschel&#8217;s decisive attitude toward Aggadic material is his discussion of R. Akiva&#8217;s view regarding revelation. According to Heschel, R. Akiva claimed that Moses ascended to heaven in order to receive the Torah.<sup> </sup>Heschel claims that &#8220;this matter of the ascent of a mortal to heaven is very important in the <em>Torah of faith</em>. Judaism demands that man should acknowledge his place. A basic rule in Israel: &#8216;God is in heaven, and you are on earth&#8217; [. . .].</p>
<p>The phrase &#8220;Torah of faith&#8221; should be understood as the doctrine of faith, since the context is &#8220;Judaism&#8217;s demand&#8221; of man. However, Tucker subverts Heschel&#8217;s intention by transforming Heschel&#8217;s prescriptive, dogmatic style into a historical, descriptive one: &#8220;The theme of human ascent to heaven is of great importance in the <em>study of religion, but</em> Judaism demands that humans should know their place. Israel lives by the rule: &#8220;God is in heaven, and you are on earth.&#8221;<sup>4</sup></p>
<p>Heschel&#8217;s critique of Maimonides&#8217; view of Torah from Heaven is the climax of <em>TMS</em> II,… Although Tucker retains Heschel&#8217;s title (&#8220;Maimonides&#8217; Ruling&#8221;), he transforms Heschel&#8217;s discussion from a Halachic attack on Maimonides to a criticism of Maimonides&#8217; &#8220;perfectionist&#8221; attitude. Tucker&#8217;s version does read that &#8220;Maimonides came down on the more stringent side,&#8221; but Tucker adds an interjection which is not present in the original text: &#8220;Is such perfectionism possible?&#8221;.Tucker proceeds to omit the phrase &#8216;if the Halacha is established according to the Sifrei,&#8217; and shifts Heschel&#8217;s Halachic polemic to the realm of criticism of the high &#8220;standard&#8221; that Maimonides set for us.</p>
<p>I disagree with his claim that Heschel is promoting the more pluralistic exegesis of the Yishmaelian  School.</p>
<p>What is the meaning of Heschel&#8217;s critique? Alan Brill rightfully points out that in Heschel&#8217;s discussion of rabbinic sources in <em>TMS</em>, &#8220;there is no historical change or driving force to history.&#8221;<sup> </sup>Heschel holds an ahistorical conception of Jewish thought. Contrary to the view that Jewish thought and practice developed in certain directions, and what was once considered legitimate might be considered heretical today (and vice versa), Heschel claims that there is a unity between generations. However, this lenient or  liberal view is not pluralistic, and it does not leave room for Maimonides&#8217; &#8220;perfectionist attitude.&#8221; Heschel sees it as the objective truth, which demands submission.</p>
<p>Tucker comments on this that the &#8220;halachic pluralism&#8221; implied by the Talmud is a &#8220;long established fact,&#8221;…However, Heschel restricts this pluralism one paragraph later and states:</p>
<p>The Divine Voice declares: &#8220;These and these are [both] the words of the living God, but Halacha is established according to the school of Hillel.&#8221; Many students who have not studied sufficiently have regarded this saying according to the rule: &#8220;split the sentence&#8221;; they took its beginning and ignored its ending [. . .] as if the world were chaotic. As if permission had been granted for each person to build an altar for himself.</p>
<p>Moreover, is the power of every scholar equal to the power of Hillel and Shammai or R. Akiva and R. Yishmael? Is an innkeeper&#8217;s wife equal to wife of a priest? Does the trivial discussion of idlers compare to the complete Torah of the forefathers? Many scholars who have not studied sufficiently cannot be considered laymen anymore but did not reach the level of the great [rabbis]. &#8221;</p>
<p>These omissions and rewordings obscure what Heschel tried to convey and are barriers between Heschel&#8217;s thought and the English reader…However, as I have shown, Tucker eliminates fundamental passages and phrases without commenting on their absence. I believe the message they convey is no petty matter.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/27/heschels-heavenly-torah-lost-in-translation/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>5</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
