<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Meet an Evangelical Orthodox Rabbi-    Rabbi Daniel Cohen	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/09/meet-an-evangelical-orthodox-rabbi-rabbi-daniel-cohen/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/09/meet-an-evangelical-orthodox-rabbi-rabbi-daniel-cohen/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Aug 2010 21:30:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Kevin Rothman		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/09/meet-an-evangelical-orthodox-rabbi-rabbi-daniel-cohen/#comment-1469</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kevin Rothman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 12 Aug 2010 21:30:51 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1805#comment-1469</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[If what you describe is truly how a segment of orthodoxy was when you were younger then I envy you because the whole of my experience has been with a community unreservedly aligned with the right... and the limbaugh-right at that.  I have a few friends who view things otherwise (radically so) but I could never describe us as a &quot;scene&quot;.  I would, however, point out that the &quot;chullent crowd in manhattan strikes me as highly promising for the future.  (btw. behaviorism is not as mindless as it is portrayed as.  while I do not personally like skinner&#039;s views or agree with them in the larger sense, he makes some salient points in his writings - he even goes so far as to say that it is manifestly unethical not to train children in an organized manner ... which I cannot help but recognize some wisdom in .... even caputo (follower of derrida) ultimately returns to an ethics of phronesis which, in the end, is simply a matter of education and acculturation... i.e. implicit behavioral training - though I am sure caputo would cringe at this.)]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If what you describe is truly how a segment of orthodoxy was when you were younger then I envy you because the whole of my experience has been with a community unreservedly aligned with the right&#8230; and the limbaugh-right at that.  I have a few friends who view things otherwise (radically so) but I could never describe us as a &#8220;scene&#8221;.  I would, however, point out that the &#8220;chullent crowd in manhattan strikes me as highly promising for the future.  (btw. behaviorism is not as mindless as it is portrayed as.  while I do not personally like skinner&#8217;s views or agree with them in the larger sense, he makes some salient points in his writings &#8211; he even goes so far as to say that it is manifestly unethical not to train children in an organized manner &#8230; which I cannot help but recognize some wisdom in &#8230;. even caputo (follower of derrida) ultimately returns to an ethics of phronesis which, in the end, is simply a matter of education and acculturation&#8230; i.e. implicit behavioral training &#8211; though I am sure caputo would cringe at this.)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/09/meet-an-evangelical-orthodox-rabbi-rabbi-daniel-cohen/#comment-1468</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 12 Aug 2010 16:40:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1805#comment-1468</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When I was young it was considered inconceivable that evangelicals would have anything  worth emulating. It’s true evangelicals have changed, but the Jews have changed even more. In my twenties I indentified with  what was called the Partisan Review crowd and later the NY Jewish Intellectuals. Today none of this is left or what’s left is scattered, under pressure and on the periphery of Jewish life. These Jewish intellectuals promoted an intellectual type of the Bohemian style,especially a life devoted to  high serious literature especially new difficult books. They valued Freudian psychoanalysis as an intrinsic part of life, were liberal to radical  in their politics,  and engaged in advanced cultural criticism. Has anyone seen one single serious novel reviewed on any of the Orthodox websites? Psychoanalysis is gone, to be replaced by books on self esteem and behavioral therapies. (See Daphne Merkin’s eloquent eulogy in this Sunday’s Times.) Seventy percent of Orthodox Jews voted for Bush and are chasidim of Fox News. In Israel the left has effectively gone underground. The cultural criticisms of our time are now used as a mark of Cain….why that’s post modernism, poo poo. I didn’t grow up in a  world where intelligent Orthodox Jews are happy to embrace Evangelical themes, and frankly I am horrified to see how it’s playing out.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When I was young it was considered inconceivable that evangelicals would have anything  worth emulating. It’s true evangelicals have changed, but the Jews have changed even more. In my twenties I indentified with  what was called the Partisan Review crowd and later the NY Jewish Intellectuals. Today none of this is left or what’s left is scattered, under pressure and on the periphery of Jewish life. These Jewish intellectuals promoted an intellectual type of the Bohemian style,especially a life devoted to  high serious literature especially new difficult books. They valued Freudian psychoanalysis as an intrinsic part of life, were liberal to radical  in their politics,  and engaged in advanced cultural criticism. Has anyone seen one single serious novel reviewed on any of the Orthodox websites? Psychoanalysis is gone, to be replaced by books on self esteem and behavioral therapies. (See Daphne Merkin’s eloquent eulogy in this Sunday’s Times.) Seventy percent of Orthodox Jews voted for Bush and are chasidim of Fox News. In Israel the left has effectively gone underground. The cultural criticisms of our time are now used as a mark of Cain….why that’s post modernism, poo poo. I didn’t grow up in a  world where intelligent Orthodox Jews are happy to embrace Evangelical themes, and frankly I am horrified to see how it’s playing out.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Kevin Rothman		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/09/meet-an-evangelical-orthodox-rabbi-rabbi-daniel-cohen/#comment-1467</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kevin Rothman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 12 Aug 2010 10:48:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1805#comment-1467</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[peak moments, better you, a million truths in your heart, decisive moments... 

these are in the rebbe&#039;s work in a way, but the difference is that ultimately they play into a larger dialectic pointing to a life of service and self sacrifice.  The question is never &quot;your values&quot; but always &quot;your obligations&quot;.  For the rebbe, i think, these are all moments not of individualistic awakening, but of realizing the metaphysical construct that already commands towards others.

this is to say that the messianic fervor, despite its other theological difficulties, at least points away from the possibility of complacency.  From man&#039;s perspective it can never be satisfied b/c he can demand the messiah but never actually make the decision that is G-d&#039;s alone.  The sorts of evangelical ideas discussed above can, in the end, be completed: &quot;well, yes, I have now thought about my values&quot;, &quot;I am now listening to the truths of my heart&quot;.   They terminate in myself and serve myself (i.e. - while &quot;my values&quot; may pertain to others, the search for &quot;my values&quot; is a search for me, to fulfill myself and my own wish to know &quot;my values&quot;... and once I do I can feel safe and assured in myself)]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>peak moments, better you, a million truths in your heart, decisive moments&#8230; </p>
<p>these are in the rebbe&#8217;s work in a way, but the difference is that ultimately they play into a larger dialectic pointing to a life of service and self sacrifice.  The question is never &#8220;your values&#8221; but always &#8220;your obligations&#8221;.  For the rebbe, i think, these are all moments not of individualistic awakening, but of realizing the metaphysical construct that already commands towards others.</p>
<p>this is to say that the messianic fervor, despite its other theological difficulties, at least points away from the possibility of complacency.  From man&#8217;s perspective it can never be satisfied b/c he can demand the messiah but never actually make the decision that is G-d&#8217;s alone.  The sorts of evangelical ideas discussed above can, in the end, be completed: &#8220;well, yes, I have now thought about my values&#8221;, &#8220;I am now listening to the truths of my heart&#8221;.   They terminate in myself and serve myself (i.e. &#8211; while &#8220;my values&#8221; may pertain to others, the search for &#8220;my values&#8221; is a search for me, to fulfill myself and my own wish to know &#8220;my values&#8221;&#8230; and once I do I can feel safe and assured in myself)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/09/meet-an-evangelical-orthodox-rabbi-rabbi-daniel-cohen/#comment-1463</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2010 21:08:54 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1805#comment-1463</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/09/meet-an-evangelical-orthodox-rabbi-rabbi-daniel-cohen/#comment-1458&quot;&gt;AS&lt;/a&gt;.

AS-
have you read Andrew Heinze&#039;s book on the topic? He connects as mussar Salanter, Freud, Dear Abby, and Abraham Twerski.  In all of the cases- they operate on a id-superego axis. How do we deal with our yetzar hara? When is food and sex good? This purpose driven life is on an inner voice trajectory as discussed in Ann Taves, Fits, Trances,and Visions.
The Self-actulaization idea is Carl Rogers- and it includes individuality, creativity, returning to one&#039;s natural needs,  complete freedom, and seize the moment.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/09/meet-an-evangelical-orthodox-rabbi-rabbi-daniel-cohen/#comment-1458">AS</a>.</p>
<p>AS-<br />
have you read Andrew Heinze&#8217;s book on the topic? He connects as mussar Salanter, Freud, Dear Abby, and Abraham Twerski.  In all of the cases- they operate on a id-superego axis. How do we deal with our yetzar hara? When is food and sex good? This purpose driven life is on an inner voice trajectory as discussed in Ann Taves, Fits, Trances,and Visions.<br />
The Self-actulaization idea is Carl Rogers- and it includes individuality, creativity, returning to one&#8217;s natural needs,  complete freedom, and seize the moment.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/09/meet-an-evangelical-orthodox-rabbi-rabbi-daniel-cohen/#comment-1462</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2010 19:10:11 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1805#comment-1462</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/09/meet-an-evangelical-orthodox-rabbi-rabbi-daniel-cohen/#comment-1461&quot;&gt;nachum&lt;/a&gt;.

Peak moments of connection are not the same as peak moments of decision or truth. The former is modified devekus the later is hearing an inner voice about ones own life.
The Rebbe stating that a Jewish home is about loyalty, dedication, and commitment is a convergence with Rav Hirsch. Here it was the preacher&#039;s &quot;have you ever asked yourself about your values?&quot; Do you commit to a purpose in life?
I thought through as I was listening to the talk- why it is not chabad. The Rebbe would be 10 ways to connect, 10 way for a miraculous marriage. Here it is 40 ways to a better you, not 40 ways to connect.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/09/meet-an-evangelical-orthodox-rabbi-rabbi-daniel-cohen/#comment-1461">nachum</a>.</p>
<p>Peak moments of connection are not the same as peak moments of decision or truth. The former is modified devekus the later is hearing an inner voice about ones own life.<br />
The Rebbe stating that a Jewish home is about loyalty, dedication, and commitment is a convergence with Rav Hirsch. Here it was the preacher&#8217;s &#8220;have you ever asked yourself about your values?&#8221; Do you commit to a purpose in life?<br />
I thought through as I was listening to the talk- why it is not chabad. The Rebbe would be 10 ways to connect, 10 way for a miraculous marriage. Here it is 40 ways to a better you, not 40 ways to connect.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: nachum		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/09/meet-an-evangelical-orthodox-rabbi-rabbi-daniel-cohen/#comment-1461</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[nachum]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2010 19:02:03 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1805#comment-1461</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Don&#039;t some of these themes appear in Jewish sources from early in the 20th century? The emphasis on peak moments of connection and the importance of family and home in religious life appeared regularly in the talks of of the Lubavitcher Rebbe.  While R. Cohen readily acknowledged the influence evangelical works had on him, perhaps they appear in the Rebbe&#039;s talks more as a result of convergence than any direct influence.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Don&#8217;t some of these themes appear in Jewish sources from early in the 20th century? The emphasis on peak moments of connection and the importance of family and home in religious life appeared regularly in the talks of of the Lubavitcher Rebbe.  While R. Cohen readily acknowledged the influence evangelical works had on him, perhaps they appear in the Rebbe&#8217;s talks more as a result of convergence than any direct influence.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: avraham rosenblum		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/09/meet-an-evangelical-orthodox-rabbi-rabbi-daniel-cohen/#comment-1459</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[avraham rosenblum]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2010 14:42:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1805#comment-1459</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The problem is that there seems to be energy in Orthodox Judaism that saps up creative energy.  I mean that you just don’t find a lot of new ideas among orthodox Jews. It almost seems to be a business to look for ideas among gentiles and then to write a book a market it among Jews as original Jewish thought while depending on the fact that if anyone discovers the goyish book it will be attributed to the subsequent Jewish author. I have seen a book about positive thinking exactly along those lines in Israel. Often I have tried to point this out and the reaction is always the gentiles got it from us.
(I do however except from this critique a few creative Jewish thinkers--the Arizal, Rebbi Nachman the Rambam and the Talmud--all who I consider creative, original and very powerful.)Let me just add that I know the that Rebbi Nachman and the Talmud and Rambam and the Arizal all borrow concepts-- but the system that they create is original and fresh and independent.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The problem is that there seems to be energy in Orthodox Judaism that saps up creative energy.  I mean that you just don’t find a lot of new ideas among orthodox Jews. It almost seems to be a business to look for ideas among gentiles and then to write a book a market it among Jews as original Jewish thought while depending on the fact that if anyone discovers the goyish book it will be attributed to the subsequent Jewish author. I have seen a book about positive thinking exactly along those lines in Israel. Often I have tried to point this out and the reaction is always the gentiles got it from us.<br />
(I do however except from this critique a few creative Jewish thinkers&#8211;the Arizal, Rebbi Nachman the Rambam and the Talmud&#8211;all who I consider creative, original and very powerful.)Let me just add that I know the that Rebbi Nachman and the Talmud and Rambam and the Arizal all borrow concepts&#8211; but the system that they create is original and fresh and independent.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/09/meet-an-evangelical-orthodox-rabbi-rabbi-daniel-cohen/#comment-1458</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2010 14:18:05 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1805#comment-1458</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Do you see this as a continuation of late 20th century mussar texts which were already appropriating modern self-help concepts? Is the chiddush that is has moved from text to congregational rabbis? Or is there a greater discontinuity from those earlier works?

Also, can you offer a brief history of the idea of &quot;self-actualization&quot; in Judaism? It seems to entail a particular understanding of the concept of &#039;self&#039; involved but I can&#039;t readily put my finger on why it always strikes me as out of place.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Do you see this as a continuation of late 20th century mussar texts which were already appropriating modern self-help concepts? Is the chiddush that is has moved from text to congregational rabbis? Or is there a greater discontinuity from those earlier works?</p>
<p>Also, can you offer a brief history of the idea of &#8220;self-actualization&#8221; in Judaism? It seems to entail a particular understanding of the concept of &#8216;self&#8217; involved but I can&#8217;t readily put my finger on why it always strikes me as out of place.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/09/meet-an-evangelical-orthodox-rabbi-rabbi-daniel-cohen/#comment-1457</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2010 14:11:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1805#comment-1457</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Yaakov, I assume he is completely sincere and assumes this is Torah, especially Hasidut. In this he is not different than Abraham Twerski. He is just telling over what he sees in Judaism. 
Moshe- I like to work in particulars, so when I get a chance to sit in a kiruv session then I will give it a details. Or if I deal with a book on the topic.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yaakov, I assume he is completely sincere and assumes this is Torah, especially Hasidut. In this he is not different than Abraham Twerski. He is just telling over what he sees in Judaism.<br />
Moshe- I like to work in particulars, so when I get a chance to sit in a kiruv session then I will give it a details. Or if I deal with a book on the topic.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Rabbi Yaakov Feldman		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/09/meet-an-evangelical-orthodox-rabbi-rabbi-daniel-cohen/#comment-1456</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rabbi Yaakov Feldman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2010 12:24:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1805#comment-1456</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In the early 80&#039;s I would use devices, insights, etc. from a certain buisness book entitled &quot;In Search of Excellence&quot; and also draw upon Dale Carnegie and others of that sort. The trick was to adapt their energy, drive, organizational insights, self-actualization skills and the like and adapt it to Torah. It was challenging but it alowed for fresh insight and ocassional brilliant revelation. The above rabbis&#039; usage of out-and-out religious texts like the ones cited in your piece, seems disingenuous.
At bottom my advice is, read inspired, acknowledge truth from whomever, and dive back into your own rich tradition.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the early 80&#8217;s I would use devices, insights, etc. from a certain buisness book entitled &#8220;In Search of Excellence&#8221; and also draw upon Dale Carnegie and others of that sort. The trick was to adapt their energy, drive, organizational insights, self-actualization skills and the like and adapt it to Torah. It was challenging but it alowed for fresh insight and ocassional brilliant revelation. The above rabbis&#8217; usage of out-and-out religious texts like the ones cited in your piece, seems disingenuous.<br />
At bottom my advice is, read inspired, acknowledge truth from whomever, and dive back into your own rich tradition.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: moshe shoshan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/09/meet-an-evangelical-orthodox-rabbi-rabbi-daniel-cohen/#comment-1455</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[moshe shoshan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2010 10:10:03 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1805#comment-1455</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&quot;the widespread use of Pentecostal materials found in kiruv organizations.&quot;
could you elaborate on this?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&#8220;the widespread use of Pentecostal materials found in kiruv organizations.&#8221;<br />
could you elaborate on this?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Melbournite		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/09/meet-an-evangelical-orthodox-rabbi-rabbi-daniel-cohen/#comment-1454</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Melbournite]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2010 08:39:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1805#comment-1454</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Setting aside the content,  I heard the style of call response many years ago in an Eydut Hamizrach minyan in Jerusalem from a local Rabbi.

I am interested in the way presentation comes from elsewhere perhaps without thought?

Some of the Braslav speakers ( forgoten the names ) are definetly Southern Baptist to my ears.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Setting aside the content,  I heard the style of call response many years ago in an Eydut Hamizrach minyan in Jerusalem from a local Rabbi.</p>
<p>I am interested in the way presentation comes from elsewhere perhaps without thought?</p>
<p>Some of the Braslav speakers ( forgoten the names ) are definetly Southern Baptist to my ears.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Pierre		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/09/meet-an-evangelical-orthodox-rabbi-rabbi-daniel-cohen/#comment-1451</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pierre]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2010 02:16:33 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1805#comment-1451</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Next will come &quot;prayer strategies&quot; and &quot;gospel&quot;-singing from AME churches...Halavi on the later!...This is just the sort of analysis I follow your blog for, now I return to the second reading, as is my custom.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Next will come &#8220;prayer strategies&#8221; and &#8220;gospel&#8221;-singing from AME churches&#8230;Halavi on the later!&#8230;This is just the sort of analysis I follow your blog for, now I return to the second reading, as is my custom.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
