<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Rav Kook on religion and other religions- from the new book	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/09/rav-kook-on-religion-and-other-religions-from-the-new-book/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/09/rav-kook-on-religion-and-other-religions-from-the-new-book/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Aug 2010 00:50:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Kevin Rothman		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/09/rav-kook-on-religion-and-other-religions-from-the-new-book/#comment-1478</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kevin Rothman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 19 Aug 2010 00:50:50 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1797#comment-1478</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[i think it is more complex than that.  all knowledge is cumulative - whether in jewish thought or outside of it.  hegel built on the framworks established by kant, by fitche, by schelling... though he retained some and rejected some, he could not have done what he did without what came before.  why is this not valid for jewish thinkers as well?  why cant kook find something in hegel and adapt it and have this be regarded as valid.... after all, the very fact that he validated the PRESENT importance of other religious traditions is, itself, a significant departure from hegel, who regarded all religions prior to protestantism as belonging to the past, as being fundamentally anachronistic (read: &quot;should just go away&quot;).  so kook took someone else&#039;s ideas and built on them like any other thinker.  the same goes for maimonides and the talmud and r. nahman, all of whom/which you have mentioned before as &quot;original&quot; - but they too draw on other sources and adapt them.  a truly original thought would be a thought that is fundamentally irrelevant to human society, it would hardly count as a thought, because it would not at all relate to the amalgam of thoughts of which society is constituted.

this is not to say that kook’s theology works for me, it doesnt, but I also dont think it means his methods were invalid]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>i think it is more complex than that.  all knowledge is cumulative &#8211; whether in jewish thought or outside of it.  hegel built on the framworks established by kant, by fitche, by schelling&#8230; though he retained some and rejected some, he could not have done what he did without what came before.  why is this not valid for jewish thinkers as well?  why cant kook find something in hegel and adapt it and have this be regarded as valid&#8230;. after all, the very fact that he validated the PRESENT importance of other religious traditions is, itself, a significant departure from hegel, who regarded all religions prior to protestantism as belonging to the past, as being fundamentally anachronistic (read: &#8220;should just go away&#8221;).  so kook took someone else&#8217;s ideas and built on them like any other thinker.  the same goes for maimonides and the talmud and r. nahman, all of whom/which you have mentioned before as &#8220;original&#8221; &#8211; but they too draw on other sources and adapt them.  a truly original thought would be a thought that is fundamentally irrelevant to human society, it would hardly count as a thought, because it would not at all relate to the amalgam of thoughts of which society is constituted.</p>
<p>this is not to say that kook’s theology works for me, it doesnt, but I also dont think it means his methods were invalid</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: avraham rosenblum		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/09/rav-kook-on-religion-and-other-religions-from-the-new-book/#comment-1477</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[avraham rosenblum]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 18 Aug 2010 17:31:36 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1797#comment-1477</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[So what is the deep thought people claim for rav kook? That he could read Hegel and every time he found something positive about Christianity in Hegel he changed the word to &quot;Judaism&quot;? It sound like the general marketing cam common today that people find good ideas in goyish books and then write up the ideas in Hebrew and market the book as original Jewish thought. Is this how hard up we are for original thinkers?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>So what is the deep thought people claim for rav kook? That he could read Hegel and every time he found something positive about Christianity in Hegel he changed the word to &#8220;Judaism&#8221;? It sound like the general marketing cam common today that people find good ideas in goyish books and then write up the ideas in Hebrew and market the book as original Jewish thought. Is this how hard up we are for original thinkers?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Itzchak		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/09/rav-kook-on-religion-and-other-religions-from-the-new-book/#comment-1449</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Itzchak]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 09 Aug 2010 12:35:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1797#comment-1449</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[כל הכבוד
keep it coming....

this may be of interest to you -in honor of Rav Kook&#039;s TZ&#039;L 75th Yaartzeit in a few days (Elul 3) :
www.myspace.orotharav

http://www.tikkun.org/article.php?story=july2010marmorstein
]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>כל הכבוד<br />
keep it coming&#8230;.</p>
<p>this may be of interest to you -in honor of Rav Kook&#8217;s TZ&#8217;L 75th Yaartzeit in a few days (Elul 3) :<br />
<a href="http://www.myspace.orotharav" rel="nofollow ugc">http://www.myspace.orotharav</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.tikkun.org/article.php?story=july2010marmorstein" rel="nofollow ugc">http://www.tikkun.org/article.php?story=july2010marmorstein</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
