<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>civil relgion &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/tag/civil-relgion/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Jan 2010 02:20:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='kavvanah.wordpress.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/c9f111237f93750b6b994fc5185d49c3?s=96&#038;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>civil relgion &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>What is the Civil Religion of the Orthodox? Models of Relgion and Society</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/12/what-is-the-civil-relgion-of-the-orthodox-models-of-relgion-and-society/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/12/what-is-the-civil-relgion-of-the-orthodox-models-of-relgion-and-society/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2010 18:57:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[sociology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[civil relgion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immanent frame]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Philip Gorski]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=533</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Philip Gorski, Professor at Yale offers three attitudes at the immanent frame toward the relationship of religion and state in America. Liberal secularists believe that the religious and political spheres should be radically separated; religious nationalists believe that they should &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/12/what-is-the-civil-relgion-of-the-orthodox-models-of-relgion-and-society/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://blogs.ssrc.org/tif/2010/01/08/a-neo-weberian-theory-of-american-civil-religion/">Philip Gorski, Professor at Yale offers three attitudes at the immanent frame</a> toward the relationship of religion and state in America.</p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Liberal secularists</strong> believe that the religious and political spheres should be radically separated; <strong>religious nationalist</strong>s believe that they should be tightly integrated; and <strong>civil religionists</strong> believe that they should be overlapping but independent.<br />
The governing metaphor of <strong>religious nationalism</strong> in the United States is blood: blood as in blood sacrifice on the battlefield, and blood as in the blood purity of the nation. The deep roots of this tradition are to be found in the bloody wars and priestly sacrifices portrayed in the Hebrew Bible.</p>
<p>The governing metaphor of <strong>liberal secularism </strong>is autonomy: autonomy as in individual choice and institutional separation. The deep roots of this tradition are to be found in the atomistic and anti-religious creed of the Epicureans. Faint echoes of it can be found in, say, the writings of Thomas Jefferson.. Its most complete—and virulent—expressions today are Randian libertarianism on the right and soft-Nietzschean post-modernism on the left.</p>
<p>The governing metaphor of <strong>civil religion,</strong> finally, is covenant: covenant as in collective commitment to a set of sacred principles and collective responsibility for their realization. The deep roots of this tradition are to be found in the Biblical covenants between the Ancient Israelites and their God. Its more immediate roots can be traced to the New England Puritans</p>
<p>For the <strong>religious nationalist</strong>, America is a “Christian nation” or, perhaps, a “Judeo-Christian nation.” In this vision, religious and political communities should be coterminous.</p>
<p>For the <strong>radical secularist,</strong> America is a liberal society comprised of autonomous individuals. In this vision, religious and political communities ought to be completely distinct.</p>
<p>For the <strong>civil religionist,</strong> finally, America is a moral community that seeks to balance solidarity and pluralism. In this vision, the religious and political communities inevitably overlap with one another.</p></blockquote>
<p><strong></strong><strong>Now how would this apply to the Orthodox community? They seem to use the religious nationalism model when dealing with Israeli society. But it seems that the majority of Centrist Orthodoxy follows liberal secularism in America. Why? They keep their religion and their Americanism bifurcated. Yet, there are selected groups and rabbis in the community that do accept civil religion. But which? On the other hand, some parts are beginning to identify with American religious nationalism and identify with Republican or Christian right values.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Can we conceptualize the community not as right and left but based on which of these three models they follow? </strong>Or to keep things closer to the way people think now- which model does Open Orthodoxy follow? (The latter may be a much harder question than it looks.) Which does the yeshivah world follow?  How about a supporter of AIPAC? Which does Chabad follow? Which does Aish Hatorah follow taking into account their production of the movie “Obsession” on their view of terrorism? Or do the  various blogs follow? And in these distinctions, one’s age and generation does matter and will change the results. <strong>Among orthodoxy, who is a libertarian, who a covnant thinker of values, and who a nationalist? Does it change the conception of orthodoxy?</strong></p>
<p>The religion of the 1950’s was a Judeo-Christian covenant. At the end of the 1970’s Robert Bellah reoriented everyone and said civil religion was empty. “Writing amidst the collective funk of the mid-1970s, Bellah famously concluded that the American civil religion was an empty and broken shell” And it led many clergy to preach that one must turn to religion to reclaim society. Without religion one has the vacuous worship of the self. <strong>What does it mean when rabbis in 2009 are still saying that religion will save you from “Sheilaism”?</strong></p>
<p>When Rav Soloveitchik writes in Confrontation that “it is quite legitimate to speak of a Judeo-Christian tradition…However, when we shift the focus from the dimension of culture to that of faith… the whole idea of a tradition of faiths and the continuum of revealed doctrines…is utterly absurd…” In the 1950’s he seems to follow the civil religion model? But does Lonley Man of Faith agree? Which of the three is he associated with now?<br />
I was asked in the comments on an earlier post: How does all this evangelicalism relate to the thinking of thinkers like Taylor and Habermas. Gorski offer an answer:</p>
<blockquote><p>.Now, there are plenty of people… who would disagree that civil religion is a necessary means to this end. First, there are non-theistic neo-Kantian rationalists—such as Rawls, Habermas, and Audi—who would be somewhat uneasy about the religious dimension of civil religion. Then, there are theistic neo-Aristotelian confessionalists—such as MacIntyre, Yoder, and Hauerwas—who would be somewhat uneasy about the civil dimension of civil religion. But each critique supplies an answer to the other.</p></blockquote>
<p><strong>Among Orthodox, are they more worried about the civil or the religion in American civil religion?</strong></p>
<p>Copyright © 2010 Alan Brill · All Rights Reserved</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/12/what-is-the-civil-relgion-of-the-orthodox-models-of-relgion-and-society/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
