<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Yehuda Brandes- Judaism and Human Rights	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/12/11/yehuda-brandes-judaism-and-human-rights/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/12/11/yehuda-brandes-judaism-and-human-rights/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2013 07:42:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Seth (Avi) Kadish		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/12/11/yehuda-brandes-judaism-and-human-rights/#comment-9443</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Seth (Avi) Kadish]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2013 07:42:20 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6434#comment-9443</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&quot;How do the Torah and Halakhah deal with the tension between these two tracks or two opposing systems for living? The fundamental axiom is that we are not dealing with tension and contradiction between the Torah and some external and alien culture, but with an internal tension that stems from the existence of two principles that coexist within the Torah itself.&quot;

I hope to argue in the non-so-distant future that a slight variation on this might be more true: It is indeed an internal tension within the Torah itself, but within a *single* principle, not two different principles. To put it more simply, Kedushat Yisrael, along with everything that Brandes correctly and persuasively says that it implies, derives in and of itself from Zelem Elohim.

How so? If we may take Zelem Elohim to mean that both God and human beings are personalities, as for instance Jonathan Sacks does in his recent book (beyond this accessible example I won&#039;t get into the range of scholarship here), then it is personal &quot;right brain&quot; relationships that religion calls for. The marriage or covenant between God and Israel is thus a fulfillment of Zelem Elohim, but that special relationship has unique ramifications. Because of this marriage, idolatry becomes a form of adultery and betrayel; a firm and hard stance against idolatry and idolators and anything else which might sway Israel from its loyalty becomes mandatory; laws are formulated for a particularist context within the relationship. But it is still because Zelem Elohim itself has been fulfilled in a unique way within this particular relationship.

In other words, Zelem Elohim is the fundamental value not just for the universal, but even for the particular.

Shabbat Shalom]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&#8220;How do the Torah and Halakhah deal with the tension between these two tracks or two opposing systems for living? The fundamental axiom is that we are not dealing with tension and contradiction between the Torah and some external and alien culture, but with an internal tension that stems from the existence of two principles that coexist within the Torah itself.&#8221;</p>
<p>I hope to argue in the non-so-distant future that a slight variation on this might be more true: It is indeed an internal tension within the Torah itself, but within a *single* principle, not two different principles. To put it more simply, Kedushat Yisrael, along with everything that Brandes correctly and persuasively says that it implies, derives in and of itself from Zelem Elohim.</p>
<p>How so? If we may take Zelem Elohim to mean that both God and human beings are personalities, as for instance Jonathan Sacks does in his recent book (beyond this accessible example I won&#8217;t get into the range of scholarship here), then it is personal &#8220;right brain&#8221; relationships that religion calls for. The marriage or covenant between God and Israel is thus a fulfillment of Zelem Elohim, but that special relationship has unique ramifications. Because of this marriage, idolatry becomes a form of adultery and betrayel; a firm and hard stance against idolatry and idolators and anything else which might sway Israel from its loyalty becomes mandatory; laws are formulated for a particularist context within the relationship. But it is still because Zelem Elohim itself has been fulfilled in a unique way within this particular relationship.</p>
<p>In other words, Zelem Elohim is the fundamental value not just for the universal, but even for the particular.</p>
<p>Shabbat Shalom</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: amar		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/12/11/yehuda-brandes-judaism-and-human-rights/#comment-9306</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[amar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2013 07:39:26 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6434#comment-9306</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Well, Levinas was deeply anti-sionist and Manitou a deeply extrem-rightist.

I don&#039;t think it is a possible to join two extrems.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Well, Levinas was deeply anti-sionist and Manitou a deeply extrem-rightist.</p>
<p>I don&#8217;t think it is a possible to join two extrems.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/12/11/yehuda-brandes-judaism-and-human-rights/#comment-9304</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2013 03:44:39 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6434#comment-9304</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I have always thought that unlike teleological systems, Torah defines right and wrong independently of values, ideals and the highest good. We have a halachic literature dealing with obligations and duties, what is permitted and forbidden, and a “Musar” literature that discusses the good, the virtues and paths necessary to achieve higher levels of spirituality. A classic example might be the Mesilas Yesharim. There is no reason to expect the 613 mitzvot to line up with some value we otherwise accept, nor is there any reason to expect a minority opinion or voice  in the Talmud corresponding to the values we may have acquired at any given historical period.  There appears to be a certain pluralism and historicism in the ideas surrounding the good, whereas in the theory of the right  and wrong the goal is to specify in casuistic detail the objective halacha applicable to everyone, independent of time and place.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have always thought that unlike teleological systems, Torah defines right and wrong independently of values, ideals and the highest good. We have a halachic literature dealing with obligations and duties, what is permitted and forbidden, and a “Musar” literature that discusses the good, the virtues and paths necessary to achieve higher levels of spirituality. A classic example might be the Mesilas Yesharim. There is no reason to expect the 613 mitzvot to line up with some value we otherwise accept, nor is there any reason to expect a minority opinion or voice  in the Talmud corresponding to the values we may have acquired at any given historical period.  There appears to be a certain pluralism and historicism in the ideas surrounding the good, whereas in the theory of the right  and wrong the goal is to specify in casuistic detail the objective halacha applicable to everyone, independent of time and place.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: TK		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/12/11/yehuda-brandes-judaism-and-human-rights/#comment-9302</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[TK]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2013 19:31:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6434#comment-9302</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Whereas it is all nice and well to conclude that &quot;universal humanistic values are part and parcel of authentic and original Jewish thought and Halakhah&quot;, we should be under no illusion that the feeling is reciprocated. 

While Jewish morality hits on a number of moral value themes including liberty vs oppression which is essential to current &quot;humanistic values&quot;, it also includes Sanctity vs. Degradation, Authority vs Subversion&quot; and others [using the terminology of Prof. J. Haidt]. 
The tension we are experiencing in our age is that current &quot;humanistic values&quot; ignores, denigrates and ultimately excludes any moral value that does not fit in its paradigm.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Whereas it is all nice and well to conclude that &#8220;universal humanistic values are part and parcel of authentic and original Jewish thought and Halakhah&#8221;, we should be under no illusion that the feeling is reciprocated. </p>
<p>While Jewish morality hits on a number of moral value themes including liberty vs oppression which is essential to current &#8220;humanistic values&#8221;, it also includes Sanctity vs. Degradation, Authority vs Subversion&#8221; and others [using the terminology of Prof. J. Haidt].<br />
The tension we are experiencing in our age is that current &#8220;humanistic values&#8221; ignores, denigrates and ultimately excludes any moral value that does not fit in its paradigm.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Jeff Eyges		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/12/11/yehuda-brandes-judaism-and-human-rights/#comment-9301</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jeff Eyges]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2013 17:46:57 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6434#comment-9301</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&lt;i&gt;Yet, Brandes is against the concept of meta-halakhah (as used by many including Eliezer Goldman, Walter Wurzburger, or Isidore Twersky) where an outside theology not part of the halakhah, such as philosophy, kabbalah or humanism, influence the worldview of the rabbi.&lt;/i&gt;

Interestingly (well, to me), David Hartman uses this term to describe the approach of Rav solovietchik, in defining a halakhah outside of spacetime and therefore not subject to the vagaries of human experience. In so doing, Hartman asserts the Rav laid the foundation for the Haredi takeover of Orthodoxy.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><i>Yet, Brandes is against the concept of meta-halakhah (as used by many including Eliezer Goldman, Walter Wurzburger, or Isidore Twersky) where an outside theology not part of the halakhah, such as philosophy, kabbalah or humanism, influence the worldview of the rabbi.</i></p>
<p>Interestingly (well, to me), David Hartman uses this term to describe the approach of Rav solovietchik, in defining a halakhah outside of spacetime and therefore not subject to the vagaries of human experience. In so doing, Hartman asserts the Rav laid the foundation for the Haredi takeover of Orthodoxy.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
