<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Foreclosure in Teaneck	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/01/foreclosure-in-teaneck/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/01/foreclosure-in-teaneck/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2010 15:28:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Yonatan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/01/foreclosure-in-teaneck/#comment-856</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Yonatan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2010 15:28:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1055#comment-856</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[On the topic of stay-at-home mothers:

Around six years ago the OU reprinted an article in Shabbat Shalom where a women defended her decision to stay home with her kids. the article generated a significant amount of criticism including an article in The Forward. 

Of course for every Mother (stay-at-home or working) its a loaded issue.  

From a sociological perspective, Chareidim are more in line with the Evangelicals on this point.

Additionally, having a wife/mother with a significant career usually means having fewer children.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>On the topic of stay-at-home mothers:</p>
<p>Around six years ago the OU reprinted an article in Shabbat Shalom where a women defended her decision to stay home with her kids. the article generated a significant amount of criticism including an article in The Forward. </p>
<p>Of course for every Mother (stay-at-home or working) its a loaded issue.  </p>
<p>From a sociological perspective, Chareidim are more in line with the Evangelicals on this point.</p>
<p>Additionally, having a wife/mother with a significant career usually means having fewer children.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Mark		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/01/foreclosure-in-teaneck/#comment-795</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mark]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2010 22:29:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1055#comment-795</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Ben Atlas - &lt;i&gt;In fact it was common in the 80s to pay several hundred dollars a month for the home phone.&lt;/i&gt;

You must be kidding! In our house, we had a timer next to our phone and were very careful not to allow international calls (or even out-of-state) calls to go on for too long. If I recall correctly, our phone bill was usually about $70-80 a month, and perhaps $120 in a month where a family member might have been traveling overseas.

Of course, you brought up an excellent point about tzedaka and why it isn&#039;t as forthcoming as it should be. Perhaps many people aren&#039;t interested in paying the few hundred dollar a month phone bill for people who are out of work but refuse to give up their dual iPhones (husband and wife), their other 3 phones for the kids, and the family plan with unlimited data for mom and dad, and unlimited texting for the kids.

Perhaps the best way to describe this recession is &quot;The entitlement recession&quot; because so many thought they were entitled to bigger houses than they can truly afford, and the entire country thought it was entitled to more imported toys than it can afford, and worst of all we think we are entitled to more government than we can afford! ]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ben Atlas &#8211; <i>In fact it was common in the 80s to pay several hundred dollars a month for the home phone.</i></p>
<p>You must be kidding! In our house, we had a timer next to our phone and were very careful not to allow international calls (or even out-of-state) calls to go on for too long. If I recall correctly, our phone bill was usually about $70-80 a month, and perhaps $120 in a month where a family member might have been traveling overseas.</p>
<p>Of course, you brought up an excellent point about tzedaka and why it isn&#8217;t as forthcoming as it should be. Perhaps many people aren&#8217;t interested in paying the few hundred dollar a month phone bill for people who are out of work but refuse to give up their dual iPhones (husband and wife), their other 3 phones for the kids, and the family plan with unlimited data for mom and dad, and unlimited texting for the kids.</p>
<p>Perhaps the best way to describe this recession is &#8220;The entitlement recession&#8221; because so many thought they were entitled to bigger houses than they can truly afford, and the entire country thought it was entitled to more imported toys than it can afford, and worst of all we think we are entitled to more government than we can afford! </p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Up to Teaneck in Debt		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/01/foreclosure-in-teaneck/#comment-773</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Up to Teaneck in Debt]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 04 Apr 2010 04:22:26 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1055#comment-773</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&quot;If they are unemployed they can just not pay the tuition and have more than enough money to pay their mortgage and utilities.&quot;

We&#039;ll see how long that&#039;ll last.  How many school closings before the other schools wise up?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&#8220;If they are unemployed they can just not pay the tuition and have more than enough money to pay their mortgage and utilities.&#8221;</p>
<p>We&#8217;ll see how long that&#8217;ll last.  How many school closings before the other schools wise up?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Ben Atlas		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/01/foreclosure-in-teaneck/#comment-763</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Atlas]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2010 19:25:05 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1055#comment-763</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[On the subject of the &quot;toys&quot;. The cost is in the plans not the devices. PDA is not a toy for a job seeker. People can&#039;t sit at home all day so they need to be connected on the go. Moreover the cost of the plan and the phone could be Tax deducted as part of the &quot;job search&quot; etc. And even though we use telephony much more these days the cost is actually comparable to what people used to pay to call long distance cousin in Brooklyn. In fact it was common in the 80s to pay several hundred dollars a month for the home phone. Except you didn&#039;t have to put up with some yenta eying your iPhone while you out to get some milk for the family.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>On the subject of the &#8220;toys&#8221;. The cost is in the plans not the devices. PDA is not a toy for a job seeker. People can&#8217;t sit at home all day so they need to be connected on the go. Moreover the cost of the plan and the phone could be Tax deducted as part of the &#8220;job search&#8221; etc. And even though we use telephony much more these days the cost is actually comparable to what people used to pay to call long distance cousin in Brooklyn. In fact it was common in the 80s to pay several hundred dollars a month for the home phone. Except you didn&#8217;t have to put up with some yenta eying your iPhone while you out to get some milk for the family.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Ben Atlas		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/01/foreclosure-in-teaneck/#comment-762</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Atlas]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2010 16:17:29 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1055#comment-762</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I am more interested if there is any communal support for these people in finding jobs, income and outright cash. Otherwise in all seriousness you can hardly call this a &quot;community&quot;.

The ugly side exposed by this recession is the indifference people feel to others, the numbness to the financial calamities. As if you are supposed to die in a plague. This is the lasting legacy of this great recession. The final erosion of the communal values amongst Jews. It also in a certain way explains the indifference during the Holocausts.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I am more interested if there is any communal support for these people in finding jobs, income and outright cash. Otherwise in all seriousness you can hardly call this a &#8220;community&#8221;.</p>
<p>The ugly side exposed by this recession is the indifference people feel to others, the numbness to the financial calamities. As if you are supposed to die in a plague. This is the lasting legacy of this great recession. The final erosion of the communal values amongst Jews. It also in a certain way explains the indifference during the Holocausts.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Cedar Lane Chick		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/01/foreclosure-in-teaneck/#comment-760</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cedar Lane Chick]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2010 15:01:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1055#comment-760</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[To comment on Mr. Atlas&#039;s comment, yes, the housing bubble was caused by exotic mortgages etc. but from what I heard from a number of young homeowners in the Teaneck/Bergenfield area many of the younger people did originally get these kinds of exotic mortgages.
There are mostly 2 income families in this area in the community. I believe the majority had the knowledge to refinance to 15 or 30 year fixed mortgages before the bubble burst. I have been told by some of these homeowners when many of them bought their homes they were told to only hold an &quot;exotic&quot; mortgage for no more than 3-5 years then they must refinance. 

Since this is not a tutiton or housing blog, I wonder sociologically if the parents mentioned above who are laying off house cleaners and gardeners, not paying their tuition bills and still buying the &quot;toys&quot; like blackberries etc. and eating out, feel that anything they can do themselves can be cut? I&#039;m wondering if they feel they still have to keep up appearances within the community (being seen in eateries and with the hottest cell phone with the cool leased car) but things that are &quot;hidden&quot; in the community (who is paying tuition or not, who is cleaning for themselves and who is not) are either not being done or suddenly done by the families?

I also wonder if the community feels they HAVE to have a dual income to pay for what they feel the community socially expects of them?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>To comment on Mr. Atlas&#8217;s comment, yes, the housing bubble was caused by exotic mortgages etc. but from what I heard from a number of young homeowners in the Teaneck/Bergenfield area many of the younger people did originally get these kinds of exotic mortgages.<br />
There are mostly 2 income families in this area in the community. I believe the majority had the knowledge to refinance to 15 or 30 year fixed mortgages before the bubble burst. I have been told by some of these homeowners when many of them bought their homes they were told to only hold an &#8220;exotic&#8221; mortgage for no more than 3-5 years then they must refinance. </p>
<p>Since this is not a tutiton or housing blog, I wonder sociologically if the parents mentioned above who are laying off house cleaners and gardeners, not paying their tuition bills and still buying the &#8220;toys&#8221; like blackberries etc. and eating out, feel that anything they can do themselves can be cut? I&#8217;m wondering if they feel they still have to keep up appearances within the community (being seen in eateries and with the hottest cell phone with the cool leased car) but things that are &#8220;hidden&#8221; in the community (who is paying tuition or not, who is cleaning for themselves and who is not) are either not being done or suddenly done by the families?</p>
<p>I also wonder if the community feels they HAVE to have a dual income to pay for what they feel the community socially expects of them?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Ben Atlas		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/01/foreclosure-in-teaneck/#comment-751</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Atlas]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2010 02:55:48 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1055#comment-751</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The massive wave of the foreclosures known as the &quot;housing bubble&quot; of two years ago was virtually all about the houses bought with exotic mortgages or secondary properties, etc. The underwater properties or proprieties with ballooning mortgage rates. The unemployment foreclosures of the conventional 30 year mortgage kind is just now starting to kick in as savings are depleted. Your are confusing these distinct categories.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The massive wave of the foreclosures known as the &#8220;housing bubble&#8221; of two years ago was virtually all about the houses bought with exotic mortgages or secondary properties, etc. The underwater properties or proprieties with ballooning mortgage rates. The unemployment foreclosures of the conventional 30 year mortgage kind is just now starting to kick in as savings are depleted. Your are confusing these distinct categories.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
