<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: A chat with Rabbi Shlomo Einhorn	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/03/26/a-chat-with-rabbi-shlomo-einhorn/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/03/26/a-chat-with-rabbi-shlomo-einhorn/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Apr 2012 22:08:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Neil Harris		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/03/26/a-chat-with-rabbi-shlomo-einhorn/#comment-4339</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Neil Harris]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 03 Apr 2012 22:08:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4804#comment-4339</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&quot;Refined&quot; might be the goal, but if presented that way, I think it might turn some people off.  &quot;Growth in becoming a better person [Jew]&quot; is a more digestable approach, I think.  If it&#039;s a trend in the non-Jewish world, then for sure (sadly) Jews will buy in (just look at everything from &quot;chulent bags&quot; to sushi).

True, BME is rooted in Messilas Yesharim, but R Itmar Schwartz only brings in the quote in the beginning of MY about devekus and that is repeated over and over and over again.  Most of the first two vols deal with our relationship with the Creator.  Now, his commentary on MY is another story.

Re: &quot;How is it that initial exposure to growth-oriented spiritual sefarim (as opposed to Chassidic texts which tend to focus on experiencing spiritualism) is so often done wrong?&quot;
I think that it depends on who you are approaching.  You and I love Mussar (and mussar), but not everyone has the sames tastes.
I dislike pickles.  No matter how you dress up a pickle, I won&#039;t like it.  I can&#039;t stand the smell (really it&#039;s the salt brine solution).  Drives me crazy, man.  However, I happen to like cucumbers.  A pickle was, at one time, a cuccumber.  
If a person&#039;s view of mussar is based on a scolding from their mashgiach or a casual reading of a classic text (without really understanding it), then I can totally understand why their &quot;inital exposure&quot; might be wrong.

Your answer, &quot;Or is it just that the “think of the day of death” attitude that Mussar started with in R’ Yisrael Salanter’s day has so slanted how prior generations see the movement that rabbeim are still subconsciously conveying it in how they teach?&quot; seems to make sense to me.

Ohr Yisrael and Madregos HaAdam are chock full of the importance of &quot;Yiras Hashem&quot; and &#039;Yiras Shamayim&quot;.  These were yesodos that were lacking in that generation (and still are lacking).  However, there are other ways to package it.  R Y Blazer explains that Yiras Shamayim is the fear or concern that our avodah/mitzvah observance won&#039;t be the best it can be when serving Hashem.  That is very different that the common view of &quot;fear of Heaven&quot;, which implies (to me) onesh and an accounting before Hashem.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&#8220;Refined&#8221; might be the goal, but if presented that way, I think it might turn some people off.  &#8220;Growth in becoming a better person [Jew]&#8221; is a more digestable approach, I think.  If it&#8217;s a trend in the non-Jewish world, then for sure (sadly) Jews will buy in (just look at everything from &#8220;chulent bags&#8221; to sushi).</p>
<p>True, BME is rooted in Messilas Yesharim, but R Itmar Schwartz only brings in the quote in the beginning of MY about devekus and that is repeated over and over and over again.  Most of the first two vols deal with our relationship with the Creator.  Now, his commentary on MY is another story.</p>
<p>Re: &#8220;How is it that initial exposure to growth-oriented spiritual sefarim (as opposed to Chassidic texts which tend to focus on experiencing spiritualism) is so often done wrong?&#8221;<br />
I think that it depends on who you are approaching.  You and I love Mussar (and mussar), but not everyone has the sames tastes.<br />
I dislike pickles.  No matter how you dress up a pickle, I won&#8217;t like it.  I can&#8217;t stand the smell (really it&#8217;s the salt brine solution).  Drives me crazy, man.  However, I happen to like cucumbers.  A pickle was, at one time, a cuccumber.<br />
If a person&#8217;s view of mussar is based on a scolding from their mashgiach or a casual reading of a classic text (without really understanding it), then I can totally understand why their &#8220;inital exposure&#8221; might be wrong.</p>
<p>Your answer, &#8220;Or is it just that the “think of the day of death” attitude that Mussar started with in R’ Yisrael Salanter’s day has so slanted how prior generations see the movement that rabbeim are still subconsciously conveying it in how they teach?&#8221; seems to make sense to me.</p>
<p>Ohr Yisrael and Madregos HaAdam are chock full of the importance of &#8220;Yiras Hashem&#8221; and &#8216;Yiras Shamayim&#8221;.  These were yesodos that were lacking in that generation (and still are lacking).  However, there are other ways to package it.  R Y Blazer explains that Yiras Shamayim is the fear or concern that our avodah/mitzvah observance won&#8217;t be the best it can be when serving Hashem.  That is very different that the common view of &#8220;fear of Heaven&#8221;, which implies (to me) onesh and an accounting before Hashem.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Micha Berger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/03/26/a-chat-with-rabbi-shlomo-einhorn/#comment-4338</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Micha Berger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 03 Apr 2012 21:30:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4804#comment-4338</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Neil, you may be talking to a more primary problem. By noting that we have to avoid certain sefarim because the typical Orthodox Jew already formed a negative impression of them, you make me wonder why? How is it that initial exposure to growth-oriented spiritual sefarim (as opposed to Chassidic texts which tend to focus on experiencing spiritualism) is so often done wrong? I realize that the typical contemporary Westerner isn&#039;t naturally fascinated by something that postpones gratification by years or decades. But is that causing us to try to present Mussar in a warped manner? Or is it just that the &quot;think of the day of death&quot; attitude that Mussar started with in R&#039; Yisrael Salanter&#039;s day has so slanted how prior generations see the movement that rabbeim are still subconsciously conveying it in how they teach?

You inadvertently raise an interesting paradox. Mesilas Yesharim is unfortunately on many O Jews&#039; &quot;feh&quot; list. R&#039; Itamar Schwartz&#039;s Bilvavi sefarim are very popular among O Jews seeking spirituality. Even though Bilvavi very very heavily leans on MY and the Ramchal&#039;s other works!

So, let&#039;s think about how to get to the next step... We find that many people are excited by a spirituality based on the same kinds of growth that are popular in the general society. (No surprise.) And yet we find a barrier to teaching most of the texts from within the tradition that are based on self-refinement and growth. So, how do we take ideas like that described in this discussion and anchor them in a vision of what &quot;refined&quot; means -- teach what it is those tools we&#039;re taking from society are supposed to be used to build -- that is drawn from the Torah?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Neil, you may be talking to a more primary problem. By noting that we have to avoid certain sefarim because the typical Orthodox Jew already formed a negative impression of them, you make me wonder why? How is it that initial exposure to growth-oriented spiritual sefarim (as opposed to Chassidic texts which tend to focus on experiencing spiritualism) is so often done wrong? I realize that the typical contemporary Westerner isn&#8217;t naturally fascinated by something that postpones gratification by years or decades. But is that causing us to try to present Mussar in a warped manner? Or is it just that the &#8220;think of the day of death&#8221; attitude that Mussar started with in R&#8217; Yisrael Salanter&#8217;s day has so slanted how prior generations see the movement that rabbeim are still subconsciously conveying it in how they teach?</p>
<p>You inadvertently raise an interesting paradox. Mesilas Yesharim is unfortunately on many O Jews&#8217; &#8220;feh&#8221; list. R&#8217; Itamar Schwartz&#8217;s Bilvavi sefarim are very popular among O Jews seeking spirituality. Even though Bilvavi very very heavily leans on MY and the Ramchal&#8217;s other works!</p>
<p>So, let&#8217;s think about how to get to the next step&#8230; We find that many people are excited by a spirituality based on the same kinds of growth that are popular in the general society. (No surprise.) And yet we find a barrier to teaching most of the texts from within the tradition that are based on self-refinement and growth. So, how do we take ideas like that described in this discussion and anchor them in a vision of what &#8220;refined&#8221; means &#8212; teach what it is those tools we&#8217;re taking from society are supposed to be used to build &#8212; that is drawn from the Torah?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Neil Harris		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/03/26/a-chat-with-rabbi-shlomo-einhorn/#comment-4337</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Neil Harris]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 03 Apr 2012 15:38:30 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4804#comment-4337</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Without R Einhorn commenting, we really don&#039;t know what he is teaching, regarding Gedolim.  I think that there&#039;s nothing wrong getting people, who are not familiar with Gedolim, to find a way to relate and a desire to strive to emulate them.

The problem is, and I find this with those within the 32-45 age bracket who are MO in the sense that they are not thinking about growth, that many hear about Mesillas Yesharim, Alei Shur, or even Michtav M&#039;Eliyahu and they get that bad taste in their mouth that they associate with Mussar.  They don&#039;t think of it as self-growth or a route to being a better Jew or person.

This is why marketing a program as a &quot;Mussar program&quot; has been highly effective for The Mussar Institute.  They are reaching a demographic that doesn&#039;t have a negative view of authentic Jewish self-growth.

Using the proven techniques of Evangelicals or Tony Robbins can be useful in reaching out to people, as I&#039;ve said before.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Without R Einhorn commenting, we really don&#8217;t know what he is teaching, regarding Gedolim.  I think that there&#8217;s nothing wrong getting people, who are not familiar with Gedolim, to find a way to relate and a desire to strive to emulate them.</p>
<p>The problem is, and I find this with those within the 32-45 age bracket who are MO in the sense that they are not thinking about growth, that many hear about Mesillas Yesharim, Alei Shur, or even Michtav M&#8217;Eliyahu and they get that bad taste in their mouth that they associate with Mussar.  They don&#8217;t think of it as self-growth or a route to being a better Jew or person.</p>
<p>This is why marketing a program as a &#8220;Mussar program&#8221; has been highly effective for The Mussar Institute.  They are reaching a demographic that doesn&#8217;t have a negative view of authentic Jewish self-growth.</p>
<p>Using the proven techniques of Evangelicals or Tony Robbins can be useful in reaching out to people, as I&#8217;ve said before.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: micha		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/03/26/a-chat-with-rabbi-shlomo-einhorn/#comment-4333</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[micha]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 02 Apr 2012 20:54:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4804#comment-4333</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[To continue Neil&#039;s thought... I would define mussar as the approach to Judaism in which the Torah is a means of becoming the person Hashem intended us to be. (And upper-case-M &quot;Mussar&quot; is perhaps when that perfection is viewed in terms of refinement of middos.) Halakhah is central to that, but so is working the program in ways beyond halakhah. It may very well be that people like Tony Robbins or Stephen Covey found the tools that work in today&#039;s Western milieu. It can&#039;t be any more off than Rav Yisrael Salanter promoting the republication of Cheshbon haNefesh, a book outlining a tool first developed by Benjamin Franklyn.

But I think the approach described is lacking the picture of the ideal. Self-help and management gurus are teaching people how to become the people they wish they were. We therefore are missing the &quot;make His Will your will&quot; peice -- closing the possibility of a gap between who I want to be, and who my Maker wants me to be.

I think this is actually exacerbated by how Rabbi Einhorn is described as using quotes from and stories about our gedolim. Yes, our gedolim tend not to fit the Mod-O mindset of his congregants. (Largely because the notion of putting a rosh yeshiva up on a pedestal is more central to chareidi life, which then skews the demographics of who gets quoted and has tales retold about them.)  But taking sound bites out of context to find those elements a Mod-O Jew would agree are worth emulating (I assume that is what is meant by putting someone&#039;s &quot;teaching in the mouth of the Gedolim&quot;, as opposed to making things up) does not produce a coherent picture of who it is I am aiming to become.

If Rabbi Einhorn is building an approach for people to whom Tony Robbins&#039; message of human potential speaks, then the population sees the world through the eyes of the greatness and majesty of man. Territory already developed by the Alter of Slabodka. Perhaps exploring his Or haTzafun would produce a vision of the Torah&#039;s ideal that fits with the direction RHE is heading.

If the notion of a well-defined ideal me is neglected, one will be left with a Judaism that is reduced to being &quot;a spade with which to hoe&quot; the ground of self-help: Keep Torah, it&#039;s the only way to really be happy. We not only need a vision, it -- unlike the tool-set -- much be firmly grounded in traditional sources.

In general, we are in the territory of providing meaning through lower-case-m mussar. It would make sense to explore and adapt the work the Mussarists already did, rather than reinventing the wheel from scratch.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>To continue Neil&#8217;s thought&#8230; I would define mussar as the approach to Judaism in which the Torah is a means of becoming the person Hashem intended us to be. (And upper-case-M &#8220;Mussar&#8221; is perhaps when that perfection is viewed in terms of refinement of middos.) Halakhah is central to that, but so is working the program in ways beyond halakhah. It may very well be that people like Tony Robbins or Stephen Covey found the tools that work in today&#8217;s Western milieu. It can&#8217;t be any more off than Rav Yisrael Salanter promoting the republication of Cheshbon haNefesh, a book outlining a tool first developed by Benjamin Franklyn.</p>
<p>But I think the approach described is lacking the picture of the ideal. Self-help and management gurus are teaching people how to become the people they wish they were. We therefore are missing the &#8220;make His Will your will&#8221; peice &#8212; closing the possibility of a gap between who I want to be, and who my Maker wants me to be.</p>
<p>I think this is actually exacerbated by how Rabbi Einhorn is described as using quotes from and stories about our gedolim. Yes, our gedolim tend not to fit the Mod-O mindset of his congregants. (Largely because the notion of putting a rosh yeshiva up on a pedestal is more central to chareidi life, which then skews the demographics of who gets quoted and has tales retold about them.)  But taking sound bites out of context to find those elements a Mod-O Jew would agree are worth emulating (I assume that is what is meant by putting someone&#8217;s &#8220;teaching in the mouth of the Gedolim&#8221;, as opposed to making things up) does not produce a coherent picture of who it is I am aiming to become.</p>
<p>If Rabbi Einhorn is building an approach for people to whom Tony Robbins&#8217; message of human potential speaks, then the population sees the world through the eyes of the greatness and majesty of man. Territory already developed by the Alter of Slabodka. Perhaps exploring his Or haTzafun would produce a vision of the Torah&#8217;s ideal that fits with the direction RHE is heading.</p>
<p>If the notion of a well-defined ideal me is neglected, one will be left with a Judaism that is reduced to being &#8220;a spade with which to hoe&#8221; the ground of self-help: Keep Torah, it&#8217;s the only way to really be happy. We not only need a vision, it &#8212; unlike the tool-set &#8212; much be firmly grounded in traditional sources.</p>
<p>In general, we are in the territory of providing meaning through lower-case-m mussar. It would make sense to explore and adapt the work the Mussarists already did, rather than reinventing the wheel from scratch.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Neil Harris		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/03/26/a-chat-with-rabbi-shlomo-einhorn/#comment-4318</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Neil Harris]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 29 Mar 2012 02:29:12 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4804#comment-4318</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Actually, &quot;tools&quot; is an excellent point.  Obviously the point is Avodas Hashem.
I think that in our leadership orphaned society, we have to use whatever tools we can find to empower ouselves to make a difference in the klal.

I recently heard a shiur (ok, I&#039;ve listened to it three times) about leadership that is highly recommended:
http://www.yutorah.org/lectures/lecture.cfm/773422/Dr_David_Pelcovitz/Leadership_Influence_and_Professionalism__]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Actually, &#8220;tools&#8221; is an excellent point.  Obviously the point is Avodas Hashem.<br />
I think that in our leadership orphaned society, we have to use whatever tools we can find to empower ouselves to make a difference in the klal.</p>
<p>I recently heard a shiur (ok, I&#8217;ve listened to it three times) about leadership that is highly recommended:<br />
<a href="http://www.yutorah.org/lectures/lecture.cfm/773422/Dr_David_Pelcovitz/Leadership_Influence_and_Professionalism__" rel="nofollow ugc">http://www.yutorah.org/lectures/lecture.cfm/773422/Dr_David_Pelcovitz/Leadership_Influence_and_Professionalism__</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Shlomo Argamon		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/03/26/a-chat-with-rabbi-shlomo-einhorn/#comment-4317</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shlomo Argamon]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 29 Mar 2012 01:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4804#comment-4317</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I&#039;m not in the target demographic, I think, though I do find a great deal of value in the &quot;motivational leadership&quot; literature.  The thing is, though, what these books and seminars really provide are *tools*, not goals, even though they might have you think they provide both.  In fact, the tools can be very useful in one&#039;s development of one&#039;s avodas Hashem, but one must go to Torah for the goals.

A wonderful term I got from the title of a book by a Tibetan Buddhist monk (of all things) is &quot;Spiritual Materialism.&quot; The idea is that many people today look at spirituality as a kind of &quot;acquisition&quot; and develop a selfish acquisitiveness which they think of as &quot;spirituality.&quot; Needless to say, this is NOT avodas Hashem. If you&#039;re not thinking about how to do Gd&#039;s will, but rather on your own &quot;spiritual fulfillment&quot; or &quot;growth&quot; or &quot;leadership&quot; you&#039;re totally missing the point, and that&#039;s a big danger with all of these motivational approaches.  Self-development must be in the service of improving avodas Hashem, not a goal in its own right.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m not in the target demographic, I think, though I do find a great deal of value in the &#8220;motivational leadership&#8221; literature.  The thing is, though, what these books and seminars really provide are *tools*, not goals, even though they might have you think they provide both.  In fact, the tools can be very useful in one&#8217;s development of one&#8217;s avodas Hashem, but one must go to Torah for the goals.</p>
<p>A wonderful term I got from the title of a book by a Tibetan Buddhist monk (of all things) is &#8220;Spiritual Materialism.&#8221; The idea is that many people today look at spirituality as a kind of &#8220;acquisition&#8221; and develop a selfish acquisitiveness which they think of as &#8220;spirituality.&#8221; Needless to say, this is NOT avodas Hashem. If you&#8217;re not thinking about how to do Gd&#8217;s will, but rather on your own &#8220;spiritual fulfillment&#8221; or &#8220;growth&#8221; or &#8220;leadership&#8221; you&#8217;re totally missing the point, and that&#8217;s a big danger with all of these motivational approaches.  Self-development must be in the service of improving avodas Hashem, not a goal in its own right.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Neil Harris		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/03/26/a-chat-with-rabbi-shlomo-einhorn/#comment-4316</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Neil Harris]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 28 Mar 2012 21:14:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4804#comment-4316</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I have read this post twice and now, at the suggestion of Dr. Brill, am offering an expanded comment. Yes, I learn Bilvavi and know the pre-1992 U2 discography pretty darn well. I found Torah concepts in Tony Robbins. 

As a 41 year old who is fully aware of pop culture, yet chooses not to engage in most of it, I found this posted discussion w/ R Einhorn to be great. I am just at the fringe of the demographic that R Einhorn is focusing on, yet he speaks to me. 

Many of my peers are in one of two categories:
Either they are observant slackers, sometimes only davening with a minyan on Shabbos Kodesh or simply going through the motions on the same intellectual and emotional level of their high school years. 

I read this post and thought of R Moshe Weinberger (Cong Aish Kodesh in Woodmere, NY), who also has an eclectic library and has found a way to speak in a language his congregants understand. 

My generation and those Gen Y&#039;ers or 15th Gen&#039;ers are in need of substance and a Yiddishkeit that allows to to both inspire others and be inspired. 

Dr. Brill&#039;s observation about those not knowing  the Rav and Reb Shlomo is so true. 

I think most institutions would help with the quest for meaning, but don&#039;t know how. Even AJOP tried to address this in Jan at their &quot;In Reach&quot; seminar.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have read this post twice and now, at the suggestion of Dr. Brill, am offering an expanded comment. Yes, I learn Bilvavi and know the pre-1992 U2 discography pretty darn well. I found Torah concepts in Tony Robbins. </p>
<p>As a 41 year old who is fully aware of pop culture, yet chooses not to engage in most of it, I found this posted discussion w/ R Einhorn to be great. I am just at the fringe of the demographic that R Einhorn is focusing on, yet he speaks to me. </p>
<p>Many of my peers are in one of two categories:<br />
Either they are observant slackers, sometimes only davening with a minyan on Shabbos Kodesh or simply going through the motions on the same intellectual and emotional level of their high school years. </p>
<p>I read this post and thought of R Moshe Weinberger (Cong Aish Kodesh in Woodmere, NY), who also has an eclectic library and has found a way to speak in a language his congregants understand. </p>
<p>My generation and those Gen Y&#8217;ers or 15th Gen&#8217;ers are in need of substance and a Yiddishkeit that allows to to both inspire others and be inspired. </p>
<p>Dr. Brill&#8217;s observation about those not knowing  the Rav and Reb Shlomo is so true. </p>
<p>I think most institutions would help with the quest for meaning, but don&#8217;t know how. Even AJOP tried to address this in Jan at their &#8220;In Reach&#8221; seminar.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/03/26/a-chat-with-rabbi-shlomo-einhorn/#comment-4315</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 28 Mar 2012 20:01:15 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4804#comment-4315</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A goal of psychoanalysis and psychoanalytically informed therapy is to enable people to become more flexible and empathic, a sign of which is humor and irony. By way of contrast self help books are addictive, create no inner structural change, and set up rigid robotic ideals. Generation Y and Z  are way too serious, way too humorless and way too focused to begin with. Putting this generation on these success/management/little engine that could steroids is deliberately aiming at creating a generation of Aspberger robots.  Rabbi Einhorn with the backing of the OU gives a seal of approval to a specific type of inner work that deters the person from greater subjectivity and individualism. So why does his approach have any priority? Is this also a matter of daas torah MO style. One answer is R. Einhorn’s combo works, makes people more frum, a world where subjectivity and individualism are not particularly desirable. But many things work. Giving out frozen yogurt after davening would cause people to have  sweet and happy associations with the shul. Walking past a shul would be like walking past a Baskin and Robbins. Another advantage of the  mind over everything approach is that it costs relatively little in time and money, and promise a quick and easy formula for self renewal. That it does. 
Even if we decide power and wealth are half the tachlis haadam beolawmo, self help books are not good models how to achieve these goals. I offer two proof texts as case studies, the Jeremy Irons character in the movie Margin Call and a TED talk by Sheryl Sandberg. Both exhibit and have great presence and strength. Does anyone think these two, (or Lehman’s  Fuld, Goldman Sachs’ Lloyd Blankfein and on and on through the Fortune 500 ) came up in the world using Tony Robbins Leadership Tapes?  What exactly do such people have and how did they become such leaders?  All I know for sure is that it took more  than having an Amazon account.    
http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=18uDutylDa4
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheryl_Sandberg]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A goal of psychoanalysis and psychoanalytically informed therapy is to enable people to become more flexible and empathic, a sign of which is humor and irony. By way of contrast self help books are addictive, create no inner structural change, and set up rigid robotic ideals. Generation Y and Z  are way too serious, way too humorless and way too focused to begin with. Putting this generation on these success/management/little engine that could steroids is deliberately aiming at creating a generation of Aspberger robots.  Rabbi Einhorn with the backing of the OU gives a seal of approval to a specific type of inner work that deters the person from greater subjectivity and individualism. So why does his approach have any priority? Is this also a matter of daas torah MO style. One answer is R. Einhorn’s combo works, makes people more frum, a world where subjectivity and individualism are not particularly desirable. But many things work. Giving out frozen yogurt after davening would cause people to have  sweet and happy associations with the shul. Walking past a shul would be like walking past a Baskin and Robbins. Another advantage of the  mind over everything approach is that it costs relatively little in time and money, and promise a quick and easy formula for self renewal. That it does.<br />
Even if we decide power and wealth are half the tachlis haadam beolawmo, self help books are not good models how to achieve these goals. I offer two proof texts as case studies, the Jeremy Irons character in the movie Margin Call and a TED talk by Sheryl Sandberg. Both exhibit and have great presence and strength. Does anyone think these two, (or Lehman’s  Fuld, Goldman Sachs’ Lloyd Blankfein and on and on through the Fortune 500 ) came up in the world using Tony Robbins Leadership Tapes?  What exactly do such people have and how did they become such leaders?  All I know for sure is that it took more  than having an Amazon account.<br />
<iframe class='youtube-player' width='500' height='282' src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/18uDutylDa4?version=3&#038;rel=1&#038;fs=1&#038;autohide=2&#038;showsearch=0&#038;showinfo=1&#038;iv_load_policy=1&#038;wmode=transparent' allowfullscreen='true' style='border:0;'></iframe><br />
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheryl_Sandberg" rel="nofollow ugc">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheryl_Sandberg</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Jack Gerouac		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/03/26/a-chat-with-rabbi-shlomo-einhorn/#comment-4314</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jack Gerouac]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2012 20:06:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4804#comment-4314</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Great post.  I am big fan of Bono and Bilvavi.  Tony Robbin&#039;s GET THE EDGE program is chock full o&#039;mussar.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Great post.  I am big fan of Bono and Bilvavi.  Tony Robbin&#8217;s GET THE EDGE program is chock full o&#8217;mussar.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Eli Webber		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/03/26/a-chat-with-rabbi-shlomo-einhorn/#comment-4313</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eli Webber]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2012 17:09:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4804#comment-4313</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/03/26/a-chat-with-rabbi-shlomo-einhorn/#comment-4302&quot;&gt;hydewatch&lt;/a&gt;.

Hyde, my friend, i disagree with your point that &quot;to me it is sad that this Rabbi was not able to find solutions to his spiritual quests in the world of Torah&quot;. It makes me negate finding inspiration from a cool breeze on a summer day, just because that wasn&#039;t in the Torah. I guess this hovers over the issue of inspiration outside the Torah which i know was the subject of letter in Torah U&#039;Maddah Journal once before. Can&#039;t remember where but somebody had some debate about going to Basbeall games.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/03/26/a-chat-with-rabbi-shlomo-einhorn/#comment-4302">hydewatch</a>.</p>
<p>Hyde, my friend, i disagree with your point that &#8220;to me it is sad that this Rabbi was not able to find solutions to his spiritual quests in the world of Torah&#8221;. It makes me negate finding inspiration from a cool breeze on a summer day, just because that wasn&#8217;t in the Torah. I guess this hovers over the issue of inspiration outside the Torah which i know was the subject of letter in Torah U&#8217;Maddah Journal once before. Can&#8217;t remember where but somebody had some debate about going to Basbeall games.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Moshe		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/03/26/a-chat-with-rabbi-shlomo-einhorn/#comment-4310</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Moshe]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2012 12:14:29 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4804#comment-4310</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This us of &quot;gedolim&quot; seems to me to be an innovation, one which perhaps takes the whole modern institution of &quot;gedolim&quot; even farther than it has come thus far. How does R. Einhorn&#039;s use of Gedolim compare with practices in other religions?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This us of &#8220;gedolim&#8221; seems to me to be an innovation, one which perhaps takes the whole modern institution of &#8220;gedolim&#8221; even farther than it has come thus far. How does R. Einhorn&#8217;s use of Gedolim compare with practices in other religions?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ADDeRabbi		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/03/26/a-chat-with-rabbi-shlomo-einhorn/#comment-4308</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ADDeRabbi]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2012 11:37:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4804#comment-4308</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Is he a kiruv rabbi? Kiruv training programs have been using Carnegie and NLP for over a decade.
With regard to Bono, I admit a soft spot. I&#039;ve darshened him before;
http://adderabbi.blogspot.com/2011/07/darshening-bono.html
]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Is he a kiruv rabbi? Kiruv training programs have been using Carnegie and NLP for over a decade.<br />
With regard to Bono, I admit a soft spot. I&#8217;ve darshened him before;<br />
<a href="http://adderabbi.blogspot.com/2011/07/darshening-bono.html" rel="nofollow ugc">http://adderabbi.blogspot.com/2011/07/darshening-bono.html</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Cheryl		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/03/26/a-chat-with-rabbi-shlomo-einhorn/#comment-4307</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cheryl]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2012 01:24:22 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4804#comment-4307</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The use of the Tony Robbins model I find interesting. I know a few 30 something women, successful professionals who were raised in the Modern Orthodox world, went to well known Modern Orthodox NYC day schools, and are now no longer observant. Their Facebook and Twitter accounts are filled with many Tony Robbins postings about his seminars, and the &quot;speak&quot; taught there on self improvement and motivation. They have traveled far and wide to participate in these seminars much like they traveled to shabbatons in their youth. It makes me wonder if  we all really need something like Robbins and if the Modern Orthodox world is not fulfilling for these successful young women.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The use of the Tony Robbins model I find interesting. I know a few 30 something women, successful professionals who were raised in the Modern Orthodox world, went to well known Modern Orthodox NYC day schools, and are now no longer observant. Their Facebook and Twitter accounts are filled with many Tony Robbins postings about his seminars, and the &#8220;speak&#8221; taught there on self improvement and motivation. They have traveled far and wide to participate in these seminars much like they traveled to shabbatons in their youth. It makes me wonder if  we all really need something like Robbins and if the Modern Orthodox world is not fulfilling for these successful young women.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
