<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Landes/ Green debate round 4	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/28/landes-green-debate-round-4/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/28/landes-green-debate-round-4/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 23:26:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Steven		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/28/landes-green-debate-round-4/#comment-2894</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Steven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 23:26:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3337#comment-2894</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/28/landes-green-debate-round-4/#comment-2857&quot;&gt;ej&lt;/a&gt;.

I admire Arthur Green, and I found his latest remarks well worth reading.  But it was ej&#039;s comment, with its note of authority and experience, that really made me pause and reflect.  more, please.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/28/landes-green-debate-round-4/#comment-2857">ej</a>.</p>
<p>I admire Arthur Green, and I found his latest remarks well worth reading.  But it was ej&#8217;s comment, with its note of authority and experience, that really made me pause and reflect.  more, please.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Lawrence Kaplan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/28/landes-green-debate-round-4/#comment-2859</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lawrence Kaplan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2011 14:57:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3337#comment-2859</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[EJ&#039;s thoughtful critique of Art Green calls to mind the Rambam&#039;s warning: First one needs the bread and meat, the discpline of halakhic study and practice;  only then can one  safely stroll through the pardes of mystical or philosophical contemplation with its promises and dangers.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>EJ&#8217;s thoughtful critique of Art Green calls to mind the Rambam&#8217;s warning: First one needs the bread and meat, the discpline of halakhic study and practice;  only then can one  safely stroll through the pardes of mystical or philosophical contemplation with its promises and dangers.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/28/landes-green-debate-round-4/#comment-2857</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2011 01:17:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3337#comment-2857</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Whatever one may think of his position, and I am not exactly a card carrying member of neo-Chasidus, it is a privilege  to have as creative  and good a man in our midst as Rabbi Arthur Green.

Recognizing Green’s  great contributions to Jewish life and thought, I remain a non believer. I do not believe our tachlis beolom in this post- Holocaust pre- Apocalypse times  is to work towards “fluid borders between “in” and “up,” or between “self” and “Other.” R.D. Laing and others of that period, (ok, I admit it was the sixties,)  may have darshened that schizophrenics are on a higher madreiga than prosaic bourgeois people, since they had obliterated their self and their ego. We know he was making a serious mistake. They were psychotic. I don’t agree religious insight comes from a deeper or higher rung of consciousness. I believe it comes from growing up, fully experiencing the various stages of  life, trying all the while to get a handle on one’s own life and times. We try over many decades to integrate aspects of  our parents and our teachers, their world and ours, and we try to negotiate our own  potential against this background of initial endowments,  family, community and external reality. Call it a Freudian or a Proustian or an Orthodox life of ever increasing finer discriminations, it is not a matter of rungs of consciousness or merging with others or the world. For better or worse the satisfactions and ecstasies’ Green seeks are pre-Oedipal. For most of us these pleasures are from a garden from which few emerge whole. Better an anthropomorphic  God up in the sky, than the regression to a time when we were in some mother- child symbiosis, with the terror of a jealous  father somewhere over the horizon. Green the mythmaker, the teacher of the Zohar, is certainly not in a position to depreciate anthropomorphisms.

Green thinks a God in heaven is a projection, whereas a God inside the body satisfies even the most ardent Feurbachian. Nonsense. The issue of projection is separate from the phenomenological location of the screen. Some  Jews project, (the Raavad’s “gedolim vetovim”), some don’t. For most Jews I tend to believe some of these terms carry no clear reference at all, whatever the temporary fleeting ideation, something like  the primitive terms in an a priori geometry. The dividing issue between Green and his  &quot;naive and childlike&quot;  opponents is whether a life devoted to a inner spiritual yenika/ nashing is superior to a grown- up life of many possible goals within the context of a Jewish life.
 
The issue in a way is the context, the background against which the chassidic and kabalistic talk stabilize their meanings.  There are few living chassidic courts that prioritize mystical merging over a life of intellectual learning of Talmud. Their goal like most of the yeshivas is to create frum, Talmudically literate balebatim. A balebus in a late capitalist fast track world does not in general have the inner stillness and patience to be medabek beshchina and  create the infinite yearning  for the zivugim necessary to bring the blessings from above into our lowly world. A mincha- mariv yes, a tikun chatzos generally no. We see the straight up Chasidim know how to scale- up their communities across continents and social classes. Whether neo-Chasidus, with far fewer material anchors  can create anything similar within their demographic is not at all obvious.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Whatever one may think of his position, and I am not exactly a card carrying member of neo-Chasidus, it is a privilege  to have as creative  and good a man in our midst as Rabbi Arthur Green.</p>
<p>Recognizing Green’s  great contributions to Jewish life and thought, I remain a non believer. I do not believe our tachlis beolom in this post- Holocaust pre- Apocalypse times  is to work towards “fluid borders between “in” and “up,” or between “self” and “Other.” R.D. Laing and others of that period, (ok, I admit it was the sixties,)  may have darshened that schizophrenics are on a higher madreiga than prosaic bourgeois people, since they had obliterated their self and their ego. We know he was making a serious mistake. They were psychotic. I don’t agree religious insight comes from a deeper or higher rung of consciousness. I believe it comes from growing up, fully experiencing the various stages of  life, trying all the while to get a handle on one’s own life and times. We try over many decades to integrate aspects of  our parents and our teachers, their world and ours, and we try to negotiate our own  potential against this background of initial endowments,  family, community and external reality. Call it a Freudian or a Proustian or an Orthodox life of ever increasing finer discriminations, it is not a matter of rungs of consciousness or merging with others or the world. For better or worse the satisfactions and ecstasies’ Green seeks are pre-Oedipal. For most of us these pleasures are from a garden from which few emerge whole. Better an anthropomorphic  God up in the sky, than the regression to a time when we were in some mother- child symbiosis, with the terror of a jealous  father somewhere over the horizon. Green the mythmaker, the teacher of the Zohar, is certainly not in a position to depreciate anthropomorphisms.</p>
<p>Green thinks a God in heaven is a projection, whereas a God inside the body satisfies even the most ardent Feurbachian. Nonsense. The issue of projection is separate from the phenomenological location of the screen. Some  Jews project, (the Raavad’s “gedolim vetovim”), some don’t. For most Jews I tend to believe some of these terms carry no clear reference at all, whatever the temporary fleeting ideation, something like  the primitive terms in an a priori geometry. The dividing issue between Green and his  &#8220;naive and childlike&#8221;  opponents is whether a life devoted to a inner spiritual yenika/ nashing is superior to a grown- up life of many possible goals within the context of a Jewish life.</p>
<p>The issue in a way is the context, the background against which the chassidic and kabalistic talk stabilize their meanings.  There are few living chassidic courts that prioritize mystical merging over a life of intellectual learning of Talmud. Their goal like most of the yeshivas is to create frum, Talmudically literate balebatim. A balebus in a late capitalist fast track world does not in general have the inner stillness and patience to be medabek beshchina and  create the infinite yearning  for the zivugim necessary to bring the blessings from above into our lowly world. A mincha- mariv yes, a tikun chatzos generally no. We see the straight up Chasidim know how to scale- up their communities across continents and social classes. Whether neo-Chasidus, with far fewer material anchors  can create anything similar within their demographic is not at all obvious.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
