<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>David Smith &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/tag/david-smith/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2010 01:57:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='kavvanah.wordpress.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/c9f111237f93750b6b994fc5185d49c3?s=96&#038;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>David Smith &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>Drawings by David Chaim Smith-  Thursday April 1, John Zorn at 6PM</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/31/drawings-by-david-chaim-smith-thursday-april-1-john-zorn-at-6pm/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/31/drawings-by-david-chaim-smith-thursday-april-1-john-zorn-at-6pm/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2010 01:57:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[David Chaim Smith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[David Smith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Zorn]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1037</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A former student is having a gallery opening tomorrow and intimate concert at opening by John Zorn and friends. Blood of Space: Drawings by David Chaim Smith Special Music Performance by John Zorn, Trevor Dunn, and Kenny Wollesen- April 1st &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/31/drawings-by-david-chaim-smith-thursday-april-1-john-zorn-at-6pm/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A former student is having a gallery opening tomorrow and intimate concert at opening by John Zorn and friends.</p>
<p><a href="http://davidchaimsmith.com/David_Chaim_Smith/2009_2010.html">Blood of Space: Drawings by David Chaim Smith </a><br />
Special Music Performance by John Zorn, Trevor Dunn, and Kenny Wollesen- April 1st at 6PM<br />
Presented by Cavin-Morris Gallery<br />
April 1, 2010- May 15, 2010<br />
Reception: April 1, 5:30 pm &#8211; 7:30 pm<br />
<em>David Chaim Smith is unstuck in time. David Chaim Smith makes drawings. These drawings are not about the art world. Yet he is not an Outsider Artist. In fact he is a perfect argument for the futility of any attempt to define O<br />
utsider. They are not about Contemporary Art’s self-referential contexts. Nor are these drawing about David Chaim Smith. They are incandescent utterances from the nexus point of unutterable ecstasy. They are inchoate maps of the un-mappable places of Original Creation. Is it dangerous to document these things? Yes it is. Throughout the history of Man it has been dangerous for the Mediators between Tangible and Intangible to absorb and expose Esoteric Teachings.</p>
<p>There is nothing New Age about this mysticism. It isn’t at all user-friendly. These intricate beautifully rendered chart-like drawings compel you to give up your own time frames and become absorbed and changed. The images settle into your psyche as well as your aesthetic reference zone. But for some reason these involved mad dances through words and sacred geometries, biomorphic and astral thought forms, incantations and exhortations are not in the least solipsistic. No more so then the constellations are or wave patterns seen from the sky or the mating dances of bees, and that is because David Chaim Smith is also a great artist who, under the pretence of being narratively self-effacing, organizes and arranges non-visual information into amazing hyperbolic cascades of visual information and composition. His ever-present artistic micro managing is kept invisible. He is a Keeper of Mysteries but his desire is for you to enter them as well so there is a tremendous amount of generosity in his Vision.</em><br />
Cavin Morris Gallery is proud to introduce the work of a true Mystic. He has thrown his artistic Body in front of us to take the Bolt of Lightning and transform its crackling hyper-intensity into black and white images of Primal Insight.<br />
For further information, please contact Shari Cavin, Randall Morris or Mariko Tanaka by tel (212) 226-3768, or email: Blugriot@aol.com.<br />
 Website	<a href="http://www.cavinmorris.com" rel="nofollow">http://www.cavinmorris.com</a><br />
Address	210 11th Ave, 2nd Fl<br />
New York (Chelsea) NY, 10001<br />
<a href="http://davidchaimsmith.com/David_Chaim_Smith/2009_2010.html">Website of Drawings by David Chaim Smith </a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/31/drawings-by-david-chaim-smith-thursday-april-1-john-zorn-at-6pm/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
