<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Aish Center in Manhattan &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/tag/aish-center-in-manhattan/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Nov 2010 16:51:24 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='kavvanah.wordpress.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/c9f111237f93750b6b994fc5185d49c3?s=96&#038;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>Aish Center in Manhattan &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>Aish Hatorah is now offering the same Torah as the Kabbalah Centre</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/11/15/aish-hatorah-is-now-offering-the-same-torah-as-the-kabbalah-centre/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/11/15/aish-hatorah-is-now-offering-the-same-torah-as-the-kabbalah-centre/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2010 05:31:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[adam jacobs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[adam jacobs kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Aish Center in Manhattan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[aish hatorah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[aish The Executive Learning Program]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rabbi Adam Jacobs Managing Director]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Executive Learning Program]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2352</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This article by Adam Jacobs of Aish presents Sefer Yetzirah as an ancient esoteric wisdom of different forms of energy and states of consciousness, useful for our secular lives. The way this shell game works is to draw equal signs &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/11/15/aish-hatorah-is-now-offering-the-same-torah-as-the-kabbalah-centre/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This article by Adam Jacobs of Aish presents Sefer Yetzirah as an ancient esoteric wisdom of different forms of energy and states of consciousness, useful for our secular lives.  The way this shell game works is to draw equal signs between different things and not worry about whether the associations works. Sefer Yetzirah= 32 states of consciousness= Huxley on altered states of consciousness= right-brain left brain pop psych= Freud= Chabad modernization of chochma and bina. As one commenter put it “where are the other 30 states and how do you actually attain them.</p>
<p>Aish usually likes the esotericism of creating a gematria to artificially connect a Zohar to modern psychology, implying we have from Sinai a deeper well of contemporary pop psych than the secular world. This one caught my eye because of the scientology or Kabbalah Centre language of guidebook, harness, tools, and benefit.  It is a “guidebook that explains the tools and techniques.”  I wonder which traditional commentaries is he reading? Notice also the lack of for its lack of reference to God.</p>
<p>People have always said that those who know kabbalah should offer something to compete with the Kabbalah Centre. American academics say that we should teach them to read Zohar and understand it as myth, symbols, and history. But that isn’t useful tools and techniques. Chabad teaches about your neshoma and your connection to God.. But is also not an esoteric guidebook to manipulate the world. Now, we have  Aish giving the world what it wants: a Da Vinci Code that will make your material life better. </p>
<p>What makes this article even more interesting is that Irwin Kula of CLAL showed up in the comments in order to call Adam Jacob&#8217;s bluff. Kula states that &#8220;traditional people like to imagine that the latest science is in the ancient texts. Kula then calls on Jacobs to get beyond the gobbeldy gook and admit that if one is interested in these topics then read the scientific literature. Kula asks Jacobs the empirical question of whether religion offers any teachings about any states of consciousness. </p>
<blockquote><p>Rabbi Adam Jacobs<br />
Managing Director, Aish Center in Manhattan Posted: November 7, 2010 &#8211; <a href="http:///www.huffingtonpost.com/rabbi-adam-jacobs/the-32-types-of-conscious_b_779128.html#comments">Full Version Here</a><br />
The most ancient (and still used) text of the Kabbalah is called the Sefer Yetzirah or Book of Formation, and its contents are generally attributed to the Biblical patriarch Abraham. The book opens with a discussion of the &#8220;32 Mystical Paths of Wisdom,&#8221; paths derived from the 10 digits on our hands (quantity) plus the 22 letters of the Hebrew alphabet, which we use to construct language and thereby describe reality (quality). These paths are also reflected in the 10 sefirot &#8212; spheres of energy that are the building blocks of physical reality yet also relate to character traits as well as states of consciousness:</p>
<p>The Sefer Yetzirah is a guidebook that explains the tools and techniques that are required to enter these states. One important (and practical) distinction that we can all make and relate to concerns the states of chochma (expansive subconsciousness) and binah (the conscious mind). Long ago, the Kabbalah knew that creativity was housed in the right brain and analytical thought in the left. Freud and Jung were familiar with these kabbalistic works and borrowed heavily from them (as did Newton and others). </p>
<p>Therefore, we are all familiar with these two states of being. Chochma is what we experience when we are at our creative best &#8212; when we are in &#8220;the zone&#8221; and experiencing a natural, easy flow. Artists, musicians and other creative people know it well and they also know that they are able to achieve, channel and create in that space in ways that would be impossible in normal waking life. Chochma is not concerned with life&#8217;s practicalities </p>
<p> Chochma is the dimension where, as Aldous Huxley wrote, &#8220;we see the world as it truly is &#8230; infinite&#8221;. He also said that in order to do that, the &#8220;doors of perception&#8221; needed to be cleansed. The Torah is the instruction manual that guides us along that path.</p>
<p>Binah is our analytical, practical and down-to-earth state. One that is useful for accounting, problem solving, computer programming, paying bills on time and the like. It is grounded and practical and has the ability to take the inspiration from chochma and &#8220;make it real&#8230;Though useful, binah does not always bring us to tranquility, harmony and big picture thinking. </p>
<p>For a stunning, impactful and crystal clear example of what I&#8217;m describing, have a look at this video of Dr. Jill Bolte Taylor, a brain scientist describing the effects of a stroke that shut down her left brain. What she describes is simply pure chochma consciousness in its most distilled form as her binah was completely switched off. It&#8217;s as beautiful as it is astounding. This is the state that the Sefer Yetzirah is teaching us to access, and there are wondrous benefits available to all those who succeed in harnessing and bonding these two great powers of the mind.</p></blockquote>
<p> The right left brain version of <a href="http://www.chabad.org/kabbalah/article_cdo/aid/380431/jewish/Right-and-Left-Brain-Activity.htm">Chabad seems traceable to a source like this.</a></p>
<p>Jacobs seems inspired by secular new age works like this <em><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Personal-Kabbalah-Paths-Inner-Purpose/dp/0806958987">Personal Kabbalah: 32 Paths to Inner Peace and Life Purpose</a></em></p>
<blockquote><p>I recommend this book if you&#8217;re looking for personal and professional success and fulfillment. It not only explains ancient wisdom in non-religious, contemporary, practical terms, it also gives you methods for accomplishment. The techniques in this book work for personal use as well as business.</p></blockquote>
<p>It is a good thing that Jacobs speaks as the authentic tradition. Image where he would be if he could innovate. As one commenter put it- &#8220;this makes Scientology believable&#8221;. Kula grasps the important point is that one readers of this pseudo-scientific religion dont really want a deep understanding because if they did they would read popular science. The question that Kula does not ask is:Why are people satisfied with this? Why are the successful MBA&#8217;s, that he gives private classes to at 10K each, happy with this?</p>
<p>Rabbi Irwin Kula comments </p>
<blockquote><p>I really do appreciate both the creativity of your response and its precision-quite an example of integrating chochmah and binah- which is nothing more than an ancient language for what we know as right brain and left brain. Traditional people often like to see contemporary scientific discoveries hinted at in their past traditions as it gives them a sense that their religious inheritance is really smart especially as it is becoming irrelevant to increasing numbers of people.</p>
<p>But forgetting about the gobbeldy gook of all this (which you point out quite humorously) especially when you can actually get a far deeper understanding of both chocmah and binah from reading Daniel Pink and other neuroscientists I have a question for you. And forget about the god stuff and the esoteric theological language that presumes all this is true in some metaphysical way, do you think there are a variety of levels/ states of consciousness that we have access to or can experience that can be parsed/explained with enough detail that we can recognize them. In other words besides asleep and awake are there other levels of awareness (making no metaphysical claim about them) that give us insight into ourselves/our world that are worth trying to attain. And last do you think there is a possibility that &#8211; admittedly in an inaccessible language and often crudely &#8211; ancient wisdoms happened upon some of those states and tried to record them in ways that might help us understand them better.<br />
Thanks,<br />
Irwin</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/11/15/aish-hatorah-is-now-offering-the-same-torah-as-the-kabbalah-centre/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>11</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
