<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Peter Beinart on his Orthodox affiliation	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/24/peter-beinhart-on-his-orthodox-affiliation/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/24/peter-beinhart-on-his-orthodox-affiliation/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 May 2010 05:08:46 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: H Sragow		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/24/peter-beinhart-on-his-orthodox-affiliation/#comment-1063</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[H Sragow]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2010 05:08:46 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1351#comment-1063</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I find it difficult to speculate on what proportions of members of a particular synagogue think actively about fundamentals.   I do find it interesting, though, that hundreds of Orthodox synagogues with hundreds of member families have huge attendance every Saturday morning, yet struggle to build a quorum of ten men on weekdays.  And I would submit that few pray with a minyan elsewhere.  

Does this mean that there is tacit acknowledgement in such synagogues (or even acceptance), that members are using the Orthodox experience for the communal benefits, and once they&#039;ve obtained sufficient communality on Saturday morning, they are exempt from further religious obligation?

Breinart&#039;s tolerant community, as well as many other tolerant communities within Orthodox synagogues, probably does feel that way.  

I have seen several spiritual leaders of such congregations, though, who speak publicly almost entirely of halachic minutiae.   They become irrelevant to the segments of the congregation who don&#039;t participate in all that jazz.  

And then there are some spiritual leaders who recognize the pattern, realize they can&#039;t beat &#039;em, and join &#039;em.  If the biggest synagogue  event is a chulent-making contest, the smart rabbi dons an apron.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I find it difficult to speculate on what proportions of members of a particular synagogue think actively about fundamentals.   I do find it interesting, though, that hundreds of Orthodox synagogues with hundreds of member families have huge attendance every Saturday morning, yet struggle to build a quorum of ten men on weekdays.  And I would submit that few pray with a minyan elsewhere.  </p>
<p>Does this mean that there is tacit acknowledgement in such synagogues (or even acceptance), that members are using the Orthodox experience for the communal benefits, and once they&#8217;ve obtained sufficient communality on Saturday morning, they are exempt from further religious obligation?</p>
<p>Breinart&#8217;s tolerant community, as well as many other tolerant communities within Orthodox synagogues, probably does feel that way.  </p>
<p>I have seen several spiritual leaders of such congregations, though, who speak publicly almost entirely of halachic minutiae.   They become irrelevant to the segments of the congregation who don&#8217;t participate in all that jazz.  </p>
<p>And then there are some spiritual leaders who recognize the pattern, realize they can&#8217;t beat &#8217;em, and join &#8217;em.  If the biggest synagogue  event is a chulent-making contest, the smart rabbi dons an apron.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Joseph		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/24/peter-beinhart-on-his-orthodox-affiliation/#comment-1060</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joseph]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2010 02:54:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1351#comment-1060</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I grew up in a YU-affiliated, modern-orthodox shul out of town (outside NY). Most of the membership was not orthodox, even as there were about 20-30 committed core frum families. Among this core, there were some &quot;Haredi-leaning&quot; families, but the community itself (including these families) was very open and warm even toward those who had different orthodox ideologies. 
Those &quot;masorati&quot; families were attracted to the shul because 1) they liked the traditional service because they grew up with it 2) they were attracted to it by the shul&#039;s organized social activities. My experience in NY and NJ was that many modern orthodox shuls were self-focused; there were few people outside the range of modern orthodoxy, as the service was not &#039;user-friendly&quot; (e.g. page numbers were not announced, etc.), and, in many places, there was little singing, and the service went too quickly for someone who was not fully educated (or even those who were fully educated!) to keep up. In some shuls, no one bothered to say hello. It is not surprising that in those outlying communities in which the orthodox are forced to interact with the non-orthodox, that there are more non-orthodox Jews who find an orthodox shul attractive; the ideological fissures between different groups of Jews are not as wide. Once the orthodox community becomes too big and too self-sufficient, there is no perceived need to reach outwards. Nor is it surprising that the lack of focus on spirituality in many places will not attract others (I&#039;m surprised such places have been able to continue for so long). I find this self-focus troubling and wish such communities would become more aware of the potential to influence and be enriched by the wider community. This would require a concerted effort on the part of the local rabbinate to address these issues]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I grew up in a YU-affiliated, modern-orthodox shul out of town (outside NY). Most of the membership was not orthodox, even as there were about 20-30 committed core frum families. Among this core, there were some &#8220;Haredi-leaning&#8221; families, but the community itself (including these families) was very open and warm even toward those who had different orthodox ideologies.<br />
Those &#8220;masorati&#8221; families were attracted to the shul because 1) they liked the traditional service because they grew up with it 2) they were attracted to it by the shul&#8217;s organized social activities. My experience in NY and NJ was that many modern orthodox shuls were self-focused; there were few people outside the range of modern orthodoxy, as the service was not &#8216;user-friendly&#8221; (e.g. page numbers were not announced, etc.), and, in many places, there was little singing, and the service went too quickly for someone who was not fully educated (or even those who were fully educated!) to keep up. In some shuls, no one bothered to say hello. It is not surprising that in those outlying communities in which the orthodox are forced to interact with the non-orthodox, that there are more non-orthodox Jews who find an orthodox shul attractive; the ideological fissures between different groups of Jews are not as wide. Once the orthodox community becomes too big and too self-sufficient, there is no perceived need to reach outwards. Nor is it surprising that the lack of focus on spirituality in many places will not attract others (I&#8217;m surprised such places have been able to continue for so long). I find this self-focus troubling and wish such communities would become more aware of the potential to influence and be enriched by the wider community. This would require a concerted effort on the part of the local rabbinate to address these issues</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/24/peter-beinhart-on-his-orthodox-affiliation/#comment-1057</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2010 23:14:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1351#comment-1057</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&lt;em&gt;a) it is a sizable proportion of many synagogues, &lt;/em&gt;

Without any serious sociological work - we get divergent guesses ranging from a small number to a majority. With such a wide range, I  suspect we may be talking about several different factors.
Most of the narratives of the journey to Orthodoxy  were about warmth and community.
Those that seek warm and community but are a-theological may be a majority. Those that are ironic and skeptical- not as many. Those that are liberal we have surveys at- 25%. What are all the sub factors in this approach? 
Orthodoxy of the last decades tended to focus on trees at the expense of forests, little bursts of ideas and not fundamentals. I am not sure that a large percentage looks at big questions or from an outsiders perspective even if the old answers no longer satisfy.

&lt;em&gt;b) the spiritual leaders of those shuls — not realizing how much of it exists — generally undercater to the needs of that portion of the population.&lt;/em&gt;

What do you think they should do? What should they be like?
If one has a clueless rabbi - why would it serve you better if they thought on a 11th grade level instead of an 8th grade level? Maybe we want rabbis to stay out of our hair, so the clueless the better. How could they serve the needs of  the liberal, when you have discussed how they could not even read a Beinhart article with comprehension?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>a) it is a sizable proportion of many synagogues, </em></p>
<p>Without any serious sociological work &#8211; we get divergent guesses ranging from a small number to a majority. With such a wide range, I  suspect we may be talking about several different factors.<br />
Most of the narratives of the journey to Orthodoxy  were about warmth and community.<br />
Those that seek warm and community but are a-theological may be a majority. Those that are ironic and skeptical- not as many. Those that are liberal we have surveys at- 25%. What are all the sub factors in this approach?<br />
Orthodoxy of the last decades tended to focus on trees at the expense of forests, little bursts of ideas and not fundamentals. I am not sure that a large percentage looks at big questions or from an outsiders perspective even if the old answers no longer satisfy.</p>
<p><em>b) the spiritual leaders of those shuls — not realizing how much of it exists — generally undercater to the needs of that portion of the population.</em></p>
<p>What do you think they should do? What should they be like?<br />
If one has a clueless rabbi &#8211; why would it serve you better if they thought on a 11th grade level instead of an 8th grade level? Maybe we want rabbis to stay out of our hair, so the clueless the better. How could they serve the needs of  the liberal, when you have discussed how they could not even read a Beinhart article with comprehension?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Menachem Mendel		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/24/peter-beinhart-on-his-orthodox-affiliation/#comment-1052</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Menachem Mendel]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2010 14:12:57 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1351#comment-1052</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I have a good friend who was president of an Orthodox synagogue while he was also defending someone who turned out to be a member of Al-Qaeda.  His former client had more of a problem with my friend&#039;s connections to Israel than his Jewishness.  When he was honored at his shul&#039;s annual dinner, it was not surprising that the Al-Qaeda connection got top billing from everyone who spoke when it came to saying something funny.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have a good friend who was president of an Orthodox synagogue while he was also defending someone who turned out to be a member of Al-Qaeda.  His former client had more of a problem with my friend&#8217;s connections to Israel than his Jewishness.  When he was honored at his shul&#8217;s annual dinner, it was not surprising that the Al-Qaeda connection got top billing from everyone who spoke when it came to saying something funny.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: H Sragow		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/24/peter-beinhart-on-his-orthodox-affiliation/#comment-1050</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[H Sragow]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2010 10:57:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1351#comment-1050</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It would be fascinating to survey some Orthodox synagogues to see what proportion of their population shares Beinhart&#039;s values and approach to Orthodoxy (in the closet or not).  I suspect that a) it is a sizable proportion of many synagogues, and b) the spiritual leaders of those shuls -- not realizing how much of it exists -- generally under-cater to the needs of that portion of the population.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It would be fascinating to survey some Orthodox synagogues to see what proportion of their population shares Beinhart&#8217;s values and approach to Orthodoxy (in the closet or not).  I suspect that a) it is a sizable proportion of many synagogues, and b) the spiritual leaders of those shuls &#8212; not realizing how much of it exists &#8212; generally under-cater to the needs of that portion of the population.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/24/peter-beinhart-on-his-orthodox-affiliation/#comment-1049</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2010 04:36:20 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1351#comment-1049</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I have only met a handful of people like Peter Beinhart (a friend of my extended family) , who are attracted to Modern Orthodoxy for the reasons he describes. and then mostly in enclaves like Kesher and parts of Silver Spring, the UWS, and perhaps parts of LA. 

These people generally would not call themselves &quot;baalei teshuva&quot; nor do they fit that mold which generally involves 1) active recruitment or involvement in an official outreach program 2) some kind of soul searching/life crisis 3) a rejection of liberalism and liberal feminism  4) a somewhat naive commitment to an idealized hareidi ideology/mythology.

In the time that I&#039;ve been living off the coasts I have encountered an exploding population of people in this latter category, especially in places like Dallas and Detroit where hareidi revivalism is flourishing while modern Orthodoxy is struggling.

I&#039;m still waiting for someone to write a serious book on the modern BT movement which was started by  handful of charismatic rabbis and has become one of the major economic engines of the hareidi world. 

[By the way, Kesher actually has a quasi egalitarian minyan - the &quot;cookie minyan,&quot; where you will likely find many of Mr. Beinhart&#039;s friends davening/singing  with their young children with equal participation of both sexes and no mechitza. Not all of those people make it upstairs for the official service on a given shabbat.]]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have only met a handful of people like Peter Beinhart (a friend of my extended family) , who are attracted to Modern Orthodoxy for the reasons he describes. and then mostly in enclaves like Kesher and parts of Silver Spring, the UWS, and perhaps parts of LA. </p>
<p>These people generally would not call themselves &#8220;baalei teshuva&#8221; nor do they fit that mold which generally involves 1) active recruitment or involvement in an official outreach program 2) some kind of soul searching/life crisis 3) a rejection of liberalism and liberal feminism  4) a somewhat naive commitment to an idealized hareidi ideology/mythology.</p>
<p>In the time that I&#8217;ve been living off the coasts I have encountered an exploding population of people in this latter category, especially in places like Dallas and Detroit where hareidi revivalism is flourishing while modern Orthodoxy is struggling.</p>
<p>I&#8217;m still waiting for someone to write a serious book on the modern BT movement which was started by  handful of charismatic rabbis and has become one of the major economic engines of the hareidi world. </p>
<p>[By the way, Kesher actually has a quasi egalitarian minyan &#8211; the &#8220;cookie minyan,&#8221; where you will likely find many of Mr. Beinhart&#8217;s friends davening/singing  with their young children with equal participation of both sexes and no mechitza. Not all of those people make it upstairs for the official service on a given shabbat.]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
