<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: The Gulen Society as Modern Orthodox- Part One	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/02/the-gulan-society-as-modern-orthodox-part-one/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/02/the-gulan-society-as-modern-orthodox-part-one/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Nov 2010 13:19:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Joey Silver		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/02/the-gulan-society-as-modern-orthodox-part-one/#comment-2056</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joey Silver]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 28 Nov 2010 13:19:20 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1571#comment-2056</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This is facinating to me. I live in Jerusalem, where my best friend for over 30 years is a Hanafi Sunni Muslim who named his first son after me (Yusuf). I have been almost 80 times in Turkey in the last 15 years. I wear a kipa there without problem, and pray in a nearby mosque with kipa &#038; siddur if I&#039;m out and about at Mincha/Maariv times. Without ever having been the object of negative reactions. I have been asked, as I entered, whether I was touring. I always answer that I&#039;m Jewish, need a place to pray, and that the mosques are conducive to prayer. I&#039;m always warmly welcomed. Once, a man at the entrance to SultanAhmet, asked me to stay after prayer and we drank tea and discussed our mutual Faiths for over an hour (till I needed to doven Maariv). I then invited him to dinner, where we continued a very amicable conversation.  I find secular Turks less tolerant of religious Moslems,  and many Turks positively anti-Arab. 
How does one get contact with the Gulen Movement? Do they have any representation in Israel which could help counter the  growing Salafi (Saudi Wahabi) infiltration of formerly moderate Muslims?
It is wonderful to find that other Jews are furthering dialogue with Moderate Muslims (and there are many such, at least in Turkey and Israel, in my experience). Yasher Koach!]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is facinating to me. I live in Jerusalem, where my best friend for over 30 years is a Hanafi Sunni Muslim who named his first son after me (Yusuf). I have been almost 80 times in Turkey in the last 15 years. I wear a kipa there without problem, and pray in a nearby mosque with kipa &amp; siddur if I&#8217;m out and about at Mincha/Maariv times. Without ever having been the object of negative reactions. I have been asked, as I entered, whether I was touring. I always answer that I&#8217;m Jewish, need a place to pray, and that the mosques are conducive to prayer. I&#8217;m always warmly welcomed. Once, a man at the entrance to SultanAhmet, asked me to stay after prayer and we drank tea and discussed our mutual Faiths for over an hour (till I needed to doven Maariv). I then invited him to dinner, where we continued a very amicable conversation.  I find secular Turks less tolerant of religious Moslems,  and many Turks positively anti-Arab.<br />
How does one get contact with the Gulen Movement? Do they have any representation in Israel which could help counter the  growing Salafi (Saudi Wahabi) infiltration of formerly moderate Muslims?<br />
It is wonderful to find that other Jews are furthering dialogue with Moderate Muslims (and there are many such, at least in Turkey and Israel, in my experience). Yasher Koach!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/02/the-gulan-society-as-modern-orthodox-part-one/#comment-1289</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 09 Jul 2010 15:04:52 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1571#comment-1289</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/02/the-gulan-society-as-modern-orthodox-part-one/#comment-1288&quot;&gt;Yonatan&lt;/a&gt;.

Hanson&#039;s law is not generally accepted as applying to the last quarter of the 20th century. There are those who think it never worked such as Jonathan Sarna. And the Jewish application was the return of Jews to Jewish Centers in the 1950&#039;s after their socialist parents rejected religion.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/02/the-gulan-society-as-modern-orthodox-part-one/#comment-1288">Yonatan</a>.</p>
<p>Hanson&#8217;s law is not generally accepted as applying to the last quarter of the 20th century. There are those who think it never worked such as Jonathan Sarna. And the Jewish application was the return of Jews to Jewish Centers in the 1950&#8217;s after their socialist parents rejected religion.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Yonatan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/02/the-gulan-society-as-modern-orthodox-part-one/#comment-1288</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Yonatan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 09 Jul 2010 15:00:11 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1571#comment-1288</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[IMHO  are two questions here: 

1) The Gulens as a modern religious movement, which we can unpack using sociology, history, etc.

2) Whether this is a viable long term movement. The concern is that second and third generation will either follow Hanson&#039;s law and move towards &quot;Islamicism&quot; or Fundementalism or completely assimilate into something like liberal Christianity or Judaism, once they are financially established.

I believe that a discomfort that I and others may feel about the Gulen movement is that, based upon our experiences as Orthodox Jews, that many second and third generation Gulen followers will move towards the former.

However, that might be moot, as prosperity and culturally adjusting has a habit of moderating the more extreme elements of a religion. Cf. Teaneck.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>IMHO  are two questions here: </p>
<p>1) The Gulens as a modern religious movement, which we can unpack using sociology, history, etc.</p>
<p>2) Whether this is a viable long term movement. The concern is that second and third generation will either follow Hanson&#8217;s law and move towards &#8220;Islamicism&#8221; or Fundementalism or completely assimilate into something like liberal Christianity or Judaism, once they are financially established.</p>
<p>I believe that a discomfort that I and others may feel about the Gulen movement is that, based upon our experiences as Orthodox Jews, that many second and third generation Gulen followers will move towards the former.</p>
<p>However, that might be moot, as prosperity and culturally adjusting has a habit of moderating the more extreme elements of a religion. Cf. Teaneck.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/02/the-gulan-society-as-modern-orthodox-part-one/#comment-1269</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2010 14:16:32 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1571#comment-1269</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/02/the-gulan-society-as-modern-orthodox-part-one/#comment-1267&quot;&gt;H Sragow&lt;/a&gt;.

I know many 7th generation Reform who are religiously thriving. But Reform has a reason for not going back to the sources, Gulen thinks they are the full ritual tradition.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/02/the-gulan-society-as-modern-orthodox-part-one/#comment-1267">H Sragow</a>.</p>
<p>I know many 7th generation Reform who are religiously thriving. But Reform has a reason for not going back to the sources, Gulen thinks they are the full ritual tradition.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: H Sragow		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/02/the-gulan-society-as-modern-orthodox-part-one/#comment-1267</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[H Sragow]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2010 03:08:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1571#comment-1267</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Arie:

I&#039;m not sure I follow your expectation concerning the generation-over-generation course of religionists that are not familiar with the holy writings, prayers, etc.  As I understand the reports, Reform has been the largest stream in American Judaism for several decades, even as its adherents largely do not understand Hebrew.  And I know proud Reform Jews whose parents and great-grandparents were also Reform.   They neither &quot;moved to a path of greater growth&quot; nor &quot;dropped out.&quot;    

I see no reason the Gulen couldn&#039;t build a similar stream in Islam that lasts many generations.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Arie:</p>
<p>I&#8217;m not sure I follow your expectation concerning the generation-over-generation course of religionists that are not familiar with the holy writings, prayers, etc.  As I understand the reports, Reform has been the largest stream in American Judaism for several decades, even as its adherents largely do not understand Hebrew.  And I know proud Reform Jews whose parents and great-grandparents were also Reform.   They neither &#8220;moved to a path of greater growth&#8221; nor &#8220;dropped out.&#8221;    </p>
<p>I see no reason the Gulen couldn&#8217;t build a similar stream in Islam that lasts many generations.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/02/the-gulan-society-as-modern-orthodox-part-one/#comment-1247</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Jul 2010 11:26:51 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1571#comment-1247</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/02/the-gulan-society-as-modern-orthodox-part-one/#comment-1246&quot;&gt;Arie Folger&lt;/a&gt;.

That is why I think I have to take their Neo-Romantic Sufism more seriously. My Orthodox analogy may be mistaken. What they spend their time reading, and listening to as mp3&#039;s at work are the saying of Gulan himself. There is a charismatic element. They teach a romantic reading of sufism and of Islam. Sufism as peace, love, understanding, interfaith, purity of the heart, sincerity in what one does. I may have been mistaken to look at the Orthodox practice that flies in the face of Islamic reformers. Rather, I should look at the universal Islam- that has elements of Dewey and Goethe- as key object transmitted. They create an Islam in the heart working toward ethics. Maybe they should be Neo-Reformers who dont get involved in reforming the law and creating new Koranic , rather a group that might eventually walk away from the law? But their current strictness seems to belie that.
Maybe they are reform in their own way and will support social justice as their Islam. As it stands they give their entire &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zakat&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;annual zakat&lt;/a&gt; to the movement, rumors are that core members tithe up to 20 or 30% of their income to support the movement.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/02/the-gulan-society-as-modern-orthodox-part-one/#comment-1246">Arie Folger</a>.</p>
<p>That is why I think I have to take their Neo-Romantic Sufism more seriously. My Orthodox analogy may be mistaken. What they spend their time reading, and listening to as mp3&#8217;s at work are the saying of Gulan himself. There is a charismatic element. They teach a romantic reading of sufism and of Islam. Sufism as peace, love, understanding, interfaith, purity of the heart, sincerity in what one does. I may have been mistaken to look at the Orthodox practice that flies in the face of Islamic reformers. Rather, I should look at the universal Islam- that has elements of Dewey and Goethe- as key object transmitted. They create an Islam in the heart working toward ethics. Maybe they should be Neo-Reformers who dont get involved in reforming the law and creating new Koranic , rather a group that might eventually walk away from the law? But their current strictness seems to belie that.<br />
Maybe they are reform in their own way and will support social justice as their Islam. As it stands they give their entire <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zakat" rel="nofollow">annual zakat</a> to the movement, rumors are that core members tithe up to 20 or 30% of their income to support the movement.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Arie Folger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/02/the-gulan-society-as-modern-orthodox-part-one/#comment-1246</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arie Folger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Jul 2010 11:13:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1571#comment-1246</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/02/the-gulan-society-as-modern-orthodox-part-one/#comment-1245&quot;&gt;Alan Brill&lt;/a&gt;.

Yes, I am aware of the existence of such schools in Orthodox kehillot / Einheitsgemeinde /communautés consistoriales, etc.. And I see first hand the product of such schools, both students who attended Alliance schools before the War, and those who attend similar schools today. In fact, I attended such a school for a few months.

Based on direct observation I can tell you that such a system can work for a limited time, but after a while, it cannot maintain observance; without knowledge and practice, there is no motivation. What does someone who neither knows the order of prayers, nor their halakhic meaning, and who hardly speaks Hebrew, perhaps doesn&#039;t even read it, do in shul? Either he is on a path to greater growth, or he gets bored and drops out.

Since you describe the Gulen as observant, I would expect that this is a situation that is tenable for a few decades at most. Once the new generation (and in your other post you speak of a 50 year old) cannot read the language of its sources, it either becomes alienated to the right or to the left. Mimeticism alone cannot maintain identity forever in a foreign land / a minority culture.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/02/the-gulan-society-as-modern-orthodox-part-one/#comment-1245">Alan Brill</a>.</p>
<p>Yes, I am aware of the existence of such schools in Orthodox kehillot / Einheitsgemeinde /communautés consistoriales, etc.. And I see first hand the product of such schools, both students who attended Alliance schools before the War, and those who attend similar schools today. In fact, I attended such a school for a few months.</p>
<p>Based on direct observation I can tell you that such a system can work for a limited time, but after a while, it cannot maintain observance; without knowledge and practice, there is no motivation. What does someone who neither knows the order of prayers, nor their halakhic meaning, and who hardly speaks Hebrew, perhaps doesn&#8217;t even read it, do in shul? Either he is on a path to greater growth, or he gets bored and drops out.</p>
<p>Since you describe the Gulen as observant, I would expect that this is a situation that is tenable for a few decades at most. Once the new generation (and in your other post you speak of a 50 year old) cannot read the language of its sources, it either becomes alienated to the right or to the left. Mimeticism alone cannot maintain identity forever in a foreign land / a minority culture.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/02/the-gulan-society-as-modern-orthodox-part-one/#comment-1245</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Jul 2010 11:06:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1571#comment-1245</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Arie,
I am surprised at your surprise. Most Orthodox Jews of Western Europe had the same period or two of Judaism and that was enough for them to be part of the geminde kehiloh In some countries, the AIU schools offered a similar model, they created the French speaking traditional Jews throughout the Islamic world.
And in the US- this approach worked for Episcopalians for 200 years. 

A major part of a separate school is to overcome the sense of alienation, persecution, or need to either assimilate or form identity politics.

For example - see here on &lt;a href=&quot;http://muslimmatters.org/2010/07/05/the-challenge-of-anger-among-young-muslims-in-america/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Muslim kids dealing with Islamophobia. &lt;/a&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Islamophobia clearly seems to be playing a role in shaping the attitudes of young Muslims. According to one Zogby international poll, 75 percent of young Muslims said they or someone they know has been discriminated against
Young Muslims are responding differently to these pressures. Forty-seven percent of college-going young Muslims drink alcohol, while 16 percent engage in binge drinking; 29 percent of Muslim students in New York public schools sometimes use a non-Muslim name to get by. Some have changed their names to Christian names. A small number have joined urban gangs. Some have left Islam and some have become more religious.
These pressures and the resulting anger may explain why Muslim youth are the most disengaged among all the youth groups surveyed by Gallup when it comes to voting. Young Muslim Americans are the lowest percentage of any youth group registered to vote.
Almost 99 percent of Muslim children attend public schools. Only one percent attend an Islamic day school. About four percent attend some form of additional Islamic education like weekend schools which are mostly limited to 40 hours of instruction per year. Therefore, the place where almost all Muslim youth are found are in American schools, colleges, and universities&lt;/blockquote&gt;

So now you have me thinking that the way to measure their success is their ability for them to create a safe haven in a complex world- even if it is in different ways in NJ, Turkey, and Uzbekistan. 

The Gulen movement downplays all differences within Islam even between Sunni and Shiites. They dont seek to explain the differences just that they done matter and that they are minor.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Arie,<br />
I am surprised at your surprise. Most Orthodox Jews of Western Europe had the same period or two of Judaism and that was enough for them to be part of the geminde kehiloh In some countries, the AIU schools offered a similar model, they created the French speaking traditional Jews throughout the Islamic world.<br />
And in the US- this approach worked for Episcopalians for 200 years. </p>
<p>A major part of a separate school is to overcome the sense of alienation, persecution, or need to either assimilate or form identity politics.</p>
<p>For example &#8211; see here on <a href="http://muslimmatters.org/2010/07/05/the-challenge-of-anger-among-young-muslims-in-america/" rel="nofollow">Muslim kids dealing with Islamophobia. </a></p>
<blockquote><p>Islamophobia clearly seems to be playing a role in shaping the attitudes of young Muslims. According to one Zogby international poll, 75 percent of young Muslims said they or someone they know has been discriminated against<br />
Young Muslims are responding differently to these pressures. Forty-seven percent of college-going young Muslims drink alcohol, while 16 percent engage in binge drinking; 29 percent of Muslim students in New York public schools sometimes use a non-Muslim name to get by. Some have changed their names to Christian names. A small number have joined urban gangs. Some have left Islam and some have become more religious.<br />
These pressures and the resulting anger may explain why Muslim youth are the most disengaged among all the youth groups surveyed by Gallup when it comes to voting. Young Muslim Americans are the lowest percentage of any youth group registered to vote.<br />
Almost 99 percent of Muslim children attend public schools. Only one percent attend an Islamic day school. About four percent attend some form of additional Islamic education like weekend schools which are mostly limited to 40 hours of instruction per year. Therefore, the place where almost all Muslim youth are found are in American schools, colleges, and universities</p></blockquote>
<p>So now you have me thinking that the way to measure their success is their ability for them to create a safe haven in a complex world- even if it is in different ways in NJ, Turkey, and Uzbekistan. </p>
<p>The Gulen movement downplays all differences within Islam even between Sunni and Shiites. They dont seek to explain the differences just that they done matter and that they are minor.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Arie Folger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/02/the-gulan-society-as-modern-orthodox-part-one/#comment-1244</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arie Folger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Jul 2010 06:47:48 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1571#comment-1244</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Fascinating people. How do they expect to transmit religious practice over the long term, without really engaging in their texts more than an hour a week? How will they maintain access to those texts without adequate study of their traditional languages Turkish and Arabic? Or should we expect a swing to the right in the coming decade or two? And if so, what does that say about the possibility - or lack thereof - of making lasting interfaith contributions?

Separately, I wonder. In Judaism, it is fairly easy to identify some basic practices and beliefs that distinguish between the Orthodox and the non-Orthodox. Without getting into details, Torah min haShamayim and keeping Shabbat and kashrut are the major determinants of membership in the Orthodox community, even as there are large fringes of Orthodox affiliated people who do not practice the above three. Even though there are major differences between Orthodox subgroups, there is an understanding of who or what is Orthodox, which kind of works.

How is the situation in Islam? Do Gulen believe like the Shiites or the Sunnites? Is there, from the perspective delineated above, that great a difference between them? To use Jewish categories, are Shiites and Sunites in each other&#039;s eyes like Sadducees and Pharisees, or like Chassidim and Mitnagdim, or like Beit Shammai and Beit Hillel? How does that impact the Gulen, conidering that they are trying to deny being Sufis? Does this predict a swing to the right among Gulen?

I wonder in what measure Gulen is Islam&#039;s equivalent to MO for Orthodox Judaism. Is it in their similarity to us, or the similarity in the relationship between each group and its respective tradition? And given that the traditions are different, does it matter whether or not we each relate in a similar way to our respective traditions?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Fascinating people. How do they expect to transmit religious practice over the long term, without really engaging in their texts more than an hour a week? How will they maintain access to those texts without adequate study of their traditional languages Turkish and Arabic? Or should we expect a swing to the right in the coming decade or two? And if so, what does that say about the possibility &#8211; or lack thereof &#8211; of making lasting interfaith contributions?</p>
<p>Separately, I wonder. In Judaism, it is fairly easy to identify some basic practices and beliefs that distinguish between the Orthodox and the non-Orthodox. Without getting into details, Torah min haShamayim and keeping Shabbat and kashrut are the major determinants of membership in the Orthodox community, even as there are large fringes of Orthodox affiliated people who do not practice the above three. Even though there are major differences between Orthodox subgroups, there is an understanding of who or what is Orthodox, which kind of works.</p>
<p>How is the situation in Islam? Do Gulen believe like the Shiites or the Sunnites? Is there, from the perspective delineated above, that great a difference between them? To use Jewish categories, are Shiites and Sunites in each other&#8217;s eyes like Sadducees and Pharisees, or like Chassidim and Mitnagdim, or like Beit Shammai and Beit Hillel? How does that impact the Gulen, conidering that they are trying to deny being Sufis? Does this predict a swing to the right among Gulen?</p>
<p>I wonder in what measure Gulen is Islam&#8217;s equivalent to MO for Orthodox Judaism. Is it in their similarity to us, or the similarity in the relationship between each group and its respective tradition? And given that the traditions are different, does it matter whether or not we each relate in a similar way to our respective traditions?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Izgad		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/02/the-gulan-society-as-modern-orthodox-part-one/#comment-1239</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Izgad]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 04 Jul 2010 04:15:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1571#comment-1239</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[My inclination is to see the prax conservatism of the Gulen as a necessary component of their theological liberalism and what might allow it to function with any degree of credibility.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My inclination is to see the prax conservatism of the Gulen as a necessary component of their theological liberalism and what might allow it to function with any degree of credibility.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: An American Jew		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/02/the-gulan-society-as-modern-orthodox-part-one/#comment-1238</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[An American Jew]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 04 Jul 2010 02:18:58 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1571#comment-1238</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[They struck me as being more of our 1950&#039;s American generation. Wanting to fit in, live in the suburbs and keep a form of religion that is acceptable to all. Their Iftar interfaith dinners and trips to Turkey seem more like AIPAC in the early days before it go so politicized. They are looking for the American/Turkish dream the same way our parents sought the American dream in the 1950&#039;s and 1960&#039;s.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>They struck me as being more of our 1950&#8217;s American generation. Wanting to fit in, live in the suburbs and keep a form of religion that is acceptable to all. Their Iftar interfaith dinners and trips to Turkey seem more like AIPAC in the early days before it go so politicized. They are looking for the American/Turkish dream the same way our parents sought the American dream in the 1950&#8217;s and 1960&#8217;s.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Howard Sragow		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/02/the-gulan-society-as-modern-orthodox-part-one/#comment-1233</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Howard Sragow]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 03 Jul 2010 00:06:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1571#comment-1233</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[So in a sense, the Gulen are just as triumphalist and intolerant as their colleagues in the Sunni world.  

But the strategy of dominance through economic expansion seems to be a good fit for their ideology (intolerance has never seemed a problem for a religion&#039;s growth prospects).]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>So in a sense, the Gulen are just as triumphalist and intolerant as their colleagues in the Sunni world.  </p>
<p>But the strategy of dominance through economic expansion seems to be a good fit for their ideology (intolerance has never seemed a problem for a religion&#8217;s growth prospects).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/02/the-gulan-society-as-modern-orthodox-part-one/#comment-1229</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Jul 2010 19:53:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1571#comment-1229</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/02/the-gulan-society-as-modern-orthodox-part-one/#comment-1228&quot;&gt;Howard Sragow&lt;/a&gt;.

They will not be invited to the interfaith table by ordinarily Sunni. Since the Obama administration has recently  agreed to work with them on interfaith issues, we will see if they create difficulties for other Islamic participants.

They have little interest in other forms of Islam, they think the other forms are not suitable for our age. They tolerate them and dont enter into arguments about Islam. They are not modernizing but creating their own universal form of Islam. 
They have aspirations to bring their form of Islam to the Balkans, Caucasus, and Central Asian Republics.  They want to restore Turkish cultural hegemony. As Tom Friedman noted two weeks ago, they are currently doing so well economically that they are not looking for equality and acceptance of Turks in the EU, but economic hegemony over the Caucasus and Central Asian republics.  They are exporting a new form of Islam in addition to heavy goods and high tech.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/02/the-gulan-society-as-modern-orthodox-part-one/#comment-1228">Howard Sragow</a>.</p>
<p>They will not be invited to the interfaith table by ordinarily Sunni. Since the Obama administration has recently  agreed to work with them on interfaith issues, we will see if they create difficulties for other Islamic participants.</p>
<p>They have little interest in other forms of Islam, they think the other forms are not suitable for our age. They tolerate them and dont enter into arguments about Islam. They are not modernizing but creating their own universal form of Islam.<br />
They have aspirations to bring their form of Islam to the Balkans, Caucasus, and Central Asian Republics.  They want to restore Turkish cultural hegemony. As Tom Friedman noted two weeks ago, they are currently doing so well economically that they are not looking for equality and acceptance of Turks in the EU, but economic hegemony over the Caucasus and Central Asian republics.  They are exporting a new form of Islam in addition to heavy goods and high tech.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
