<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Three Hirschian Novelists	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/04/30/three-hirschian-novelists/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/04/30/three-hirschian-novelists/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Sep 2012 15:55:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Katamon Yifrah		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/04/30/three-hirschian-novelists/#comment-6773</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Katamon Yifrah]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 05 Sep 2012 15:55:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5049#comment-6773</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&lt;i&gt;Already, in a 1907 story, an orthodox university student leaves university for a few weeks at home with his extended Hirschian family, a philistine among philistines.  He sees the only ones who care about Zion, anti-semtiism, Torah, ideas, and Sinai are the college Orthodox students.

When I was in college, several of us found out about R. I.Breuer and were reading the essays that are in English translation.  But noone I know has any time or interest in that now.

Interesting that R. Breuer read Mann.  Mann&#039;s &quot;Buddenbrooks&quot; is an amazing portrait and critique of the pre-WWI German bourgeoisie.&lt;/i&gt;]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><i>Already, in a 1907 story, an orthodox university student leaves university for a few weeks at home with his extended Hirschian family, a philistine among philistines.  He sees the only ones who care about Zion, anti-semtiism, Torah, ideas, and Sinai are the college Orthodox students.</p>
<p>When I was in college, several of us found out about R. I.Breuer and were reading the essays that are in English translation.  But noone I know has any time or interest in that now.</p>
<p>Interesting that R. Breuer read Mann.  Mann&#8217;s &#8220;Buddenbrooks&#8221; is an amazing portrait and critique of the pre-WWI German bourgeoisie.</i></p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Pinchos Chalk		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/04/30/three-hirschian-novelists/#comment-6769</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pinchos Chalk]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 05 Sep 2012 04:36:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5049#comment-6769</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Pinchos Kohn is described as a life-long friend and adversary of Isaac Breuer, a nice description.

The description of his pinings for rural life is a bit disingenous. He did study kabbalah however, as did his father, and considered himself to be &#039;acharon le&#039;chasidei ashkenaz&#039;.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Pinchos Kohn is described as a life-long friend and adversary of Isaac Breuer, a nice description.</p>
<p>The description of his pinings for rural life is a bit disingenous. He did study kabbalah however, as did his father, and considered himself to be &#8216;acharon le&#8217;chasidei ashkenaz&#8217;.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Sarah Prais		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/04/30/three-hirschian-novelists/#comment-6550</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sarah Prais]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2012 14:09:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5049#comment-6550</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[If someone were in a position to translate previously Breuer&#039;s previosuly untranslated works, ie. they had the necessary German knowledge and translation skills, and familiarity with Breuer, his works and his context, who would publish the translation?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If someone were in a position to translate previously Breuer&#8217;s previosuly untranslated works, ie. they had the necessary German knowledge and translation skills, and familiarity with Breuer, his works and his context, who would publish the translation?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Lawrence Kaplan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/04/30/three-hirschian-novelists/#comment-4465</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lawrence Kaplan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 May 2012 15:20:32 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5049#comment-4465</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Much fascinating detail can be  found in Breuer&#039;s memoir Darki, translated  from the German. Jacob Rosenheim opposed R. Raphael Beuer&#039;s suceeding his father. R. Joseph Breuer, then the head of the Hirsh school, was not in the running. Rosenheim was a separatist, but, unlike the  Breuers, he did  not make it into an ikkar of emunah.  Rosenheim supported the idea of a union of all Orthodox rabbis in Germany, separatists  and non-separatists. R. Solmon Breur scotched the idea.  Isaac Breuer criticized  Rosenheim for being &quot;soft&quot; on non-separatism.  He also criticized  him and  R. Pinhas Kohen for not pushing Agudah to  take  an  activist stance re settling the land of Israel.   In his memoir he is much more  sharply critical of Rosenheim than Kohen, with whom he seems to have been friendly. The editors of Darki note that some harsh phrases were removed from the book at the  request of Breuer&#039;s widow. Given the book&#039;s sharpness as it stands, one can only imagine  what was removed!

The evidence that Breuer read Mann and Goethe comes from Kurzweil and Jacob Katz. One need not rely on Daphne Merkin. As Alan correctly noted, high culture is one thing, bourgeois values another.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Much fascinating detail can be  found in Breuer&#8217;s memoir Darki, translated  from the German. Jacob Rosenheim opposed R. Raphael Beuer&#8217;s suceeding his father. R. Joseph Breuer, then the head of the Hirsh school, was not in the running. Rosenheim was a separatist, but, unlike the  Breuers, he did  not make it into an ikkar of emunah.  Rosenheim supported the idea of a union of all Orthodox rabbis in Germany, separatists  and non-separatists. R. Solmon Breur scotched the idea.  Isaac Breuer criticized  Rosenheim for being &#8220;soft&#8221; on non-separatism.  He also criticized  him and  R. Pinhas Kohen for not pushing Agudah to  take  an  activist stance re settling the land of Israel.   In his memoir he is much more  sharply critical of Rosenheim than Kohen, with whom he seems to have been friendly. The editors of Darki note that some harsh phrases were removed from the book at the  request of Breuer&#8217;s widow. Given the book&#8217;s sharpness as it stands, one can only imagine  what was removed!</p>
<p>The evidence that Breuer read Mann and Goethe comes from Kurzweil and Jacob Katz. One need not rely on Daphne Merkin. As Alan correctly noted, high culture is one thing, bourgeois values another.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Yitzchak Schaffer (@yitznewton)		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/04/30/three-hirschian-novelists/#comment-4463</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Yitzchak Schaffer (@yitznewton)]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 May 2012 14:00:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5049#comment-4463</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Any of these available in translation? I actually bought one of I. Breuer&#039;s in German, but my German is next to negligible.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Any of these available in translation? I actually bought one of I. Breuer&#8217;s in German, but my German is next to negligible.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: yudel		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/04/30/three-hirschian-novelists/#comment-4459</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[yudel]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2012 22:42:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5049#comment-4459</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Funny, but my first reaction was: How quaint it was that men were writing modern Orthodox novels! Today it all seems to be women.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Funny, but my first reaction was: How quaint it was that men were writing modern Orthodox novels! Today it all seems to be women.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/04/30/three-hirschian-novelists/#comment-4458</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2012 19:26:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5049#comment-4458</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Selig Schachnowitz was older and Rosenheim took over as editor of ‘Der Israelit. Rosenheim was opposed to all who did not become Agudah. He and Breuer first fell over after WWI and then even more when Breuer made Aliyah.  Things got worse between the two families after WWII.

&lt;em&gt;Where did Pinchas Kohn daven when he was in Frankfort?&lt;/em&gt; With Breuer- they both worked on Breuer’s journal and Kohn was considered a Hirschian by everyone. There were many discussions and the journals preserve all the little positions and skirmishes.  There needs to be a conference based on the journal articles to sort it all out. 

&lt;em&gt; I am not clear how or if Isaac Breuer’s achievements were of the same historical significance.&lt;/em&gt; He created a model of the German Orthodox intellectual  and his definitions of Tideism are more widespread then the real Hirsch.

&lt;em&gt;As for attitudes to bourgeois life and secular culture, my impression is that Rosenheim in his newspaper was less strident than Isaac Breuer. Is this true?&lt;/em&gt;

Yes, but the ironies are that the Frankfort circle and Rav Dessler were just as strident.

&lt;em&gt; “Buddenbrooks” didn’t exist in a cultural vacuum. Was Isaac Breuer similar to Kurzweil, a connoisseur of German and modern culture?&lt;/em&gt;

Yes, very much so, but not as a synthesis. Mann shows the decadence and Torah is the eternal value that will return us to an ideal state in Zion.

&lt;em&gt; If yes, why is he ranting against those bourgeois Frankfort Jews who valued Goethe and Schiller?&lt;/em&gt;

It is the bourgeois elements that he hated- cramming for exams, professionalism, materialism. He like high culture and Avant Garde not mid-brow pretend to care. He also wanted this ideal Torah-state to appear.

&lt;em&gt;But Scholem in his review of The New Kuzari, (see Prof. Kaplan’s, comment to your 4/23 post), disparages Breuer for precisely the sins that Breuer is projecting onto his friends and neighbors in the kehila? &lt;/em&gt;

All the German Jews continued to bicker like Polish Hasidim in their new homes in Rehavia. But yes, Scholem has a point.  Scholem who was reading anti-nomianism, mysticism, surrealism in the 1930 would not consider a bildungsroman as Avant Garde.

&lt;em&gt;I mean complaining about Weimar Culture is itself an example of bourgeois Orthodox provincialism.&lt;/em&gt;

You said it!]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Selig Schachnowitz was older and Rosenheim took over as editor of ‘Der Israelit. Rosenheim was opposed to all who did not become Agudah. He and Breuer first fell over after WWI and then even more when Breuer made Aliyah.  Things got worse between the two families after WWII.</p>
<p><em>Where did Pinchas Kohn daven when he was in Frankfort?</em> With Breuer- they both worked on Breuer’s journal and Kohn was considered a Hirschian by everyone. There were many discussions and the journals preserve all the little positions and skirmishes.  There needs to be a conference based on the journal articles to sort it all out. </p>
<p><em> I am not clear how or if Isaac Breuer’s achievements were of the same historical significance.</em> He created a model of the German Orthodox intellectual  and his definitions of Tideism are more widespread then the real Hirsch.</p>
<p><em>As for attitudes to bourgeois life and secular culture, my impression is that Rosenheim in his newspaper was less strident than Isaac Breuer. Is this true?</em></p>
<p>Yes, but the ironies are that the Frankfort circle and Rav Dessler were just as strident.</p>
<p><em> “Buddenbrooks” didn’t exist in a cultural vacuum. Was Isaac Breuer similar to Kurzweil, a connoisseur of German and modern culture?</em></p>
<p>Yes, very much so, but not as a synthesis. Mann shows the decadence and Torah is the eternal value that will return us to an ideal state in Zion.</p>
<p><em> If yes, why is he ranting against those bourgeois Frankfort Jews who valued Goethe and Schiller?</em></p>
<p>It is the bourgeois elements that he hated- cramming for exams, professionalism, materialism. He like high culture and Avant Garde not mid-brow pretend to care. He also wanted this ideal Torah-state to appear.</p>
<p><em>But Scholem in his review of The New Kuzari, (see Prof. Kaplan’s, comment to your 4/23 post), disparages Breuer for precisely the sins that Breuer is projecting onto his friends and neighbors in the kehila? </em></p>
<p>All the German Jews continued to bicker like Polish Hasidim in their new homes in Rehavia. But yes, Scholem has a point.  Scholem who was reading anti-nomianism, mysticism, surrealism in the 1930 would not consider a bildungsroman as Avant Garde.</p>
<p><em>I mean complaining about Weimar Culture is itself an example of bourgeois Orthodox provincialism.</em></p>
<p>You said it!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/04/30/three-hirschian-novelists/#comment-4457</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2012 18:41:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5049#comment-4457</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I would like to have a better understanding how Sachanowitz, Rosenheim, R. Pinchas Kohn and R. Isaac Breuer interacted? I think Rosenheim opposed R. Joeseph Breuer succeeding his father  R.Shlomo Breuer in 1928, but I am not clear what  were the issues and where the others stood. Selig Schachnowitz was an editor of ‘Der Israelit. My impression is that R. Pinchas Kohn and Yaakov Rosenheim were tight, colleagues working for a common cause, but where was Isaac Breuer in this mix? (Did they talk, were they “broygiz”?) At some point the Breuer family stopped talking to the Rosenheims, or so I was told by a great-etc. grandchild of Hirsch, but when? As you say, Kohn looked to the older traditional South German Jewry and was no Hirschian; Rosenheim was, but maybe not in the Breuer way of Hirsch and only Hirsch. Where did Pinchas Kohn daven when he was in Frankfort? Were  there discussions printed in Frankfort about these  different perspectives? I feel Rosenheim and R. Pinchas Kohn were historically important Jewish personalities and public figures. They were instrumental in creating the Agudah, which in turn was an important player in the European Jewish world before the war, and in the development of charedi Orthodoxy after the war, especially here in America. I am not clear how or if Isaac Breuer’s achievements were of the same historical significance. 

As for attitudes to bourgeois life and secular culture, my impression is that Rosenheim in his newspaper was less strident than Isaac Breuer. Is this true? Some puzzles remain. Daphne Merkin in her eulogy of her mother Ursula Merkin in the Forward says “and my grandfather, Isaac Breuer, was as avid an appreciator of Thomas Mann’s “Buddenbrooks” as he was of Rashi’s commentary.” “Buddenbrooks” didn’t exist in a cultural vacuum. The Gerer Rebbe and Reb Elchanan Wasserman were not reading Thomas Mann with pleasure. Was Isaac Breuer similar to Kurzweil, a connoisseur of German and modern culture? If yes, why is he ranting against  those bourgeois Frankfort Jews who valued Goethe and Schiller? Maybe Daphne Merkin was just being naughty? But Scholem in his review of The New Kuzari, (see Prof. Kaplan’s, comment to your 4/23 post), disparages Breuer for precisely the sins that Breuer is projecting onto his friends and neighbors in the kehila? I would like to understand this “you are a bourgeois philistine” criticism. Was this a platitude of German Jewish self criticism? Was this a new idea whose referent was floating?  I mean complaining about Weimar Culture is itself an example of bourgeois Orthodox provincialism.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I would like to have a better understanding how Sachanowitz, Rosenheim, R. Pinchas Kohn and R. Isaac Breuer interacted? I think Rosenheim opposed R. Joeseph Breuer succeeding his father  R.Shlomo Breuer in 1928, but I am not clear what  were the issues and where the others stood. Selig Schachnowitz was an editor of ‘Der Israelit. My impression is that R. Pinchas Kohn and Yaakov Rosenheim were tight, colleagues working for a common cause, but where was Isaac Breuer in this mix? (Did they talk, were they “broygiz”?) At some point the Breuer family stopped talking to the Rosenheims, or so I was told by a great-etc. grandchild of Hirsch, but when? As you say, Kohn looked to the older traditional South German Jewry and was no Hirschian; Rosenheim was, but maybe not in the Breuer way of Hirsch and only Hirsch. Where did Pinchas Kohn daven when he was in Frankfort? Were  there discussions printed in Frankfort about these  different perspectives? I feel Rosenheim and R. Pinchas Kohn were historically important Jewish personalities and public figures. They were instrumental in creating the Agudah, which in turn was an important player in the European Jewish world before the war, and in the development of charedi Orthodoxy after the war, especially here in America. I am not clear how or if Isaac Breuer’s achievements were of the same historical significance. </p>
<p>As for attitudes to bourgeois life and secular culture, my impression is that Rosenheim in his newspaper was less strident than Isaac Breuer. Is this true? Some puzzles remain. Daphne Merkin in her eulogy of her mother Ursula Merkin in the Forward says “and my grandfather, Isaac Breuer, was as avid an appreciator of Thomas Mann’s “Buddenbrooks” as he was of Rashi’s commentary.” “Buddenbrooks” didn’t exist in a cultural vacuum. The Gerer Rebbe and Reb Elchanan Wasserman were not reading Thomas Mann with pleasure. Was Isaac Breuer similar to Kurzweil, a connoisseur of German and modern culture? If yes, why is he ranting against  those bourgeois Frankfort Jews who valued Goethe and Schiller? Maybe Daphne Merkin was just being naughty? But Scholem in his review of The New Kuzari, (see Prof. Kaplan’s, comment to your 4/23 post), disparages Breuer for precisely the sins that Breuer is projecting onto his friends and neighbors in the kehila? I would like to understand this “you are a bourgeois philistine” criticism. Was this a platitude of German Jewish self criticism? Was this a new idea whose referent was floating?  I mean complaining about Weimar Culture is itself an example of bourgeois Orthodox provincialism.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
