<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Leon Wieseltier on the Steinsaltz Talmud &#8211; 1989	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/11/07/leon-wieseltier-on-the-steinsaltz-talmud-1989/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/11/07/leon-wieseltier-on-the-steinsaltz-talmud-1989/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2010 18:21:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Lawrence Kaplan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/11/07/leon-wieseltier-on-the-steinsaltz-talmud-1989/#comment-1959</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lawrence Kaplan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2010 18:21:37 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2303#comment-1959</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Har Nof Academic: I agree with you that all the features you list are very positive  and make the  Steinsaltz Talmud very user friendly and helpful. I still find the commentary thin. I used  the Hebrew Steinsaltz with my son when he was in High School and over the years in my Talmud classes in McGill and I found  that the commentary rarely, if ever,  explains the logical connectives of the sugya , what  makes  the question a question,  why the answer is an answer. Any interesting questons I had were almost always unaddressed. I have switched in my classes to Art Scroll. I try to get my students  to use the Hebrew rather than the English Art Scroll, with --alas-- little success.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Har Nof Academic: I agree with you that all the features you list are very positive  and make the  Steinsaltz Talmud very user friendly and helpful. I still find the commentary thin. I used  the Hebrew Steinsaltz with my son when he was in High School and over the years in my Talmud classes in McGill and I found  that the commentary rarely, if ever,  explains the logical connectives of the sugya , what  makes  the question a question,  why the answer is an answer. Any interesting questons I had were almost always unaddressed. I have switched in my classes to Art Scroll. I try to get my students  to use the Hebrew rather than the English Art Scroll, with &#8211;alas&#8211; little success.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/11/07/leon-wieseltier-on-the-steinsaltz-talmud-1989/#comment-1929</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Nov 2010 14:40:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2303#comment-1929</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[So going from a world where a literate ehrliche yid pretty much learned a lot of chayei adam to one in which they are expected to be able to learn shas and rishonim over the course of 80 years is only OK if that happens without the use of crutches like Artscroll? 

Do you realize that the notion that in order to be a good Orthodox  Jew you had to be a full time yeshiva student who perhaps happens to have a day job is a rather recent development of our religion?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>So going from a world where a literate ehrliche yid pretty much learned a lot of chayei adam to one in which they are expected to be able to learn shas and rishonim over the course of 80 years is only OK if that happens without the use of crutches like Artscroll? </p>
<p>Do you realize that the notion that in order to be a good Orthodox  Jew you had to be a full time yeshiva student who perhaps happens to have a day job is a rather recent development of our religion?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Har Nof Academic		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/11/07/leon-wieseltier-on-the-steinsaltz-talmud-1989/#comment-1927</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Har Nof Academic]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Nov 2010 07:56:37 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2303#comment-1927</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As someone who has enjoyed the Steinsaltz Talmud for years, I must comment.

Wieseltier&#039;s article is inaccurate:

1) Rashi&#039;s comments were left in their spot- on the inside folio margins.
2) The author also implies that Tosafot was omitted - not true.

Wieseltier&#039;s criticism of the work not being &quot;academic&quot; is silly.  The goal of the project was to make the Talmud accessible to the masses.  

As far as calling him a &quot;guru,&quot; or the never-ending suspicious questioning of his background, I think his oeuvre speaks for itself.

Prof. Kaplan - what you call &quot;thin,&quot; I find appealing - Artscroll is too wordy.  Steinsaltz is concise, clear and readable.  The translation utilizes the aramaic roots of modern Hebrew words when possible, giving the learner an opportunity to develop his Talmudic vocabulary.

Hitherto, there has not been a decent review of the work.  In my estimation, here are some valuable contributions of the work:

1) Vocalization of the text
2) Paragraphing 
3) Rich material on the margins: history, biography, flora &#038; fauna, illustrations, textual variations, etc.
4) Clear and concise translation
5) Brief discussions of relevant halakha and citations of passages in Rambam and Shulchan Aruch
6) Introductions and Summaries of each Chapter
7) Indexes! (perhaps one of the most valuable contribution) - a scriptural index, an index of Tannaim &#038; Amoriam found in the Masechet,  and a topical index. (You can argue that with the Bar Ilan search, etc. today the index is unnecessary - but still important in my opinion).

With all of its benefits, unfortunately the Steinsaltz is not as popular as the newer translations - Artscroll and Oz V&#039;Hadar&#039;s Metivta. But it&#039;s easier to schlep with you on and Egged bus!

(site editor-please use an email next time, even an anon gmail)]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As someone who has enjoyed the Steinsaltz Talmud for years, I must comment.</p>
<p>Wieseltier&#8217;s article is inaccurate:</p>
<p>1) Rashi&#8217;s comments were left in their spot- on the inside folio margins.<br />
2) The author also implies that Tosafot was omitted &#8211; not true.</p>
<p>Wieseltier&#8217;s criticism of the work not being &#8220;academic&#8221; is silly.  The goal of the project was to make the Talmud accessible to the masses.  </p>
<p>As far as calling him a &#8220;guru,&#8221; or the never-ending suspicious questioning of his background, I think his oeuvre speaks for itself.</p>
<p>Prof. Kaplan &#8211; what you call &#8220;thin,&#8221; I find appealing &#8211; Artscroll is too wordy.  Steinsaltz is concise, clear and readable.  The translation utilizes the aramaic roots of modern Hebrew words when possible, giving the learner an opportunity to develop his Talmudic vocabulary.</p>
<p>Hitherto, there has not been a decent review of the work.  In my estimation, here are some valuable contributions of the work:</p>
<p>1) Vocalization of the text<br />
2) Paragraphing<br />
3) Rich material on the margins: history, biography, flora &amp; fauna, illustrations, textual variations, etc.<br />
4) Clear and concise translation<br />
5) Brief discussions of relevant halakha and citations of passages in Rambam and Shulchan Aruch<br />
6) Introductions and Summaries of each Chapter<br />
7) Indexes! (perhaps one of the most valuable contribution) &#8211; a scriptural index, an index of Tannaim &amp; Amoriam found in the Masechet,  and a topical index. (You can argue that with the Bar Ilan search, etc. today the index is unnecessary &#8211; but still important in my opinion).</p>
<p>With all of its benefits, unfortunately the Steinsaltz is not as popular as the newer translations &#8211; Artscroll and Oz V&#8217;Hadar&#8217;s Metivta. But it&#8217;s easier to schlep with you on and Egged bus!</p>
<p>(site editor-please use an email next time, even an anon gmail)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Steve Brizel		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/11/07/leon-wieseltier-on-the-steinsaltz-talmud-1989/#comment-1925</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Steve Brizel]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 09 Nov 2010 22:44:48 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2303#comment-1925</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Wieseltier&#039;s article is remarkably similar to Charedi attacks on both the Steinsalz and ArtScroll translations. Let&#039;s face reality-if one solely relies on ArtScroll without ever becoming textually literate in &quot;the real McCoy&quot; and being able to access and understand the views of  Rishonim, then ArtScroll and Steinsalz are both highly addictive crutches that will never enable the user to become a Ben Torah or Talmid Chacham. I recommend Halacha Brurah which retains Tzuras HaDaf, but which presents great summaries of the Rishonim and Acharonim on every sugya. 
It is important to remember that ArtScroll followed Steinsalz&#039;s entry after R Shach ZL placed R Steinsalz in cherem for his views on Biblical personalities and the JO published an article that was highly critical of R Steinsalz&#039;s views on Talmudic development. The haskamos to the early ArtScroll volumes refer Bderech Remez to the above controversies.  It should also be noted that Tradition also published an article and response about how the Steinsalz edition was unconventional in its analysis of a certain sugya in Bava Metzia.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Wieseltier&#8217;s article is remarkably similar to Charedi attacks on both the Steinsalz and ArtScroll translations. Let&#8217;s face reality-if one solely relies on ArtScroll without ever becoming textually literate in &#8220;the real McCoy&#8221; and being able to access and understand the views of  Rishonim, then ArtScroll and Steinsalz are both highly addictive crutches that will never enable the user to become a Ben Torah or Talmid Chacham. I recommend Halacha Brurah which retains Tzuras HaDaf, but which presents great summaries of the Rishonim and Acharonim on every sugya.<br />
It is important to remember that ArtScroll followed Steinsalz&#8217;s entry after R Shach ZL placed R Steinsalz in cherem for his views on Biblical personalities and the JO published an article that was highly critical of R Steinsalz&#8217;s views on Talmudic development. The haskamos to the early ArtScroll volumes refer Bderech Remez to the above controversies.  It should also be noted that Tradition also published an article and response about how the Steinsalz edition was unconventional in its analysis of a certain sugya in Bava Metzia.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/11/07/leon-wieseltier-on-the-steinsaltz-talmud-1989/#comment-1915</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2010 20:09:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2303#comment-1915</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Steinsaltz Talmud is a much more mysterious achievement than the Schottenstein Talmud, which in and of itself is sort of a unbelievable phenomenon. How did a baal teshuva who spent most of his younger life immersed in secular studies even think of undertaking such a project while still in his mid twenties? There is much we don’t know about this great man, Adin Steinsaltz. And needless to say Wiesltier with his know it all, prissy and condescending attitude is of absolutely no help. 
The mystery only increases if one reads the fascinating essay on the creation of the Schottenstein translation. http://www.printingthetalmud.org/essays/15.pdf
I want to add a few polemical points. 1)Both translations were conceived by chassidish people, Steinsaltz a Lubavitcher, and R. Hershel Goldwurm z”l, . When Goldwurm passed away much of the heavy lifting was done by R. Yisroel Simcha Schorr who also has close chassidish connections. Nosson Sherman is associated with Stolin. 2) The common thread of the circle of people who worked on the Schottenstein project is Bais Medrah Gevohah in Monsey circa 1950 -1970, and then the larger circle of Lakewood, the Mir etc. 3) These ‘’guys’’ illustrate a style of charedi Orthodoxy that formed  the larger cadre  that created the center of  charedi life in America…not totally Litvish like Philly, RJJ, Skokie or Lakewood and not totally chassidish like Satmar, Bobov etc., but conversant and comfortable with both groups, while being somewhat Americanized and educated. 4) This group already knew the mesechte with rishonim and the major achronim before they undertook the translation. I can’t imagine Steinsaltz knew Shas and its commentaries before he ever started. 5) Hershel Goldwurm deserves special mention. He was brilliant, very quick mind, sharp, heimish, a Belzer during the interregnum, a chassidesher lamdan of the highest caliber.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Steinsaltz Talmud is a much more mysterious achievement than the Schottenstein Talmud, which in and of itself is sort of a unbelievable phenomenon. How did a baal teshuva who spent most of his younger life immersed in secular studies even think of undertaking such a project while still in his mid twenties? There is much we don’t know about this great man, Adin Steinsaltz. And needless to say Wiesltier with his know it all, prissy and condescending attitude is of absolutely no help.<br />
The mystery only increases if one reads the fascinating essay on the creation of the Schottenstein translation. <a href="http://www.printingthetalmud.org/essays/15.pdf" rel="nofollow ugc">http://www.printingthetalmud.org/essays/15.pdf</a><br />
I want to add a few polemical points. 1)Both translations were conceived by chassidish people, Steinsaltz a Lubavitcher, and R. Hershel Goldwurm z”l, . When Goldwurm passed away much of the heavy lifting was done by R. Yisroel Simcha Schorr who also has close chassidish connections. Nosson Sherman is associated with Stolin. 2) The common thread of the circle of people who worked on the Schottenstein project is Bais Medrah Gevohah in Monsey circa 1950 -1970, and then the larger circle of Lakewood, the Mir etc. 3) These ‘’guys’’ illustrate a style of charedi Orthodoxy that formed  the larger cadre  that created the center of  charedi life in America…not totally Litvish like Philly, RJJ, Skokie or Lakewood and not totally chassidish like Satmar, Bobov etc., but conversant and comfortable with both groups, while being somewhat Americanized and educated. 4) This group already knew the mesechte with rishonim and the major achronim before they undertook the translation. I can’t imagine Steinsaltz knew Shas and its commentaries before he ever started. 5) Hershel Goldwurm deserves special mention. He was brilliant, very quick mind, sharp, heimish, a Belzer during the interregnum, a chassidesher lamdan of the highest caliber.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Yitz		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/11/07/leon-wieseltier-on-the-steinsaltz-talmud-1989/#comment-1914</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Yitz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2010 20:00:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2303#comment-1914</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[What are all your thoughts on the new mesivta (Oz Vehadar) gemmaras?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What are all your thoughts on the new mesivta (Oz Vehadar) gemmaras?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/11/07/leon-wieseltier-on-the-steinsaltz-talmud-1989/#comment-1913</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2010 19:57:13 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2303#comment-1913</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Artscroll followed the traditional model of naming the endeavor after the donors.  Steinsaltz naming the work after himself when he was really the editor invites that kind of criticism.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Artscroll followed the traditional model of naming the endeavor after the donors.  Steinsaltz naming the work after himself when he was really the editor invites that kind of criticism.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Pat		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/11/07/leon-wieseltier-on-the-steinsaltz-talmud-1989/#comment-1908</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pat]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2010 06:44:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2303#comment-1908</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Judging from the date and portion of the critique provided, it was assessing the Steinsaltz English Talmud, not the Hebrew Talmud being celebrated by the Global Day.  As a native Israeli, Steinsaltz has an impressive English vocabulary but his command of grammar was probably not good enough for him to do his own editing of an English edition.  So he indeed wrote the commentary -- it was the English translation of it that was not totally his own (although he surely had the last word on that as well). Also, who was on the supposed &quot;paid committee&quot; and what exactly were their roles--and their pay (as compared to, say, the reported 70 scholars who worked on the $21m Schottenstein?)  If making any use of research assistants or editors prevented characterizing a book (or commentary) as being authored by a single person, you&#039;d have to add a lot of names to a lot of books.   And hey -- I only see the name &quot;Leon Wieseltier&quot; on the review -- was he trying to tell us no &quot;paid committee&quot; of NYT editors reviewed it?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Judging from the date and portion of the critique provided, it was assessing the Steinsaltz English Talmud, not the Hebrew Talmud being celebrated by the Global Day.  As a native Israeli, Steinsaltz has an impressive English vocabulary but his command of grammar was probably not good enough for him to do his own editing of an English edition.  So he indeed wrote the commentary &#8212; it was the English translation of it that was not totally his own (although he surely had the last word on that as well). Also, who was on the supposed &#8220;paid committee&#8221; and what exactly were their roles&#8211;and their pay (as compared to, say, the reported 70 scholars who worked on the $21m Schottenstein?)  If making any use of research assistants or editors prevented characterizing a book (or commentary) as being authored by a single person, you&#8217;d have to add a lot of names to a lot of books.   And hey &#8212; I only see the name &#8220;Leon Wieseltier&#8221; on the review &#8212; was he trying to tell us no &#8220;paid committee&#8221; of NYT editors reviewed it?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/11/07/leon-wieseltier-on-the-steinsaltz-talmud-1989/#comment-1907</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2010 03:12:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2303#comment-1907</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/11/07/leon-wieseltier-on-the-steinsaltz-talmud-1989/#comment-1904&quot;&gt;Lawrence Kaplan&lt;/a&gt;.

Shamma Friedman, Essay on the Occasion of the Publication of a Hebrew Edition of the Art Scroll Talmud” (Hebrew), Badad 7 Bar Ilan University, (1998), pp.77-91.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/11/07/leon-wieseltier-on-the-steinsaltz-talmud-1989/#comment-1904">Lawrence Kaplan</a>.</p>
<p>Shamma Friedman, Essay on the Occasion of the Publication of a Hebrew Edition of the Art Scroll Talmud” (Hebrew), Badad 7 Bar Ilan University, (1998), pp.77-91.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Lawrence Kaplan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/11/07/leon-wieseltier-on-the-steinsaltz-talmud-1989/#comment-1904</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lawrence Kaplan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2010 00:57:33 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2303#comment-1904</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It would be worthwhile to compare the El Am Talmud on Berakhot with Art Scroll.

In BDD ,Vol. 7 I think, there is a review of the English and Hebrew Art Scroll on Berkahot by Prof Shama Friedman. It&#039;s generally quite positive.

I alway felt that Rabbi Steinsaltz&#039;s Hebrew commentary was rather thin.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It would be worthwhile to compare the El Am Talmud on Berakhot with Art Scroll.</p>
<p>In BDD ,Vol. 7 I think, there is a review of the English and Hebrew Art Scroll on Berkahot by Prof Shama Friedman. It&#8217;s generally quite positive.</p>
<p>I alway felt that Rabbi Steinsaltz&#8217;s Hebrew commentary was rather thin.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: tzvee		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/11/07/leon-wieseltier-on-the-steinsaltz-talmud-1989/#comment-1903</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tzvee]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2010 00:50:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2303#comment-1903</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I don&#039;t recall seeing a better Talmud commentary &quot;By LEON WIESELTIER&quot; published in the past 21 years.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I don&#8217;t recall seeing a better Talmud commentary &#8220;By LEON WIESELTIER&#8221; published in the past 21 years.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Jon		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/11/07/leon-wieseltier-on-the-steinsaltz-talmud-1989/#comment-1902</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jon]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 07 Nov 2010 18:18:15 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2303#comment-1902</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[What&#039;s the problem with Schottenstein?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What&#8217;s the problem with Schottenstein?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
