<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>blog &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/category/blog/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Apr 2010 18:59:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='kavvanah.wordpress.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/c9f111237f93750b6b994fc5185d49c3?s=96&#038;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>blog &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>The Best of the Theological Blogosphere in 2009 (and on&#8230;)</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/27/the-best-of-the-theological-blogosphere-in-2009-and-on/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/27/the-best-of-the-theological-blogosphere-in-2009-and-on/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Apr 2010 05:01:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1188</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[List that seems to be treated with respect at Resident Theologian&#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; All That To Say&#8230; — Mark Love is the Director of Missional Leadership at Rochester College in Michigan. As a former preacher and &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/27/the-best-of-the-theological-blogosphere-in-2009-and-on/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>List that seems to be treated with respect at <a href="http://resident-theology.blogspot.com/2010/04/best-of-theological-blogosphere-in-2009.html">Resident Theologian</a>&#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211;</p>
<div>
<a href="http://lovesramblings.blogspot.com/">All  That To Say&#8230;</a> — Mark Love is the Director of Missional Leadership  at Rochester College in Michigan. As a former preacher and professor at  Abilene Christian, and having just finished his PhD course work at  Luther, Mark&#8217;s experience and training give him a wonderfully creative  and playful approach to theology in general, and to reading biblical  texts in particular. Also, I stole my &#8220;Sunday Sabbath Poetry&#8221; series  from his &#8220;Dylan on a Sunday&#8221; series, which is hitting two years this  summer.</p>
<p><a href="http://itself.wordpress.com/">An und für sich</a> — Quite possibly  one of the most prolific and thoughtful group blogs around, especially  given that the authors aren&#8217;t getting paid. Adam Kotsko &amp; co. have  created an engaging place for philosophical, theological, cultural, and  textual conversations to be had; and Adam in particular is a kind of  blogging force of nature, routinely offering innovative and off-the-wall  comments and interpretations on any number of subjects. The snark rears  its head from time to time, but it&#8217;s usually in good fun. And even when  it&#8217;s not, it&#8217;s no less worth the read.</p>
<p><a href="http://churchandpomo.typepad.com/">The Church and   Postmodern Culture</a> — This one ebbs and flows, depending on recent  releases or engagement with particular works, but when it&#8217;s going, it&#8217;s  great. The contributors and books claimed and produced here are  especially noteworthy.</p>
<p><a href="http://nondefixi.blogspot.com/">Clavi Non Defixi</a> — Evan Kuehn,  though a long-time read for many, has been a recent discovery for me.  Evan focuses primarily on matters academic, journalistic, ecumenical,  historical-theological, and/or library-related. Though often reliable  enough as a purely compendious  source, Evan also offers constructive thoughts on a regular basis in  relation to current events in his fields of interest. I should also add  how impressive his levelheadedness is, given the waters he regularly  wades into.</p>
<p><a href="http://davidayres.blogspot.com/">David Ayres: Prayers &amp;  Poems</a> — David is a friend from Abilene Christian, and he&#8217;s just now finishing  up his undergraduate degree in Bible, on his way to an MDiv and a rich  ministry of the word. He also happens to be one of my favorite poets,  and it is a grateful marvel that such a gifted wordsmith is going into  full-time preaching.</p>
<p><a href="http://experimentaltheology.blogspot.com/">Experimental  Theology</a> — Richard Beck somehow finds the time in his busy schedule as a  husband, father, professor, teacher, researcher, speaker, writer, and  sometime-preacher not only to post on his blog daily, but to plan and execute complex, long-term series  exploring such extensive subjects as <a href="http://experimentaltheology.blogspot.com/2009/08/purity-and-defilement-part-1-mercy-and.html">purity  and defilement</a>, <a href="http://experimentaltheology.blogspot.com/2009/09/varieties-illusions-of-religious.html">religious  experience</a>, and the <a href="http://experimentaltheology.blogspot.com/2008/11/theology-of-calvin-and-hobbes-table-of.html">theology  of Calvin and Hobbes</a>. Though I regret not getting to know Richard  while in Abilene, it&#8217;s been wonderful sharing various conversations back  and forth since moving to Atlanta.</p>
<p><a href="http://faith-theology.blogspot.com/">Faith and Theology</a> — Ben  Myers&#8217; blog is the premier theological entry in the genre for good  reason. His easygoing, facilitator style creates space for conversation  and cross-pollination, serving as an exemplary model for the medium,  while his excerpts from papers and forays into constructive work are  exceptional. Not that he needs one from anyone, much less me, but F&amp;T comes with the highest recommendation.</p>
<p><a href="http://fireandrose.blogspot.com/">The  Fire and the Rose</a> — David Congdon, PhD student of systematics up at  Princeton, doesn&#8217;t blog a lot anymore; but when he does, it&#8217;s worth  reading.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.sojo.net/">God&#8217;s Politics</a> — Though the flurry of  posts bears weeding through, and I continue to have my worries that Jim  Wallis has become a soft spokesman for the Obama administration (and/or  thinks first in terms of &#8220;values&#8221; and &#8220;the global context&#8221; and not &#8220;the  church&#8221;), there is still a great deal of penetrating thought and  extraordinary work being done by, at, and through the Sojourners folks.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.inhabitatiodei.com/">Inhabitatio  Dei</a> — Halden&#8217;s blog is a warehouse of sincere ecclesial concern,  rich theological depth, unyielding rhetoric, and constant cultural  criticism. As it stands Halden is the regnant gadfly of the theological  blogosphere, and even when exaggerating or targeting someone or  something he deems blasphemous, his posts not only ensure you know where  you stand, but the force of  his arguments demands careful attention to one&#8217;s own and clarifies the importance of the  witness of the church in America. In other words, essential reading.</p>
<p><a href="http://forsclavigera.blogspot.com/">James  K.A. Smith</a> — Though I&#8217;ve been exposed to Dr. Smith&#8217;s work in myriad  ways, I haven&#8217;t had the opportunity to sit down and read a book of his  start to finish &#8212; a lack I hope to remedy soon &#8212; but it has been  enjoyable to be able to read him in short bursts online. (And it is an  overwhelming challenge to realize just how much out of his discipline,  including fiction and poetry, he reads!)</p>
<p><a href="http://www.joshuacase.net/">Joshua Case</a> — Josh is a  fellow MDiv student at Candler, and I enjoy telling him that he is wrong  on a regular basis. He is also an immensely talented thinker, writer,  networker, dreamer, speaker, minister, and podcaster. Universities and  seminaries prove their worth by creating space for people like Josh and I  to argue matters out, at the very least with respect, hopefully in  love. That has certainly been the case for us, and I&#8217;m glad to know the  kind of work Josh is doing is being done by the kind of person Josh is.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.michaeljgorman.net/">Michael  Gorman</a> — Sitting in Austin&#8217;s airport last January, I discovered to  my surprise and delight that Michael Gorman &#8212; the Michael Gorman, eminent New Testament scholar and  hero of my brother Garrett &#8212; had added me to his blogroll. I quickly  returned the favor, not simply as thanks, but because I had long been  reading Gorman&#8217;s work (both on and offline) and continue to appreciate  his various emphases in reading Paul, admiring his position vis-a-vis  the interlaced Hays-Wright-LTJ schools of thought. It is a strange, and  if anything a cool  academic/ecclesial world we inhabit, where scholars like Gorman take up  blogging. Hopefully others continue to follow suit.</p>
<p><a href="http://narrativeandontology.blogspot.com/">Narrative and  Ontology</a> — Philip Sumpter is an Old Testament PhD student in Germany with a  perpetual flow creative engagement of texts, the Psalms in particular,  as well as what seems like a wholesale intimacy with the work of Brevard  Childs. Good stuff here.</p>
<p><a href="http://pauljgriffiths.com/posts/">Paul J. Griffiths</a> — Clearly  the most erudite and learned spare-time blogger I am aware of, Griffiths&#8217; every-so-often posts &#8212; on  Catholicism, on Augustine, on literature, on politics &#8212; are simply  extraordinary fair.</p>
<p><a href="http://cruciality.wordpress.com/">Per Crucem ad Lucem</a> — Jason  Goroncy seems to me the most disciplined and unique blogger on offer: an  Australian Presbyterian minister and theologian, with expertise in P.T.  Forsyth and interests in cooking, the arts, and more. I enjoy  especially his &#8220;Monthly Bests&#8221; that update us on his reading, watching,  listening, eating forays. Fun, different, and always something new.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.leithart.com/">Peter  Leithart</a> — Leithart&#8217;s attention to the text and &#8212; not here a  contradiction! &#8212; theological readings thereof are unparalleled, and the  quick shots across the bow that constitute his postings are concise,  direct, and always on point. How are we so lucky that such a man blogs  on a near daily basis?</p>
<p><a href="http://preachermike.com/">Preacher Mike</a> — Mike Cope was the  preacher at Highland Church of Christ in Abilene for nearly two decades  before leaving the position last summer. I had the privilege of being a  member at Highland from 2004 to 2008, as well as both being a student in  a class taught my Mike at ACU  and taking a graduate course with Mike as a fellow student. Though God has graciously not called me to the pulpit, Mike  Cope proved to me simply through the patient gracefulness of his own  preaching that the proclaimed word continues to have power to shape  God&#8217;s people over time. My own understanding &#8212; and understanding is surely too weak a  word &#8212; of Scripture, proclamation, women&#8217;s roles, new creation, and the  mission of the church are all profoundly grounded in four sustained  years of attending to the weekly voice of Highland&#8217;s pulpit. That Mike  is no longer regularly preaching only means his other work, which most  certainly includes his blog, has more attention.</p>
<p><a href="http://rainandtherhinoceros.wordpress.com/">Rain and the   Rhinoceros</a> — Another excellent blogger who only resurfaces from time  to time, Ry Siggelkow (no less fake-sounding than his actual pseudonym,  R.O. Flyer) does great work and always commands attention when he  posts.</p>
<p><a href="http://jamesmccarty.wordpress.com/">Seeking  First The  Kingdom</a> — It has been an odd and unique pleasure to have  come to know Jimmy McCarty first by way of reading one another, and  then in person, and now in friendship. I first read him on Sojourners  more than a year and a half ago; we learned of one another&#8217;s blogs by  way of our respective engagements with torture and with the homeless;  then we discovered we each belonged to that strange American tradition  called the churches of Christ. Jimmy finished his M.A. at Claremont last  May, then moved here to Atlanta to begin his PhD in Religious Ethics at  Emory.</p>
<p><a href="http://theologyforum.wordpress.com/">Theology Forum</a> — This one  is run by Kent Eilers, Kyle Strobel, and Steve Duby, and from what I  can tell, attends to various theological topics from a decidedly  Reformed/Protestant perspective. There have been some rich discussions  here recently, and I always enjoy seeing a new post up, as I know I will  inevitably be learning something new.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.theopolitical.com/">Theopolitical</a> — Davey  Henreckson, PhD student at Notre Dame, keeps things straightforward and  on topic: intersections between theology, political theory, and  historical practice, usually in the form of reviewing or walking through  important books, never without personal or constructive comment. This  is an area of which I am supremely ignorant but in which I am extremely  interested, so Davey&#8217;s blog is an indispensable resource.</p>
<p><a href="http://penniman.blogspot.com/">Vita  Brevis</a> — I came to John Penniman&#8217;s blog by way of Evan&#8217;s link to his  unbelievably helpful <a href="http://penniman.blogspot.com/2009/09/how-to-get-accepted-to-theologyreligion.html">guide  to applying to PhD programs</a> &#8212; which, I will have you know, I  printed out and read twice over, with liberal underlining and  highlighting. (It is my field guide for this fall&#8217;s descent into  application hell.) Since then I&#8217;ve come to realize that I barely missed  John here at Candler (he left a year ago for Fordham), and have come  readily to enjoy his entries in historical theology, particularly of  late regarding the evolution of Roman primacy in relation to the  Catholic Church&#8217;s recent troubles.</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/27/the-best-of-the-theological-blogosphere-in-2009-and-on/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>After 7 and a half months.</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/24/after-7-and-a-half-months/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/24/after-7-and-a-half-months/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 25 Apr 2010 02:15:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1167</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Well, I have been blogging for longer than I expected. I had a medical virus this week and was ill so I did not post but people still showed up. No one emailed to to ask if I stopped blogging &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/24/after-7-and-a-half-months/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Well, I have been blogging for longer than I expected.</p>
<p>I had a medical virus this week and was ill so I did not post but people still showed up. No one emailed to to ask if I stopped blogging the way people did during autumn breaks. So this is good.</p>
<p><strong>Evaluation of posts after almost eight months.</strong></p>
<p>1] I post random clipped items that I read because people ask me what I find interesting on the web  They are almost always from blogs of other faiths or ethics. Now, there are new tools like “read something” to share articles but this seems to work fine. I tend to select lists. This is my cork board.</p>
<p>2] I post interfaith clippings of Jews or Jewish texts. These get steady hits and serve as a repository. These rarely get a publishable comment. (I don’t post the islamophobia and xenophobia.)</p>
<p>3] I post pieces on Jewish meditation, Zohar, and kabbalistic ritual. These are intermittent but always generate the most comments and the most personal emails.</p>
<p>4] I post long reviews of the most important theological works of the year. This has been the most surprisingly successful for determining if I have a book review to pitch to a journal and to determine if I have 1k or 8k words.  These are the works that usually don’t get reviewed on blogs because the book was too complex for this format.</p>
<p>5] Finally, I post sociological observations on the Orthodox community in comparison to the other faiths as it appears on my feed. These generate the most links on other blogs and the massive influx of temporary readers but are not my major concern. However, when I feel I have come up with something, then I do theme and variations for a while.</p>
<p>6] Every 2 months I look at the wide range of Jewish academic journals and download the pdfs. I do this to professionally keep up with the field but have not had time to comment on more than a few articles.</p>
<p><strong>Evaluation of the technical aspects of the blog</strong></p>
<p>a] I could arrange this in magazine format as five topics, wordpress allows that but this is working OK.</p>
<p>b] If anyone has any suggestions for widgets or plug-ins, then let me know. I have not found a good widget for finding old posts yet. The cloud does not yield a sufficient index.</p>
<p>c] I have gotten used to receiving my best discussions and comments by email. I did not think it would. On the other hand, phone calls are a bit much and I do not then have a printed record of the comments.</p>
<p>d] I have not upgraded yet for a memory increase to allow mp3s and video. I am debating if I want to do file hosting here or at itunes u channel.</p>
<p>e] I get the most hits on snow days. I get the least before Hag.</p>
<p>f] Only a handful of readers ever click through to links.</p>
<p>g] When you are kind enough to send me typos, I correct them in the text. I do not bother posting the list of typos.</p>
<p><strong>Any Suggestions?</strong></p>
<p><strong>On Book old and new</strong></p>
<p>I will be speaking and having a book signing at NYU-Bronfman Center this Monday April 26<sup>th</sup> at 6:30.</p>
<p>I will be speaking at DAVAR in Teaneck on MAY 8<sup>th</sup> after musaf, shalos seudot, and then book signing after havdalah.  Order book in advance at $48 and you can pick it up before shabbos.</p>
<p>Finally, my first volume had an orange color on top; I will make the second volume light blue, magenta, or green. But should I change the text at the bottom of the cover? Rambam hilkhot AZ had 4 font sizes and was attractive on the page. None of the standard Talmud editions for AZ have the same eye appeal.  Do any Rishonim have an attractive first page of AZ? Neither Meiri, Yeraim, nor anything by Mosad Harav Kook has better typography. Does it pay to switch? <strong>Should I keep the Rambam and just change title and color?</strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/24/after-7-and-a-half-months/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>5</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>List of Top Relgion Blogs</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/25/list-of-top-relgion-blogs/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/25/list-of-top-relgion-blogs/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2010 05:39:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=848</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[People regularly ask me what I read on the Web for these Evangelical, Catholic and Muslim trends.  The SSRC just published a study of the top relgious blogs, where most people are getting their information, which gets the most hits, &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/25/list-of-top-relgion-blogs/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>People regularly ask me what I read on the Web for these Evangelical, Catholic and Muslim trends.  The SSRC just published a study of the top relgious blogs, where most people are getting their information, which gets the most hits, and which have the most authority. For those looking to to expand their blog horizons, it is worth looking at the list. The article itself is less interesting for those already online.</p>
<p>Here is a <a href="http://blogs.ssrc.org/tif/religion-blogosphere/religion-blogosphere-a2/">list of the top blogs with one line descriptions and links.</a></p>
<p><a href="http://blogs.ssrc.org/tif/religion-blogosphere/religion-blogosphere-3/">Here is a discussion of how to judge what is on top- authority, hits. But at he bottom it has the blogs arranged by topic: Academic, Cultural, News, Political.</a> It also has a list of which blogs get the most comments.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/25/list-of-top-relgion-blogs/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rules for Comments</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/28/rules-for-comments/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/28/rules-for-comments/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2009 03:04:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=422</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I have received hits by the thousand this weekend that I did not expect because of two very different posts. I am posting some rules for comments and will eventually create a page for the rules. I have tried to &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/28/rules-for-comments/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have received hits by the thousand this weekend that I did not expect because of two very different posts. I am posting some rules for comments and will eventually create a page for the rules. I have tried to write these rules without getting anyone upset and have tried to avoid an overly harsh tone.</p>
<p>I aspire to an informed discussion that stays on topic as much as possible. I like comments that clarify the ideas, correct details, and offer important parallels. I also like comments that discuss the application of an idea to life.</p>
<p>Also since many of you have just showed up after three months, feel free to give substantive comments to older posts. I am still engaged with most of these topics.</p>
<p>First, I like the quote from Eleanor Roosevelt that goes like this: <strong>Great minds discuss ideas. Average minds discuss events. Small minds discuss people. </strong> So please comment on the ideas.</p>
<p>Second, I have little tolerance for basic questions: if you could answer your question with a quick trip to Wikipedia, a Google search, Stanford Encyclopedia of philosophy, or opening the Mishneh Berurah, then do so. I am not teaching a class here.</p>
<p>Third, the blog assumes that you read academic works, social theory, and Jewish texts. If you’re not an insider to the various discourses we participate in and you’re still interested in the topic, figure out a way to become more of an insider.</p>
<p>Fourth, no comments with an overly harsh tone, snark, or condescension to major authors. And no snappy reactions to the title of a post that has little to do with the content of the post.</p>
<p>Fifth, do not parachute in with a personal agenda or think that this is another place for  graffiti tagging with your 1 millionth comment of your personal view of the world. If you want a venue with unrestricted free speech where you can comment indefinitely and be cherished for the unique intellectual snowflake you undoubtedly are, then you definitely shouldn’t comment. (I admit this one is a bit harsh; I got caught in the string of similes.)</p>
<p>I allow comments in the hope that reader input will spur thinking in interesting directions. Answering basic questions or fielding snarky comments do not stimulate thinking.</p>
<p>If you find that the blog posts have spurred your thinking and believe you are able to return the favor in some way, then you should definitely comment.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/28/rules-for-comments/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Post is the name of a breakfast Cereal</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/27/post-is-the-name-of-a-breakfast-cereal/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/27/post-is-the-name-of-a-breakfast-cereal/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2009 23:03:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[books]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[popular religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[post-modern]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=411</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Post is the name of a cereal company that makes Raisin Bran, Honey Combs and Shredded Wheat. In 2006, they discontinued Post-Toasties, the brand of choice in summer camp. When I hear the prefix post-, I think of cereal. The &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/27/post-is-the-name-of-a-breakfast-cereal/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Post is the name of a cereal company that makes Raisin Bran, Honey Combs and Shredded Wheat. In 2006, they discontinued Post-Toasties, the brand of choice in summer camp. When I hear the prefix post-, I think of cereal.<br />
The latest infection of language is to call everything is post- and post-modern. People who want change apply it to every change they want and people who are against change call all change as post –modern. Simply things like the modern poetry of Rilke or the thought of Hegel can be called Post-modern by those who have not read/heard of them.<br />
People throw around terms indiscriminately. I do not like the term right and left- there has to be a description.  Right and left differ between decades and countries. I do not like it when the word existential is used as a synonym for emotional or important. Nor do I like it when hermeneutic, which means the horizons and assumptions that allow for interpretation, is used for exegesis. And I do not like when the word “unique,” which in Rav Soloveitchik means revelatory and outside of culture, is used for special.<br />
So here is a <a href="http://www.inhabitatiodei.com/2009/12/17/youre-not-post-anything-so-shut-the-hell-up/">little screed from another blog inhabitato dei,</a> with the expletives removed.</p>
<blockquote>
<h3>You’re not “post-“ anything so shut up!</h3>
<p>If there was one term I could actually effect a moratorium on I think it would have to be the phrase “post-”. But, since I can’t effect a moratorium, allow me to propose an axiom instead:<br />
Any conceptual position (theological, philosophical, etc.) that describes itself using the modifier “post-” is <em>never</em> actually “post-” anything in anything other than a temporal sense (and usually that’s not the case either).</p>
<p>Postmetaphysical? No. Postfoundationalist? No, you were never foundationalist to start with. Postliberal? No, you’re still liberal. Postmodern? Shut up, that’s just stupid. Post-postmodern? Kneecaps, meet baseball bat.</p>
<p>The only possible places where I can think of the term “post-” having any real usefulness are in the realms of architecture and art history. Insofar as it gets used by philosophers and theologians its just an attempt to short circuit an argument by pretending that the views you are attacking were a developmental stage you  went through when you were young and not quite as well read as you obviously are now. To call any view “post-” anything is just a masquerade alloying one to define your adversary as wrong, arcane, and naive from the outset.</p>
<p>In short, adopting the language of “post-” is unforgivably cheap and masks a lack of ability to actually make good arguments against things you want to criticize.</p></blockquote>
<p>There are indeed large cultural changes afoot. Gen Y- the Millennial are the most liberal generation alive and their immediate seniors gen X is the most conservative. And more importantly- Since the 1730&#8217;s, every 30-35 years American culture has dramatically shifted from liberal to conservative and back again. But describe it. Calling it post-modern is like the 1958 person saying &#8220;we cant kept kosher outside the house- we are modern&#8221; or the 2000 person saying &#8220;of course we are libertarian and not interested in high culture, are we dont seek religious experience, we are Orthodox.&#8221;  </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/27/post-is-the-name-of-a-breakfast-cereal/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Best of 2009 &#8211; theology</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/22/best-of-2009-theology/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/22/best-of-2009-theology/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Dec 2009 04:10:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ben myers]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=388</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Here are selections from list from a blog of a Protestant theology instructor. I like lists of good books.  I do not know if all the links carried over to this page. Best theology books of 2009 from Faith and &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/22/best-of-2009-theology/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here are selections from list from a blog of a Protestant theology instructor. I like lists of good books.  I do not know if all the links carried over to this page.<br />
<a href="http://faith-theology.blogspot.com/2009/12/best-books-of-2009.html" target="_blank">Best theology books of 2009</a> from <a href="http://www.google.com/reader/view/feed/http%3A%2F%2Ffaith-theology.blogspot.com%2Ffeeds%2Fposts%2Fdefault" target="_blank">Faith and Theology</a> by Ben Myers</p>
<ul>
<li>Theology: David Kelsey, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0664220525?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faithandtheol-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0664220525" target="_blank">Eccentric Existence: A Theological Anthropology</a>, 2 vols. (WJK)</li>
<li>Biblical studies (OT): John Goldingay, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0830825630?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faithandtheol-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0830825630" target="_blank">Old Testament Theology: Israel&#8217;s Life</a> (IVP)</li>
<li>Systematic theology: T. F. Torrance, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0830828915?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faithandtheol-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0830828915" target="_blank">Incarnation</a> and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0830828923?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faithandtheol-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0830828923" target="_blank">Atonement</a> (IVP)</li>
<li>Essay collection (single author): John Milbank, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1606081624?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faithandtheol-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=1606081624" target="_blank">The Future of Love: Essays in Political Theology</a> (Cascade)</li>
<li>Essay collection (multi-author): Oliver Crisp and Michael Rea (eds), <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0199203563?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faithandtheol-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0199203563" target="_blank">Analytic Theology: New Essays in the Philosophy of Theology</a> (Oxford UP)</li>
<li>Theological history: John Witte Jr., <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0521548241?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=faithandtheol-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0521548241" target="_blank">The Sins of the Fathers: The Law and Theology of Illegitimacy Reconsidered</a> (Cambridge UP)</li>
<li>Essay: Sarah Coakley, <a href="http://divinity.uchicago.edu/martycenter/publications/criterion/spring_09.pdf" target="_blank">&#8220;Is There a Future for Gender and Theology? On Gender, Contemplation, and the Systematic Task,&#8221;</a> Criterion 47:1 (2009)</li>
</ul>
<p>Anyone have any recommendations in Jewish thought?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/22/best-of-2009-theology/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>11</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Two Months</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/16/two-months/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/16/two-months/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2009 03:04:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[alan brill]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=262</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Well, I have managed to still be here after 2 months. I have learned that when I go away for a few days, I need to place a notice that I am away. I have learned that many people show &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/16/two-months/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Well, I have managed to still be here after 2 months.</p>
<p>I have learned that when I go away for a few days, I need to place a notice that I am away.</p>
<p>I have learned that many people show up Saturday night -after shabbat. Most people visit in the weekday evenings. I cannot usually guess what get the most hits. I expected the Trude Weiss Rosmarin post to get many hits and a friend even transcribed the entire article. But I would have not expected that the <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/19/david-nirenberg-on-the-jewish-muslim-relations-in-christian-spain/">David Nirenberg article</a> on Jewish-Muslim relations in Christian Spain to be one of big hits. On the other hand, I am quite surprised that no one is looking at the Novak posts <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/03/novak-social-contract-part-ii-of-iii-parts/">here </a>and <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/13/novak-natural-law-in-judiasm-part-1/">here</a>. I learned that <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/10/avot-ibn-ezra-and-being-a-mentch/">three book reviews from Haaretz </a>in a single post is too much. I also learned that if I announce<a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/05/catholic-jewish-interfaith-dialogue-timothy-m-dolan-and-arnold-m-eisen/"> a public event</a>, I find that readers will show up.</p>
<p>I will be teaching contemporary Jewish thought in the Spring, thinkers of the last 15 years. So even if people are not interested in Novak, you will hear more about Fishbane, Halbertal, Boyarin and others. And more on Sacks and Benedict. There will also be more Kabbalah and spirituality.</p>
<p>If you want to comment on a post then post it, dont send an email. But if you want to comment on the general content or to let me know you are out there,  and you are not already on weekly (or monthly) email contact feel free to drop me a line.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/16/two-months/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>One Month of the Blog</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/12/one-month-of-the-blog/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/12/one-month-of-the-blog/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2009 06:14:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=147</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I have been doing this for one month. I have posted more than I thought I would.  I received 80 hits after yom tov from 8-12 Sunday Oct 11. Most of my readers look at the blog in the early &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/12/one-month-of-the-blog/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have been doing this for one month.</p>
<p>I have posted more than I thought I would.  I received 80 hits after yom tov from 8-12 Sunday Oct 11. Most of my readers look at the blog in the early morning 6-9:30, or dinner time 5-8, or then nighttime 10-2Am. I have more hits on Saturday nights than on all day Friday.  I do not have a large office contingent looking at it during a cubicle lunch break- 1-2 PM.   Most people do not go to the links to look at the full versions of articles but are happy with my citations. But people do look at the related material not summarized on the site. Jewish posts get more hits than posts on general religion. More people are getting here through a wordpress product than a google product.  Finally, if you want to comment, then write a comment, not a personal email.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/12/one-month-of-the-blog/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
