<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Terror, Religion, and Liberal Thought- Richard Miller Part I	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/05/06/terror-religion-and-liberal-thought-richard-miller-part-i/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/05/06/terror-religion-and-liberal-thought-richard-miller-part-i/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 May 2011 20:00:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/05/06/terror-religion-and-liberal-thought-richard-miller-part-i/#comment-3049</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2011 20:00:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3521#comment-3049</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I don&#039;t have time to offer anything detailed, but here are a few points:

First, what is the problem that Miller is trying to address, it seems there are two, that a) liberals from outside the faith committed to pluralism cannot offer a critique of those guided by a particularistic faith or b) people within the faith ought to offer the same kind of critique that everyone outside the faith does based on universals? If, a) then see below, if b), so what? As a secular liberal I care that some religion lets universals in explicitly, or through a back door of &quot;meta halakhic concern&quot; or ignores it altogether as long as they are not harming anyone? If you really do care then you have assumed the stance of a particular kind liberalism where the lack of universal values within a religious culture makes it unworthy of respect, and at that point you have repudiated a). 

Second, it seems that Rawls  etc.  already give pretty good accounts of why pluralism has limits in the realm of public reason and how public discourse is necessary in shaping our shared intuitions. In that context intuitionism is just an everyday discursive practice, not an alternative metaethical position.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I don&#8217;t have time to offer anything detailed, but here are a few points:</p>
<p>First, what is the problem that Miller is trying to address, it seems there are two, that a) liberals from outside the faith committed to pluralism cannot offer a critique of those guided by a particularistic faith or b) people within the faith ought to offer the same kind of critique that everyone outside the faith does based on universals? If, a) then see below, if b), so what? As a secular liberal I care that some religion lets universals in explicitly, or through a back door of &#8220;meta halakhic concern&#8221; or ignores it altogether as long as they are not harming anyone? If you really do care then you have assumed the stance of a particular kind liberalism where the lack of universal values within a religious culture makes it unworthy of respect, and at that point you have repudiated a). </p>
<p>Second, it seems that Rawls  etc.  already give pretty good accounts of why pluralism has limits in the realm of public reason and how public discourse is necessary in shaping our shared intuitions. In that context intuitionism is just an everyday discursive practice, not an alternative metaethical position.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/05/06/terror-religion-and-liberal-thought-richard-miller-part-i/#comment-3047</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2011 21:09:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3521#comment-3047</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I paged through the Miller book per your recommendation, and not finding anything that caught my attention, I must confess to having relegated  it to book heaven or wherever old books go to rest. In my library it’s strict survival of the fittest, few exceptions allowed. I hope to benefit from your more attentive reading. My problem with the Miller book is that it looked to me like  a form of  intuitionism in the style of W.D. Ross. Ross simply gave a list of our obligations and left it at that. He assumed that we simply have some special faculty called Intuition for apprehending these truths, a view which is no longer at all obvious given all the new work on experimental ethics. Similar problems arise with natural law, mussar tivi, derech hasechel and all the rest of Jewish hand waving.  Besides even in ostensibly simple cases like the trolley problem, most everybody loses their bearings within 2-3 hypothetical cases.(See Frances Kamm’s Mortality, Morality v.1.)  So when all these rabbis say there is a morality that is prior to halacha, I agree, but I have no clear conviction what the rules and principles that constitute this morality  might be other than the simple mnemonic maxims like not to steal, murder and so on. We minimally need an account why  more particular moral beliefs are rational. Simply repeating that they are,  is a start, but not much of an argument.  
 
Looking at particular cases, what is wrong with a utilitarianism that gives greater weight  to ”our welfare” over those of outsiders,  a sort of aneeyei ircha gone haywire? After all discounting utilities in some way or other must indeed be rational in cases of justice between generations. If the well being of those alive many centuries from now count equally to our well being, ain ledavar sof, and we all are obligated to live forever at the subsistence level. There is no clear consensus to my knowledge on exactly how to discount the future. An intermediate case are those who live far away in a different nation? The answer how to treat the world poor is far from obvious, with no clear intuitions. ((http://www.amazon.com/Living-High-Letting-Die-Innocence/dp/0195108590/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&#038;ie=UTF8&#038;qid=1304882116&#038;sr=1-1) and the subsequent reviews of the book by Martha Nussbaum and many others.) OTOH,  “we” but not some of our charedi coreligionists, feel that within a society, nation, country there should be no discounting in favor of one’s own group. We accept a duty of fair play, and some charedim do not. The easiest way to handle these charedi views  is to argue and try to establish some form of contractualism,  which would then provide arguments that utilitarianism is incorrect as such; in which case  skewed utilitarianism (group egoism) would be also  obviously unacceptable. In addition, going down the contractualist road seems to me the only way to give any rational account why  moral principles have a priority over halacha. Just asserting the existence of an outside impartial framework of morality and leaving it at that is lame. It’s even more complicated because we do have to provide a space for halacha within this moral framework.

When charedim steal from each other they don’t justify their behavior by adopting some nihilist or relativist view…e.g. who says stealing is wrong? Their problem is to feel bound to the society at large, considering that even if America is basically a just society, there is so much inequality and waste, it might be similar enough to life in some failed state or to the draft under the Czar. My hunch is that Scanlon’s version of contractualism would work best in an Orthodox context. A good summary of Scanlon’s views can be found here: http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/contractualism/]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I paged through the Miller book per your recommendation, and not finding anything that caught my attention, I must confess to having relegated  it to book heaven or wherever old books go to rest. In my library it’s strict survival of the fittest, few exceptions allowed. I hope to benefit from your more attentive reading. My problem with the Miller book is that it looked to me like  a form of  intuitionism in the style of W.D. Ross. Ross simply gave a list of our obligations and left it at that. He assumed that we simply have some special faculty called Intuition for apprehending these truths, a view which is no longer at all obvious given all the new work on experimental ethics. Similar problems arise with natural law, mussar tivi, derech hasechel and all the rest of Jewish hand waving.  Besides even in ostensibly simple cases like the trolley problem, most everybody loses their bearings within 2-3 hypothetical cases.(See Frances Kamm’s Mortality, Morality v.1.)  So when all these rabbis say there is a morality that is prior to halacha, I agree, but I have no clear conviction what the rules and principles that constitute this morality  might be other than the simple mnemonic maxims like not to steal, murder and so on. We minimally need an account why  more particular moral beliefs are rational. Simply repeating that they are,  is a start, but not much of an argument.  </p>
<p>Looking at particular cases, what is wrong with a utilitarianism that gives greater weight  to ”our welfare” over those of outsiders,  a sort of aneeyei ircha gone haywire? After all discounting utilities in some way or other must indeed be rational in cases of justice between generations. If the well being of those alive many centuries from now count equally to our well being, ain ledavar sof, and we all are obligated to live forever at the subsistence level. There is no clear consensus to my knowledge on exactly how to discount the future. An intermediate case are those who live far away in a different nation? The answer how to treat the world poor is far from obvious, with no clear intuitions. ((<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Living-High-Letting-Die-Innocence/dp/0195108590/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&#038;ie=UTF8&#038;qid=1304882116&#038;sr=1-1" rel="nofollow ugc">http://www.amazon.com/Living-High-Letting-Die-Innocence/dp/0195108590/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&#038;ie=UTF8&#038;qid=1304882116&#038;sr=1-1</a>) and the subsequent reviews of the book by Martha Nussbaum and many others.) OTOH,  “we” but not some of our charedi coreligionists, feel that within a society, nation, country there should be no discounting in favor of one’s own group. We accept a duty of fair play, and some charedim do not. The easiest way to handle these charedi views  is to argue and try to establish some form of contractualism,  which would then provide arguments that utilitarianism is incorrect as such; in which case  skewed utilitarianism (group egoism) would be also  obviously unacceptable. In addition, going down the contractualist road seems to me the only way to give any rational account why  moral principles have a priority over halacha. Just asserting the existence of an outside impartial framework of morality and leaving it at that is lame. It’s even more complicated because we do have to provide a space for halacha within this moral framework.</p>
<p>When charedim steal from each other they don’t justify their behavior by adopting some nihilist or relativist view…e.g. who says stealing is wrong? Their problem is to feel bound to the society at large, considering that even if America is basically a just society, there is so much inequality and waste, it might be similar enough to life in some failed state or to the draft under the Czar. My hunch is that Scanlon’s version of contractualism would work best in an Orthodox context. A good summary of Scanlon’s views can be found here: <a href="http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/contractualism/" rel="nofollow ugc">http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/contractualism/</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/05/06/terror-religion-and-liberal-thought-richard-miller-part-i/#comment-3044</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2011 23:24:48 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3521#comment-3044</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Not primary and secondary or ethics and law, rather a fundamental ethical intuition as natural law, or mizvot shikliot, or mussar tivi or derekh hashechel of Saadayah, Rabbis Hirsch, Kook, and Hertz, or rambam. One cannot enter into a closed scriptural universe without the universal ethical. Miller wants to keep the legal and religious discussion from losing its bearing, he wants us to still be able to judge if they have lost their bearing, and he wants to locate where it loses its bearing.  Midrashim that paint Edom or Moav as ethically depraved dont speak with a multicultural voice and say that in their culture murder is accepted so we have to accept it. Miller wants a universal moment. 
He also puts his finger on the exact moments when we lose the moral train of thought and start condemning the other side for reduction of the tradition.

Maimonides codified the laws of slavery and stated that the law allows x, y,z- nevertheless he ended the section by stating there there are also moral universals of the &quot;ways of the pious&quot; and the &quot;ways of the wise.&quot;
&quot;The way of the pious and the ways of the wise is to be compassionate and to pursue justice, not to overburden or oppress a slave, and to provide them from every dish and every drink. The early sages would give their slaves from every dish on their table. They would feed their servants before sitting to their own meals... Slaves may not be maltreated of offended - the law destined them for service, not for humiliation. Do not shout at them or be angry with them, but hear them out.&quot;]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Not primary and secondary or ethics and law, rather a fundamental ethical intuition as natural law, or mizvot shikliot, or mussar tivi or derekh hashechel of Saadayah, Rabbis Hirsch, Kook, and Hertz, or rambam. One cannot enter into a closed scriptural universe without the universal ethical. Miller wants to keep the legal and religious discussion from losing its bearing, he wants us to still be able to judge if they have lost their bearing, and he wants to locate where it loses its bearing.  Midrashim that paint Edom or Moav as ethically depraved dont speak with a multicultural voice and say that in their culture murder is accepted so we have to accept it. Miller wants a universal moment.<br />
He also puts his finger on the exact moments when we lose the moral train of thought and start condemning the other side for reduction of the tradition.</p>
<p>Maimonides codified the laws of slavery and stated that the law allows x, y,z- nevertheless he ended the section by stating there there are also moral universals of the &#8220;ways of the pious&#8221; and the &#8220;ways of the wise.&#8221;<br />
&#8220;The way of the pious and the ways of the wise is to be compassionate and to pursue justice, not to overburden or oppress a slave, and to provide them from every dish and every drink. The early sages would give their slaves from every dish on their table. They would feed their servants before sitting to their own meals&#8230; Slaves may not be maltreated of offended &#8211; the law destined them for service, not for humiliation. Do not shout at them or be angry with them, but hear them out.&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Larry Yudelson		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/05/06/terror-religion-and-liberal-thought-richard-miller-part-i/#comment-3043</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Larry Yudelson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2011 23:06:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3521#comment-3043</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Let me try an interpretation of what I understand him to be saying, based on your presentation.

Miller is calling for the problems of religion to be responded to by making ethics primary and other concerns secondary. (One can hear the argument: Isn&#039;t it unethical to make ethics a secondary consideration? Hence, this approach.)

Defending religion against bin Laden by arguing that bin Laden isn&#039;t truly religious fails to reflect proper emotional ethical response to bin Laden. (It&#039;s also an example of the True Scotsman fallacy.)

Chapter two is much more problematic from a Jewish perspective, because it insists the argument be carried out on the basis of ethics. We do not kill Amelekite babies because it is wrong to do so, not because of incidental problems of identifying them. This is problematic for traditional Judaism because the Talmud assiduously avoids ethically rejecting immoral Biblical precepts, even as it overturns them. Rav Aharon is being Talmudic in his rejection of the Jim Crow rabbis of Tzfat. Miller seems to be arguing that there is an ethical obligation to speak out for ethics, and bring ethics into the discourse, even if it has not previously been there. 

The problem with this is does one&#039;s ethics apply to one&#039;s language, or to the effect of one&#039;s language? Should Rav Lichestein use language designed to appeal to the amoral Orthodox middle, rather than ethical language that is in fact a red flag of treif to much of the community? Can one separate one&#039;s ethical obligations from their consequences?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Let me try an interpretation of what I understand him to be saying, based on your presentation.</p>
<p>Miller is calling for the problems of religion to be responded to by making ethics primary and other concerns secondary. (One can hear the argument: Isn&#8217;t it unethical to make ethics a secondary consideration? Hence, this approach.)</p>
<p>Defending religion against bin Laden by arguing that bin Laden isn&#8217;t truly religious fails to reflect proper emotional ethical response to bin Laden. (It&#8217;s also an example of the True Scotsman fallacy.)</p>
<p>Chapter two is much more problematic from a Jewish perspective, because it insists the argument be carried out on the basis of ethics. We do not kill Amelekite babies because it is wrong to do so, not because of incidental problems of identifying them. This is problematic for traditional Judaism because the Talmud assiduously avoids ethically rejecting immoral Biblical precepts, even as it overturns them. Rav Aharon is being Talmudic in his rejection of the Jim Crow rabbis of Tzfat. Miller seems to be arguing that there is an ethical obligation to speak out for ethics, and bring ethics into the discourse, even if it has not previously been there. </p>
<p>The problem with this is does one&#8217;s ethics apply to one&#8217;s language, or to the effect of one&#8217;s language? Should Rav Lichestein use language designed to appeal to the amoral Orthodox middle, rather than ethical language that is in fact a red flag of treif to much of the community? Can one separate one&#8217;s ethical obligations from their consequences?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
