<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>avi chai &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/tag/avi-chai/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2010 22:52:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='kavvanah.wordpress.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/c9f111237f93750b6b994fc5185d49c3?s=96&#038;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>avi chai &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>A Continuous Judaism Between Halakhah and Hiloni by Elchanan Shilo</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/01/a-continuous-judaism-between-halakhah-and-hiloni-by-elhanan-shilo/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/01/a-continuous-judaism-between-halakhah-and-hiloni-by-elhanan-shilo/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Jun 2010 04:27:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[religious zionism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sociology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[avi chai]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[dati hiloni]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[elhanan shilo]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[makor rishon]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1438</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Here is an article By Elchanan Shilo, “A Continuous Judaism between halakhah and Hiloni” that appeared in the Shabbat Supplement of Mekor Rishon on May 7 2010 and it has been posted on Tzav Pius (One of the many inscrutable &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/01/a-continuous-judaism-between-halakhah-and-hiloni-by-elhanan-shilo/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here is an article By Elchanan Shilo, “A Continuous Judaism between halakhah and Hiloni” that appeared in the Shabbat Supplement of  Mekor Rishon on  May 7 2010 <a href="http://www.tzavpius.org.il/node/413">and it has been posted on Tzav Pius</a> (One of the many inscrutable projects of the Avi  Chai Foundation.)<br />
It is an interesting article and brings together many ideas currently floating around. Yet, I am not sure if he is not just recreating 1920’s Conservative Judaism  or a European Geminde system. Nor am I sure that all the parts of his argument work together. Shilo, who teaches Jewish thought, wants to undo the division between those who keep halakhah and those who pick and choose. <strong>He brings together those who are halakhic, with those who pick and choose, and he includes in his expanded approach both those who only occasionally find something that speaks to them in Judaism and those leaving halakhic oservance.</strong> Here is a freehand summary and paraphrase of selected lines and an even more freehand translation of key lines.</p>
<blockquote><p><strong>A Continuous Judaism Between Halakhah and Hiloni by Elchanan Shilo</strong></p>
<p><strong>“The time has come to stop building bridges between the religious and the secular and instead to create a new wider existence.</strong> The religious Zionist community, whose strength is enough for both sides, is capable of building this expanse in order to break the divisions of the past.”</p>
<p>Modernity brought (1)education (2)a bourgeois life (3) a halakhicification of Judaism.The first two are good. But the later creates a division between religious and secular. The division was originally encouraged for the pride of building an educated community who knew and kept halakhah. <strong>Now we need to erase the divide by mixed schools and individualized patterns of observance.</strong></p>
<p>We already have many people who have individualized approaches.  Some people find halakhah and the religious life stifling and not life enhancing , others find it fits perfectly and enhances their lives. Generally we are happy when people discover observance but we should understand that it does not fit everyone and we should accept that people regularly give up observance. People go back and forth. <strong>His solution is to prevent absolute secularization- and see the community as a very wide range of observances with people going both directions at all times. </strong> In this approach, the formerly frum (Datla”sh) who don’t fit into the secular world would remain comfortably part of religious world. (Datla”sh is at least 25 % of the religious Zionist community)</p>
<p>Shilo argues that his approach should not be confused with the liberalism of Reform and Conservative.  The later movements judged Orthodoxy as primitive and that they are progressive. They created a new ideology with justifications for none observance. Shilo wants a broad tent without any judgment or ideology. </p>
<p>He accepts the older American model of having a men’s section, a women’s section, and mixed section. No judging and no definite answer. Some people follow the halakhah and some people follow their need not to have a mehitza. {He emailed me to tell me that he thought these mixed pulpits still existed in the US. His American father remembers them. He did not know that they dont exist anymore.}</p>
<p>Liberal religious Zionist weddings have mixed dancing after the officials leave combining both halkhah and actual practice. But he asks why not has both separate and mixed dancing right from the start? Halakhah without ideology or non-observance of Halakhah without ideology wont topple the edifice. </p>
<p>There are no hard definitions of God’s will only soft ones that vary with the individual. <strong>Shilo advocates that we should turn to the writings of Rabbi Mordechai Leiner of Izbitz, the Mei Hashiloah.</strong> People can have different callings from God, some in the halakhah and some not in the halkhah. How do we know that God wants everyone to keep halakhah, maybe sometimes there is intentional sin for the sake of heaven or different paths for different people. </p>
<p>We don’t want to delegitimize Jews or close options. He advocates a practical Judaism or an actual Judaism or a realistic Judaism. <strong>Many people want to keep Shabbat and even love Shabbat but are not interested in the details of squeezing, mixing, or smoothing on the Sabbath</strong> Many just want to keep up the tradition or the family values.</p>
<p>A different case is that people can like Shabbat but also have normal sexual needs . They do not want to be told that it is the evil inclination, rather they want to enjoy sexuality and the Sabbath. They don’t want a dichotomy of either being part of the frum world or the secular world.<br />
Not keeping hair covering, going mixed swimming, and mixed dancing can be done without any ideology of either rejecting Orthodoxy or  forcing people into a social ghetto.</p>
<p><strong>The beit midrash should be open to all. And the criteria for how to study and what to study is not determined by halakhah but by relevance, interest, meaning  and poetics.</strong></p>
<p>People don’t want a Reform Shabbat in the synagogue they want a traditional Shabbat that they can mold to their own meaning.<br />
Halakhah has to stop fighting a radical secularism and secularist have got to stop fighting the halkahic world. A wide practical Jewish life can bring people together.</p></blockquote>
<p><strong>OK, so is this new or old? Feasible or not? Are all details worked out or are their dangling elements. Read the full Hebrew article and let me know if there is something that will catch on here or is it just a idea.</strong></p>
<p>Update with <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/03/response-by-rabbi-david-bigman-and-others-to-elchanan-shilo/">a response by Rabbi David Bigman.</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/01/a-continuous-judaism-between-halakhah-and-hiloni-by-elhanan-shilo/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Peter Beinart on Day Schools</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/25/peter-beinart-on-day-schools/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/25/peter-beinart-on-day-schools/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2010 03:13:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[avi chai]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[day schools]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[peter beinart]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1364</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Back in 1999, Beinart framed the rise of day schools as a rejection of the original acceptance of public school. The growth of Jewish Day Schools is an abandonment of the American public square. Beinart pointed out that the rise &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/25/peter-beinart-on-day-schools/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Back in 1999, Beinart framed the rise of day schools as a rejection of the original acceptance of public school. The growth of Jewish Day Schools is an abandonment of the American public square.</p>
<p>Beinart pointed out that the rise of day school had other factors than the obvious religious commitment.  Even though day schools were originally for ideologically driven Orthodox who have not totally integrated into America, Day Schools became a form of private school for those moving up the latter. </p>
<p>Now, it seems the drive for day schools is the ideological need to create an enclave, in many classes an upper middle class Orthodox enclave.  In this type of school, what counts? the education or the creation of the enclave?  Some families are clearly still interested in creating private schools better than the public schools while others no longer ask if the day school if better than the public school in social studies, English, arts, or college preparation.  Beinart reminds us to account for the role of the school in social mobility,class and caste. At the end of the twentieth century, day schools were “in” but the word “day school” may have had three different meanings- <strong>a prep school for Jews, a community school for identity, and a day school to create an enclave. </strong><a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/11/peripheral-vision/"> Studies done by Avi Chai</a> do not differentiate types of schools or factor in class and caste. (<a href="http://www.peje.org/docs/GrowthToronto.pdf">One of the decent studies available on the web</a>, which was done privately by Alex Pomson, shows that in Toronto day schools are not growing relative to population increase.)</p>
<p>Jews supported public school because it helped enforce the separation of Church and State.  Jews did   encourage Christian kids to go to pre-Vatican II Catholic and Protestant schools because it would not have helped their integration. In those days, thinking of America as a Christian country would have meant Jews are excluded. Now, Jews do not worry about the possibility if there are Christian schools that do not offer an American secular narrative  Jews do not worry about being outsiders. Nor do American Orthodox Jews currently worry about the possibility of Afrocentric, Muslim, Hindu, and Sikh private schools.</p>
<p>What  do day school parents feel about the melting pot? I would suspect that many are oblivious or against. Or it is only useful for everyone else. Do some of the parents see that if you exclude yourself from the socialization of the rest of the country then you start to look sectarian? Or if you accept the melting pot for viewing sports and listening to Lady Gaga, but not for social science thinking and historical narrative  then you create a hybridization that may not work in all contexts.  (In the full article, Beinhart cheers for the creation of the New-Jew HS in Boston as outside the box.)</p>
<p><a href="http:// http://www.theatlantic.com/past/issues/99oct/9910jewishschools.htm">Read full version of Beinart on Jewish schools here.</a></p>
<blockquote><p>Preparing children for &#8220;the general American environment&#8221; meant public education as both practice and ideology. &#8220;The public school,&#8221; says Alvin I. Schiff, the Irving I. Stone Distinguished Professor of Education at Yeshiva University, in New York, &#8220;was considered sacred, holy. It was the method and setting by which Jews could become Americans.&#8221;<br />
All the talk about Jewish identity may also obscure a less high-minded reason for the Jewish-school boom: as Jews have moved up the economic ladder, their commitment to public education has waned.<br />
&#8220;As the public schools have eroded,&#8221; Miller says, &#8220;we are no longer being compared so much to public schools as to other independents.&#8221; Jewish leaders argue that because Jews make up such a small proportion of the U.S. population, the growth of Jewish schools has no real impact on the overall health of American public education. But public schools rely more heavily on Jewish support than the numbers would suggest, in part because Jewish organizations, fearful of any breakdown of the wall between Church and State, have traditionally lobbied hard against school vouchers and other government aid to private schools. As awareness grows that voucher programs might benefit financially strapped Jewish schools, that opposition may diminish.<br />
Yet such parents, by choosing Jewish schools, are preparing their children to lead more observant, less assimilated lives than they do. Some even describe the phenomenon as an inversion of a practice in nineteenth-century Europe whereby parents would remain Jewish but baptize their children.<br />
Why a growing number of relatively secular Jewish parents are abandoning the education model of their youth is a topic of considerable debate within the organized Jewish world</p>
<p>THERE is another, even more sensitive issue lurking behind the Jewish-school phenomenon. Earlier generations of Jews, according to Eduardo Rauch, of the Jewish Theological Seminary, in New York, sent their children to public school not simply as a means of ascending into the middle class but as a show of national loyalty. Today, in contrast, parents are willing to consider Jewish schools in part because they no longer fear being viewed as outsiders. They take their integration into mainstream America as a given. But what if earlier generations were correct &#8212; that full equality in an overwhelmingly Christian country is, in fact, reliant on Jewish willingness to participate in a common system of education?<br />
In fact, when discussing issues like Afrocentrism and bilingual education, American Jewish leaders sometimes bemoan the demise of the melting-pot ideal in this country. Yet separate religious schools both rely on that demise and exacerbate it. The Orthodox community, for its part, has rarely celebrated the melting pot, and generally worries less about total acceptance by the broader culture. </p></blockquote>
<p>For our last discussion about day schools, see here- <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/11/catholic-schools-and-jewish-day-schools/">Catholic Schools and Jewish Day Schools.</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/25/peter-beinart-on-day-schools/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Key findings of the Avi Chai report on young Jewish leaders</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/12/key-findings-of-the-avi-chai-report-on-young-jewish-leaders/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/12/key-findings-of-the-avi-chai-report-on-young-jewish-leaders/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2010 03:49:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[popular religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sociology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[avi chai]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[joshua venture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[young jewish leaders]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1105</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Here is a sense of the ideology of the leaders of the new organizations and they will someday head the established ones. Any trends? Is it what you expected? Notice the day school graduates did not remain Orthodox, so that &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/12/key-findings-of-the-avi-chai-report-on-young-jewish-leaders/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here is a sense of the ideology of the leaders of the new organizations and they will someday head the established ones.<br />
Any trends? Is it what you expected? Notice the day school graduates did not remain Orthodox, so that Orthodox who have the Avi-Chai definition of leadership remains at the 10% mark. We expected already the lack of Antisemitism as a drive and a lack of us-them relationship with the world. So this means that those of you under 40 who do have the us-them divide may feel alienated from the community&#8217;s leaders.   </p>
<blockquote><p><a href="http:///blogs.jta.org/philanthropy/article/2010/04/12/1011534/key-findings-of-the-avi-chai-report-on-young-jewish-leaders">Key findings of the Avi Chai report on young Jewish leaders</a><br />
By Jacob Berkman · April 12, 2010</p>
<p>A team of six researchers studied Jews between the age of 22 and 40, who serve as Jewish leaders, which they defined as those who have spearheaded new Jewish initiatives, direct existing mainstream Jewish organizations or somehow are thought leaders or activists on Jewish endeavors.The researchers interviewed some 250 leaders across country, but claim to have identified more than 3,000 who might be considered young Jewish leaders.</p>
<p>Among the key findings</p>
<p>    * They do not feel threatened by Antisemitism.<br />
    * They prefer to reject us-them relationships with non-Jews and want to be inclusive of non-Jews in their programing.<br />
    * They hold strong views on the organized Jewish community and need for new ways of organizing it and are critical of federations, traditional synagogues and agencies that engage in protective activities.<br />
    * While many believe that most young Jewish leaders totally buck the mainstream of Judaism, the report suggests that a large segment actually involve themselves in those organizations such as Jewish federations, Friends of the IDF and AIPAC. &#8220;It&#8217;s not true they want nothing to do with traditional causes, especially those who are economically secure and relate to the networking core of traditional Jewish organizations.&#8221;<br />
    * Around 40 percent of Jewish leaders attended day school, only 10-11 percent of those are Orthodox.<br />
    * Two thirds attended Jewish summer camps.<br />
    * Half have spent more than four months of study in Israel.<br />
    * They believe that Jewish peoplehood means the celebration of diaspora Jewish culture that is rich, diverse and inclusive.<br />
    * Most do not see Israel as central to Jewish identity and peoplehood, and there is a broad range of how much criticism about Israel they can tolerate.</p></blockquote>
<p>On a similar note we have to congratulate Rabbi Ari Weiss of Uri L’Tzedek who won a Joshua Venture Grant. Uri L’Tzedek is defined as created to &#8220;engage, empower, and inspire the American Orthodox Jewish community to enact social change both within and beyond its own communal borders.&#8221; <a href="http://joshuaventuregroup.org/fellows">For the other 2010 winners- here.</a> <a href="joshuaventuregroup.org/fellows/alumni">For past years- here.</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/12/key-findings-of-the-avi-chai-report-on-young-jewish-leaders/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>6</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Peripheral Vision</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/11/peripheral-vision/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/11/peripheral-vision/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2009 05:30:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[sociology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[avi chai]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[day schools]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marvin Schick]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=15</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In the new &#8220;Census of Jewish Day Schools in the United States 2008-09&#8221; released this week by Marvin Schick We have the following statistic: Outside of New York and New Jersey, 47% of day school students are enrolled in non-Orthodox &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/11/peripheral-vision/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the new &#8220;Census of Jewish Day Schools in the United States 2008-09&#8221; released this week by Marvin Schick</p>
<p>We have the following statistic:</p>
<blockquote><p>Outside of New York and New Jersey, 47% of day school students are enrolled in non-Orthodox schools.</p></blockquote>
<p>Yet 83% of all day school students are in orthodox schools. It emphasizes again the role of regional differences and the enormous difference between center and periphery. The very image of a day school is different out of NY-NJ.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.avi-chai.org/Static/Binaries/Publications/Key_Findings_of_2008_09_Day_School_Census_Final.pdf" target="_self">Report</a></p>
<p>It was usually the same in most countries. In Congress Poland, Cracow had Yeshivot and Italian cultural influence, Lublin only had the yeshivot, while Podolia, the birthplace of Hasidism, was out of town. A major economic center, but culturally on the periphery.  Similarly in Spain, Castille was not the same as cultured Gerona. Many peripheries  were sources of new ideas.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/11/peripheral-vision/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
