<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Post Evangelical Roundtable and Orthodoxy	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/05/05/post-evangelical-roundtable-and-orthodoxy/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/05/05/post-evangelical-roundtable-and-orthodoxy/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 May 2011 17:30:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: rejewvenator		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/05/05/post-evangelical-roundtable-and-orthodoxy/#comment-3122</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[rejewvenator]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2011 17:30:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3513#comment-3122</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[You can&#039;t eat your cake and have it too. If the most important thing is right practices, it&#039;s inevitable that teachers will discourage difficult questions. After all honest engagement and struggle often subverts practice. 

The reality is that we don&#039;t have all the answers, and no faith does. The confrontation between uncertainty and the soul can be avoided, or embraced, but it cannot be resolved. The idea that we can be simple in our faith and loyal in our practices has much less traction today.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>You can&#8217;t eat your cake and have it too. If the most important thing is right practices, it&#8217;s inevitable that teachers will discourage difficult questions. After all honest engagement and struggle often subverts practice. </p>
<p>The reality is that we don&#8217;t have all the answers, and no faith does. The confrontation between uncertainty and the soul can be avoided, or embraced, but it cannot be resolved. The idea that we can be simple in our faith and loyal in our practices has much less traction today.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Arie Folger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/05/05/post-evangelical-roundtable-and-orthodoxy/#comment-3035</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arie Folger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2011 09:20:24 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3513#comment-3035</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The following is a remarkable paragraph: &lt;em&gt;I have five kids now, and my main desire for them is to avoid all the behavior-based Christianity I lived growing up. Yes, we teach them foundational, doctrinal things about why we believe what we believe, but ultimately my wife and I are trying to model an honest faith that is slathered in enough grace to give us freedom to wrestle with the tough questions.&lt;/em&gt;

I am not sure what he means with &quot;behavior-based Christianity,&quot; but clearly, Orthodox education includes socialization for following and internalizing Orthodox behavior. If he means that behavior should not be a soulless empty shell, but be anchored in solid faith, I definitely agree. But IO wonder, do I detect an atitude I often see in less committed Jewish families, of turning away from the behavioral bubble, claiming that by exposing the kids early on to public school and irreligious culture, their faith will be stronger, deeper and truer. Whoever makes it through that boot camp surely has a truer, deeper faith, but the numbers who won&#039;t get there are statistically most significant.

IOW, I can&#039;t imagine the solution being to throw the baby out with the bath water. If there is not enough faith, and behavior is mitzvat anashim milumada, then the solution isn&#039; to have less practice, but to have more faith talk.

OTOH, his remark about &quot;freedom to wrestle with the tough questions&quot; rings very true for us. Stories about teachers making students feel that tough questions are not welcome, are legion, and those are very damaging experiences.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The following is a remarkable paragraph: <em>I have five kids now, and my main desire for them is to avoid all the behavior-based Christianity I lived growing up. Yes, we teach them foundational, doctrinal things about why we believe what we believe, but ultimately my wife and I are trying to model an honest faith that is slathered in enough grace to give us freedom to wrestle with the tough questions.</em></p>
<p>I am not sure what he means with &#8220;behavior-based Christianity,&#8221; but clearly, Orthodox education includes socialization for following and internalizing Orthodox behavior. If he means that behavior should not be a soulless empty shell, but be anchored in solid faith, I definitely agree. But IO wonder, do I detect an atitude I often see in less committed Jewish families, of turning away from the behavioral bubble, claiming that by exposing the kids early on to public school and irreligious culture, their faith will be stronger, deeper and truer. Whoever makes it through that boot camp surely has a truer, deeper faith, but the numbers who won&#8217;t get there are statistically most significant.</p>
<p>IOW, I can&#8217;t imagine the solution being to throw the baby out with the bath water. If there is not enough faith, and behavior is mitzvat anashim milumada, then the solution isn&#8217; to have less practice, but to have more faith talk.</p>
<p>OTOH, his remark about &#8220;freedom to wrestle with the tough questions&#8221; rings very true for us. Stories about teachers making students feel that tough questions are not welcome, are legion, and those are very damaging experiences.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
