<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: The Evangelical Habitas or how to be Orthoprax	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/04/the-evangelical-habitas-or-how-to-be-orthoprax/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/04/the-evangelical-habitas-or-how-to-be-orthoprax/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 May 2010 19:16:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/04/the-evangelical-habitas-or-how-to-be-orthoprax/#comment-947</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2010 19:16:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1235#comment-947</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/04/the-evangelical-habitas-or-how-to-be-orthoprax/#comment-946&quot;&gt;AS&lt;/a&gt;.

let me try and unpack what you are saying. This may take another round.
The question is what are the various orthoprax speech patterns in the community? For example, I was recently reading about the evangelicals and one of the dividing lines in Christian rock is about the Christian faith of Bono and U2&#039;s religion. It is a different speech pattern to follow U2 say &quot;I still haven&#039;t found what I&#039;m looking for&quot; then to say &quot;I heard God&#039;s word in my heart.&quot;Both of them are weak metaphysical commitments and both are certain and corrigible forms of orthopraxy. That was your point, I think. But my point was that those who reject U2, the language of U2 is not orthoprax even if they still follow all the other precepts and praxis. My point in the little video provided was that in sociology we usually label the more &quot;ortho&quot; group as the orthoprax. 
For example, in the study of meditation - monastic life is called orthoprax. Do you adhere to the meditation practice? Someone who became more modern and no longer accepts the metaphysical parts of the practice is now less orthoprax. Even if they keep the original practice like the Dalai Lama, he is seen as an adapter or a syntheiszer, not as the orthoprax.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/04/the-evangelical-habitas-or-how-to-be-orthoprax/#comment-946">AS</a>.</p>
<p>let me try and unpack what you are saying. This may take another round.<br />
The question is what are the various orthoprax speech patterns in the community? For example, I was recently reading about the evangelicals and one of the dividing lines in Christian rock is about the Christian faith of Bono and U2&#8217;s religion. It is a different speech pattern to follow U2 say &#8220;I still haven&#8217;t found what I&#8217;m looking for&#8221; then to say &#8220;I heard God&#8217;s word in my heart.&#8221;Both of them are weak metaphysical commitments and both are certain and corrigible forms of orthopraxy. That was your point, I think. But my point was that those who reject U2, the language of U2 is not orthoprax even if they still follow all the other precepts and praxis. My point in the little video provided was that in sociology we usually label the more &#8220;ortho&#8221; group as the orthoprax.<br />
For example, in the study of meditation &#8211; monastic life is called orthoprax. Do you adhere to the meditation practice? Someone who became more modern and no longer accepts the metaphysical parts of the practice is now less orthoprax. Even if they keep the original practice like the Dalai Lama, he is seen as an adapter or a syntheiszer, not as the orthoprax.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/04/the-evangelical-habitas-or-how-to-be-orthoprax/#comment-946</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2010 18:57:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1235#comment-946</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[If a community as a whole (like modern orthodoxy)  is possessed by a high degree of &quot;skepticism, rationality, liberalism or disinterest&quot; which then affects its speech and behavior, then doesn&#039;t this become its distinct mode of orthopraxy reflecting a weaker commitment to the metaphysical ontology that performative ritual and orthopraxy in general is meant to reinforce?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If a community as a whole (like modern orthodoxy)  is possessed by a high degree of &#8220;skepticism, rationality, liberalism or disinterest&#8221; which then affects its speech and behavior, then doesn&#8217;t this become its distinct mode of orthopraxy reflecting a weaker commitment to the metaphysical ontology that performative ritual and orthopraxy in general is meant to reinforce?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
