<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>interfaith &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/category/interfaith/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Jul 2010 14:10:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='kavvanah.wordpress.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/c9f111237f93750b6b994fc5185d49c3?s=96&#038;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>interfaith &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>Joseph Weiler, traditional Jew, defends the freedom to affix a Crucifix</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/06/joseph-weiler-traditional-jew-defends-the-crucifix/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/06/joseph-weiler-traditional-jew-defends-the-crucifix/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 06 Jul 2010 13:51:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[joseph h h weiler]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[joseph weiler]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[religious pluralism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1617</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Joseph H. H. Weiler, expert in international law, who has more degrees -earned and honorary- than almost anyone else has written a piece defending the freedom the affix a crucifix. Some of my readers may know him because he is &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/06/joseph-weiler-traditional-jew-defends-the-crucifix/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_Weiler">Joseph H. H. Weiler,</a> expert in international law, who has more degrees -earned and honorary- than almost anyone else has written a piece defending the freedom the affix a crucifix.  Some of my readers may know him because he is mainly situated at NYU and is a traditional Jew. I was once on a panel with him post 9/11. In the post-EU world, one part of the EU can hold another part to its standards. The placing of a crucifix was brought to court of European Court of Human Rights and banned in school use. <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/italy/7862824/Italy-appeals-against-ban-on-school-crucifixes.html">Italy appealed the ban.</a> Below is part of the defense of the Crucifix by Joseph Weiler. </p>
<blockquote><p>13. Consider a photograph of the Queen of England hanging in the classroom. Like the Cross, that picture has a double meaning. It is a photo of the Head of State. It is, too, a photo of the Titular head of the Church of England. It is a bit like the Pope who is a Head of State and Head of a Church. Would it be acceptable for someone to demand that the picture of the Queen may not hang in the school since it is incompatible with their religious conviction or their right to education since – they are Catholics, or Jews, or Muslims? Or with their philosophical conviction – they are atheists? Could the Irish Constitution or the German Constitution not hang on a class room wall or be read in class since in their Preambles we find a reference to the Holy Trinity and the Divine Lord Jesus Christ in the former and to God in the latter? Of course the right of freedom from religion must ensure that a pupil who objects may not be required actually to engage in a religious act, perform a religious ritual, or have some religious affiliation as a condition for state entitlements. He or she should certainly have the right not to sing God Save the Queen if that clashes with their world view. But can that student demand that no one else sing it?</p>
<p>21. Today, the principal social cleavage in our States as regards religion is not among, say Catholics and Protestants, but among the religious and the ‘secular’. Secularity, Laïcité is not an empty category which signifies absence of faith. It is to many a rich world view which holds, inter alia, the political conviction that religion only has a legitimate place in the private sphere and that there may not be any entanglement of public authority and religion. For example, only secular schools will be funded. Religious schools must be private and not enjoy public support. It is a political position, respectable, but certainly not “neutral.” The non-laique, whilst fully respecting freedom of and from religion, embrace some form of public religion as I have already noted. Laïcité advocates a naked public square, a classroom wall bereft of any religious symbol. It is legally disingenuous to adopt a political position which splits our society, and to claim that somehow it is neutral.</p>
<p>    23. If the social pallet of society were only composed of blue yellow and red groups, than black – the absence of color – would be a neutral colour. But once one of the social forces in society has appropriated black as its colour, than that choice is no longer neutral. Secularism does not favour a wall deprived of all State symbols. It is religious symbols which are anathema. </p>
<p>    24. What are the educational consequences of this?<br />
    25. Consider the following parable of Marco and Leonardo, two friends just about to begin school. Leonardo visits Marco at his home. He enters and notices a crucifix. What is that?’, he asks. ‘A crucifix – why, you don’t have one? Every house should have one.’ Leonardo returns to his home agitated. His mother patiently explains: ‘They are believing Catholics. We are not. We follow our path. Now imagine a visit by Marco to Leonardo’s house. ‘Wow!’, he exclaims, ‘no crucifix? An empty wall?’ “ We do not believe in that nonsense” says his friend. Marco returns agitated to his house. ‘Well’, explains his mother, ‘We follow our path.” The next day both kids go to school. Imagine the school with a crucifix. Leonardo returns home agitated: ‘The school is like Marco’s house. Are you sure, Mamma, that it is okay not to have a crucifix?’ That is the essence of Ms. Lausti’s complaint. But imagine, too, that on the first day the walls are naked. Marco returns home agitated. ‘The school is like Leonardo’s house,’ he cries. ‘You see, I told you we don’t need it.’</p>
<p>27. Make no mistake: A State-mandated naked wall, as in France, may suggest to pupils that the State is taking an anti-religious attitude. We trust the curriculum of the French Republic, to teach their children tolerance and pluralism and dispel that notion. There is always an interaction between what is on the wall and how it is discussed and taught in class. Likewise, a crucifix on the wall, might be perceived as coercive. Again, it depends on the curriculum to contextualize and teach the children in the Italian class tolerance and pluralism. There may be other solutions such as having symbols of more than one religion or finding other educationally appropriate ways to convey the message of pluralism.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.ilsussidiario.net/News/Politics-Society/2010/7/1/EXCLUSIVE-Joseph-Weiler-How-I-defended-the-Crucifix-Before-the-European-Court-of-Human-Rights/1/96909/">Read the whole thing here.</a></p></blockquote>
<p>Notice his definitions of the open society, tolerance and pluralism. A lack of religion in the public sphere is itself a religious decision. Also note how far the defense of the crucifix has no connection to medieval polemics or even the polemics of the age of tolerance and the Enlightenment. One is not proving either side right or wrong, nor is one conflating liberal tolerance with pluralism. Many modern orthodox Jews still respond to questions in medieval terms or attempting to fit Enlightenment tolerance into the classic positions. Neither one is where current discussions of human rights start.</p>
<p>Any thoughts on his arguments? Would Judaism agree? Would Judaism seeking a place to defend its own religious liberty in the US agree?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/06/joseph-weiler-traditional-jew-defends-the-crucifix/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Jewish -Islamic Encounter: Death of Sheikh Bukhari and rise of US encounter</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/03/jewish-islamic-encounter-death-of-sheikh-bukhari-and-rise-of-us-encounter/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/03/jewish-islamic-encounter-death-of-sheikh-bukhari-and-rise-of-us-encounter/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2010 22:30:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[islam and judaism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish muslim encounter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sufi]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1465</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Two items in the paper of importance to the Jewish-Muslim encounter. Sufi sheikh who preached nonviolence laid to rest By LAUREN GELFOND FELDINGER. In a small and ancient family plot attached to his ancestral home in Jerusalem’s Old City, regional &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/03/jewish-islamic-encounter-death-of-sheikh-bukhari-and-rise-of-us-encounter/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Two items in the paper of importance to the Jewish-Muslim encounter.</p>
<blockquote><p><a href="http://www.jpost.com/Israel/Article.aspx?id=177302"><strong>Sufi sheikh who preached nonviolence laid to rest</strong></a><br />
By LAUREN GELFOND FELDINGER.</p>
<p>In a small and ancient family plot attached to his ancestral home in Jerusalem’s Old City, <strong>regional Sufi leader Sheikh Abdul Aziz Bukhari</strong> was laid to rest on Tuesday at age 61, after a long struggle with heart disease. He was head of the mystical Naqshabandi Holy Land Sufi Order.</p>
<p>A longtime proponent of nonviolence and interfaith unity, Bukhari found his inspiration in Islamic law and tradition, as well as in the writings of Mohandas Gandhi, Martin Luther King Jr. and Nelson Mandela. “The stronger one is the one who can absorb the violence and anger from the other and change it to love and understanding. It is not easy; it is a lot of work. But this is the real jihad,” he once told the Globaloneness Project in an interview.</p>
<p>His teachings and practices put him in danger and under great stress that over the years harmed his health, said Sheikh Ghassan Manasra of Nazareth, whose father heads the regional Holy Land Qadari Sufi Order. “Sheikh Bukhari influenced lots of people, worked hard to bridge the religions and cultures; and his teaching is keeping part of the youth on the right path. We worked together for many years and succeeded many times and failed many times and decided to stay on the [path] of God to bring peace, tolerance, harmony and moderation,” he said.</p>
<p>“But on both sides, Jewish and Muslim, there are moderates but also extreme people, and our work was very dangerous, with a lot of pressure and stress until now, and I think this explains, in part, his heart problems.”</p>
<p>Bukhari later also got involved in the Interfaith Coordinating Council in Israel, the Interfaith Encounter Association, and the Sulha Peace Project, and in 2007 launched the “Jerusalem Hug” every June 21, where Israelis, Palestinians and foreigners of all faiths form a human chain of prayer around the Old City.</p>
<p><strong>During Operation Cast Lead, Bukhari initiated a delegation of Arab youth and religious leaders to show solidarity with the students and teachers in Sderot and to share the pain of his own family’s experience in Gaza.<br />
“He was really special,” Rabbi Tzion Cohen, a native of Sderot who is chief rabbi of the Shaar Hanegev region, said of their meeting.<br />
“Despite his own great pain for his family, and despite the fact that some of the group got heated up during the discussion, he and his wife remained gentle and patient and so very kind. I was truly impressed by their pleasantness.”</strong></p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p><a href="http://www.jta.org/news/article/2010/05/30/2739373/report-us-muslim-jewish-engagement-growing"><strong>Muslim-Jewish engagement is growing in the United States, with the greatest expansion during the past two years, a new report found </strong></a></p>
<p>Even as the political situation in the Middle East continues to heat up, more groups dedicated to Muslim-Jewish education, dialogue and joint social action are being formed, according to the report issued by the Center for Muslim-Jewish Engagement in Los Angeles, a partnership between Hebrew Union College, Omar Ibn Al Khattab Foundation and the University of Southern California. The data were collected from two surveys conducted in November 2009.</p>
<p>More than 70 percent of these groups have emerged since 9/11. Of those, half were created in the past 24 months. Half of the groups have no staff or budget, demonstrating a heavy reliance on volunteerism. Fifty percent of existing groups raise less than $250 a year, according to the report. </p>
<p>Many of the newest groups emerged from the Weekend of Twinning, a two-year-old project of the Foundation for Ethnic Understanding that has brought together more than 200 mosques and synagogues for weekends of joint activity. Seventy percent of the mosques and synagogues that took part in the 2009 weekend say they have developed ongoing relationships.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/06/03/jewish-islamic-encounter-death-of-sheikh-bukhari-and-rise-of-us-encounter/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>From Bergen County to Istanbul</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/09/from-bergen-county-to-istanbul/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/09/from-bergen-county-to-istanbul/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 09 May 2010 15:37:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Harun Yahya]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[islam and judaism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1160</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Here is an interesting interfaith moment of a frum couple from Bergen county finding themselves on Turkish TV. I knew of this as soon as it occurred but was waiting for the You Tube. The couple are interested in Jewish &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/09/from-bergen-county-to-istanbul/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here is an interesting interfaith moment of a frum couple from Bergen county finding themselves on Turkish TV. I knew of this as soon as it occurred but was waiting for the You Tube.  The couple are interested in Jewish Muslim reconciliation and were in correspondence with Adnan Oktar (Harun Yahya) and visited him and found themselves recorded for posterity. Adnan Oktar (Harun Yahya) is the leading Turkish creationist rejecting secular Turkey and the more rational Islamic approaches. Adnan Oktar (Harun Yahya) has a rich debate around him on the web. Look at his <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adnan_Oktar">wiki page</a> and the <a href="http://commentsaboutadnanoktar.com/">Anti-Wiki pages.</a> and <a href="http://whoisharunyahya.wordpress.com/category/adnan-oktar/">hate sites against him.</a> Was he anti-Semitic and then saw the light after a prison term and is now pushing for Jewish-Muslim reconciliation? Was he imprisoned and placed in a psycho ward as a set-up victim of the state or did he deserve it? <a href="http://newhumanist.org.uk/2131/sex-flies-and-videotape-the-secret-lives-of-harun-yahya">Here is a critical article.</a></p>
<p>Update<br />
Gil Amminadav writes to me after reading the links on this post. </p>
<blockquote><p>&#8220;We had read some of the allegations against Harun Yahya before (as well as his group&#8217;s responses), but nothing as emphatic as that Humanist article! It was a very well-written piece.  If we had read all of this before agreeing to meet with him, I can&#8217;t say that it would have changed anything; we believe that part of the purpose of cultivating a sensitivity towards negative and defamatory speech is to remind us that, when all is said and done, there is quite a lot said, and not nearly as much actually known.  Even with truth to a single allegation, we are not interested in judging, we are interested in working.  Another&#8217;s personal failures serve to remind us of our own &#8211; narcissism is hardly a unique trait.  All in all, the man struck us as sincerely interested in promoting friendship and fellowship, from within his own cultural context, and for that we give him much credit and hope that he inspires others to do the same, God willing.  If he has an imbalanced sexuality or mistreats others in any way, then we hope that God brings him &#8220;a healing of soul and a healing of body,&#8221; and that anyone who feels harmed by him is brought the same.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>&#8220;Elana and Gil Amminadav run Derusha Publishing, an indie  publishing house based in New Jersey. Among their publications is <a href="http://www.derushapublishing.com/the-naked-crowd.shtml">Hakham Jose Fauer&#8217;s recent book</a>. &#8220;So here are these young Jewish seekers who didn&#8217;t realize they were going to broadcast our  conversation until we actually sat down. I am not sure what to make of it. This stuff is going on all the time. Here is the TV interview in two parts. </p>
<p><iframe class='youtube-player' width='500' height='282' src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/2Xw3P3P2TCc?version=3&#038;rel=1&#038;fs=1&#038;autohide=2&#038;showsearch=0&#038;showinfo=1&#038;iv_load_policy=1&#038;wmode=transparent' allowfullscreen='true' style='border:0;'></iframe></p>
<p><iframe class='youtube-player' width='500' height='282' src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/0GT1Mx1LRgE?version=3&#038;rel=1&#038;fs=1&#038;autohide=2&#038;showsearch=0&#038;showinfo=1&#038;iv_load_policy=1&#038;wmode=transparent' allowfullscreen='true' style='border:0;'></iframe></p>
<p><a href="http://us1.harunyahya.com/Detail/T/EDCRFV/productId/23466/ADNAN_OKTAR_S_LIVE_INTERVIEW_WITH_JEWISH_GUESTS_FROM_DERUSHA_PUBLISHING_(USA)_ON_HARUNYAHYA.TV_(APRIL_14,_2010)">From the transcript:</a></p>
<blockquote><p>Look. See how Islam resembles Judaism? The fact they resemble one another stems from their being the same in the faith of the Prophet Abraham (pbuh) and very ancient Sunna, insha&#8217;Allah.</p>
<p>GIL AMMINADAV: Yes, even more. It is a river and everyone drinks from the river. And some people drink from here and some people drink from there. But it is the same river. Beyond Abraham (pbuh), Ishmael (pbuh), Isaac (pbuh) and Jacob (pbuh) and all these beyond today, you have people drinking from the same river and know. Unfortunately, it seems we have seen a lot of people, unfortunately a lot of Israeli, has forgotten. We are supposed to be the people of memory but we have forgotten. But we are now remembering</p>
<p>GIL AMMINADAV: We have a sheikh, a tzadik  (righteous teacher). His name was Rabbi Nachman ben Feiga, very nice person. He talks about the flip (sudden change) from this world order to the next world order. Inthe blink of an eye. No guns, no tanks, no missiles, just prayer</p>
<p>ELANA AMMINADAV: We also find that a lot of times we are looking forsomething called mussar, like instruction on how we can change ourselves. So when we find a Holy Book that teaches us or that points out things that might be problems in our people. Like things in the Qur&#8217;an talk about how the Jews might have worshipped their Rabbis. So then we can look at ourselves and say, why someone would say that to us, and that can teach us how to change and how to make ourselves better. </p></blockquote>
<p>Gil&#8217;s statement afterward:</p>
<div>&#8220;We believe it is worthwhile for human beings to see  the benefit in making religion a positive, unifying, and enriching  force in their lives and in their relationships.  Meetings between those  people who speak the language of friendship are key components of the  widespread change unfolding around us.  We were honored to reflect upon  the sanctity of Judaism, Islam, and other expressions of humanity&#8217;s  relationship with God, for those who find sanctity in them, with Mr.  Harun Yahya, a delightful, spiritually-sensitive educator and communal  leader in Istanbul.  We hope that as human beings recognize more of each  other in themselves, we will enter the next chapter of human history  with a liberating new vision of the future.&#8221;</div>
<p><strong><br />
For a sense of how common this is becoming. Harun Yahya has had many Israeli guests on his show</strong> including members of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2004_attempt_to_revive_the_Sanhedrin">current attempted Sanhedrin.</a> A national Haredi yearning for the Ottoman Empire?</p>
<p><a href="http://www.thesanhedrin.org/en/images/1/1f/Hachrazah_5769_Kislev_15c.pdf">From the transcript:</a><br />
<a href="http://en.harunyahya.tv/videoDetail/Lang/4/Product/19282/ADNAN_OKTAR_AND_SANHEDRIN_RABBIS_ON_LIVE_TV_PROGRAM_%28DECEMBER_1,_2009%29">The video is here:</a></p>
<blockquote><p>RABBI ABRAHAMSON: Hello, my name is Benyamin Abrahamson. I am an orthodox Chassidic Jew from Israel. And I work as a historian or a kind of consultant to the court in Jerusalem that Rabbi Hollander is talking about. Mostly people here know me from my<br />
endless discussions about the similarities between the Islam and Jewish customs. I enjoy talking about the Hadiths, Tabari, Ibn Hisham and al-Waqidi, and talking about the kings of Himyar as I much as I enjoy talking about the Midrash Rabbah, the Midrashei Geulah,<br />
Rambam, Tosefos or the Shulchan Aruch. I like very much to talk about the common shared customs between Islam and Judaism, about the similarities in architecture between the masjid and the synagogue, between the similarities of the calendar, holidays and customs. But it is<br />
clear to me that there is more than just similarities, that they obviously go back to a common root and a common faith.</p></blockquote>
<p>So what do we make of this reapproachment? It is not the commonality of Jews living in Arab lands or of neighbors. It is not exactly dialogue, theology, or formulated views. And it is happening on the margins. Help me make sense of the implications. I do not want to discuss the people involved, just the encounter.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/09/from-bergen-county-to-istanbul/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Passover Seder Through Muslim Eyes</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/02/passover-seder-through-muslim-eyes/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/02/passover-seder-through-muslim-eyes/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2010 20:26:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[holidays]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[moses]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[passover]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1032</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It has been an annual sighting in the newspapers for the last four years, several Muslim appreciations of Passover. This holiday and the exodus from Egypt is discussed in the Koran. These human interest pieces allow modern Muslim to show &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/02/passover-seder-through-muslim-eyes/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It has been an annual sighting in the newspapers for the last four years, several Muslim appreciations of Passover.  This holiday and the exodus from Egypt is discussed in the Koran. These human interest pieces allow modern Muslim to show their interfaith and tolerance credentials. The first is one of the best on the web, the second is the one that came to my attention as this year&#8217;s syndicated version, the third is a famous one from an Egyptian author 2007 that made the Israeli papers.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.readingislam.com/servlet/Satellite?c=Article_C&amp;cid=1175751840758&amp;pagename=Zone-English-Discover_Islam%2FDIELayout">Out of Egypt  By Prof. Shahul Hameed</a></p>
<blockquote><p>Many Jews may be surprised to learn that Islam as preached by Muhammad (peace be upon him) was the same religion preached by Abraham, as well as of all other prophets mentioned in the Torah and the Bible. Muslims honor all the prophets of the Jews – Abraham, Jacob, Joseph, Moses, David and Solomon among others – as their own prophets.</p>
<p>Here is how Allah ordered Muhammad to follow the religion of the Patriarch Abraham:</p>
<p>[And lastly, We have inspired thee, O Muhammad, with this message: Follow the creed of Abraham, who turned away from all that is false, and was not of those who ascribe divinity to aught beside God.] (An-Nahl 16:23)</p>
<p>In fact, the most important belief that unites Muslims and Jews is the faith in the One God as the Creator, Sustainer and Law-Giver of the universe. Both religions teach the need for establishing the Law of God on earth, so that there will be peace and harmony flourishing everywhere.</p>
<p>As Muslims have a Shari`ah (Law) to live by, the Jews have their Halakha (a compendium of laws, based on the Torah).</p>
<p>It is particularly noteworthy that in the Quran, there is no story that is recounted as many times and with as much emphasis, as the story of the bondage of the Children of Israel and their subsequent deliverance from Egypt&#8217;s Pharaoh. The Quran quotes Moses as saying to his people:</p>
<p>[O my people! Remember the blessings which God bestowed upon you when he raised up prophets among you, and made you your own masters, and granted unto you favors such as He had not granted to anyone else in the world.] (Al-Mai&#8217;idah 5:20)</p>
<p>It was Moses, with the help and guidance of God Almighty, who led them out of  Egypt towards a land of promise. Allah in the Quran says what means:  </p>
<p>[O children of Israel! Remember those blessings of Mine with which I graced you, and how I favored you above all other people. And guard yourselves against a day when no soul will in aught avail another, nor will intercession be accepted from it, nor will compensation be received from it, nor will they be helped. And remember the time when We saved you from Pharaoh&#8217;s people, who afflicted you with cruel suffering, slaughtering your sons and sparing only your women — which was an awesome trial from your Sustainer; and when We cleft the sea before you, and thus saved you and caused Pharaoh&#8217;s people to drown before your very eyes] (Al-Baqarah 2:47-50)</p>
<p>The story is narrated elsewhere in the Quran, where we may read these verses:</p>
<p>[We took the Children of Israel across the sea: Pharaoh and his hosts followed them in insolence and spite. At length, when overwhelmed with the flood, he said: &#8220;I believe that there is no god except Him Whom the Children of Israel believe in: I am of those who submit to Allah.&#8221; It was said to him: &#8220;Ah, now? But a little while before, wast thou in rebellion! and thou didst mischief and violence! This day shall We save thee in the body, that thou may be a sign to those who come after thee! but verily, many among mankind are heedless of Our Signs!&#8221;</p>
<p>We settled the Children of Israel in a beautiful dwelling-place, and provided for them sustenance of the best: it was after knowledge had been granted to them, that they fell into schisms. Verily Allah will judge between them as to the schisms amongst them, on the Day of Judgment.] (Yunus 10:90-93)</p>
<p>The torments inflicted on the Children of Israel by the Pharaoh were continuous and harsh; and so God sent His prophets Moses and Aaron (peace be upon them) to warn the tyrant that he should stop the oppression of the Children of Israel and free them.</p>
<p>But he was arrogant and refused to free the Jewish slaves, until the last of the plagues God sent as punishment. The first-born of both man and beast were destined to fall down dead on that fateful night. Pesach, or Passover, means protection in Hebrew, and the name refers to this last of the plagues sent by God to the Egyptians. While the Egyptians suffered this plague, the angel of death passed over the houses of the Israelites. To protect themselves, the Israelites had marked their homes with lamb&#8217;s blood so that the angel of death could easily &#8220;pass over&#8221; their homes.</p>
<p>Under guidance from God, the Israelites fled Egypt; while the Pharaoh and his men pursued them. It seemed like their journey would end at the Red Sea which prevented their escape.</p>
<p>But a miracle happened when Moses struck the water with his staff: The waves of the Red Sea parted and the Israelites hurried along the passage between the parted waves. Pharaoh and his soldiers followed; but by the time the Israelites reached the other shore, the sea closed in engulfing their pursuers. Thus the Israelites were delivered from bondage, and the Pharaoh and his people perished.  </p>
<p>Muslims are in sympathy with the Jewish celebration of the Pesach, as the fast on `Ashura&#8217; amply demonstrates. When the Prophet Muhammad came to Madinah on the tenth of the lunar month of Muharram, he found that the Jews there were fasting.</p>
<p>The Prophet asked them why they were fasting on this day, and they explained that it was the day that God saved the Children of Israel from the Pharaoh, and that Moses fasted in thanks on this day. The Prophet said, &#8220;We have more claim to Moses than you.&#8221; He fasted on that day and commanded Muslims to fast on the day. (Al-Bukhari)</p>
<p>Professor Shahul Hameed is a consultant to the Reading Islam Website. He also held the position of the President of the Kerala Islamic Mission, Calicut, India. He is the author of three books on Islam published in the Malayalam language. His books are on comparative religion, the status of women, and science and human values.</p></blockquote>
<p>StarTribune.com  March 23, 2010<br />
<a href="http://www.startribune.com/yourvoices/88903517.html">Passover Seder Through Muslim Eyes By Zafar Siddiqui</a></p>
<blockquote><p>This past Sunday, I attended an interfaith Seder at the Temple of Aaron synagogue in St. Paul. It was a beautiful event. By the end of the Seder meal, I could not but come to a conclusion that the story of Moses (peace be upon him) and his followers’ struggle against the tyranny of the Pharaoh will continue to inspire countless people, communities, and countries in seeking the freedom and dignity that God bestowed on the children of Adam.</p>
<p>It may come as a surprise to a lot of people that Muslims observe the fast of &#8216;Ashura to commemorate the day when God delivered Moses (peace be upon him) and his followers from slavery. The day of &#8216;Ashura falls on the 10th day of the Muslim month of Muharram.</p>
<p>Moses is called Musa in Arabic. He is also called &#8220;Kalim Allah&#8221; (One who spoke with God). He is the most mentioned prophet in the Qur&#8217;an.  The Muslim narrative about the exodus story is detailed and has a strong parallel to the Biblical narrative. Some excerpts from the Qur’an are given below.</p>
<p>Moses&#8217; Childhood<br />
&#8220;And We had already conferred favor upon you another time, when We inspired to your mother what We inspired, [Saying], ‘Cast him into the chest and cast it into the river, and the river will throw it onto the bank; there will take him an enemy to Me and an enemy to him.’ And I bestowed upon you love from Me that you would be brought up under My eye.</p>
<p>[And We favored you] when your sister went and said, ‘Shall I direct you to someone who will be responsible for him?’ So We restored you to your mother that she might be content and not grieve. And you killed someone, but We saved you from retaliation and tried you with a [severe] trial. And you remained [some] years among the people of Madyan. Then you came [here] at the decreed time, O Moses.&#8221; (20: 38-41)</p>
<p>The Burning Bush<br />
&#8220;And has the story of Moses reached you? – When he saw a fire and said to his family, “Stay here; indeed, I have perceived a fire; perhaps I can bring you a torch or find at the fire some guidance. And when he came to it, he was called, “O Moses, indeed, I am your Lord, so remove your sandals. Indeed, you are in the sacred valley of Tuwā. And I have chosen you, so listen to what is revealed [to you]. Indeed, I am God. There is no deity except Me, so worship Me and establish prayer for My remembrance.” (20: 9-14)</p>
<p>Moses and his brother Aaron confront Pharaoh<br />
&#8220;So go to him and say, ‘Indeed, we are messengers of your Lord, so send with us the Children of Israel and do not torment them. We have come to you with a sign from your Lord. And peace will be upon he who follows the guidance.&#8221; (20:47)</p>
<p>Moses and his duel with Pharaoh’s magicians<br />
&#8220;They said, “O Moses, either you throw or we will be the first to throw.” He said, “Rather, you throw.” And suddenly their ropes and staffs seemed to him from their magic that they were moving [like snakes]. And he sensed within himself apprehension, did Moses. God said, “Fear not. Indeed, it is you who are superior. And throw what is in your right hand; it will swallow up what they have crafted. What they have crafted is but the trick of a magician, and the magician will not succeed wherever he is.&#8221; So the magicians fell down in prostration. They said, “We have believed in the Lord of Aaron and Moses.&#8221; (20: 65-70)</p>
<p>Freedom at last<br />
&#8220;And We had inspired to Moses, “Travel by night with My servants and strike for them a dry path through the sea; you will not fear being overtaken [by Pharaoh] nor be afraid [of drowning].” So Pharaoh pursued them with his soldiers, and there covered them from the sea that which covered them.&#8221; (20: 77-78)</p>
<p>As I was going through the Haggadah at the Seder, these parallel narrations came to my mind. In a world where injustices, occupations, and wars abound, the story of Moses gives us hope that God will never let any injustice thrive for long. The challenges may seem like the veritable sea in front of us, but, as a follower of Moses, I believe that nothing is impossible for God. Peace is inevitable.</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="http://www.mediamonitors.net/heshamahassaballa11.html">Hesham A. Hassaballa</a> is a Chicago physician and columnist for Beliefnet.com and Media Monitors Network (MMN). He is author of &#8220;Why I Love the Ten Commandments,&#8221; published in the book &#8220;Taking Back Islam: American Muslims Reclaim Their Faith&#8221; (Rodale Press).</p>
<p>And here is a link to one from 2007 that made the Israeli papers because it acknowledged the plight of Arab Jews and the Jewish lineage of many current Arabs.</p>
<blockquote><p><a href="http://news.zionism-israel.com/2007/04/hisham-al-tuhi-many-arabs-have-jewish.html">In an article on the Arab reformist websites Aafaq (April 9, 2007) and Middle East Transparent (April 8, 2007</a>), Egyptian author Hisham Al-Tuhi rejects the view that Muslims should not convey holiday greetings to non-Muslims on their holidays, reviews the history of Jews in Arab countries in the 20th century, and wishes Jews still living in Arab countries a happy Passover. </p>
<p>The Jews Who Remain &#8220;Still Celebrate Their Holidays in Silence, Forgotten&#8230; Is Not the Least We Can Say to Them: Jewish Arabs Happy Passover!?&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8220;Despite this  despite the nationalization, the expulsion, the banishment, the bombings, the racism, the enmity, and the marginalization; despite their being reviled with the ugliest abuse in the prayers of the Muslims, in all of the Arab mosques and in some of the churches; despite their being called infidels and cursed, and being accused of treason, in the books, the newspapers, and the TV stations, [both] governmental and private  despite all this, they still live in Egypt, Iraq, Yemen, Bahrain, Tunisia, Morocco, Libya, Syria, Lebanon, Algeria, and in other countries of the Arab Middle East!</p>
<p>&#8220;And they still celebrate their holidays in silence, forgotten. And they still passionately love their countries who treated them cruelly, and will no accept any substitute [for them].</p>
<p>&#8220;Is not the least we can say to them: Jewish Arabs happy Passover!?&#8221; </p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/02/passover-seder-through-muslim-eyes/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rabbi Eliezer Ashkenazi on Pour out thy Wrath</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/27/rabbi-eliezer-ashkenazi-on-pour-out-thy-wrath/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/27/rabbi-eliezer-ashkenazi-on-pour-out-thy-wrath/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 28 Mar 2010 01:45:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[liturgy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[beer hagolah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[eliezer ashkenazi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gentiles]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[moshe rivkes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pour out thy wrath]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1020</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Rabbi Eliezer Ashkenazi (1513-1585), rabbi in Egypt, Italy and Poland, was a rational thinker and major influence in his era. He wrote an important Biblical commentary and defended the traditional medieval rationalism against Maharal. The following passage played a role &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/27/rabbi-eliezer-ashkenazi-on-pour-out-thy-wrath/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rabbi Eliezer Ashkenazi  (1513-1585), rabbi in Egypt, Italy and Poland, was a rational thinker and major influence in his era. He wrote an important Biblical commentary and defended the traditional medieval rationalism against Maharal. The following passage played a role in subsequent early modern legal discussions and seems to have been forgotten in twentieth century discussions. Ashkenazi removes his, and our, current gentiles from the curse.</p>
<p><strong>“Pour out thy wrath upon the nations”</strong></p>
<blockquote><p>Some of the Gentiles among whom we are exiled under their protection have thought that God forbid we are cursing them. </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>It only applies to the nations that do not know Him, that deny the Exodus from Egypt because they don’t accept the miracles and wonders. It is quite clear that the Gentiles among whom we are exiled all know about the Exodus and believe in it, and know its details…We only curse the idol worshipers who don’t believe in creation and who destroyed the Temple, not the nations who became Edom and Ishmael (Christianity and Islam) because they were still not created…But now our Gentiles and the Ishmaelites know God, and acknowledge the Exodus, forefend for us to curse them from our religion.<br />
And when we do curse those who afflict us and unjustly persecute us, that curse is not from our religion, forefend, but as a person who curses one who afflicts another…<br />
Our holy Torah announces this in the name of the head of the faithful [Abraham] that God does not desire this, as it is written, “Will you destroy the righteous with the wicked?” And the master of the prophets [Genesis 18:23] said, “One person will sin and the whole community should be cut off?” And from the writings it is clarified that we are not allowed from our religion to curse nations that acknowledge the Exodus from Egypt and know God even if they have not received the Torah…<br />
That is why it was not permitted for Israel to conquer the land of Canaan until after the Exodus, that even after they know about God they did not believe or accept…. </p></blockquote>
<p>Rabbi Ashkenazi acknowledges that Gentiles accept God, creation and even the providential Exodus story. Ashkenazi draws a distinction between the negative attitude toward Gentiles in the Talmud and the attitude toward contemporary Christians by stating that Gentiles at the time of the Temple were idolaters without a belief in God. He further distances himself from prior teachings of contempt by stating that the curses that the Midrash heaps upon Rome have no connection to the later nations of Edom.  Ashkenazi proclaims that Jews do not curse others. Even when Christians persecute Jews, the persecution stems not from their religion but from unfortunate occurrences between people. One cannot hold a people accountable for the injustice of some of them, and certainly one cannot hold their religion responsible for the injustice committed by certain members of it. </p>
<p>Ashkenazi also explains the four sons as the wise son is Isaac, the wicked son is Christianity, the simple son is Jacob, and the son that does not know how to ask is Islam. There is a recent dissertation written under the direction of Menachem Kellner on Ashkenazi, Neta Ecker, Universalism in the Thought of Rabbi Eliezer Ashkenazi” Unpublished Dissertation Haifa University 2010)</p>
<p>The importance of this passage of Rabbi Eliezer Ashkenazi is that it is quoted as a source text by R. Moshe Rivkes in the eighteenth-century as a general halakhah. </p>
<p><em>The rabbis of the Talmud meant by the term ‘idolaters’ the pagans who lived in their time, who worshipped the stars and the constellations and did not believe in the Exodus from Egypt and in the creation of the world out of nothing. But the nations under whose benevolent shadow we, the Jewish nation, are exiled and are dispersed among them, they do believe in the creation of the world out of nothing and the Exodus from Egypt and in the essentials of faith, and their whole intention is toward the Maker of heaven and earth, as other authorities have written…<br />
So rather than a prohibition not to save them [if they were idolaters],  on the contrary, we are required to pray for their welfare <strong>as Rabbi Eliezer Ashkenazi wrote at length on the passage  from the Passover haggadah “Pour out thy Wrath.”</strong> King David prayed to God to pour out his wrath on the idolater who did not believe in creation from nothing or the signs and wonders that God performed for us in Egypt and at the giving of the Torah. The nations<br />
In whose shadow we live and under whose wings we are protected do believe in all of this. Therefore, we are always required to pray for the welfare and success of the kingdom and the ministers, in all their provinces. Indeed, Maimonides ruled according to Rabbi Joshua, that the pious of the nations have a portion in the world to come. (Be&#8217;er haGolah to Hoshen Mishpat 425:5) </em></p>
<p>Translation and comments &#8211; Copyright © 2010 Alan Brill • All Rights Reserved </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/27/rabbi-eliezer-ashkenazi-on-pour-out-thy-wrath/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Alan Lew Z”L – Between Paul Williams and Paul Knitter</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/24/alan-lew-z%e2%80%9dl-%e2%80%93-between-paul-williams-and-paul-knitter/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/24/alan-lew-z%e2%80%9dl-%e2%80%93-between-paul-williams-and-paul-knitter/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2010 06:16:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Buddhism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[spirituality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Alan lew]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bu-jew]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Buddhism & Judaism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish renewal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[paul knitter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[paul williams]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=996</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Rabbi Alan Lew, (1944- 2009) was the spiritual leader of San Francisco’s Congregation Beth Sholom. He was in the forefront of attempting to cultivate a spirituality bridging Judaism and Buddhism. Lew&#8217;s coming of age as a Jew actually happened as &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/24/alan-lew-z%e2%80%9dl-%e2%80%93-between-paul-williams-and-paul-knitter/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rabbi Alan Lew, (1944- 2009) was the spiritual leader of San Francisco’s Congregation Beth Sholom. He was in the forefront of attempting to cultivate a spirituality bridging Judaism and Buddhism. </p>
<p>Lew&#8217;s coming of age as a Jew actually happened as he sought to deepen his Zen Buddhist practice. Disillusioned by the Judaism he&#8217;d experienced as a child, Lew was considering becoming ordained as a lay Buddhist priest. But he found himself unable to sew a priestly garment while on a retreat in the 1970s at Tassajara, a Zen center in Carmel Valley. As he meditated on that resistance, Lew said that &#8220;there was some sense of conflict between my being ordained as a Buddhist with my being Jewish.&#8221; It became a turning point, leading Lew toward Judaism, and ultimately to rabbinical school. </p>
<p>Lew seems to have a Buddhist view toward reality, its root metaphors without the religion itself.  Life is a great sea of Being, an endless flow, we are all interconnected, and feel other people’s suffering. He formulates Judaism as mindfulness using the metaphor of “layered grid of awareness” as a bridge idea, both Buddhism and Judaism have a layer grid of awareness.  Jewish prayer is about energy exchange and mindfulness. </p>
<blockquote><p>That we are afloat in a great sea of being, an endless flow of becoming in which we are connected to all beings.”  (This is Real, 16)<br />
We die to the world every time we breathe out, and every time we breathe in, every time our breath returns to us of its own accord, we are reborn, and the world rises up into being again. (Ibid, 17)</p>
<p>Every spiritual tradition I am aware of speaks of a kind of layered mindfulness, a sensibility that works up and out of the body, to the heart and then to the mind and then finally to the soul. The Buddhist sutra On Mindfulness describes this kind of layered grid of awareness, and the Kabala, the Jewish mystical tradition, speaks of it too. According to the Kabala, we start out with our awareness in Asiyah – the world of physicality, the world of the body, our most immediately accessible reality. Then we become aware of the heart, yetzirah – the world of formation or emotion, that shadowy world between conception and its realization in material form. From there we move on to the world of pure intellect, Briyah, or creation, and then to Atzilut, the realm of pure spiritual emanation. (Ibid, 190)</p>
<p>I would visualize the words as an energy exchange – the words going up to God and God’s attention coming down. Prayer began bringing me to the same place my Zen practice had taken me… Before I prayed, I would study, in a prayer shawl and teffilin, sitting in half-lotus (One God Clapping, 154)</p>
<p>So yoga and directed meditation became part of the practice I offered at my synagogue. The meditation group changed the whole tenor of the Friday night minyan. Suddenly the service had great density and feeling… My goal was to help Jews deepen their Jewish practice with Buddhist-style meditation techniques, (Ibid 287)<br />
Meditation and Jewish practice lead us to experience the oneness of all beings. We are all connected; each of us is created in the divine image, and other people’s suffering is our own. (Ibid 296)<br />
But the first noble truth is that everything is suffering, and both Judaism and Buddhism insist that the only appropriate response to this suffering is to turn toward it, to attend to it. Avalokiteshvara, the Bodhisattva of Compassion, is “The Hearer of the Cries of the World,” and the Torah God is repeatedly described as hearing the cries of the oppressed. (Ibid 297)</p></blockquote>
<p>I am used to the critique that Bu-Jews remove the religion from Buddhism and only leave the meditation However, I found in one review of Lew compare him unfavorably with Paul Williams, <em>The Unexpected Way. </em> So I read the latter work. Williams was a trained professor of Buddhism, familiar with the languages and the religion of Buddhism, who converted to Catholicism later in life. Williams study of Buddhism lead him to reject a religion without a theistic God, revelation, redemption, reward, and providence.  He wrote a coherent, rational, and theological critique of Buddhism from a catholic point of view. The book was not one of those bad books for Jewish outreach kiruv that know neither Buddhism nor Judaism, and have little rationalism. This was a defense of theistic religion.  Reading Lew in light of Williams, one is struck by the lack of any engagement with the theology of Judaism or Buddhism, beyond the metaphors.  Lew comes off as more pragmatic than grasping the path of enlightenment, in either tradition. <a href="http://www.pbs.org/wnet/religionandethics/week126/cover.html">Or here is the debate in another context:</a></p>
<blockquote><p>Rabbi LEW: It&#8217;s perfectly all right to use elements of one practice to nourish another, but you have to have a sense of what your central practice is, and you have to have integrity about following that path.<br />
Nathan Katz practiced Buddhism for 15 years, and thinks there are irreconcilable differences between the two religions.<br />
Professor NATHAN KATZ: I would say the fundamental difference between the two traditions is one is theistic and one is not. And even if you take the most esoteric, Judaic concepts of God, they still don&#8217;t reconcile with the Buddhist criticism of all concepts of God.</p></blockquote>
<p>On the other hand, I just read Paul Knitter’s <em>Without Buddha I Could Not Be A Christian.</em> Knitter as a progressive catholic, ex-priest, boldly proclaims himself a syncretic who follows two religions.  Knitter describes how his seminary students see it as adultery.  Buddhism lets him give up the traditional categories of God, religious language, and revelation. The book harvests the last quarter century of American appreciation for Buddhism as a contribution for religion.  Alan Lew avoided Buddha, Buddhist ritual, and Buddhist holidays and created what he called “Buddhist style”  practices for import into Judaism. Knitter is not satisfied with Buddhist style and feels that accepting refuge in the Dharma does not conflict with being a Catholic.</p>
<p>Are there other solutions for Judaism?  Are there other places to make the division between Judaism and Buddhism? For example, one of the sometimes readers of this blog who lives a haredi life in Brooklyn wants to write a book on non-dual Judaism from the sources of Judaism- Chabad, Rav Nahman,  Nefesh HaHayyim,  and Ramak. This would directly present Jewish thought, in a way that Lew does not. But at the same time, it would not reject the insights of seeing oneself in the Buddhist mirror. A Jewish theist who knows Kabbalah may not have to throw out the best that they see reflected elsewhere.  Any thoughts?</p>
<p>Copyright © 2010 Alan Brill • All Rights Reserved</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/24/alan-lew-z%e2%80%9dl-%e2%80%93-between-paul-williams-and-paul-knitter/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>9</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Jewish respect and admiration for Muslim religiosity</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/15/jewish-respect-and-admiration-for-muslim-religiosity/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/15/jewish-respect-and-admiration-for-muslim-religiosity/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2010 18:27:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mysticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[popular religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rabbis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[islam and judaism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[yitzhak farhi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[zvi Zohar]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=944</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Here is something from last week by Zvi Zohar, Jewish respect and admiration for Muslim religiosity A full English translation of the original account is here. The original Hebrew article, with extensive footnotes was &#8220;An Awesome Event in the City &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/15/jewish-respect-and-admiration-for-muslim-religiosity/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here is something from last week by Zvi Zohar, Jewish respect and admiration for Muslim religiosity </p>
<p><a href="http://www.ihsis.org/Uploads/admin/Lisbon2009-Rabbi-Sheikh.pdf">A full English translation of the original account is here.</a> The original Hebrew article, with extensive footnotes was &#8220;An Awesome Event in the City of Damascus&#8221; in Tolerance in Religious Traditions (Shlomo Fisher ed., 2008). </p>
<p><em>Here I consider one such source, found in the writings of Rabbi Yitzhak Farhi of Jerusalem (1782-1853). It tells of a relationship between two outstanding men in late 18th century Damascus: a great Sufi sheikh and the Chief Rabbi of Damascus.<br />
One of the two heroes of Farhi’s tale, the Sufi sheikh, attained great mastery of the Seven Wisdoms, i.e., the body of universal human knowledge. Since a person’s perfection is contingent upon mastery of these wisdoms, the sheikh was more perfect than all the Jews of his generation, with the exception of the rabbi of Damascus, who was his equal and even slightly his superior in the realm of universal wisdom. </p>
<p>But the Seven Wisdoms are of course only one aspect of religious perfection: the highest form of religious accomplishment is the encounter with God and closeness to Him. In this realm, the realm of religious-mystical experience, it emerges quite clearly from Rabbi Farhi’s account that the sheikh was on a higher level than the rabbi. In that account, it was the sheikh who guided the rabbi along the paths of mystical experience, by way of the garden and the pool, until their joint entry into the Holy of Holies to encounter the Divine Reality reflected in the holy name YHVH. The words on the golden tablet they gazed upon were: “I envision YHWH before me always”. This formula is to be found in every synagogue. Yet as related by Farhi, the one who actualised the promise born by this verse, the person who was indeed able to envision in his consciousness “He Who Spoke and the universe was created”, was not the Jewish rabbi but the Muslim sheikh.</p>
<p>At the end of their joint journey, the rabbi shed copious tears, acknowledged the sheikh’s advantage in this crucial realm, and concluded: “It is becoming upon us to do even more than that”. </p>
<p>Rabbi Yitzhak Farhi, addressing his audience in Jerusalem and the Ottoman Empire in the fourth decade of the 19th century, presented the Sufi sheikh as an ideal spiritual figure reaching the greatest heights of awe of God.<br />
And above all else, there are shared elements and a partnership in the mystical experience itself—and in the joint focus of this experience: “He Who Spoke and the universe was created”. Not a Muslim God, and not a Jewish God, but the God of all existence, the Creator of all. </em></p>
<p>* Zvi Zohar is a professor of Sephardic Law and Ethics at Bar Ilan University, a Senior Research Fellow at the Shalom Hartman Institute of Advanced Judaic Studies in Jerusalem. A full translation, analysis and discussion of Rabbi Farhi’s account will soon be published in Jewish Studies Quarterly under the title “The Rabbi and the Sheikh”.<br />
<a href="http://www.commongroundnews.org/article.php?id=27423">Read Full op-ed Version here.</a></p>
<p>Update: I received a comment of Islamaphobia with an IP number from the Israel Tel Aviv Ministry-of-finance. Dont they at least tell people not to make such statements from work? Or at least not in English?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/15/jewish-respect-and-admiration-for-muslim-religiosity/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Does the Church ‘Get’ the Holocaust? A Response to Kevin Madigan</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/03/does-the-church-%e2%80%98get%e2%80%99-the-holocaust-a-response-to-kevin-madigan/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/03/does-the-church-%e2%80%98get%e2%80%99-the-holocaust-a-response-to-kevin-madigan/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 03 Mar 2010 06:06:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[holocaust]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[adorno]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[alan brill]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kevin madigan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pope Benedict]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=876</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I agreed to give a Jewish response to the following paper by the Harvard historian Professor Kevin Madigan at a recent conference. The papers have just been published. Madigan spoke as a historian and I spoke about memory. For those &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/03/does-the-church-%e2%80%98get%e2%80%99-the-holocaust-a-response-to-kevin-madigan/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I agreed to give a Jewish response to the following paper by the Harvard historian Professor Kevin Madigan at a recent conference. The papers have just been published. Madigan spoke as a historian and I spoke about memory. For those interested in the topic, the papers provide a full bibliography in the footnotes.<br />
Kevin Madigan, <a href="http://escholarship.bc.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1228&amp;context=scjr">Has the Papacy &#8216;Owned&#8217; Vatican Guilt for the Church&#8217;s Role in the Holocaust?</a><br />
Alan Brill, <a href="http://escholarship.bc.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1230&amp;context=scjr">Does the Church ‘Get’ the Holocaust? A Response to Kevin Madigan</a></p>
<p><strong>Here are my conclusions. If you want more information then see the original papers or if you want to enter the discussion, then please read the original papers first.</strong> </p>
<p><em>A few concluding observations<br />
(1) There is a sincere attempt by the Vatican for reconciliation, and reconciliation is indeed the goal.</p>
<p>(2) There is also a sincere attempt by the Vatican for moral reckoning of antisemitism; however, they also have other forefront concerns, including the pastoral, liturgical, and doctrinal life of the Church.</p>
<p>(3) I completely agree with Professor Madigan’s conclusions to the question about historic reckoning. Nevertheless, issues should not be conceptualized only in the present.</p>
<p>(4) However, the understanding of Jewish Holocaust memory is intermittent. Most of the time the Holocaust is understood as a Jewish tragedy, though Vatican speeches may not reveal this understanding. When going to a Holocaust memorial to show respect to the Jewish people while<br />
accompanied by a group of Jews, Church representatives need to understand that the Holocaust is not the “30 million people killed by the fascists” nor is it a “universal problem of inhumanity and evil in the world.” For Jews, it is a war against six million Jews as Jews, with the Jews singled out for extermination. At a minimum this is demanded by diplomacy and propriety; at best it requires empathy for Jewish memory. There is a noticeable lack of a personal empathy and empathetic regret.</p>
<p>(5) Is there an understanding by the Church of the Jewish sense of the Tremendum? Do they &#8220;get” the Jewish silence, bereft of theological answers? Do they “get” the rupturing of Jewish faith, leaving a sense of Jewish brokenness? The answer is no. Few Jews evoke the eternal<br />
covenants as a comfort<br />
.<br />
(6) Finally, current Church statements made in light of the Holocaust, are not addressing the past 2000 years of Christian anti-Judaism. Fr. Edward Flannery’s observation in the Introduction to his book The Anguish of the Jews” still holds true: Christians have torn from their history<br />
books the pages that Jews have memorized.</em></p>
<p><strong>From one of the sections that I was particularly interested in:</strong><br />
<em>Pope Benedict conceptualizes the Holocaust using the critical theory of the Frankfort School, especially that of Theodore Adorno and Jürgen Habermas… He speaks to the Historikerstreit, occuring in the 1980s which debated the role of the Holocaust in history. He sides with Adorno and Habermas against Nolte and Fest. But this discussion does not in any way respond to Jewish memory.<br />
Neither does his discussion of the Holocaust in Spe Salvi (In Hope We Are Saved) which asserts that the horrible injustices of history should not have the final word. There must finally be true justice. But that, in the words the Pope quotes from Adorno, would require a world “where not only present suffering would be wiped out, but also that which is irrevocably past would be undone.” This would mean the resurrection of the dead (no. 42). God now reveals his true face in the figure of the sufferer who shares man&#8217;s God-forsaken condition by taking it upon himself. This innocent sufferer has attained the certitude of hope: there is a God, and God can create justice in a way that we cannot conceive, yet we can begin to grasp it through faith. Yes, there is a resurrection of the flesh. (42-43)</p>
<p>In Benedict’s theological works on the Christian meaning of modernity, especially as typified by the Holocaust, his goal is to provide salvific hope before a rampant loss of values. Jewish memory of the Holocaust is not addressed. When Pope Benedict considers the theological<br />
issues of the Holocaust he thinks of Adorno’s question and the pastoral answer of crucifixion and resurrection. He does not think of recent Jewish Holocaust theologians. In this, Pope Benedict is similar to many Orthodox Jewish theologians, who are not interested in historicity or Holocaust theology, and are more concerned with either the eternal values of the halakhah or the pastoral need to spread Judaism. They hear a commanding voice from Sinai and Zion and not from Auschwitz. Thus, it would be unfair to ask Benedict to adopt specific positions in Holocaust theology or to place the Jewish-Christian relationship at the center of his theology. He is a pastoral leader for Catholics, and he has a vision for their doctrinal, liturgical, and institutional needs. It is fair, however, to expect him to address the specific Jewish memory of the Holocaust when he is speaking to a Jewish audience at a Jewish sponsored event, such as at Yad Vashem.</em></p>
<p><strong>If you have never read the Studies in Jewish Christian relations before, especially since it does not show up in google search, <a href="http://escholarship.bc.edu/scjr/vol1/iss1/">here is the first issue from 4 years ago</a>, which is a good place to start.</strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/03/does-the-church-%e2%80%98get%e2%80%99-the-holocaust-a-response-to-kevin-madigan/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Review of Zolli&#8217;s Il Nazareno</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/24/review-of-zollis-il-nazareno/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/24/review-of-zollis-il-nazareno/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2010 17:27:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[holocaust]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[anna foa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[eugenio zolli]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[israel zolli]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=844</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A review just appeared in Italian, and is online in translation, by the Jewish Historian Anna Foa of &#8220;Il Nazareno&#8221; by Rabbi Zolli.  Jews do not usually want to discuss the case of the Chief Rabbi of Rome who converted &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/24/review-of-zollis-il-nazareno/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A review just appeared in Italian, and is online in translation, by the Jewish Historian Anna Foa of &#8220;Il Nazareno&#8221; by Rabbi Zolli.  Jews do not usually want to discuss the case of the Chief Rabbi of Rome who converted to Catholicism after the war and became Eugenio Zolli. The review attempts to situate his views within trends in Jewish scholarship and what was being taught at the various seminaries and Jewish academies. Unlike the German Jewish authors (geiger, Buber) and later Israeli authors (Klausner) who painted Jesus as a liberal Jew, Zolli stresses the discontinuity of the two faiths. Christianity as forgiveness and love.</p>
<blockquote><p>&#8220;All by myself, I read the Gospel, and experienced measureless delight. What a surprise I received in the middle of the green lawn: &#8216;But I say to you: Love your enemies.&#8217; And from the height of the cross: &#8216;Father, forgive them.&#8217; The New Testament really is a covenant&#8230; brand new! Everything in it seemed to me to have an extraordinary importance. Teachings like: &#8216;Blessed are the pure of heart&#8217; and the prayer from the cross draw a line of demarcation between the world of ancient ideas and a new moral cosmos. Yes! Here there arises a new world. Here are delineated the sublime forms of the Kingdom of Heaven, of the persecuted who have not persecuted in return, but have loved.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>On the other hand, he warned the Jewish community of Rome of the true treat of the Nazis and wanted to declare a total state of emergency and the Jewish community leaders did not see the need. “One cannot deny that the measures he suggested &#8212; such as the closing of the temple and of the oratories, the general alarm, and many other things &#8212; would have saved the lives, if not of all, of very many Jews.”</p>
<p><a href="http://chiesa.espresso.repubblica.it/articolo/1342271?eng=y">Full version of book review</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.zenit.org/article-9927?l=english">Interview with the editor</a></p>
<p><em><strong>The rabbi who studied Jesus by Anna Foa</strong></em></p>
<p><em>The book &#8220;Il Nazareno&#8221; by Eugenio Zolli appeared in 1938, published by the Istituto delle Edizioni Accademiche in Udine. Israel Zolli, who would later become Eugenio, was at the time chief rabbi in Trieste, and had not yet become – as he would a year later – chief rabbi of Rome in the place of Rabbi David Prato,</em></p>
<p><em>Seven years later, in February 1945, causing great scandal in the Italian Jewish world and a great stir in the non-Jewish community as well, Israel Zolli converted to Catholicism, taking Pope Pacelli&#8217;s name with baptism, and thus becoming Eugenio Zoll.</em></p>
<p><em>A volume about Jesus Christ written by a prominent rabbi, then, destined a short time later, in spite of this book and the vague whiff of heresy that surrounded him for many years, to become the leading rabbi of the Roman Jewish community.</em></p>
<p><em>Is the book a prefiguring of the author&#8217;s later journey, an anticipation of his subsequent baptism? Or does it reflect a journey of exegetical studies, with attention to the figure of Jesus Christ, undertaken by much European Jewish exegetical thought beginning in the second half of the nineteenth century?</em> <em></em></p>
<p><em>The rabbi from Trieste writes about Jesus and about relations between early Christianity and the rabbinical culture of the time with accents and ideas not dissimilar from those of his teachers at the rabbinical college of Florence, Chayes and Margulies, and raising far less serious controversies than Joseph Klausner&#8217;s book on &#8220;Jesus the Nazarene,&#8221; which at its publication in Hebrew in Jerusalem in 1921 was attacked by both Orthodox Jews and Christians…</em></p>
<p><em>This area of study was very popular with Jewish scholars all over Europe, and in particular with those from Germany, heirs of the Science of Judaism and linked with the reformed currents, which strongly emphasized the Jewishness of Jesus and highlighted the correspondences between rabbinical Judaism and early Christianity. But it was also a favorite of Christian scholars, especially Protestant ones, in nineteenth-century Germany, in the setting of the school of Tubingen and of the later schools of liberal theology, and was assimilated, at the beginning of the new century, by modernist Catholic scholars.</em></p>
<p><em> Italian Jewish culture did not share this attention to the historical figure of Christianity, to the Jewish categories of its preaching, and to its Jewish roots in general.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/24/review-of-zollis-il-nazareno/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>4</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>R. Bernard Lander, Officer Krupke, and Rav Moshe Feinstein</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/17/r-bernard-lander-officer-krupke-and-rav-moshe-feinstein/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/17/r-bernard-lander-officer-krupke-and-rav-moshe-feinstein/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2010 06:01:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rabbis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sociology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bernard Lander]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lander juvenile delinquents.]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lander touro]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Moshe feinstein dialogue]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[moshe Feinstein interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Moshe Feinstein Lander]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rav Moshe Feinstein]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=805</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Rabbi Bernie Lander A”H died last week. He was from the G.I Generation also called the Greatest Generation. They lived through the depression, WWII, and the rise from the tenements of NY to middle class. They tended to seek solutions &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/17/r-bernard-lander-officer-krupke-and-rav-moshe-feinstein/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rabbi Bernie Lander A”H died last week. He was from the G.I Generation also called the Greatest Generation. They lived through the depression, WWII, and the rise from the tenements of NY to middle class. They tended to seek solutions in social sciences and thought of law as social realism. He came of age in the Judaism of the 1930’s atheistic and Communist fleeing from religion. His writings followed the Chicago school of social science, which looked at society based on class, caste, and place of immigrant settlement. </p>
<p>Lander’s Phd and book was on what to do with juvenile delinquents. The short films Dead End Kids and Bowery Boys were intended to portray what downtown Jews were like. The Chicago school considered that juvenile delinquency portrayed in these films was due to the breakdown of the social fabric of family, school, religion, and community. <a href="http://www.risa.co.uk/sla/song.php?songid=15021">Think of the song     </a><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pq28qCklEHc"> &#8220;Gee, Officer Krupke&#8221; </a>from West Side Story where the kids are blamed by judge, social worker, psychologist, and police. Lander in his Towards an Understanding of Juvenile Delinquency blamed the breakdown on inter-group conflicts, like between the Sharks and the Jets.  Bear in mind that West Side story was originally to be Jews and Irish in a rumble. Lander always thought in terms of class and social structure. He advocated education for the lower classes. In the 1960’s, he followed the ideas of alienation. &#8220;My conclusion,&#8221; he said, &#8220;was that the rioting was a reflection of how students were being treated as automatons. There was no relationship between students and university anymore. They were rioting against the depersonalization of American education.</p>
<p>Lander had been working on social issues since he worked for Mayor La Guardia to serve on a Civil Rights commission in 1941 and “from 1961 to 1969, Rabbi Dr. Lander researched poverty at Notre Dame, a Catholic University” He researched the juvenile delinquents and poverty of Spanish Harlem. His answer was education [and the Church]. He wrote a report on the need for government funding for education and housing for the Lavanburg Corner House for delinquents. “Dr. Lander pioneered no-frills education when adult education for the working class was in its infancy.”</p>
<p>So when he created Touro, he was thinking in terms of class and caste and creating a school for urban ethnic lower class Jews. “Touro, which was created in part on the model of more than a dozen small Catholic colleges interspersed throughout New York, was Lander’s way of enabling tradition-minded Jews to acquire a college education without having to go through the secularizing and depersonalized university machine.” Currently, Jews have forgotten about the class issues and see everything as religious ideology. </p>
<p>Lander as a member of the Greatest Generation saw things in terms of class, while the silent generation who were the major leaders of Modern Orthodoxy saw things in terms of the stable suburbia of the 1950’s. The Silent Generation catered to the middle class, spoke of liberal arts, and avoided getting their hands dirty with [gentiles or] social problems. By the 1980’s, modern Orthodoxy was already catering to a predominately second generation college, while Lander, still aiming at first generation college, understood that in social terms without an education then you don’t have social stability. If one is not thinking about religious ideology but about class, then there was little difference between his schools in 123st and Adam Clayton Powell Jr Blv in Harlem and his Brooklyn campuses.(If anyone from Touro is reading this and wants to commission a full 20 page article, then let me know).</p>
<p>Rabbi Lander dealt with more American social issues, had more exposure to gentiles, and had a more dynamic vision than the younger YU products who assumed the 1950’s would last forever. Most of the thinkers of the 1950’s Conservative movement were forged in the Greatest Generation, while modern Orthodoxy was more of a Silent generation movement (except for the older rabbis such as Rackman and Israel Miller). </p>
<p>The last time I saw Rabbi Lander was <a href="http://eucharistiemisericor.free.fr/index.php?page=1703092_card_vingt_trois">March 2009 was when the Catholic Cardinals came for their annual visit </a>and were hosted by Touro. The topic was to &#8220;train young believers in modernity, to train young believers in tradition.&#8221; There was a tour of the Holocaust museum and a plan to work together on Holocaust education, a discussion of current issues, and then speeches over dinner of fellowship and working together. It was a far cry from the responsa of Rav Moshe Feinstein from over 40 years prior. (I have the teshuvah at hand, as well as Aleksandrov and the Dali Lama in Hebrew, as part of my forthcoming BOOK TWO)</p>
<p><em>19 Adar I, 5727 – March 1, 1967 To my honored friend, Rabbi Dov Ber Lander<br />
Regarding the matter that you promised to attend the meeting on the 23rd of Adar I where Catholics and Protestants together with Jews from the Synagogue Council of America and Rabbis from the Rabbinical Council of America will meet. Even though you will only speak general words, it is obvious and clear that this is a severe prohibition of appurtenances of idolatry.  </p>
<p>For a plague is now spreading in many places because of the new pope (Pope Paul VI) whose only intention is to move all Jews away from their holy and pure faith to accept the Christian Faith. For it is easier to accomplish this through these methods than through hate and murder that previous popes have used. Therefore any dealing with them even on general matters and all [the more so] actual coming close for a meeting is forbidden with the severe prohibition of “coming close to idolatry.” There is also a prohibition of enticing and leading astray.”<br />
Even if you and the other rabbis who go there will be careful with your words and you will also not flatter the priests and their faith as do the Reform and Conservative rabbis, who entice and lead others to go astray, many people will learn from them that it is permitted to go to the events such as the lectures of the missionaries.  </p>
<p>Furthermore, you should not even send a letter there expressing what you planned on saying for any interaction with them further assists their evil plans. It is also forbidden to participate in any manner in meetings like these for I heard that they want to have in Boston and Rome. Anyone who joins with them will be considered one who entices and leads astray the Jewish people. For this that the Catholic missionaries tried so hard for all these years and had very little success, but through these rabbis who lack knowledge who want to join with them, it is possible that many will apostate. We cannot justify the one who entices by saying this was not his intention; he is guilty of a capital offense in this act and all that consequences. .</p>
<p>Therefore, do not be concerned with not keeping your promise to attend and speak. For on the contrary, perhaps through this that you do not go on account of the prohibition, perhaps others will not go and you will bring merit to the community.  Your Friend, Moshe Feinstein. </em></p>
<p>Based on David Ellenson, &#8220;Two Responsa of Rabbi Moshe Feinstein.&#8221; Chronicle of Hebrew Union College, Volume LII, Nos. 1 and 2, Fall 2000-2001.</p>
<p>When reading Rav Moshe, did you agree with his visceral reactions? Do you think that Rabbi Bernard Lander who had been working for Notre Dame thought that all Catholic clergy were out to convert the Jews? Do you think that he thought that in 2009 when hosting the Cardinals</p>
<p>When the septuagenarian Orthodox Rabbis who proudly proclaim that they follow Rav Soloveitchik, were busy flattering the Cardinals and discussing how they have been good friends for decades and how much they trust the Cardinals- were they still in the apprehensiveness of the 1960’s? Were these senior Orthodox rabbis, for whom the Catholic clergy are old and trusted friends, still viewing the meetings as a hidden missionary agenda? When those Jews who work in community organizing are continuously working with Catholic clergy in social projects, are they still waiting for the conversionary speech? What about when Orthodox rabbis or Orthodox organizations state that Catholic social theology and Halakhah are the same on marriage and that they should work with their Catholic friends in banning same-sex marriage? Are they still expecting missionary activity after the joint worldview statement? How about when Orthodox rabbis eagerly listen, and then applaud wildly, when Pastor Hagee tells them that God will bring the Jews to Israel where they will even convert after the wars of Gog and Magog?<br />
Is the change just due to the Culture Wars and new found Islamophobia or is there something more?</p>
<p>Copyright © 2010 Alan Brill • All Rights Reserved</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/17/r-bernard-lander-officer-krupke-and-rav-moshe-feinstein/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>My New Book Just Came Out-Judaism and Other Religions</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/13/my-new-book-just-came-out-judaism-and-other-religions/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/13/my-new-book-just-came-out-judaism-and-other-religions/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 14 Feb 2010 00:43:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Buddhism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[spirituality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[alan brill]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr Brill]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jewish interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Judaism and other religions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[nathan Katz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rabbi Brill]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rabbi David Rosen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ruth Langer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=785</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[My book Judaism and Other Religions is to be officially released on March 2nd by Palgrave-Macmillan. But it is already available in the warehouse and available for purchase, Be the first one on your block to own one. Buy it &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/13/my-new-book-just-came-out-judaism-and-other-religions/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My book <strong>Judaism and Other Religions</strong> is to be officially released on March 2nd by Palgrave-Macmillan. But it is already available in the warehouse and available for purchase, Be the first one on your block to own one. Buy it now:</p>
<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Judaism-Other-Religions-Models-Understanding/dp/0230622267/ref=ntt_at_ep_dpt_2">Click here to buy it at Amazon </a></strong></p>
<p><a href="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="165" data-permalink="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/about/brill0230622267-2/" data-orig-file="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg" data-orig-size="396,594" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;}" data-image-title="Brill0230622267" data-image-description="" data-medium-file="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg?w=200" data-large-file="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg?w=396" class="alignleft size-medium wp-image-165" title="Brill0230622267" src="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg?w=200&#038;h=300" alt="" width="200" height="300" srcset="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg?w=200&amp;h=300 200w, https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg?w=100&amp;h=150 100w, https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg 396w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /></a></p>
<p><strong>Editorial Reviews</strong></p>
<p>“This wide-ranging but carefully organized collection of Jewish thought about other religions constitutes an indispensable resource for Jews and non-Jews engaged in interreligious relations today and for Jews seeking to develop a text-based contemporary Jewish theology of religions for our global world. Brill accompanies his lucid presentations of each approach with insightful critiques that will help guide their contemporary applications.”—Ruth Langer, Associate Professor of Jewish Studies, Theology Department Associate Director, Center for Christian-Jewish Learning, Boston College</p>
<p>“Serious Jewish engagement with other religions has substantially deepened and widened in recent years, both stimulating and responding to an increasing interest in Judaism from within the other world religions. Brill’s book provides essential access to the classical sources within the Jewish tradition relevant to this encounter.”—Rabbi Dr. David Rosen, International Director of Interreligious Affairs, AJC</p>
<p>“This is an excellent work: reflective, engaging, well-written, and perhaps most important—timely. Brill knows both the theoretical foundations for interreligious dialogue and rabbinic approaches to ‘other religions.’ It is a fine piece of scholarship, and it is also creative in bringing together three fields of discourse in a way they have not before been aligned. It blends both traditional and modern thinking about interreligious dialogue, and it analyzes these materials convincingly.”—Nathan Katz, Professor of Religious Studies, Florida International University</p>
<p><strong>Product Description</strong></p>
<p>With insight and scholarship, Alan Brill crisply outlines the traditional Jewish approaches to other religions for an age of globalization. He provides a fresh perspective on Biblical and Rabbinic texts, offering new ways of thinking about other faiths. In the majority of volume, he develops the categories of theology of religions for Jewish texts. He arranges the texts according classification widely used in interfaith work: inclusivist, exclusivist, universalist, and pluralist.</p>
<p>Judaism and Other Religions is essential for a Jewish theological understanding of the various issues in encounters with other religions. With passion and clarity, Brill argues that in today’s world of strong religious passions and intolerance, it is necessary to go beyond secular tolerance toward moderate and mediating religious positions.</p>
<p><strong><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Judaism-Other-Religions-Models-Understanding/dp/0230622267/ref=ntt_at_ep_dpt_2">Click here to buy it at Amazon </a></strong></p>
<p>There is a forthcoming sequel volume <strong>Judaism and World Religions,</strong> which will be available at the end of 2010.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/13/my-new-book-just-came-out-judaism-and-other-religions/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>10</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2009/09/brill02306222671.jpg?w=200" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">Brill0230622267</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Aleksandrov, Rav Kook, Buddhism, and Gentile Religion</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/13/aleksandrov-rav-kook-buddhism-and-gentile-religion/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/13/aleksandrov-rav-kook-buddhism-and-gentile-religion/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 14 Feb 2010 00:03:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Buddhism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[alexsandrov]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gentile relgion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mikhteve Mehkar]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rabbi Kook]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rav Kook]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Shmuel Alexandrov]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=778</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I subscribe to the VBM shiur by Tamir Granot on the letters of Rav Kook. Currently, the discussion is a letter of Rav Kook to Shmuel Aleksandrov on the topic of modern philosophy and the wisdom of other religions. The &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/13/aleksandrov-rav-kook-buddhism-and-gentile-religion/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I subscribe to the <a href="http://vbm-torah.org/archive/igrot/10igrot.htm">VBM shiur by Tamir Granot on the letters of Rav Kook. </a>Currently, the discussion is a letter of Rav Kook to Shmuel Aleksandrov on the topic of modern philosophy and the wisdom of other religions. The shiur is entirely from Rav Kook’s perspective, I want to add a little background on Alexandrov and the give Alexandrov&#8217;s perspective.</p>
<p>The initial letter from him is in Samuel Alexandrov, <em>Mikhteve meḥḳar u-viḳoret: al devar ha-Yahadut ṿeha-rabanut ba-zeman ha-aḥaron </em>(Yerushalaim: M. ṿe-G. Aleksandrov 1931).  The first volume of<em> Mikhteve Mehkar</em> from 1906 is readily available, but the 1931 second volume is missing from JTSA and YU, rumored by a catalog to be at Penn and seems to only really exist in the US at Harvard. However, it is available in several copies at JNUL.  Most of the following is from Alexandrov’s letter. </p>
<p>Rabbi Shmuel Aleksandrov (d. 1941) had been a close friend of Rabbi Abraham Isaac Kook in Volozhin, where they both studied. Unlike Kook, Aleksandrov never left Russia, and became a rabbi in Bobruisk. Until his death at the hands of the Germans in 1941, Aleksandrov was a spiritual leader to many rabbis, particularly during the severe religious persecutions of the 1920s and &#8217;30s in the USSR. </p>
<p>Aleksandrov propounded a grand theory of the relationship between Jews and Gentiles, containing deep roots in the Kabbalah and Maharal. According to Aleksandrov, of the two trees in the Garden of Eden, the Tree of Life and the Tree of Knowledge, the former is an exclusively Jewish possession, i.e. Torah, while the Tree of Knowledge belongs to the Gentiles. Among its fruits are scientific-technical progress, philosophy, and art. Nevertheless, there exists a mystical exchange of the fruits of both trees. By giving to the world the fruits of the Tree of Life, Jews consecrate the Gentile world, while simultaneously Jews receive from the Gentiles the fruits of vital knowledge and ideas.</p>
<p>Among these ideas of the nations, Alexandrov especially seeks to find a place for the wisdom learned from other religions, specifically the idea of Buddhist nothingness. Aleksandrov claimed that one universal truth forms the basis of all religions; hence, the Buddhist concept of nirvana and Hasidic concept of <em>ayin </em>point to the same concept in different words.  He made this assertion based not on the study of texts nor from encountering Buddhists, but rather from the conceptualizations of religion found in the writings of Schelling and Schopenhauer. </p>
<p>Alexandrov postulates a universal religion given by Moses and reiterated by Plato,that overcomes the abstract intellect knowledge of contemporary knowledge by incorporating emotional and psychological knowledge, and offering individual salvation. </p>
<p>Aleksandrov reinterprets the thought of his forefather the Maharal to suggest a complementary movement between Israel and the nations, rather than an antagonistic struggle. For Alexandrov, the dialectic of Israel and the nations, presented by Maharal, will be overcome at the end of days when all national differences will be abolished by the coming of the Messiah. </p>
<p>Rabbi Kook found this approach to concede too much to universalism. Rav Kook responded to Aleksandrov’s universal claims with a inclusivist claim that all truth is from Judaism, and in other places states that Jews can elevate the light in other faiths. Here, Rav Kook presents his view of God as not the monotheism of the philosophers, rather the light, the spectrum of colors, and Edenic watering  of the Zohar. Rav Kook accentuates  the Schopenhauer pessimism of Buddhism and states that even Buddhists want to get beyond the pessimism of this world. (Google Schopenhauer and Buddhism for more details).  I don’t have a scan of Alexandrov in my computer but I will cite Rav Kook as in the VBM shuir and another paragraph from latter in the same letter. He writes:</p>
<blockquote><p>Monotheism is a fabrication of gentiles, an imprecise translation, a sort of self-contradictory comprehensible infinity, and therefore can lead to nothing. This is not the source of the name of the God of Israel, the infinite, incomprehensible root of all existence, because He is the existence of the world who can be comprehended and spoken of only through the nuances of colors through many deeds and abundant peace, his profusion of love and courage. Israel proclaims, “This is my God and I will adore Him,” and can see these [colors], not the barren wilderness of Islamic monotheism, nor Buddhism’s negation, only the highest existence which brings joy to all and gives life to everything, revealed through the subjective revelation of all hearts who seek and comprehend him.</p>
<p>As for the reality of nothingness in the statements of those of Buddhist leanings, it seems that they mean the reality of the force which aspires to negate and nullify absolutely…Jewish consciousness, however, in the goodness of God’s knowledge, brings about a recognition of the absolute reality. …Thus we find that even this contradiction between Buddhism and Judaism is not absolute opposites, because reality as viewed without God is everywhere evil and bitter, and in its midst lies the longing for absolute negation, which will in the end be fulfilled. </p></blockquote>
<p>Aleksandrov had observed that Jews throughout history acquired knowledge from the wisdom all of nations during the exile, and claimed that contemporary Jews can continue this process through study of Buddhism and other religions. Rav Kook, on the other hand, found all of religion in Judaism, minimizing any need to study other religions.</p>
<p>This debate played itself out in their differing concepts of religion. For Aleksandrov, an infinite inner core of the Divine resides behind the particular Jewish commandments; the current versions express the infinite by limiting it to concrete forms. In contrast, for Rav Kook, the commandments in their concrete particular forms contain an infinite essence that needs to be brought into daily life.<br />
For Aleksandrov, Judaism and its commandments are themselves limits on the infinite Divine, while for Rav Kook the commandments are the very conduits of the infinite. </p>
<p>Once we move beyond the 19th century German idealism of the debate &#8211; what value does this debate hold for today? Any Thoughts?<br />
On the subject of Buddhism and Judaism, here was one of my very first posts on this blog &#8211; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/13/first-jewish-reference-to-the-dalai-lama/">The first Jewish reference to the Dalai Lama.</a></p>
<p>Copyright © 2010 Alan Brill • All Rights Reserved</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/13/aleksandrov-rav-kook-buddhism-and-gentile-religion/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>8</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Jonathan Boyarin, The Unconverted Self</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/06/jonathan-boyarin-the-unconverted-self/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/06/jonathan-boyarin-the-unconverted-self/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2010 02:24:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[interfaith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[chosen people]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[goyiche kup]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[goyim]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jonathan boyarin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[unconverted self]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=727</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[People on the outside, or with a polemic bone to pick, tend to view interfaith dialogue as discussions that continue the medieval theological positions. As if people debate about when the Messiah will come or use 13th century definitions An &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/06/jonathan-boyarin-the-unconverted-self/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>People on the outside, or with a polemic bone to pick, tend to view interfaith dialogue as discussions that continue the medieval theological positions. As if people debate about when the Messiah will come or use 13th century definitions  An example some of the new activity in interfaith dialogue is a paper first delivered at the Jesuit-Jewish Dialogue Conference held at Fordham University, is the new book by Jonathan Boyarin,  <em>The Unconverted Self: Jews, Indians, and the Identity of Christian Europe </em>University of Chicago Press, 208 page.</p>
<p>The book <a href="http://www.forward.com/articles/124887/">was reviewed in this week’s Forward.</a> Boyarin comes from the field of anthropology, not theology, and asks how did the concept of the “other” become constructed? What was the role of the Jew as the “other” compared to the native American.</p>
<p>The book rejects “The conventional wisdom is that Europe found its “other,” its supposed opposite against which it could define itself, when it found the indigenous peoples of the New World. Rather, “European Christians had been dealing with “others” — namely, Jews and Muslims — long before that greedy Italian navigator met the Arawaks of the Caribbean.”</p>
<p>The review points out that the book assumes a great deal of prior knowledge about earlier categories. &#8220;He assumes, therefore, a familiarity with Spain’s limpieza de sangre (blood purity laws first enacted in the late 15th century) and the ideas of Bartolomé de las Casas (a 16th-century missionary who quaintly suggested not brutalizing Africans and indigenous Americans).&#8221; </p>
<p>My question is to ask his observations back at the Jewish categories. How do Jews use blood purity laws to view gentiles? In the famous The <a href="http://userwww.sfsu.edu/~epf/2001/hernandez.html">Las Casas-Sepúlveda Controversy</a>, which side would Jews take? I am grossly over simplifying since there debate involved detailed knowledge of Aristotelian commentaries and medieval thought, but the basis controversy is that Las Casas thought that there is a concept of humanity and Sepulveda believed in a hierarchy, so that Christians are superior to indigenous people. Do Jews create a hierarchy?</p>
<p>The reviewer reacts to the idea of imposing one’s definitions of rationality onto another. </p>
<blockquote><p>One of the more interesting (and disturbing) sections of “The Unconverted Self” concerns how Christians defined what it meant to be human. In the 12th century, reason was supposedly the criterion — and if Jews did not demonstrate their capacity for reason by becoming Christian, then they must be something less than human.</p></blockquote>
<p>Do Jews define reason in specific Jewish ways and then proclaim that the other side has a goyiche kop? Do Jews think that Judaism is more rational than other faiths and still assume that they are using universal criteria for rationality? If an anthropologist were to ask how Jews view the world would there be anthropological categories of the other that have little to do with Rabbinic concepts of chosen people and books of Jewish thought and more to do with self definitions and hierarchical perceptions of the other?</p>
<p>Copyright © 2010 Alan Brill • All Rights Reserved</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/06/jonathan-boyarin-the-unconverted-self/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
