<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Ka&#8217;et Orthodox Dance Ensemble	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/15/kaet-orthodox-dance-ensemble/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/15/kaet-orthodox-dance-ensemble/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2011 07:57:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: SSecunda		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/15/kaet-orthodox-dance-ensemble/#comment-2439</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[SSecunda]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2011 07:57:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2838#comment-2439</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I must not have been clear:
&quot;sexuality should be allowed to flourish independently of relationships, issurim like negiah and shikhvat zera levatala, etc.&quot;]
Sexuality is independent of (1) negiah (2) shikhvat zera, ec. He was saying what anyone mildly familiar with sexuality studies knows.  That sexuality is not simply using sexual organs or erotic touching... We are both saying the same thing.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I must not have been clear:<br />
&#8220;sexuality should be allowed to flourish independently of relationships, issurim like negiah and shikhvat zera levatala, etc.&#8221;]<br />
Sexuality is independent of (1) negiah (2) shikhvat zera, ec. He was saying what anyone mildly familiar with sexuality studies knows.  That sexuality is not simply using sexual organs or erotic touching&#8230; We are both saying the same thing.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Pierre		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/15/kaet-orthodox-dance-ensemble/#comment-2433</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pierre]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Jan 2011 15:06:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2838#comment-2433</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[but you&#039;d said Israeli wanted that sexuality should be allowed to flourish apart from relationships - I&#039;m not sure what other sexuality was intended, as you then listed what are generally considered issurim outside of sanctioned relationships. Chi Gong and tai chi and similar systems have people - within the parameters of their own bodies - conceiving of sexual energy as something that can be and should be refined and channeled, and then manipulate it through routes throughout the body (and not confined to &#039;their&#039; organs), to lead to healing, vitality and with practice, higher insight - again, for the most part in ways that aren&#039;t the issurim you describe that the Israeli seemed to be encouraging. It is not necessary to physical touch anyone to do much of this work, and avoiding emission for any but reproductive purposes is something precisely esteemed.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>but you&#8217;d said Israeli wanted that sexuality should be allowed to flourish apart from relationships &#8211; I&#8217;m not sure what other sexuality was intended, as you then listed what are generally considered issurim outside of sanctioned relationships. Chi Gong and tai chi and similar systems have people &#8211; within the parameters of their own bodies &#8211; conceiving of sexual energy as something that can be and should be refined and channeled, and then manipulate it through routes throughout the body (and not confined to &#8216;their&#8217; organs), to lead to healing, vitality and with practice, higher insight &#8211; again, for the most part in ways that aren&#8217;t the issurim you describe that the Israeli seemed to be encouraging. It is not necessary to physical touch anyone to do much of this work, and avoiding emission for any but reproductive purposes is something precisely esteemed.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ssecunda		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/15/kaet-orthodox-dance-ensemble/#comment-2422</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ssecunda]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Jan 2011 07:29:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2838#comment-2422</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[That is certainly the case with me and some of my friends - and I refer more to the Platonic tie.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>That is certainly the case with me and some of my friends &#8211; and I refer more to the Platonic tie.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/15/kaet-orthodox-dance-ensemble/#comment-2418</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Jan 2011 21:02:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2838#comment-2418</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The old joke of the necktie being a brisker gartel has much truth for the Orthodox world writ large. To extend the joke/metaphor a bit, perhaps many Modern Orthodox Americans look to moving to Israel in order to no longer having to wear a tie.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The old joke of the necktie being a brisker gartel has much truth for the Orthodox world writ large. To extend the joke/metaphor a bit, perhaps many Modern Orthodox Americans look to moving to Israel in order to no longer having to wear a tie.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ssecunda		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/15/kaet-orthodox-dance-ensemble/#comment-2417</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ssecunda]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Jan 2011 20:23:37 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2838#comment-2417</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[That&#039;s precisely what he was talking about, but he considered it a nonconventional form of sexuality.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>That&#8217;s precisely what he was talking about, but he considered it a nonconventional form of sexuality.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Pierre		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/15/kaet-orthodox-dance-ensemble/#comment-2414</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pierre]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Jan 2011 16:49:33 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2838#comment-2414</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Random response to the random thoughts on the body;
As a single person who does an internal tai chi related system, I&#039;m amazed this Israeli seriously trained in chi-work didn&#039;t discuss *sublimating* the sexual thoughts, drives and body functions into cultivating such energy productively...which is precisely a component of these systems! And I think THAT does need to &#039;flourish&#039; in Judaism. There are such profoundly unhealthy views of the body going on in the world at large, observant Jewish societies have lashed back not simply the &#039;other&#039; direction - but away from the body as such. I think this Israeli was seriously trained in being Israeli more  than anything else.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Random response to the random thoughts on the body;<br />
As a single person who does an internal tai chi related system, I&#8217;m amazed this Israeli seriously trained in chi-work didn&#8217;t discuss *sublimating* the sexual thoughts, drives and body functions into cultivating such energy productively&#8230;which is precisely a component of these systems! And I think THAT does need to &#8216;flourish&#8217; in Judaism. There are such profoundly unhealthy views of the body going on in the world at large, observant Jewish societies have lashed back not simply the &#8216;other&#8217; direction &#8211; but away from the body as such. I think this Israeli was seriously trained in being Israeli more  than anything else.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ssecunda		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/15/kaet-orthodox-dance-ensemble/#comment-2401</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ssecunda]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2011 19:54:50 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2838#comment-2401</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Random related thoughts on Orthodoxy  the body:
The other day I was at a fascinating forum made up mainly of Dati Israelis  - along with two American olim, including myself.  The topic was the sexual challenges of singles - especially older singles -  in the Orthodox community. It was fascinating to watch the different discourses, Israeli and American, take shape.  The Israeli discourse about the body was so different than the American Modern Orthodox one - or lack thereof.   One hippy-ish Israeli there who has trained seriously in tai chi and leads a chabura in Jewish sources and body movement gave an impassioned speech about how sexuality should be allowed to flourish independently of relationships, issurim like negiah and shikhvat zera levatala, etc.  
I cannot for a moment imagine anything similar being said at an American MO gathering about singles and sexuality...]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Random related thoughts on Orthodoxy  the body:<br />
The other day I was at a fascinating forum made up mainly of Dati Israelis  &#8211; along with two American olim, including myself.  The topic was the sexual challenges of singles &#8211; especially older singles &#8211;  in the Orthodox community. It was fascinating to watch the different discourses, Israeli and American, take shape.  The Israeli discourse about the body was so different than the American Modern Orthodox one &#8211; or lack thereof.   One hippy-ish Israeli there who has trained seriously in tai chi and leads a chabura in Jewish sources and body movement gave an impassioned speech about how sexuality should be allowed to flourish independently of relationships, issurim like negiah and shikhvat zera levatala, etc.<br />
I cannot for a moment imagine anything similar being said at an American MO gathering about singles and sexuality&#8230;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
