<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>prayer &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/tag/prayer/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 May 2010 02:55:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='kavvanah.wordpress.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/c9f111237f93750b6b994fc5185d49c3?s=96&#038;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>prayer &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>Cordovero on the nature of Prayer</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2010 02:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[devekut]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[moshe cordovero]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[prayer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1230</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[For those following the more pietistic discussion on Ramak’s prayer, here is some more for discussion. The first text is on devekut. The second text is on the inability of prayer to rise without ascending level by level through the &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For those following the more pietistic discussion on Ramak’s prayer, here is some more for discussion. The first text is on devekut. The second text is on the inability of prayer to rise without ascending level by level through the known levels. One cannot prayer directly to the Eyn Sof. Any reactions or insights? I am delivering a conference paper next week on the topic, so all observations are helpful. Any insights to the meditation process?</p>
<p><strong>Devekut</strong></p>
<p>“Through these mysteries, a man is able to cleave to his master with will…”<br />
A person can cleave to Him through directing his will to the mystery of the sefirot, the Tetragrammaton, and the [other] Divine names. One who does not know the mystery of how to cleave to Him will not have the ability to grasp (beit ahizah),  because His place of grasping is through His sefirot, His precious names and holy Tetragrammaton.<br />
“In directing the heart to know the wisdom of His dominance in the highest mystery.” The dominance of hokhmah is a wondrous mystery. The first way to reach a state of cleaving to the Divine (devekut) is through the study of the mysteries of the Torah and the understanding of the hidden secrets in the Torah.<br />
The second is “when he worships his Master in prayer,” that is, the mystery of prayer and the way of cleaving to Him.<br />
“He will cleave like a flame in a coal&#8221;—for man’s will and soul that ascend from the walls of his heart will certainly be bound to the supernal palaces. Thus, man should first meditate on repairing malkhut, Her repairs are the mystery of the palaces, which bind and cleave together with malkhut like a flame bound in a coal, while his soul and meditation are a flame from the coal that is malkhut. Similarly, the palaces that spread out from and cleave to Her are like a flame spreading out from amidst the coal, yet cleaving to it. Because of this, the [palaces] return to their source and are swallowed up in Her through his soul that returns and is swallowed in its source. With the soul’s ascent, the [palaces] are raised as well, since only through the soul can they spread out below. Now this is the mystery of man’s intention and breath of his mouth created from the vapor of his mouth and the soul (neshamah) arising through breath (neshimah), that they cleave and return to their source. If it happens that the palaces, and further, the hizonim, spread out from there, he should meditate on binding and unifying her specifically from the palace of paved sapphire (livnat hasappir) and higher. There is the beginning of holy cleaving, binding themselves in unification.<br />
 <br />
<strong>Ascent of prayers</strong></p>
<p>When the Shekhinah is completely filled with prayers, then the prayers rise and ascend to a place where there is no pain and no lack.<br />
The purpose of ascent into worship of God is so the prayer should reach this place. Some people meditate in times of need, as it is written, &#8220;Israel are wise in that they know how to pray in times of need.&#8221; However, better and more meritorious is he who raises all of his prayers there [even not in a time of need].<br />
This form of worship is more desirable because it does not come out of pain or need, but rather from cleaving through worship to the true Object of worship.<br />
The masses think that the intention reaches there by itself; they are completely outside the palace, so that when they call the king from afar, the king does not answer them.<br />
Rather, it is necessary to call to the gatekeeper. The gatekeeper takes them in his hand and brings them into the control of the princes, from prince to prince of each palace, until they are brought to the king in his chamber, where they will find Him and bring their needs before Him.<br />
For those who pray or cleave to Ein Sof by itself, their goal remains far from them. He is only close to the one who knows His palaces and gatekeepers.<br />
Indeed,  for those who speak to the gatekeeper which is the attribute of malkhut, the attribute will bring them to the higher attributes higher, level after level through all the levels.<br />
These people will certainly enter to the King, Ein Sof, the Root of all roots, in His room, a wondrous place, and speak with Him, in the mystery of the ascent of prayer. Immediately, it will be powerful.  </p>
<p>Copyright © 2010 Alan Brill • All Rights Reserved</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/cordovero-on-the-nature-of-prayer/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>20</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Michael Fishbane – Sacred attunements – part III</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/27/michael-fishbane-%e2%80%93-sacred-attunements-%e2%80%93-part-iii/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/27/michael-fishbane-%e2%80%93-sacred-attunements-%e2%80%93-part-iii/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2009 22:30:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[spirituality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[micahel fishbane]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pardes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[prayer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[revelation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sacred attunements]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sinai]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=409</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Sacred Attunements chapters 2 and 3 continued from part I here and part II here. Chapter II – “Jewish theology begins at Sinai, but God was before this event” Sinai is commitment, creation of scripture, prophecy. Divine presence and efectivity &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/27/michael-fishbane-%e2%80%93-sacred-attunements-%e2%80%93-part-iii/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sacred Attunements chapters 2 and 3 continued from <a href="http:///kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/21/sacred-attunments-part-1/">part I here</a> and <a href="http:///kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/19/michael-fishbane-–-sacred-attunement-–-part-ii/">part II here.</a></p>
<p>Chapter II – “Jewish theology begins at Sinai, but God was before this event”</p>
<p>Sinai is commitment, creation of scripture, prophecy. Divine presence and efectivity is the horizon. It takes courage to live in the light of the truth of the covenant.We want to enter the language of revelation.</p>
<p>(This is a great existential definition sharply removing Sinai from the symbolic and human, but not going as far into the experiential-mystical as Rav Kook. One of the times Fishbane spoke at the local minyan, he discussed Rav Kook and it seemed like he was using the <em>or penimi</em> without the <em>or makif</em>. he shows nice use of Ricouer)</p>
<p>“The decisive turn to Sinai is made by the solitary spirit..” First, we move out of habit into commitment, then attentiveness to encounter. We return to community to formulate a life of justice and righteousness. Our model Moses could endure censural vastness and then return to work in the community unlike Elijah and Job who were lost in silent submission and did not formulate a covenant with God.</p>
<p>Three cords of Torah, Sinai is an ongoing spirit of Jewish living producing the Oral Torah and behind all the Torah is a broader Torah kelulah, a openness to Being. Behind the Torah was Sinai is an even deeper Torah kelulah which pulsates through reality, through Being. (Nice ability to avoid Heschel’s dichotomy of Torah from Sinai and Torah from Heaven).</p>
<p>Texts unfold into life by means of interpretation</p>
<p>Peshat is subjugation of self to text. But there is no one peshat. It is ever constructed in the acts of reading and speaking. Peshat is attentiveness to details of the text.</p>
<p>Derush – contemporary ongoing meanings, relationship words to each other, conjoined words, oral words- this is the oral Torah. Drush gathers textual cations into a vortex of instruction.  It helps us become human and build character. Drush is a serious theological task. Mythic conceptions are not childlike crudities but creative imagination striving to grasp what is sensed.</p>
<p>Remez is finding the supersensual ideas of philosophy in the text. In great hands, like those of Maimonides he returns to the peshat and finds the openings to the higher truths in the text. Remez offer stairwells, or Jacob’s Ladder to high truths.</p>
<p>Sod – revealing and concealing of aspects of divinity. It seeks alignment with the language and energies of discussions of divine structures. We move beyond the text to a meta-communicative level. The eye for symbols, the ear for sounds, and the mouth for the recitation and mindful meditative life-rhythm.</p>
<p>Chapter III “Living within the covenant, we are challenged to actualize the principles of Sinai at every moment, through the bonds we forge with persons and things in the course of life.”</p>
<p>Halakhah is the gesture of the generations – ongoing practices cultivated and inculcated for the various spheres of life.</p>
<p>Fishbane calls God –“the life of all life” from a neoplatonic piyyut of Saadyah. This is his preferred term for God.</p>
<p>The second half of the chapter is on prayer and has lots of insights. Many of the paragraphs are poetic insights strung together. I need to teach it once in the context of other exhortations to prayer (Hirsch, Heschel, Rav Kook, Rebbe Reshab) in order to grasp the finer points.</p>
<p>“The phenomena of prayer responds to the vastness of sounds and sights which surround us in the natural world.”</p>
<p>(Most studies of Jewish prayer have parroted the work of Fredrich Heiler who has two types of prayer- petitionary and mystical. Moshe Greenberg on Biblical Prayer, Heinneman on Rabbinic prayer, Scholem on Kabbalistic prayer, Soloveitchik on Halakhic prayer have all used Heiler’s typology. But most Jewish prayer is actually Adoration, in which we praise to the King. Our prayer gestures are based on adoration to the King, and the Psalms we use are not petition but adoration.) Evelyn Underhill has a great book on Adoration produced almost the same year as Heiler.</p>
<p>Fishbane moves into the world of adoration using Gademer, Rilke, and the Psalms.</p>
<p>He presents four levels, a PARDES of prayer</p>
<p>Peshat- yes it is submission to the text—but also the silence before response, the articulation of human needs,, and a realization of the gaps and gifts of the world.</p>
<p>Derush-meaning in the present.Remez  &#8211; higher wisdom and abstractions- he asks: what would they say?</p>
<p>Sod- reaching the unfathomable, toward the Transcendent, toward religious censura</p>
<p>He ends the chapter with a homily explaining gemilut hasadim as radical kindness.</p>
<p>(Great, contemporary Jewry can use a lot more on kindness and gemilut Hasidim)  but then returning to Heidegger and Rosenzweig –we get “”Ultimately, the phenomena of hesed is the practice of death….successively divesting oneself.”</p>
<p>(If one sees oneself in a tight knit community then Miktav  MiEliyahu offers a world of mashbia and mekabel were everyone is always giving and receiving. But if one is an isolated individual then there it is death to give.)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/27/michael-fishbane-%e2%80%93-sacred-attunements-%e2%80%93-part-iii/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lord Jonathan Sacks on the Siddur</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/29/lord-jonathan-sacks-on-the-siddur/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/29/lord-jonathan-sacks-on-the-siddur/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2009 05:44:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[liturgy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[popular religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rabbis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[and dignity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[faith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Franz Rosenzweig]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hope]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jonathan Sacks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jonathan Sacks Siddur]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[justice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lord sacks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[orthodox universalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[prayer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[redemption]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[revelation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[universalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[witness]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=316</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[1] When I think of certain prayer books commentaries, I sometimes think of them with a few words. Hirsch – moral aspiration, Birnbaum &#8211; historical anti-Semitism Artscroll – Hashem centered,   Rebbe – attachment to God For Sacks, the words are &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/29/lord-jonathan-sacks-on-the-siddur/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>1] When I think of certain prayer books commentaries, I sometimes think of them with a few words. Hirsch – moral aspiration, Birnbaum &#8211; historical anti-Semitism Artscroll – Hashem centered,   Rebbe – attachment to God</p>
<p><strong>For Sacks, the words are hope, faith, and dignity.</strong></p>
<p>Full disclosure – I received a copy from the publisher after <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/08/lord-jonathan-sacks-on-the-concept-of-witness/">my last post on the idea of witness in his thought</a>. In short, my reaction is that his books are generally well crafted and delivered publicly, but here we have short comments not fully explained or justified.</p>
<p>2]  Collective Prayer</p>
<p>His message throughout the siddur is collective faith, we join with others. Prayer concerns the past and future of the community, the people Israel. The prayer is adoration and praise for God – our highest aspirations for the Jewish people. He favors Yehudah Halevi– prayer shows a God of history and human events. We learn from prayer the need to maintain faith, hope, dignity, and pride.</p>
<p>What is prayer? Prayer changes us – it is self-fulfillment He opens the book with a definition that prayer is conversation with God and never actually uses that definition in the book. From his commentary, prayer is listening and shaping oneself from the liturgy. Symbols need meditations therefore many do the yehi ratzon (cf. Hirsch).</p>
<p>His commentary is not very spiritual, emotional, or experiential, despite his use of these words. For example, he states the repetition of the amidah is the peak of religious experience because it contains the kedushah which was based on prophetic and mystic visions. Liturgy is not experience or experiential. Nor will one find much solace or human struggle in the prayer book.</p>
<p>Like the commentaries on Book of Common Prayer – he offers Biblical teachings applied in everyday life. The book is not very Rabbinic.</p>
<p>The commentary on the weekday shaharit is on the history of the liturgy and on the Shabbat shaharit is more theological.</p>
<p>3] Justice</p>
<p>His vision is that prayer will teach us personal and social responsibilitie. There is a cosmic moral standard of justice  God’s eternal values for the affairs of humankind-are justice to the oppressed, food to the hungry, freedom to captives, and hope to those at the margins of society.” Korban (sacrifice) is the pledging of ourselves to do his will. Peace the ultimate hope of monotheism. [Wow – this is nice universalism and good ethical monotheism- will it mold Orthodoxy?]</p>
<p>He writes: We believe that “The world is the product of single will , not the blind clash of conflicting elements”.[what of divine mandated clashes and exclusivism?]</p>
<p>He writes &#8220;Havdalah means making distinctions&#8221;, &#8220;to make order out of chaos, God wants us to be creative.&#8221; That is great homiletic but will it encourage the production of what the wider world calls creativity?</p>
<p>4] Revelation</p>
<p>Sacks writes that in contrast to the universal demands on Jews, Revelation is particular – it is our covenant of love with God – a relationship.Torah is our written constitution, collective memory, and record of covenant- not just sacred literature The message, however, of revelation is the universal justice, compassion, inalienable rights for the downtrodden.[This is the point were I find this commentary as selected quotes from his books on global ethics. Nothing is substantiated or justified here but they are justified in the books.In addition, the books come from speeches delivered in public to answer a need. These comments have no criteria for their inclusion.]</p>
<p>5] Christian locutions</p>
<p>a) Sacks writes that Resurrection is hope “ Jews kept hope alive, hope kept the Jewish people alive.”We have a divine promise and hope defeats tragedy</p>
<p>This is one of my pet peeve – tikvah and spes are not the same even if both translated as hope.</p>
<p>The former word tikvah is restoration –</p>
<p>[There is a debate of Radak and Ramban is if has the same meaning as kav – to make a line.]</p>
<p>Nahmanides says that just as a blueprint has lines drawn so too our tikvah for the national redemption is already drawn. Christian meaning of spes is of unseen things, the future, as part of the supernatural virtues of faith hope, and charity. For Christians hope is a virtue, for Jews, God (or Torah) has kept up Jewish hope for the redemption. One hopes in God, one does not hope as a virtue.</p>
<p>Sacks uses the word in several places in the Christian sense  and even has locutions like faith, hope, and dignity – cf the Christian faith, hope and charity</p>
<p>The use of the word hope in this sense is also used often in Shakespeare</p>
<p>b) On page 146 – he writes we are your witnesses, the bearers of your name. (Jews don&#8217;t use it like this)- <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/08/lord-jonathan-sacks-on-the-concept-of-witness/">see my prior post</a></p>
<p>c) He uses the phrase “free air of hope” – page 152 coined by the Irish theologian <em>George Tyrrell</em> (1861 – 1909).</p>
<p>6] He views religious language as metaphor</p>
<p>In many places he has a variant of the following: God is unknowable and belong words – the goal is to get behind words.</p>
<p>7] As a book</p>
<p>Well…A large number of quotes are quite cryptic – he likes good phrases better than good comments. Many times one cannot make out what it means. The full ideas in other books are here reduced to bon mots. Comments sometimes say “it may be” “may reflect” – so the effect is a more of a homily than a commentary.</p>
<p>Sometimes he cites his sources – in one case there are three cited names in a single  passage&#8212;and then there are many pages without a single citation. Yet, in his other works he cites the author of the interpretation. It seems arbitrary.</p>
<p>8] Sources and comparisons</p>
<p>a) On the topic of liturgy and spontaneity, he surprisingly does not use the usually rabbinic passages on keva and kavvanah but discusses the topic through passages the in Bible. Source seems to be an unnamed book on the Bible or early Rabbinics.</p>
<p>b) He cites historical material from a much much earlier decade with any new insight- he does not references to Yakovson (Jacobson), Abrahams, Elbogen or other works that he relies on.</p>
<p>c) Conspicuous in its absence is the Lubavitcher Rebbe since Sacks relied heavily on the Rebbe in earlier works and adapted a volume of the Rebbe on parashah. But Sacks makes prayer thankfulness and adoration – and does not follow the Rebbe that prayer is connection to God.</p>
<p>d) Sacks noticeably quotes Rav Soloveitchik in his introduction, as if to claim continuity or authenticity, but does not follow his approach to prayer in the commentary.For Soloveitchik, Prayer is the personal existential cry in which there is personal redemption through the tefilot and more importantly, the Torah give us words that raise us above our natural inarticulate grunts of animals.</p>
<p>e) Isaiah Berlin on negative freedom and positive freedom – is unattributed here, and presented as Hazal. In addition, he states that Jews as eternal from Tolstoy (in an earlier work he credited the citation to Hertz quoting Tolstoy) This quote of Tolstoy is also in Isaiah Berlin.But quoting that Jews are eternal from Tolstoy&#8212;and not from Krokhmal, Kook, Rosenzweig or Reines—reduced it to a bon mot.</p>
<p>f) In Alenu, he explains “leTaken Olam bemalkhut Shadai” as Lurianic tikkun – is it from Elliott Dorff in My People’s Prayer Book?</p>
<p>9] The sections in the introduction on study, mysticism, and history was less than adequate and quite vague. The section on mysticism could be from more than half a century ago. It has a tone of “Mysticism devalues world”</p>
<p>He takes Kabbalat Shabbat from Elbogen recognized by Elbogen&#8217;s its mistaken reliance on Solomon Schechter.  And one is not inspired to confidence when he writes that the source of Ushpezin is a nebulous “Jewish mystical tradition.”</p>
<p>10]  Now what of his frequent citation of Franz Rosenzweig on creation, revelation, redemption? I don&#8217;t get this one.</p>
<p>This triad is originally from Hermann Cohen where the triad is a divine meaning to creation in the natural order, the revelation of ethics in the human mind, and human work to make the world a better place. (One finds this Cohen triad occasionally in Rav Soloveitchik;s homilies.)</p>
<p>For Rosenzweig, it is God presence as meaning that negates nihilism, revelation is human love for God, and the liturgical fulfillment of eternity. Prayer along with poetry and love are means to let us be existentially human. For Gershom Scholem, it is a creation of emanation and tzimtzum, revelation of creativity and antinomianism, and redemption through apocalyptic change.</p>
<p>But for Sacks, it is God in nature, God revealed in Torah and prayer, and our redemption in history and life. Where is this mild version from and why bother linking it to Rosenzweig? I have not checked yet, but Netiv Binah by Jacobson and Taamei Hamizvot by Heinneman both combine Hirsch and Rosenzweig into a milder form.</p>
<p>Yet the way Sacks frames the triad it can just as well be Albo’s God, Revelation, and Reward or Cordovero’s God, Torah and Israel. There is a triad in Rabbinic thought and liturgy and in the Rabbinic reading of the Bible which has been formulated different ways in different eras. (see Max Kadushin’s Organic Thinking on this thinking in triads) I am not sure why Sacks attributed his reading to Rosenzweig when Albo or Cordovero would have better served his needs.</p>
<p>But then I found on the web a position similar to Sacks&#8212;“Rabbi Shlomo Wolbe explained that mans&#8217; relationship with G-d is three-dimensional; we know Him through His creation, His revelation at Sinai, and His promise of redemption.” Did both Sacks and Wolbe take it from Jacobson or Heinneman? Or another secondary source produced by German Jewry? Hmm..</p>
<p><strong>In short, I like the Orthodox universalism, but will stick to reading his longer works,</strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/29/lord-jonathan-sacks-on-the-siddur/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>5</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
