<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: The Soncino Bible editor Abraham Cohen “The Message of the Bible”	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/22/the-soncino-bible-editor-abraham-cohen-the-message-of-the-bible/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/22/the-soncino-bible-editor-abraham-cohen-the-message-of-the-bible/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2013 20:33:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: DF		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/22/the-soncino-bible-editor-abraham-cohen-the-message-of-the-bible/#comment-7529</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[DF]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2013 20:33:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5833#comment-7529</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thanks for this post, Alan. Dr. Cohen was clearly a tremendous talmid chacham. His &quot;Rishonim&quot; edition of the Chumash neatly summarizes the opinions of the basic mikras gedolos rishonim in a clear and cogent way.
As for the Soncino shas - I feel I may be one of the only Jews around who has gone through, page by page, nearly the entire Soncino shas. As they were prepared by different men, some volumes are better than others. The works of Eli Cashdan, for example, are excellent, while those of Leo Baeck, less so.  The &quot;square brackets&quot;, as he called them, where Dr. Epstein placed his comments of general interest, appear less and less frequent as one ventures further into Kodshim, and in some volumes are simply non existent. A. Cohen had a large hand in it, as did Judah Slotki and others.
The best feature of the shas, by the way, is not the translation itself, but the way it breaks the Gemara up into segements. As anyone knows, other than the occasional colon (&quot;two dots&quot;) which might appear every 3 or 4 pages, there are no breaks in the page. This makes is very difficult to know who is responding to what, and what argument goes with what. I can tell you that even bachurim spending all day in yeshivah frequently miss the thread of argument. The Soncino&#039;s paragraphing makes the give and take come alive. And it does it all without interpolating commentary into every single sentence of the pasasge like Artscroll does, resulting in a 78 volume edition.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thanks for this post, Alan. Dr. Cohen was clearly a tremendous talmid chacham. His &#8220;Rishonim&#8221; edition of the Chumash neatly summarizes the opinions of the basic mikras gedolos rishonim in a clear and cogent way.<br />
As for the Soncino shas &#8211; I feel I may be one of the only Jews around who has gone through, page by page, nearly the entire Soncino shas. As they were prepared by different men, some volumes are better than others. The works of Eli Cashdan, for example, are excellent, while those of Leo Baeck, less so.  The &#8220;square brackets&#8221;, as he called them, where Dr. Epstein placed his comments of general interest, appear less and less frequent as one ventures further into Kodshim, and in some volumes are simply non existent. A. Cohen had a large hand in it, as did Judah Slotki and others.<br />
The best feature of the shas, by the way, is not the translation itself, but the way it breaks the Gemara up into segements. As anyone knows, other than the occasional colon (&#8220;two dots&#8221;) which might appear every 3 or 4 pages, there are no breaks in the page. This makes is very difficult to know who is responding to what, and what argument goes with what. I can tell you that even bachurim spending all day in yeshivah frequently miss the thread of argument. The Soncino&#8217;s paragraphing makes the give and take come alive. And it does it all without interpolating commentary into every single sentence of the pasasge like Artscroll does, resulting in a 78 volume edition.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: IH		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/22/the-soncino-bible-editor-abraham-cohen-the-message-of-the-bible/#comment-7220</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[IH]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 23 Dec 2012 23:58:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5833#comment-7220</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Slightly off topic, but in November, Christine Hayes delivered the Tikvah Center’s annual Gruss lecture on  &quot;Divine Law: A Tale of Two Concepts (And Three Responses)&quot;  which I found excellent and thought provoking.  It can be viewed on http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=z5gdHl8cR7U 

Given her interest in, and command of Rabbinics, I was surprised by her choice of language in the Huffington Post piece you linked.  Maybe it&#039;s just me, but I fear she has left hostage to fortune – at least in regard of the Orthodox community -- by her use of the word “violence” (most particularly in “Correction #2”).   I look forward to reading the book, rather than watching the course online.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Slightly off topic, but in November, Christine Hayes delivered the Tikvah Center’s annual Gruss lecture on  &#8220;Divine Law: A Tale of Two Concepts (And Three Responses)&#8221;  which I found excellent and thought provoking.  It can be viewed on <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=z5gdHl8cR7U" rel="nofollow ugc">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=z5gdHl8cR7U</a> </p>
<p>Given her interest in, and command of Rabbinics, I was surprised by her choice of language in the Huffington Post piece you linked.  Maybe it&#8217;s just me, but I fear she has left hostage to fortune – at least in regard of the Orthodox community &#8212; by her use of the word “violence” (most particularly in “Correction #2”).   I look forward to reading the book, rather than watching the course online.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
