<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: The Social Animal by David Brooks	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/10/the-social-animal-by-david-brooks/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/10/the-social-animal-by-david-brooks/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2011 16:01:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/10/the-social-animal-by-david-brooks/#comment-2783</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2011 16:01:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3219#comment-2783</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&quot;Die Yuppie Scum, Die?&quot; is so 80s. We need a new mantra. How about &quot;Die Necon Scientism, Die&quot;?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&#8220;Die Yuppie Scum, Die?&#8221; is so 80s. We need a new mantra. How about &#8220;Die Necon Scientism, Die&#8221;?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: avrahambronstein		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/10/the-social-animal-by-david-brooks/#comment-2776</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[avrahambronstein]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2011 02:57:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3219#comment-2776</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/10/the-social-animal-by-david-brooks/#comment-2774&quot;&gt;ej&lt;/a&gt;.

EJ - there&#039;s a class in our society that&#039;s since recovered from 2008, got its bonus this year, and found that nothing&#039;s really changed. Remember, Brooks&#039; book is perpetually set in 2010. The market is booming, unemployment notwithstanding; that&#039;s not their problem.

That&#039;s the class Brooks writes about. The New Yorker excerpt was infuriating because it was essentially explaining how the upper class (which is more and more polarized from everyone else) is actually different from the rest of us, and is that way for reasons that go back to the womb. The way they pick up on cues, the way they read people and situations - their brains are actually wired differently than ours. It leads to, and supports, a smug conservatism that believes that the privileged deserve what they have - its just nature taking its course - and those who are not privileged are that way for scientifically measurable, hard-wired reasons.

Going back to Alan&#039;s question, it is more than a little frustrating to consider a community where the vast majority of households are two-income professionals - meaning the top 5% of wage-earning households in the country - and yet everyone complains that they cannot make ends meet.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/10/the-social-animal-by-david-brooks/#comment-2774">ej</a>.</p>
<p>EJ &#8211; there&#8217;s a class in our society that&#8217;s since recovered from 2008, got its bonus this year, and found that nothing&#8217;s really changed. Remember, Brooks&#8217; book is perpetually set in 2010. The market is booming, unemployment notwithstanding; that&#8217;s not their problem.</p>
<p>That&#8217;s the class Brooks writes about. The New Yorker excerpt was infuriating because it was essentially explaining how the upper class (which is more and more polarized from everyone else) is actually different from the rest of us, and is that way for reasons that go back to the womb. The way they pick up on cues, the way they read people and situations &#8211; their brains are actually wired differently than ours. It leads to, and supports, a smug conservatism that believes that the privileged deserve what they have &#8211; its just nature taking its course &#8211; and those who are not privileged are that way for scientifically measurable, hard-wired reasons.</p>
<p>Going back to Alan&#8217;s question, it is more than a little frustrating to consider a community where the vast majority of households are two-income professionals &#8211; meaning the top 5% of wage-earning households in the country &#8211; and yet everyone complains that they cannot make ends meet.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/10/the-social-animal-by-david-brooks/#comment-2774</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2011 23:04:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3219#comment-2774</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Here is a recent article from Haretz, easily applicable to America that gives a more realistic picture.
http://www.haaretz.com/print-edition/opinion/israel-is-no-country-for-women-1.347809

There is a total disconnect on Brooks part from what happened in 2008. Ever since then everyone is confused where we are going as a country, should we expect inflation or deflation, will the dollar fall apart, when we will stop piling on trillions of debt? Unless this couple is clueless, they worry if their savings will be worth anything down the road? 

I did find one happy woman just this morning, courtesy of Failed Messiah. You gotta love her. It&#039;s Adar so I couldn&#039;t resist. 

http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Em-e6w4e1v0&#038;feature=player_embedded]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here is a recent article from Haretz, easily applicable to America that gives a more realistic picture.<br />
<a href="http://www.haaretz.com/print-edition/opinion/israel-is-no-country-for-women-1.347809" rel="nofollow ugc">http://www.haaretz.com/print-edition/opinion/israel-is-no-country-for-women-1.347809</a></p>
<p>There is a total disconnect on Brooks part from what happened in 2008. Ever since then everyone is confused where we are going as a country, should we expect inflation or deflation, will the dollar fall apart, when we will stop piling on trillions of debt? Unless this couple is clueless, they worry if their savings will be worth anything down the road? </p>
<p>I did find one happy woman just this morning, courtesy of Failed Messiah. You gotta love her. It&#8217;s Adar so I couldn&#8217;t resist. </p>
<p><iframe class='youtube-player' width='500' height='282' src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/Em-e6w4e1v0?version=3&#038;rel=1&#038;fs=1&#038;autohide=2&#038;showsearch=0&#038;showinfo=1&#038;iv_load_policy=1&#038;wmode=transparent' allowfullscreen='true' style='border:0;'></iframe></p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/10/the-social-animal-by-david-brooks/#comment-2773</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2011 19:11:13 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3219#comment-2773</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/10/the-social-animal-by-david-brooks/#comment-2772&quot;&gt;avrahambronstein&lt;/a&gt;.

From the Salon review:

&lt;strong&gt;His buzzed-up new fiction/science amalgam had me leaping to my feet -- to yell, &quot;Die, yuppie scum, die!&quot;&lt;/strong&gt;
I had begun reading it determined to be dispassionate and analytic and fair, but I couldn&#039;t bear it for long: I learned to loathe Harold and Erica, the two upscale avatars of upper-middle-class values that Brooks marches through life in the story. And then I began to resent the omniscient narrator who narrates &lt;strong&gt;this exercise in unthinking consumption and privilege that is, supposedly, the ideal of happiness;&lt;/strong&gt; it&#039;s like watching a creepy middle-aged man fuss over his Barbie and Ken dolls, posing them in their expensive accessories and cars and houses and occasionally wiggling them in simulated carnal relations (have no worries, though: Like Barbie and Ken, no genitals appear anywhere in the book), while periodically pausing to tell his audience how cool it all is, and what is going on inside his dolls&#039; soft plastic heads.
&lt;strong&gt;Brooks has created a world where history doesn&#039;t matter and there are no troubling external intrusions on the blithe reality of Harold and Erica. If ever you are in the market for the antithesis of the Great Russian Novel, here it is, the petty provincial string of anecdotes about only two characters who never experience a moment of self-doubt or inner turmoil.&lt;/strong&gt;
I don&#039;t know whom this book is really written for.. . I suspect that its only virtue is in uniting C.P. Snow&#039;s two cultures, both of which will be populated with peeved readers flinging the book with great force across rooms everywhere.

So Avraham, when you visit a centrist Orthodox community that fits this bill: Do you want to scream Die Yuppie Scum, Die?  Do you associate the Five Towns with &quot;unthinking consumption and privilege&quot;? But back to my original question: What attitude should one take toward it? Should one want to change it? Should one reject it? Should one remain aloof and seek true philosophy? If one just smirks in irony then one actually is Brooks]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/10/the-social-animal-by-david-brooks/#comment-2772">avrahambronstein</a>.</p>
<p>From the Salon review:</p>
<p><strong>His buzzed-up new fiction/science amalgam had me leaping to my feet &#8212; to yell, &#8220;Die, yuppie scum, die!&#8221;</strong><br />
I had begun reading it determined to be dispassionate and analytic and fair, but I couldn&#8217;t bear it for long: I learned to loathe Harold and Erica, the two upscale avatars of upper-middle-class values that Brooks marches through life in the story. And then I began to resent the omniscient narrator who narrates <strong>this exercise in unthinking consumption and privilege that is, supposedly, the ideal of happiness;</strong> it&#8217;s like watching a creepy middle-aged man fuss over his Barbie and Ken dolls, posing them in their expensive accessories and cars and houses and occasionally wiggling them in simulated carnal relations (have no worries, though: Like Barbie and Ken, no genitals appear anywhere in the book), while periodically pausing to tell his audience how cool it all is, and what is going on inside his dolls&#8217; soft plastic heads.<br />
<strong>Brooks has created a world where history doesn&#8217;t matter and there are no troubling external intrusions on the blithe reality of Harold and Erica. If ever you are in the market for the antithesis of the Great Russian Novel, here it is, the petty provincial string of anecdotes about only two characters who never experience a moment of self-doubt or inner turmoil.</strong><br />
I don&#8217;t know whom this book is really written for.. . I suspect that its only virtue is in uniting C.P. Snow&#8217;s two cultures, both of which will be populated with peeved readers flinging the book with great force across rooms everywhere.</p>
<p>So Avraham, when you visit a centrist Orthodox community that fits this bill: Do you want to scream Die Yuppie Scum, Die?  Do you associate the Five Towns with &#8220;unthinking consumption and privilege&#8221;? But back to my original question: What attitude should one take toward it? Should one want to change it? Should one reject it? Should one remain aloof and seek true philosophy? If one just smirks in irony then one actually is Brooks</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: avrahambronstein		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/10/the-social-animal-by-david-brooks/#comment-2772</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[avrahambronstein]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2011 19:01:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3219#comment-2772</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Here&#039;s another negative, though less contemplative, review of the book.
http://www.salon.com/books/review/2011/03/04/pz_myers_on_david_brooks_the_social_animal/index.html]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here&#8217;s another negative, though less contemplative, review of the book.<br />
<a href="http://www.salon.com/books/review/2011/03/04/pz_myers_on_david_brooks_the_social_animal/index.html" rel="nofollow ugc">http://www.salon.com/books/review/2011/03/04/pz_myers_on_david_brooks_the_social_animal/index.html</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: chakira		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/03/10/the-social-animal-by-david-brooks/#comment-2768</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[chakira]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2011 13:53:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3219#comment-2768</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[One could paint a convincing picture of degeneration from Hegel&#039;s visions of sociality and sittlichkeit to Brooks, where sociality only exists to give us a more fulfilled suburban life due to the contingencies of evolution noticed by overachieving suburban scientists. The goal of articulation, of making the world transparent to ourselves, goes from life praxis or philosophical imperative  to somewhat useful thing for kiddie Soccer. I disagree with the impulse to denigrate the achievements of Shabbos Baseball leagues and Cholent cook offs, not to mention residencies at Beth Israel. My beef is not with the way of life, which seems nice enough compared to the various alternatives on display in Libya or even five miles away in Newark. Rather it is with the substitution of the self justification of this way of life for thought. Brooks is only the latest to buzz this cultural meme, and much more unacceptable in this regard is the faux production of literature ala Jonathan Franzen that raises, as one reviewer noted, the logic of &quot;f*ck it, i&#039;ll have the steak&quot; to the level of a Kantian antinomy.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One could paint a convincing picture of degeneration from Hegel&#8217;s visions of sociality and sittlichkeit to Brooks, where sociality only exists to give us a more fulfilled suburban life due to the contingencies of evolution noticed by overachieving suburban scientists. The goal of articulation, of making the world transparent to ourselves, goes from life praxis or philosophical imperative  to somewhat useful thing for kiddie Soccer. I disagree with the impulse to denigrate the achievements of Shabbos Baseball leagues and Cholent cook offs, not to mention residencies at Beth Israel. My beef is not with the way of life, which seems nice enough compared to the various alternatives on display in Libya or even five miles away in Newark. Rather it is with the substitution of the self justification of this way of life for thought. Brooks is only the latest to buzz this cultural meme, and much more unacceptable in this regard is the faux production of literature ala Jonathan Franzen that raises, as one reviewer noted, the logic of &#8220;f*ck it, i&#8217;ll have the steak&#8221; to the level of a Kantian antinomy.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
