<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Post-Orthodoxy	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/24/post-orthodoxy/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/24/post-orthodoxy/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2013 19:03:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: YM Goldstein		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/24/post-orthodoxy/#comment-7331</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[YM Goldstein]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2013 19:03:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5851#comment-7331</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/24/post-orthodoxy/#comment-7244&quot;&gt;BZ Niderberg&lt;/a&gt;.

I don&#039;t think that this can be solved by a &quot;movement&quot;; Each individual must make the effort to make his/her Judaism come alive, every day.  It takes work and effort.  Its not a &quot;leisure activity&quot;]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/24/post-orthodoxy/#comment-7244">BZ Niderberg</a>.</p>
<p>I don&#8217;t think that this can be solved by a &#8220;movement&#8221;; Each individual must make the effort to make his/her Judaism come alive, every day.  It takes work and effort.  Its not a &#8220;leisure activity&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Post-Orthodox, Post-Post Secularism &#124; jewish philosophy place		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/24/post-orthodoxy/#comment-7265</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Post-Orthodox, Post-Post Secularism &#124; jewish philosophy place]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 Dec 2012 14:54:39 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5851#comment-7265</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[[...] I really liked this post by Alan Brill on his blog over at the Book of Doctrines and Opinions. https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/24/post-orthodoxy/. It suggests what may be a pressing need to re-tool the categories through which we think these [...]]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] I really liked this post by Alan Brill on his blog over at the Book of Doctrines and Opinions. <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/24/post-orthodoxy/" rel="nofollow ugc">https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/24/post-orthodoxy/</a>. It suggests what may be a pressing need to re-tool the categories through which we think these [&#8230;]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Vikuah Mayyim Hayyim		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/24/post-orthodoxy/#comment-7258</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Vikuah Mayyim Hayyim]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 Dec 2012 01:58:15 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5851#comment-7258</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Dr. Brill,
I think that you are missing one vitally important point. For most MO educators, resorting to enthusiasm is all that they can do. They have very little education, the teachers dont read books, and they did not become teachers becuase they are smart. They virtually have no ability to understand the concerns of their most gifted students. They write off those students who dont want their emotionalism.
When the brightest students are bored to death by the trite naarishkeit that these teachers try to pawn off as education, they are written off by the teachers as &quot;shkatzim with no neshama.&quot; I know of a prominent MO school where, when the Principal announced that one of the seniors was admitted to an elite university, one of the Rebbeim loudly proclaimed &quot;Baruch Dayan Ha-Emes.&quot;]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dr. Brill,<br />
I think that you are missing one vitally important point. For most MO educators, resorting to enthusiasm is all that they can do. They have very little education, the teachers dont read books, and they did not become teachers becuase they are smart. They virtually have no ability to understand the concerns of their most gifted students. They write off those students who dont want their emotionalism.<br />
When the brightest students are bored to death by the trite naarishkeit that these teachers try to pawn off as education, they are written off by the teachers as &#8220;shkatzim with no neshama.&#8221; I know of a prominent MO school where, when the Principal announced that one of the seniors was admitted to an elite university, one of the Rebbeim loudly proclaimed &#8220;Baruch Dayan Ha-Emes.&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Steve Brizel		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/24/post-orthodoxy/#comment-7256</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Steve Brizel]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Dec 2012 20:40:50 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5851#comment-7256</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I would suggest that MO has a vocal LW , an influentual RW, and a central core that I call the silent majority. The real question is whether the dual moves by so many MO either towards the Charedi world or towards a lack of observance will leave the silent majority and the RW of MO as the Sheiris HaPletah of MO as the next generation, or as a more committed MO that has more in common with the Charedi world , desepite hashkafic differences. The other issue that was not discussed, but bears serious discussion is whether MO can generate its own Talmidei Chachamim and Bnei Torah who take learning seriously, and who are respected as such in the MO world, except by abandoning a high income career and investing much time and effort in serious high level Talmud Torah.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I would suggest that MO has a vocal LW , an influentual RW, and a central core that I call the silent majority. The real question is whether the dual moves by so many MO either towards the Charedi world or towards a lack of observance will leave the silent majority and the RW of MO as the Sheiris HaPletah of MO as the next generation, or as a more committed MO that has more in common with the Charedi world , desepite hashkafic differences. The other issue that was not discussed, but bears serious discussion is whether MO can generate its own Talmidei Chachamim and Bnei Torah who take learning seriously, and who are respected as such in the MO world, except by abandoning a high income career and investing much time and effort in serious high level Talmud Torah.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/24/post-orthodoxy/#comment-7255</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Dec 2012 20:08:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5851#comment-7255</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/24/post-orthodoxy/#comment-7254&quot;&gt;YM&lt;/a&gt;.

The list of issues is from the original article on Evangelicals. Personally, I actually dont frame it that way. My own statement is that their plausibility structure has been broken (see Peter Berger for details on the term). What actually broke it would take a sociological study or at least some perceptive gen y.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/24/post-orthodoxy/#comment-7254">YM</a>.</p>
<p>The list of issues is from the original article on Evangelicals. Personally, I actually dont frame it that way. My own statement is that their plausibility structure has been broken (see Peter Berger for details on the term). What actually broke it would take a sociological study or at least some perceptive gen y.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: YM		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/24/post-orthodoxy/#comment-7254</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[YM]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Dec 2012 20:02:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5851#comment-7254</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/24/post-orthodoxy/#comment-7241&quot;&gt;Shaya&lt;/a&gt;.

Your characterization of the issues R. Shagar &quot;dealt in&quot; is not quite correct.  

I&#039;d recommend reading &quot;shvirat kelim&quot; where he discusses sociological issues and &quot;b&#039;torato yehegeh&quot; where students&#039; interest in gemara is a motif.  The former book is a largely a polemic against various dati-leumi &quot;ideologies&quot;, but the chapter on humanities essentially states that the humanities are necessarily corrupting but necessary to study anyway.  Thus they must be taught/studied in a way that minimizes harm.

I can&#039;t imagine that translations of R. Shagar could have much of an impact on American MO.  People who find that R. Soloveichik&#039;s philosophical writings are a bit dated or litvish can readh him in Hebrew. The people who writing and leaving comments on various &quot;satire&quot; or &quot;apikorus&quot; blogs are not going to be much interested in non-Maimonidean understandings of tshuva or parallels between Chabad and Wittgenstein.  Parenthetically I think that Dr. Brill might be projecting a bit when he describes the issues that millenials have with MO.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/24/post-orthodoxy/#comment-7241">Shaya</a>.</p>
<p>Your characterization of the issues R. Shagar &#8220;dealt in&#8221; is not quite correct.  </p>
<p>I&#8217;d recommend reading &#8220;shvirat kelim&#8221; where he discusses sociological issues and &#8220;b&#8217;torato yehegeh&#8221; where students&#8217; interest in gemara is a motif.  The former book is a largely a polemic against various dati-leumi &#8220;ideologies&#8221;, but the chapter on humanities essentially states that the humanities are necessarily corrupting but necessary to study anyway.  Thus they must be taught/studied in a way that minimizes harm.</p>
<p>I can&#8217;t imagine that translations of R. Shagar could have much of an impact on American MO.  People who find that R. Soloveichik&#8217;s philosophical writings are a bit dated or litvish can readh him in Hebrew. The people who writing and leaving comments on various &#8220;satire&#8221; or &#8220;apikorus&#8221; blogs are not going to be much interested in non-Maimonidean understandings of tshuva or parallels between Chabad and Wittgenstein.  Parenthetically I think that Dr. Brill might be projecting a bit when he describes the issues that millenials have with MO.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/24/post-orthodoxy/#comment-7253</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Dec 2012 19:51:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5851#comment-7253</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/24/post-orthodoxy/#comment-7252&quot;&gt;Eric&lt;/a&gt;.

I never said those things in the article.
The topic was &quot;self-conscious that they are less committed than their parents&quot; not actual observance. 
And this long after Durkhiem, I do not assume that their self-professed reasons are the same as the actual reasons.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/24/post-orthodoxy/#comment-7252">Eric</a>.</p>
<p>I never said those things in the article.<br />
The topic was &#8220;self-conscious that they are less committed than their parents&#8221; not actual observance.<br />
And this long after Durkhiem, I do not assume that their self-professed reasons are the same as the actual reasons.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Eric		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/24/post-orthodoxy/#comment-7252</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eric]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Dec 2012 19:41:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5851#comment-7252</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[ If you examined the parents as closely, would you find similar lackings?
Was the rupture really as sudden as you depict it, and is it really a general rule that the older kids in a MO family remain religious while the younger ones don&#039;t?
Are you really telling us that young adults who criticize Orthodoxy for being too materialistic then go on to abandon observance due to career pressures?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p> If you examined the parents as closely, would you find similar lackings?<br />
Was the rupture really as sudden as you depict it, and is it really a general rule that the older kids in a MO family remain religious while the younger ones don&#8217;t?<br />
Are you really telling us that young adults who criticize Orthodoxy for being too materialistic then go on to abandon observance due to career pressures?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: evanstonjew		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/24/post-orthodoxy/#comment-7251</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[evanstonjew]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Dec 2012 19:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5851#comment-7251</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[There are three  ways MO can work in America , political idealism, content and style.

Susan Sontag in her essay on Camp said  “Jews and homosexuals are the outstanding creative minorities in contemporary urban culture. Creative, that is, in the truest sense: they are creators of sensibilities. The two pioneering forces of modern sensibility are Jewish moral seriousness and homosexual aestheticism and irony.” 

The day when Jews were the center of moral seriousness has come and gone with generation X, and the  emphasis on careers and income. The ability to attach oneself to Torah learning and use it as a vehicle for a life of  intellectual and spiritual growth, is also in short supply in genY Jews. There is a fair amount of evidence that Generation Y and the Millennials are dumbing down, (see link),  and the ideal of a life devoted to study, books and thinking is incompatible with a generation that grew up with the internet and virtual reality. We are left with the hope there is a strong enough style that is a reflection of Orthodox  culture and makes one proud to be Orthodox. 

A  great part of the success of charedim is due to their style and taste, and the feelings of pride that comes in being a chasidisher yid or a ben torah. How does one create an appropriate elitist, aristocratic sensibility in MO, when the communities are identified with pop cultural interests and middle class lifestyles? MO Jews are too close to the life they have created to have the distance to be self aware and ironic about their lifestyle, and are too envious and upwardly mobile to be satisfied with what they have.  
http://www.theamericanconservative.com/articles/the-myth-of-american-meritocracy/]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There are three  ways MO can work in America , political idealism, content and style.</p>
<p>Susan Sontag in her essay on Camp said  “Jews and homosexuals are the outstanding creative minorities in contemporary urban culture. Creative, that is, in the truest sense: they are creators of sensibilities. The two pioneering forces of modern sensibility are Jewish moral seriousness and homosexual aestheticism and irony.” </p>
<p>The day when Jews were the center of moral seriousness has come and gone with generation X, and the  emphasis on careers and income. The ability to attach oneself to Torah learning and use it as a vehicle for a life of  intellectual and spiritual growth, is also in short supply in genY Jews. There is a fair amount of evidence that Generation Y and the Millennials are dumbing down, (see link),  and the ideal of a life devoted to study, books and thinking is incompatible with a generation that grew up with the internet and virtual reality. We are left with the hope there is a strong enough style that is a reflection of Orthodox  culture and makes one proud to be Orthodox. </p>
<p>A  great part of the success of charedim is due to their style and taste, and the feelings of pride that comes in being a chasidisher yid or a ben torah. How does one create an appropriate elitist, aristocratic sensibility in MO, when the communities are identified with pop cultural interests and middle class lifestyles? MO Jews are too close to the life they have created to have the distance to be self aware and ironic about their lifestyle, and are too envious and upwardly mobile to be satisfied with what they have.<br />
<a href="http://www.theamericanconservative.com/articles/the-myth-of-american-meritocracy/" rel="nofollow ugc">http://www.theamericanconservative.com/articles/the-myth-of-american-meritocracy/</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Yashar		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/24/post-orthodoxy/#comment-7248</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Yashar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Dec 2012 17:06:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5851#comment-7248</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As a member of Generation Y who for a long time had a Facebook status as Observant Jew (but now listed at MO) I feel like dipping my toes in here.  Here is my story of why I struggled with the label.

My parents are both JTS graduates but I grew up in a yeshivish shul (NCSY was banned by our Rav).  Our city only had two options for elementary school: standard centrist or Schechter.  As the former could not teach me basic english or hebrew grammer and had abysmal secular studies, I went to Schechter.  But I woke up early to daven every day, I had a tutor for Talmud and I attended mishmar at the local yeshiva. I really identified religiously more with my friends at the other school as Orthodox.  

For Jewish high school my only choice was a pluralistic day school and it was the best possible choice.  While I may be weaker in some subjects such as Talmud, we had real classes in Jewish history, philosophy, and ethics as well as a very wide-ranging approach to Jewish studies and texts with teachers from every background (literary, critical, legalistic, religious zionist) that gave the students a real intellectual and tolerant basis to explore and expand their Jewish practice.

I did not go to Israel after high school.

I went to an Ivy League school and became an engineer but still took many Jewish studies classes, had chevrutot, and attended shiurim on campus.  

I acknowledge my path was unique.  I am not a member of the &quot;inner-circle&quot; of New York modern orthodoxy.  But I may be better off for it.  I am still strong in my Modern Orthodox observance and I fully credit my parents educational choices for me especially my high school, and even more so when I saw what many of my college classmates who went to MO day schools and yeshivot/seminaries went through.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As a member of Generation Y who for a long time had a Facebook status as Observant Jew (but now listed at MO) I feel like dipping my toes in here.  Here is my story of why I struggled with the label.</p>
<p>My parents are both JTS graduates but I grew up in a yeshivish shul (NCSY was banned by our Rav).  Our city only had two options for elementary school: standard centrist or Schechter.  As the former could not teach me basic english or hebrew grammer and had abysmal secular studies, I went to Schechter.  But I woke up early to daven every day, I had a tutor for Talmud and I attended mishmar at the local yeshiva. I really identified religiously more with my friends at the other school as Orthodox.  </p>
<p>For Jewish high school my only choice was a pluralistic day school and it was the best possible choice.  While I may be weaker in some subjects such as Talmud, we had real classes in Jewish history, philosophy, and ethics as well as a very wide-ranging approach to Jewish studies and texts with teachers from every background (literary, critical, legalistic, religious zionist) that gave the students a real intellectual and tolerant basis to explore and expand their Jewish practice.</p>
<p>I did not go to Israel after high school.</p>
<p>I went to an Ivy League school and became an engineer but still took many Jewish studies classes, had chevrutot, and attended shiurim on campus.  </p>
<p>I acknowledge my path was unique.  I am not a member of the &#8220;inner-circle&#8221; of New York modern orthodoxy.  But I may be better off for it.  I am still strong in my Modern Orthodox observance and I fully credit my parents educational choices for me especially my high school, and even more so when I saw what many of my college classmates who went to MO day schools and yeshivot/seminaries went through.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AIWAC		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/24/post-orthodoxy/#comment-7247</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AIWAC]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Dec 2012 16:29:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5851#comment-7247</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Interesting post. The contrasts with the situation in Israel are striking. While it is true that we face many of the same intellectual and spiritual challenges, the solutions are different. Here we are not tied to any one school - be it intellectual, spiritual or otherwise. Anyone who doesn&#039;t feel welcome in one community can easily find another one more accepting and accommodating. Furthermore, there has been increasing acceptance of categories of &#039;not-so-observant&#039; Jews called &quot;dati lite&quot;, which allows for further cooling off without burning out entirely. Furthermore, the spectrum of observance here is fuzzier and less denomination-oriented and so allows for easier movement, especially with the existence of a large group of &#039;traditional&#039; Jews.

I have to ask, though - is American MO truly that monolithic in terms of communities and goals?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Interesting post. The contrasts with the situation in Israel are striking. While it is true that we face many of the same intellectual and spiritual challenges, the solutions are different. Here we are not tied to any one school &#8211; be it intellectual, spiritual or otherwise. Anyone who doesn&#8217;t feel welcome in one community can easily find another one more accepting and accommodating. Furthermore, there has been increasing acceptance of categories of &#8216;not-so-observant&#8217; Jews called &#8220;dati lite&#8221;, which allows for further cooling off without burning out entirely. Furthermore, the spectrum of observance here is fuzzier and less denomination-oriented and so allows for easier movement, especially with the existence of a large group of &#8216;traditional&#8217; Jews.</p>
<p>I have to ask, though &#8211; is American MO truly that monolithic in terms of communities and goals?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Harris Tilevitz		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/24/post-orthodoxy/#comment-7246</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Harris Tilevitz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Dec 2012 15:06:37 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5851#comment-7246</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I am not qualified to judge whether the generational shifts in terms of observance are avoidable or not. It seems to me that there are many factors which cause those changes some of which are, I suppose, unavoidable. I do believe, however, that the lack of acknowledgement by the MO schools that societal change is afoot and their inability to meet that change by altering how Judaism is taught is very much to blame - blame at least in terms of not staunching the bleeding. 

If the theory is that one of MO&#039;s tenets is to meet secular society head-on and acknowledge the value of pluralism (both Jewish and secular) within an &quot;observant&quot; context, then the school is doing an injustice to the student by not figuring out how to truly teach how to understand and synthesize all of these ideas. They need to recognize the needs of their students, including those who question God, mitzvot, prayer and the Torah. They need to proactively discuss the questioning these students do and be upfront in asking them &quot;why&quot;. What do the questions mean to them? I am not suggesting that schools encourage students to experiment or leave the fold if they choose, but rather that they become better equipped with the (current) reality of how many of them will graduate from the MO school and community at the same time. And they need to emphasize to the student that leaving the fold doesn&#039;t preclude their return. 

It would be disingenuous for me to insist that there no attempt to do this. Courses like &quot;Faith and Doubt&quot; and attendant readings is one great example of what is currently offered to meet this need. But there are not many. And the comment that these schools offer an understanding of Judaism that is &quot;a mile wide and only an inch deep&quot; is a perfect characterization. It seems that to few opportunities are used to show that the history of Judaism has been about questioning and change. 

It is, indeed, &quot;complicated.&quot;  The shift to the right and the insularization of the &quot;black hat&quot; world is repulsive to many of us who, as baby boomers, grew up believing that we can observe and still be part of the world at large. But indeed, the millenials and later seem not to understand that in spite of the difficulty, it is indeed possible to walk both lines. 

Some would say that by sending our children out into the world via MO schools we are leading them into Pardes and should not be surprised by the fact that some will not return. Some will not return because it is not in their nature. Some because it is just not convenient to do so. The best we can do is make sure that none fail to return because they have been taught there is only one way to believe or observe. Perhaps they should be proactively taught that the visit is &quot;complicated&quot; but rewarding. 

Or maybe, none of this matters. That cycles will be cycles and all the intellectual handwringing that we do is meaningless and in the long run everything will be ok...or it won&#039;t.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I am not qualified to judge whether the generational shifts in terms of observance are avoidable or not. It seems to me that there are many factors which cause those changes some of which are, I suppose, unavoidable. I do believe, however, that the lack of acknowledgement by the MO schools that societal change is afoot and their inability to meet that change by altering how Judaism is taught is very much to blame &#8211; blame at least in terms of not staunching the bleeding. </p>
<p>If the theory is that one of MO&#8217;s tenets is to meet secular society head-on and acknowledge the value of pluralism (both Jewish and secular) within an &#8220;observant&#8221; context, then the school is doing an injustice to the student by not figuring out how to truly teach how to understand and synthesize all of these ideas. They need to recognize the needs of their students, including those who question God, mitzvot, prayer and the Torah. They need to proactively discuss the questioning these students do and be upfront in asking them &#8220;why&#8221;. What do the questions mean to them? I am not suggesting that schools encourage students to experiment or leave the fold if they choose, but rather that they become better equipped with the (current) reality of how many of them will graduate from the MO school and community at the same time. And they need to emphasize to the student that leaving the fold doesn&#8217;t preclude their return. </p>
<p>It would be disingenuous for me to insist that there no attempt to do this. Courses like &#8220;Faith and Doubt&#8221; and attendant readings is one great example of what is currently offered to meet this need. But there are not many. And the comment that these schools offer an understanding of Judaism that is &#8220;a mile wide and only an inch deep&#8221; is a perfect characterization. It seems that to few opportunities are used to show that the history of Judaism has been about questioning and change. </p>
<p>It is, indeed, &#8220;complicated.&#8221;  The shift to the right and the insularization of the &#8220;black hat&#8221; world is repulsive to many of us who, as baby boomers, grew up believing that we can observe and still be part of the world at large. But indeed, the millenials and later seem not to understand that in spite of the difficulty, it is indeed possible to walk both lines. </p>
<p>Some would say that by sending our children out into the world via MO schools we are leading them into Pardes and should not be surprised by the fact that some will not return. Some will not return because it is not in their nature. Some because it is just not convenient to do so. The best we can do is make sure that none fail to return because they have been taught there is only one way to believe or observe. Perhaps they should be proactively taught that the visit is &#8220;complicated&#8221; but rewarding. </p>
<p>Or maybe, none of this matters. That cycles will be cycles and all the intellectual handwringing that we do is meaningless and in the long run everything will be ok&#8230;or it won&#8217;t.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: BZ Niderberg		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/12/24/post-orthodoxy/#comment-7244</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[BZ Niderberg]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Dec 2012 13:54:39 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5851#comment-7244</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[One of the points you mention as a cause for turnoff is the political-intellectual narrowness of the Orthodox community. This is built in. It is worth noting that Orthodoxy has from its inception been as much a political construct as a religious one, and rigid political conformity, both klapei hutz and klapei pnim, has always been among its demands. The creation of Orthodoxy may have been a necessary response in the age of Reform, but it did and continues to have a corrupting influence on the religious life it claims to espouse and protect. Nowhere is this more apparent than in Israel, although it is equally, if less obviously, true in the Diaspora. Perhaps observance without Orthodoxy is untenable, as Yehuda suggests, but there lies the road to a more genuine, satisfying, coherent, supple and inclusive Jewish experience. We&#039;ll never get there until we learn how to live and feel our Jewishness without hyphenation.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One of the points you mention as a cause for turnoff is the political-intellectual narrowness of the Orthodox community. This is built in. It is worth noting that Orthodoxy has from its inception been as much a political construct as a religious one, and rigid political conformity, both klapei hutz and klapei pnim, has always been among its demands. The creation of Orthodoxy may have been a necessary response in the age of Reform, but it did and continues to have a corrupting influence on the religious life it claims to espouse and protect. Nowhere is this more apparent than in Israel, although it is equally, if less obviously, true in the Diaspora. Perhaps observance without Orthodoxy is untenable, as Yehuda suggests, but there lies the road to a more genuine, satisfying, coherent, supple and inclusive Jewish experience. We&#8217;ll never get there until we learn how to live and feel our Jewishness without hyphenation.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
