<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Rabbi Einhorn’s Sermons	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/04/03/rabbi-einhorns-sermons/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/04/03/rabbi-einhorns-sermons/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2012 22:18:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Neil Harris		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/04/03/rabbi-einhorns-sermons/#comment-4350</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Neil Harris]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2012 22:18:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4849#comment-4350</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I&#039;ve read these posted sermons and I would love to find out what kind of feedback the congregants give Rabbi Einhorn.   

If secular references are the bait to draw in people, then is the actual big prize?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ve read these posted sermons and I would love to find out what kind of feedback the congregants give Rabbi Einhorn.   </p>
<p>If secular references are the bait to draw in people, then is the actual big prize?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: freshwatersnark		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/04/03/rabbi-einhorns-sermons/#comment-4341</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[freshwatersnark]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 04 Apr 2012 12:36:50 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4849#comment-4341</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I&#039;m a wanderer and stranger here, as someone once said, and as he didn&#039;t say, I&#039;m an am-haaretz and a curmudgeon.  So people may find me completely off base.  Before reading the two recent posts, I was completely unfamiliar with Rabbi Einhorn, so I will limit my comments to one of  the sermons discussed above, &quot;The Wayward Teen and the Satmar Rov&quot; without generalizing.

R. Einhorn quotes &quot;David,&quot; an &quot;at-risk teen,&quot; rejecting the Satmar Rebbe&#039;s explanation of yachatz as recounted by R. Einhorn: 

“I disagree! We do not cast away this broken matzah. In fact, we hide it, protect it, and when the time is right – at the highlight of our Seder – Tzafun, the emergence of the Afikomen, we bring that “discarded” one front and center.”

&quot;And together,&quot; concludes, R. Einhorn,  &quot;we fell to weeping.&quot; 

When I read this it bothered me.  Like proffered candy in a dirty hand, what was touching and inspiring suddenly became distasteful, and it took a minute to understand why.  It is manipulative.

R. Einhorn is pandering to the all-too-human desire to see the downfall of the great as he sets up Rav Teitelbaum&#039;s interpretation to be felled (&quot;drashed&quot;?) when  &quot;David&quot; slings his zinger.  And it&#039;s a good one.  But try listening with your mind&#039;s ear to the words R. Einhorn puts in &quot;David&#039;s&quot; mouth.  A pensive, yet quick-thinking teenager might have had the thought, but would never have expressed it in the words R. Einhorn supposedly quotes.  (I could pedantically point out a half-dozen verbal false notes, but will spare you.)  &quot;David&#039;s&quot; self-identification with the piece of matzah that is not &quot;cast away,&quot; but hidden in order to be &quot;front and center&quot; is intended to be transparent to R. Einhorn&#039;s audience.  But it would also have been transparent to &quot;David&#039;s&quot; listeners and to &quot;David&quot; himself, and the last thing an &quot;at-risk&quot; teenager would want to admit in the presence of his peers and rabbi.

Concluding this touching but highly improbable tale, R. Einhorn recounts that upon hearing &quot;David&#039;s&quot; words, &quot;we fell to weeping,&quot; apparently causing him to fall into faux-biblical idiom.  It&#039;s a nasty fall, since nobody in America has fallen to weeping in more than sixty years.  I read that phrase as a flag planted in the text to assuage the author&#039;s conscience by warning halfway alert readers that he is fibbing.  

Probably the dishonesty doesn&#039;t show when delivered by a good performer to an audience willingly suspending disbelief, but doesn&#039;t it matter nonetheless?  Shouldn&#039;t a sermon showcase the Torah and Jewish tradition, rather than an invented human-interest story?  Did R. Einhorn need to set the scene in his &quot;challenging, yet rewarding, task of working with at-risk teens,&quot; or recount a saying in the name of Rav Teitelbaum as a foil for &quot;David&#039;s&quot; wisdom in the manner of Jesus&#039; supposed ripostes to the Pharisees?  It may be good theater and good salesmanship and bring people into the shul, but shouldn&#039;t we expect more from a kli kodesh?  Doesn&#039;t that expression imply holiness of means as well as ends? 

Regarding the turn to secular motivational literature and techniques generally, and the overriding importance given to congregation-building, is no one else reminded of that wonderful remark of Heschel, &quot;the hands are the hands of Jacob, but the voice is the voice of Esau?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m a wanderer and stranger here, as someone once said, and as he didn&#8217;t say, I&#8217;m an am-haaretz and a curmudgeon.  So people may find me completely off base.  Before reading the two recent posts, I was completely unfamiliar with Rabbi Einhorn, so I will limit my comments to one of  the sermons discussed above, &#8220;The Wayward Teen and the Satmar Rov&#8221; without generalizing.</p>
<p>R. Einhorn quotes &#8220;David,&#8221; an &#8220;at-risk teen,&#8221; rejecting the Satmar Rebbe&#8217;s explanation of yachatz as recounted by R. Einhorn: </p>
<p>“I disagree! We do not cast away this broken matzah. In fact, we hide it, protect it, and when the time is right – at the highlight of our Seder – Tzafun, the emergence of the Afikomen, we bring that “discarded” one front and center.”</p>
<p>&#8220;And together,&#8221; concludes, R. Einhorn,  &#8220;we fell to weeping.&#8221; </p>
<p>When I read this it bothered me.  Like proffered candy in a dirty hand, what was touching and inspiring suddenly became distasteful, and it took a minute to understand why.  It is manipulative.</p>
<p>R. Einhorn is pandering to the all-too-human desire to see the downfall of the great as he sets up Rav Teitelbaum&#8217;s interpretation to be felled (&#8220;drashed&#8221;?) when  &#8220;David&#8221; slings his zinger.  And it&#8217;s a good one.  But try listening with your mind&#8217;s ear to the words R. Einhorn puts in &#8220;David&#8217;s&#8221; mouth.  A pensive, yet quick-thinking teenager might have had the thought, but would never have expressed it in the words R. Einhorn supposedly quotes.  (I could pedantically point out a half-dozen verbal false notes, but will spare you.)  &#8220;David&#8217;s&#8221; self-identification with the piece of matzah that is not &#8220;cast away,&#8221; but hidden in order to be &#8220;front and center&#8221; is intended to be transparent to R. Einhorn&#8217;s audience.  But it would also have been transparent to &#8220;David&#8217;s&#8221; listeners and to &#8220;David&#8221; himself, and the last thing an &#8220;at-risk&#8221; teenager would want to admit in the presence of his peers and rabbi.</p>
<p>Concluding this touching but highly improbable tale, R. Einhorn recounts that upon hearing &#8220;David&#8217;s&#8221; words, &#8220;we fell to weeping,&#8221; apparently causing him to fall into faux-biblical idiom.  It&#8217;s a nasty fall, since nobody in America has fallen to weeping in more than sixty years.  I read that phrase as a flag planted in the text to assuage the author&#8217;s conscience by warning halfway alert readers that he is fibbing.  </p>
<p>Probably the dishonesty doesn&#8217;t show when delivered by a good performer to an audience willingly suspending disbelief, but doesn&#8217;t it matter nonetheless?  Shouldn&#8217;t a sermon showcase the Torah and Jewish tradition, rather than an invented human-interest story?  Did R. Einhorn need to set the scene in his &#8220;challenging, yet rewarding, task of working with at-risk teens,&#8221; or recount a saying in the name of Rav Teitelbaum as a foil for &#8220;David&#8217;s&#8221; wisdom in the manner of Jesus&#8217; supposed ripostes to the Pharisees?  It may be good theater and good salesmanship and bring people into the shul, but shouldn&#8217;t we expect more from a kli kodesh?  Doesn&#8217;t that expression imply holiness of means as well as ends? </p>
<p>Regarding the turn to secular motivational literature and techniques generally, and the overriding importance given to congregation-building, is no one else reminded of that wonderful remark of Heschel, &#8220;the hands are the hands of Jacob, but the voice is the voice of Esau?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
