<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Nyaya and Monotheism	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/13/nyaya-and-monotheism/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/13/nyaya-and-monotheism/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2013 14:58:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: walter benjamin		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/13/nyaya-and-monotheism/#comment-9082</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[walter benjamin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2013 14:58:51 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6367#comment-9082</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Amit
 I will just say you have not had better than tertiary sources or &#039;worse&#039;. A rejoinder is not worthy to engage in but I will remind you that even according to the  Vedanta &#039;moksha&#039; is also a illusion.

But to sum it up more succinctly diff peoples have diff mentalities and in the end salvation is a gift to mankind no matter how many &#039;revolutions&#039; of the mental state he/she must churn in order to find the &#039;door&#039;.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Amit<br />
 I will just say you have not had better than tertiary sources or &#8216;worse&#8217;. A rejoinder is not worthy to engage in but I will remind you that even according to the  Vedanta &#8216;moksha&#8217; is also a illusion.</p>
<p>But to sum it up more succinctly diff peoples have diff mentalities and in the end salvation is a gift to mankind no matter how many &#8216;revolutions&#8217; of the mental state he/she must churn in order to find the &#8216;door&#8217;.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Amit		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/13/nyaya-and-monotheism/#comment-9073</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Amit]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2013 15:54:36 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6367#comment-9073</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/13/nyaya-and-monotheism/#comment-9067&quot;&gt;Ira Rohde&lt;/a&gt;.

Shankara charya revived Hinduism ..

I do not know but do you know as per hinduism : the primary aim od this life is to get moksha or liberation.
This is not Jewish aim or aim of Judaism mainstream.
So,Jewish  do not have Monastic tradition and renunciation/Celibacy .Judaism is more akin to householder family dharma. because of marriage and children .There is no other school in Judaism .Now the difference between householder life and monastic life are poles apart.Monastic life is purely centered on divine with no family ties,no money.So complete surrender.The experience of those monastics can not be there in Judaism and so Jewish mind will not be able to understand those experiences.Also as per Hinduism,this is KALI YUGA.,Hindu time is cyclic and Jewish time is linear.Most important difference,we have worship of divine as personal relationship in the sense of these relationships :
1)Mother 2)father 3)child 4)friend 5)servant.

Does mainstream Judaism revere divine as mother? NO.
Does Mainstream Judaism revere animals as also divine ,,because they are also created by divine? NO.
All hindu divine persona have animals as their instruments.
Different manifestation of Mother goddess has pet animals from Lion to Parrot,so automatically people become kind to such animals and become vegetarians.

Does Judaism revere stones like ShaliGrama as representative of divine ?
NO
So in the sense ,we see divine everywhere and in each particle and dust  and in each manifestation whether it is human or animal or living or not.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/13/nyaya-and-monotheism/#comment-9067">Ira Rohde</a>.</p>
<p>Shankara charya revived Hinduism ..</p>
<p>I do not know but do you know as per hinduism : the primary aim od this life is to get moksha or liberation.<br />
This is not Jewish aim or aim of Judaism mainstream.<br />
So,Jewish  do not have Monastic tradition and renunciation/Celibacy .Judaism is more akin to householder family dharma. because of marriage and children .There is no other school in Judaism .Now the difference between householder life and monastic life are poles apart.Monastic life is purely centered on divine with no family ties,no money.So complete surrender.The experience of those monastics can not be there in Judaism and so Jewish mind will not be able to understand those experiences.Also as per Hinduism,this is KALI YUGA.,Hindu time is cyclic and Jewish time is linear.Most important difference,we have worship of divine as personal relationship in the sense of these relationships :<br />
1)Mother 2)father 3)child 4)friend 5)servant.</p>
<p>Does mainstream Judaism revere divine as mother? NO.<br />
Does Mainstream Judaism revere animals as also divine ,,because they are also created by divine? NO.<br />
All hindu divine persona have animals as their instruments.<br />
Different manifestation of Mother goddess has pet animals from Lion to Parrot,so automatically people become kind to such animals and become vegetarians.</p>
<p>Does Judaism revere stones like ShaliGrama as representative of divine ?<br />
NO<br />
So in the sense ,we see divine everywhere and in each particle and dust  and in each manifestation whether it is human or animal or living or not.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Amit		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/13/nyaya-and-monotheism/#comment-9072</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Amit]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2013 15:38:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6367#comment-9072</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The  soul called in Hinduism.,,it is called &quot;Atman&quot;.Atman is transcendental and I do not know if you ever heard the concept of &quot;Samadhi&quot;.
google : Samadhi.

Samādhi (Sanskrit: समाधि) in Hinduism, Buddhism, Jainism, Sikhism and yogic schools is a higher level of concentrated meditation, or dhyāna. In the yoga tradition, it is the eighth and final limb identified in the Yoga Sūtras of Patañjali.

It has been described as a non-dualistic state of consciousness in which the consciousness of the experiencing subject becomes one with the experienced object,[1] and in which the mind becomes still, one-pointed or concentrated[2] while the person remains conscious. In Buddhism, it can also refer to an abiding in which mind becomes very still but does not merge with the object of attention, and is thus able to observe and gain insight into the changing flow of experience.[3]

Judaism is very different from Hinduism and since  meditative practise /celibacy was not part of Judaism ,I am afraid to say that it is very difficult for a Jewish person to understand Hinduism.

You do not have concept of Kundalini,Brahmacharya,Ojas/Tejas,Chakras in your tradition since Kaballah was incorporated into JUdaism in 16th century officially as per wikipedia and was very influenced by Sufism.

If you are not celibate,then your chance of divine realisation : called &quot;Nirvakalpa Samadhi&quot; is zero as per Hinduism.You can get &quot; Sarvakalpa Samadhi&quot; only.Great Sages like Shankaracharya were monastics and Judaism has no monastic concept and no celibacy.So..it is very difficult for a Jew to understand or experience the mystical aspects of Hinduism because Judaism is for a different mindset and culture.

Then second concept which Judaism does not preach is &quot;Non Violence&quot;  towards Animals because Jewish religion as such has no condemnation for meat eating and killing of chicken etc.Otherwise Judaism would be another Hinduism school or Jainism school.To a Sage : Meat eating is hurting a creature of divine for food because the sage sees the same Divine Soul in him and in the creature.There is no difference in the transcendental soul existing in a animal creature or a human being.The material &quot;mind&#039; being a manifestation of soul may be different but the transcendental soul is same.
Our whole culture of Hinduism reveres divine soul in all.That is why there is concept of Namaste.Second thing ,in Judaism,a Guru is just a human being and he should not be bowed because he is a human being.
Where as in Hinduism,we see him as a divine being in the sense that he reflects the divine soul in him more clearly than rest of populace and  we surrender on his feet..that means we give our mind to such a divine realised being.Without True Guru&#039;s grace ,no chance of divine realisation as per Hinduism.Guru is the match maker which brings you close to divine.Hindus bow to their parents because the parents are their creators.Humility,trust in your divine realised Guru  and ahimsa are the corner stones of divine realisation.The trust should be so much,that if this Guru who is divine realised says you have to jump in a well,you have to do it with complete faith,that everything what he says  is best 
for you.So,there are many fakes also in this line,who can fool you.But a divine realised soul is different.It is a misfortune that such sages are so few in this world.

.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The  soul called in Hinduism.,,it is called &#8220;Atman&#8221;.Atman is transcendental and I do not know if you ever heard the concept of &#8220;Samadhi&#8221;.<br />
google : Samadhi.</p>
<p>Samādhi (Sanskrit: समाधि) in Hinduism, Buddhism, Jainism, Sikhism and yogic schools is a higher level of concentrated meditation, or dhyāna. In the yoga tradition, it is the eighth and final limb identified in the Yoga Sūtras of Patañjali.</p>
<p>It has been described as a non-dualistic state of consciousness in which the consciousness of the experiencing subject becomes one with the experienced object,[1] and in which the mind becomes still, one-pointed or concentrated[2] while the person remains conscious. In Buddhism, it can also refer to an abiding in which mind becomes very still but does not merge with the object of attention, and is thus able to observe and gain insight into the changing flow of experience.[3]</p>
<p>Judaism is very different from Hinduism and since  meditative practise /celibacy was not part of Judaism ,I am afraid to say that it is very difficult for a Jewish person to understand Hinduism.</p>
<p>You do not have concept of Kundalini,Brahmacharya,Ojas/Tejas,Chakras in your tradition since Kaballah was incorporated into JUdaism in 16th century officially as per wikipedia and was very influenced by Sufism.</p>
<p>If you are not celibate,then your chance of divine realisation : called &#8220;Nirvakalpa Samadhi&#8221; is zero as per Hinduism.You can get &#8221; Sarvakalpa Samadhi&#8221; only.Great Sages like Shankaracharya were monastics and Judaism has no monastic concept and no celibacy.So..it is very difficult for a Jew to understand or experience the mystical aspects of Hinduism because Judaism is for a different mindset and culture.</p>
<p>Then second concept which Judaism does not preach is &#8220;Non Violence&#8221;  towards Animals because Jewish religion as such has no condemnation for meat eating and killing of chicken etc.Otherwise Judaism would be another Hinduism school or Jainism school.To a Sage : Meat eating is hurting a creature of divine for food because the sage sees the same Divine Soul in him and in the creature.There is no difference in the transcendental soul existing in a animal creature or a human being.The material &#8220;mind&#8217; being a manifestation of soul may be different but the transcendental soul is same.<br />
Our whole culture of Hinduism reveres divine soul in all.That is why there is concept of Namaste.Second thing ,in Judaism,a Guru is just a human being and he should not be bowed because he is a human being.<br />
Where as in Hinduism,we see him as a divine being in the sense that he reflects the divine soul in him more clearly than rest of populace and  we surrender on his feet..that means we give our mind to such a divine realised being.Without True Guru&#8217;s grace ,no chance of divine realisation as per Hinduism.Guru is the match maker which brings you close to divine.Hindus bow to their parents because the parents are their creators.Humility,trust in your divine realised Guru  and ahimsa are the corner stones of divine realisation.The trust should be so much,that if this Guru who is divine realised says you have to jump in a well,you have to do it with complete faith,that everything what he says  is best<br />
for you.So,there are many fakes also in this line,who can fool you.But a divine realised soul is different.It is a misfortune that such sages are so few in this world.</p>
<p>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Ira Rohde		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/13/nyaya-and-monotheism/#comment-9067</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ira Rohde]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2013 05:38:26 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6367#comment-9067</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[For a while I read the U.S.A. publication Namarupa Magazine, founded by Eddie Stern, the head of the most established group of the late yogi Sri K. Pattabhi Jois&#039; students of &quot;Ashtanga Yoga&quot; in New York. Often times Stern has to go reconstruct how old poojas were performed.The overall impression I&#039;ve gotten is that Hindus by modern times and for some time previously have been distanced from many of the liturgical-sacramental (such as how to many different poojas were performed) as well as the legalistic-ritual aspects (their &quot;shastras&quot; or legal tractates), and have been caught up in the philosophical/mystical/individualistic salvation aspects of their own religion at the expense of the legal &#038; sacramental. I could blame a good part of this on British suppression, domination and rule, but I somehow don&#039;t think that&#039;s the whole story. The entire Jewish tradition has been unified into something more internally consistent, despite a lot of persecution. A number of times Stern and his associates  have to go reconstruct how old poojas were performed.
Judaism insisted that liturgical and legal aspects be brought in line at a base level with basic philosophical considerations. That ruled out many practices, but it actually makes our sacramental/liturgical/legal tradition more alive for us (hard as that may be to believe with the noise of talkers in synagogue), than for many Hindus, it seems. Rashi, Rambam, Saadya and Ramban wrote about speculative matters, about commentary on the Torah, but also about the tractates of at least the Mishnah if not the Talmud. My impression is that Shankara&#039;s work does not cover the various Shastras, although I may be wrong, and maybe I don&#039;t have a complete bibliography. Shankara seems to me much less interested in the sacramental/ritual/legalistic. Even earlier, already the Upanishads are less concerned with the older, cultic parts of the Veda, the various details of the horse sacrifice. Of course, Shankara had a much larger corpus of tradition to cope with than the Rambam. But at least Shankara comments on the Vedas and the Upanishads, which he sees as the &quot;logos&quot; of God, to use a Philonic expression, and keeps Shankara within &quot;orthodox Hinduism.&quot; Ghazali and others in Islam also unified the speculative with Hadith and the legal and sacramental traditions. Were there such people in Hinduism? 
I&#039;m sure much Kalaam and philosophy, theosophy, and Divine psychology in the West was influenced by Hindu as well as Buddhist thought, but there often is a difference in emphasis. Indians (as well as, perhaps, some of the ancient Greeks as part of the Indo-Aryan heritage) remain much more interested in the immanent aspect of God, valuing &quot;subjective&quot; truth, God as in my soul, over the &quot;transcendent&quot; aspect, God as a relationship with an &quot;Other&quot; outside oneself. Buber seems right about that. Jews inscribe &quot;Know before whom you stand&quot; above the Holy Ark, unlike the Greek Temple at Dephi, which had the inscriptions &quot;Know thyself&quot; and &quot;Everything in measure (the Golden Mean).&quot;  Jews have a predominantly &quot;objective&quot; focus of knowledge.
I&#039;m familiar with Radhakrishnan&#039;s anthology of excerpted translations somewhat. Another of my former teachers is, as well: I remember when I was studying the anthology in depth and I had happened to bring it along concealed in my bag to a Tai Chi class with Mori veRabbi Prof. H. Sober, and he referenced the Radhakrishnan anthology (he must have been reading my thoughts, I&#039;m quite convinced) so I brought the book over to him, and he proceeded to look up and quote a section from Sri Aorobindo.
Hinduism and Buddhism were used by Christians and Buddhists to try to prove that Judaism, or for that matter even Parsis and perhaps some non-speculative Islam was not &quot;spiritual&quot; enough for the individual. But by proclaiming allegiance but in effect neglecting the significance of the communal/sacramental/ritual/legalistic aspects of their tradition, are Hindus really remaining true to their own concept of &quot;dharma?&quot;]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For a while I read the U.S.A. publication Namarupa Magazine, founded by Eddie Stern, the head of the most established group of the late yogi Sri K. Pattabhi Jois&#8217; students of &#8220;Ashtanga Yoga&#8221; in New York. Often times Stern has to go reconstruct how old poojas were performed.The overall impression I&#8217;ve gotten is that Hindus by modern times and for some time previously have been distanced from many of the liturgical-sacramental (such as how to many different poojas were performed) as well as the legalistic-ritual aspects (their &#8220;shastras&#8221; or legal tractates), and have been caught up in the philosophical/mystical/individualistic salvation aspects of their own religion at the expense of the legal &amp; sacramental. I could blame a good part of this on British suppression, domination and rule, but I somehow don&#8217;t think that&#8217;s the whole story. The entire Jewish tradition has been unified into something more internally consistent, despite a lot of persecution. A number of times Stern and his associates  have to go reconstruct how old poojas were performed.<br />
Judaism insisted that liturgical and legal aspects be brought in line at a base level with basic philosophical considerations. That ruled out many practices, but it actually makes our sacramental/liturgical/legal tradition more alive for us (hard as that may be to believe with the noise of talkers in synagogue), than for many Hindus, it seems. Rashi, Rambam, Saadya and Ramban wrote about speculative matters, about commentary on the Torah, but also about the tractates of at least the Mishnah if not the Talmud. My impression is that Shankara&#8217;s work does not cover the various Shastras, although I may be wrong, and maybe I don&#8217;t have a complete bibliography. Shankara seems to me much less interested in the sacramental/ritual/legalistic. Even earlier, already the Upanishads are less concerned with the older, cultic parts of the Veda, the various details of the horse sacrifice. Of course, Shankara had a much larger corpus of tradition to cope with than the Rambam. But at least Shankara comments on the Vedas and the Upanishads, which he sees as the &#8220;logos&#8221; of God, to use a Philonic expression, and keeps Shankara within &#8220;orthodox Hinduism.&#8221; Ghazali and others in Islam also unified the speculative with Hadith and the legal and sacramental traditions. Were there such people in Hinduism?<br />
I&#8217;m sure much Kalaam and philosophy, theosophy, and Divine psychology in the West was influenced by Hindu as well as Buddhist thought, but there often is a difference in emphasis. Indians (as well as, perhaps, some of the ancient Greeks as part of the Indo-Aryan heritage) remain much more interested in the immanent aspect of God, valuing &#8220;subjective&#8221; truth, God as in my soul, over the &#8220;transcendent&#8221; aspect, God as a relationship with an &#8220;Other&#8221; outside oneself. Buber seems right about that. Jews inscribe &#8220;Know before whom you stand&#8221; above the Holy Ark, unlike the Greek Temple at Dephi, which had the inscriptions &#8220;Know thyself&#8221; and &#8220;Everything in measure (the Golden Mean).&#8221;  Jews have a predominantly &#8220;objective&#8221; focus of knowledge.<br />
I&#8217;m familiar with Radhakrishnan&#8217;s anthology of excerpted translations somewhat. Another of my former teachers is, as well: I remember when I was studying the anthology in depth and I had happened to bring it along concealed in my bag to a Tai Chi class with Mori veRabbi Prof. H. Sober, and he referenced the Radhakrishnan anthology (he must have been reading my thoughts, I&#8217;m quite convinced) so I brought the book over to him, and he proceeded to look up and quote a section from Sri Aorobindo.<br />
Hinduism and Buddhism were used by Christians and Buddhists to try to prove that Judaism, or for that matter even Parsis and perhaps some non-speculative Islam was not &#8220;spiritual&#8221; enough for the individual. But by proclaiming allegiance but in effect neglecting the significance of the communal/sacramental/ritual/legalistic aspects of their tradition, are Hindus really remaining true to their own concept of &#8220;dharma?&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Amit Kumar		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/13/nyaya-and-monotheism/#comment-9061</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Amit Kumar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2013 19:42:05 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6367#comment-9061</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[in Judaism in my limited knowlede ,you have Ein Soph.The definition of that is given here : Ein Sof is the divine origin of all created existence, in contrast to the Ein (or Ayn), which is infinite no-thingness. It was first used by Azriel ben Menahem, who, sharing the Neoplatonic view that God can have no desire, thought, word, or action, emphasized by it the negation of any attribute

Contrast this with Brahman : 

ParaBrahman (Sanskrit) [from para beyond + Brahman (neuter) universal self or spirit] - That which is beyond Brahman. The self-enduring, eternal, self-sufficient cause of all causes, the essence of everything in the cosmos. In the Vedic style of writing, ParaBrahman is referred to as tat (that) as opposed to the manifest universe called idam (this). ParaBrahman means Supreme Brahman, or Supreme Cosmic Spirit, or Godhead. 

It is also called Nirguna Brahman(without attributes).

Shekhina : Shekinah, Shechinah, Shechina, or Schechinah (Hebrew: שכינה‎), is the English spelling of a grammatically feminine Hebrew name of God in Judaism. The original word means the dwelling or settling, and denotes the dwelling or settling of the Divine Presence of God, especially in the Temple in Jerusalem..

Contrast this with Shakti :
Shakti (Sanskrit pronunciation: [ˈʃʌktɪ]) (Devanagari: शक्ति; from Sanskrit shak, &quot;to be able&quot;), meaning &quot;Power&quot; or &quot;empowerment,&quot; is the primordial cosmic energy and represents the dynamic forces that are thought to move through the entire universe in Hinduism.[1] Shakti is the concept, or personification, of divine feminine creative power, sometimes referred to as &#039;The Great Divine Mother&#039; in Hinduism. On the earthly plane, shakti most actively manifests through female embodiment and creativity/fertility, though it is also present in males in its potential, unmanifest form.[2]
Not only is Shakti responsible for creation, it is also the agent of all change. Shakti is cosmic existence as well as liberation, its most significant form being the Kundalini Shakti,[3] a mysterious psychospiritual force.[4] Shakti exists in a state of svātantrya, dependence on no one, being interdependent with the entire universe..

The  colour Blue in Hinduism 

In Hinduism, Gods like Lord Vishnu, Lord Krishna, Lord Ram and Lord Shiva are shown as having blue or dusky skin. The color of the skin is shown as either blue or sometimes black. Hindu religion is full of symbolisms and the blue color is also a symbol. Most avatars of Hindu gods are also shown in blue color.
Blue is the color of the infinite. All Hindu gods are an attempt by the human mind to give form to the formless Brahman (God). The color blues symbolizes immeasurable and all pervading reality – formless Brahman.
Swami Chinmayananda talking on the subject says that whatever is immeasurable can appear to the mortal eye only as blue; thus the cloudless summer sky is blue to us because the endless distance of space is interpreted by the physical eye as blue in color.

The Blue colour in Judaism : 
Blue in Judaism is used to symbolise divinity, because blue is the color of the sky and sea. It can also represent equilibrium, since its hue suggests a shade midway between white and black, day and night.[1]
In the Torah, the Israelites were commanded to put fringes, tzitzit, on the corners of their garments, and to weave within these fringes a “twisted thread of blue (tekhelet).”[2] The oral law requires that this blue thread be made from a dye extracted from a sea creature known as the hilazon. Maimonides claimed that this blue was the color of “the clear noonday sky”; Rashi, the color of the evening sky.[3]
According to several rabbinic sages, blue is the color of God’s Glory

In Judaism,You have NOAH as the ancestor.
In Hinduism,We have MANU (from which the word MAN comes)as the Primordial ancestor.

See the similarities between the flood stories of Matsaya purana and flood stories in Judaism.

During the period of mahapralaya, Lord Vishnu had taken Matsya Avatar (fish incarnation) to save the seeds of all lives and Manu.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>in Judaism in my limited knowlede ,you have Ein Soph.The definition of that is given here : Ein Sof is the divine origin of all created existence, in contrast to the Ein (or Ayn), which is infinite no-thingness. It was first used by Azriel ben Menahem, who, sharing the Neoplatonic view that God can have no desire, thought, word, or action, emphasized by it the negation of any attribute</p>
<p>Contrast this with Brahman : </p>
<p>ParaBrahman (Sanskrit) [from para beyond + Brahman (neuter) universal self or spirit] &#8211; That which is beyond Brahman. The self-enduring, eternal, self-sufficient cause of all causes, the essence of everything in the cosmos. In the Vedic style of writing, ParaBrahman is referred to as tat (that) as opposed to the manifest universe called idam (this). ParaBrahman means Supreme Brahman, or Supreme Cosmic Spirit, or Godhead. </p>
<p>It is also called Nirguna Brahman(without attributes).</p>
<p>Shekhina : Shekinah, Shechinah, Shechina, or Schechinah (Hebrew: שכינה‎), is the English spelling of a grammatically feminine Hebrew name of God in Judaism. The original word means the dwelling or settling, and denotes the dwelling or settling of the Divine Presence of God, especially in the Temple in Jerusalem..</p>
<p>Contrast this with Shakti :<br />
Shakti (Sanskrit pronunciation: [ˈʃʌktɪ]) (Devanagari: शक्ति; from Sanskrit shak, &#8220;to be able&#8221;), meaning &#8220;Power&#8221; or &#8220;empowerment,&#8221; is the primordial cosmic energy and represents the dynamic forces that are thought to move through the entire universe in Hinduism.[1] Shakti is the concept, or personification, of divine feminine creative power, sometimes referred to as &#8216;The Great Divine Mother&#8217; in Hinduism. On the earthly plane, shakti most actively manifests through female embodiment and creativity/fertility, though it is also present in males in its potential, unmanifest form.[2]<br />
Not only is Shakti responsible for creation, it is also the agent of all change. Shakti is cosmic existence as well as liberation, its most significant form being the Kundalini Shakti,[3] a mysterious psychospiritual force.[4] Shakti exists in a state of svātantrya, dependence on no one, being interdependent with the entire universe..</p>
<p>The  colour Blue in Hinduism </p>
<p>In Hinduism, Gods like Lord Vishnu, Lord Krishna, Lord Ram and Lord Shiva are shown as having blue or dusky skin. The color of the skin is shown as either blue or sometimes black. Hindu religion is full of symbolisms and the blue color is also a symbol. Most avatars of Hindu gods are also shown in blue color.<br />
Blue is the color of the infinite. All Hindu gods are an attempt by the human mind to give form to the formless Brahman (God). The color blues symbolizes immeasurable and all pervading reality – formless Brahman.<br />
Swami Chinmayananda talking on the subject says that whatever is immeasurable can appear to the mortal eye only as blue; thus the cloudless summer sky is blue to us because the endless distance of space is interpreted by the physical eye as blue in color.</p>
<p>The Blue colour in Judaism :<br />
Blue in Judaism is used to symbolise divinity, because blue is the color of the sky and sea. It can also represent equilibrium, since its hue suggests a shade midway between white and black, day and night.[1]<br />
In the Torah, the Israelites were commanded to put fringes, tzitzit, on the corners of their garments, and to weave within these fringes a “twisted thread of blue (tekhelet).”[2] The oral law requires that this blue thread be made from a dye extracted from a sea creature known as the hilazon. Maimonides claimed that this blue was the color of “the clear noonday sky”; Rashi, the color of the evening sky.[3]<br />
According to several rabbinic sages, blue is the color of God’s Glory</p>
<p>In Judaism,You have NOAH as the ancestor.<br />
In Hinduism,We have MANU (from which the word MAN comes)as the Primordial ancestor.</p>
<p>See the similarities between the flood stories of Matsaya purana and flood stories in Judaism.</p>
<p>During the period of mahapralaya, Lord Vishnu had taken Matsya Avatar (fish incarnation) to save the seeds of all lives and Manu.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Amit Kumar		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/13/nyaya-and-monotheism/#comment-9060</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Amit Kumar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2013 19:28:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6367#comment-9060</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[All idols are symbolic presentation of divine power.Nama and Rupa.These symbols are used in meditation to contemplate divine in duality school.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>All idols are symbolic presentation of divine power.Nama and Rupa.These symbols are used in meditation to contemplate divine in duality school.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Amit Kumar		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/13/nyaya-and-monotheism/#comment-9059</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Amit Kumar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2013 19:27:26 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6367#comment-9059</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Sir,
I read your posts with interest.Hinduism and Judaism have some similarities especially in Kaballah pov.Shakti and Shekhina are very similar.We consider Shakti - the femenine creative power of divine and you consider Shekhina as mother of Israel and femenine.You address her as a Bride,We address her as a Mother goddess.Secondly,We have concept  of Brahman and you have concept of Ein Soph.Kindly check the definitions.You have Hashem - god with attributes and we have Ishwar(which is god with Attributes)..You have reincarnation concept though as per your belief ,the full soul does not reincarnate but a part of it.We say the whole subtle body incarnates and goes to a new body and the cycle goes on till he is liberated with divine knowldge.We have Preya and Shreya and you have Yetzer hara and Yetzer tov.Check out the definitions.We have para vidya(Spiritual knowledge) and Apara vidya(Material KNowledge and you have similar terms in Daas/Daat Elyon (&quot;Higher Knowledge&quot;) and Daas/Daat Tachton (&quot;Lower Knowledge&quot;) are two alternative levels of perception of reality in Hasidic thought

All idols are symbolic presentation of divine power.Nama and Rupa.These symbols are used in meditation to contemplate divine in duality school.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sir,<br />
I read your posts with interest.Hinduism and Judaism have some similarities especially in Kaballah pov.Shakti and Shekhina are very similar.We consider Shakti &#8211; the femenine creative power of divine and you consider Shekhina as mother of Israel and femenine.You address her as a Bride,We address her as a Mother goddess.Secondly,We have concept  of Brahman and you have concept of Ein Soph.Kindly check the definitions.You have Hashem &#8211; god with attributes and we have Ishwar(which is god with Attributes)..You have reincarnation concept though as per your belief ,the full soul does not reincarnate but a part of it.We say the whole subtle body incarnates and goes to a new body and the cycle goes on till he is liberated with divine knowldge.We have Preya and Shreya and you have Yetzer hara and Yetzer tov.Check out the definitions.We have para vidya(Spiritual knowledge) and Apara vidya(Material KNowledge and you have similar terms in Daas/Daat Elyon (&#8220;Higher Knowledge&#8221;) and Daas/Daat Tachton (&#8220;Lower Knowledge&#8221;) are two alternative levels of perception of reality in Hasidic thought</p>
<p>All idols are symbolic presentation of divine power.Nama and Rupa.These symbols are used in meditation to contemplate divine in duality school.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Arie Folger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/13/nyaya-and-monotheism/#comment-9058</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arie Folger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2013 19:23:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6367#comment-9058</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/13/nyaya-and-monotheism/#comment-9057&quot;&gt;Alan Brill&lt;/a&gt;.

;-)  I will practice my meditation ... Seriously, wow, you expect to write over 40 posts on this, I really look forward. Having patience will be hard, though. Thank you for the treat.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/13/nyaya-and-monotheism/#comment-9057">Alan Brill</a>.</p>
<p>😉  I will practice my meditation &#8230; Seriously, wow, you expect to write over 40 posts on this, I really look forward. Having patience will be hard, though. Thank you for the treat.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/13/nyaya-and-monotheism/#comment-9057</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2013 19:15:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6367#comment-9057</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/13/nyaya-and-monotheism/#comment-9056&quot;&gt;Arie Folger&lt;/a&gt;.

you have to learned the virtue of patience as asked in the posts and om addition not to blur everything. Give me 40 blog posts and then ask.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/13/nyaya-and-monotheism/#comment-9056">Arie Folger</a>.</p>
<p>you have to learned the virtue of patience as asked in the posts and om addition not to blur everything. Give me 40 blog posts and then ask.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Arie Folger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/13/nyaya-and-monotheism/#comment-9056</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arie Folger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2013 19:12:40 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6367#comment-9056</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This is fascinating. But can you please elaborate on the Indian pantheon? All those temples dedicated to various gods, how do they fit in to the above monotheism? Or are these simply different (from our perspective then really radically different) takes on the Veda?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is fascinating. But can you please elaborate on the Indian pantheon? All those temples dedicated to various gods, how do they fit in to the above monotheism? Or are these simply different (from our perspective then really radically different) takes on the Veda?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: zjb		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/13/nyaya-and-monotheism/#comment-9050</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[zjb]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2013 03:25:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6367#comment-9050</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Reblogged this on &lt;a href=&quot;http://jewishphilosophyplace.wordpress.com/2013/11/13/nyaya-and-monotheism/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;jewish philosophy place&lt;/a&gt; and commented: 
I found this useful as a primer to Indian philosophy. I&#039;m re-blogging this for to keep on file, as it were, for possible future use. --ZJB]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Reblogged this on <a href="http://jewishphilosophyplace.wordpress.com/2013/11/13/nyaya-and-monotheism/" rel="nofollow">jewish philosophy place</a> and commented:<br />
I found this useful as a primer to Indian philosophy. I&#8217;m re-blogging this for to keep on file, as it were, for possible future use. &#8211;ZJB</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/13/nyaya-and-monotheism/#comment-9046</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2013 18:30:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6367#comment-9046</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/13/nyaya-and-monotheism/#comment-9045&quot;&gt;Larry Yudelson (@yudel)&lt;/a&gt;.

It is their intrinsic terminology. There are 6 Orthodox approaches or visions, the word is &quot;darshan&quot; and 3 heterodox ones.
If we spoke this way then the first 3 Orthodox ones would be philosophy, kabbalah, and halakhah. The fourth would be science which we dont have our own tradition. The fifth and most interesting one is -atheism which they keep as Orthodox and the sixth is yoga - which we lack.
Their heterodox is Buddhism, Jainism, materialism. Our heterodox would be Christianity, or gnosticism.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/13/nyaya-and-monotheism/#comment-9045">Larry Yudelson (@yudel)</a>.</p>
<p>It is their intrinsic terminology. There are 6 Orthodox approaches or visions, the word is &#8220;darshan&#8221; and 3 heterodox ones.<br />
If we spoke this way then the first 3 Orthodox ones would be philosophy, kabbalah, and halakhah. The fourth would be science which we dont have our own tradition. The fifth and most interesting one is -atheism which they keep as Orthodox and the sixth is yoga &#8211; which we lack.<br />
Their heterodox is Buddhism, Jainism, materialism. Our heterodox would be Christianity, or gnosticism.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Larry Yudelson (@yudel)		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/13/nyaya-and-monotheism/#comment-9045</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Larry Yudelson (@yudel)]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2013 18:22:48 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6367#comment-9045</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Could you elaborate on the &quot;schools&quot; terminology? Is it an indigenous term or is it an external category? If we were to speak about &quot;schools&quot; of Jewish philosophy, what would that look like?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Could you elaborate on the &#8220;schools&#8221; terminology? Is it an indigenous term or is it an external category? If we were to speak about &#8220;schools&#8221; of Jewish philosophy, what would that look like?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
