<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Tzvia Greenfield &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/tag/tzvia-greenfield/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 May 2010 14:21:59 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='kavvanah.wordpress.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/c9f111237f93750b6b994fc5185d49c3?s=96&#038;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>Tzvia Greenfield &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>Tzvia Greenfield and Judith Butler</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/tzvia-greenfield-and-judith-butler/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/tzvia-greenfield-and-judith-butler/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 03 May 2010 14:21:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ethics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[religious zionism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[judith butler]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tzvia Greenfield]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1222</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Tzvia Greenfield, our haredi Meretz Keneset member, just published an appreciation of Judith Butler, the feminist literary critic, on Israel/Palestine. My first reaction was one of treating it as an extreme posture. I mean, come on, one could not get &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/tzvia-greenfield-and-judith-butler/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Tzvia Greenfield, our haredi Meretz Keneset member, just published an appreciation of Judith Butler, the feminist literary critic, on Israel/Palestine. </p>
<p>My first reaction was one of treating it as an extreme posture. I mean, come on, one could not get almost any rabbi or Jewish communal figure anywhere on the spectrum to read Judith Butler. I thought of Leib Weisfish, who was on the speaking circuit in the 1980’s as a Mea Shearim dwelling Haredi Neturai Karta who was a passionate admirer of Nietzsche. Weisfish maintained a correspondence with Walter Kaufman, the translator and wanted the grave of Nietzsche to be transferred to Israel.</p>
<p>But my second thought was back to Greenfield’s haredism, which is not a sectarian culturally limited Haredism of Meah Shearim and probably should not be called Haredism. Her view seems to be closer to the older Rabbi Isaac Breuer influence world of Agudah from Germany where one can have a PhD in literature or biochemistry. But one holds that the Torah is above any politics, beyond any this worldly referent, and not subject to any personal choice- a radical separation of Torah and Derekh Eretz. Rabbi Breuer could discuss the secular world based on Nietzsche and Schopenhauer because the Torah was pure and entirely above society. He could also say that the Torah from a this-worldly perspective is biased against women but that is OK since Torah is to be considered from the eternal perspective. A few decades ago, there were still academics from the Poalai Agudah world that had such views. </p>
<p>(In 1990, Rav Shakh basically dissolved Poalai Agudah, telling them that “Torah only” was the only acceptable career, source of ideas, or worldview. The approach of Torah and a sharply bifurcated derekh eretz was no longer to be tolerated.)</p>
<p>So here is Greenfield&#8217;s article praising Judith Butler that the occupation needs to end because it would be the collapse of Israel as a democracy and as source of knowledge and talent. I am less interested in the political details as much as the synthesis of Meretz and Orthodoxy played out through Judith Butler. The reason for the sudden interest in Butler is because she passed through Israel a few months ago and obviously met with Meretz. In addition, Butler seems to at work on a monograph on Judaism, human rights, and Hannah Arendt.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1166426.html"><strong>Greenfield From Haaretz</strong></a>	</p>
<blockquote><p>Yet another terrifying possibility, of course, is that Israel would consciously renounce its own self-definition as a Western democracy. It would then gradually turn into a dictatorship that defines itself as Jewish. It would use armed force to continue to control all the territory west of the Jordan River, and would continue to deny the Palestinians&#8217; right to either freedom or equality. A choice of that kind would destroy Israel as a modern state, and accordingly also its ability to defend itself and to develop as a secure, flourishing, 21st-century society. </p>
<p>In this case as well, it is clear that most of the country&#8217;s intelligentsia, and indeed anyone with initiative, would leave Israel. Israel would remain with its religious population and its rightists &#8211; some of whom are capable of defending it, but most of whom are devoid of high-level development and management skills. The Israeli-Jewish dictatorship would thus suffer from a substantive weakness that would eventually lead to its defeat at the hands of its Muslim enemies. </p>
<p>It is sad to think that this process has apparently already started: The collapse of education and higher learning, together with the political corruption and the tremendous growth of those sectors that are not prepared to share the social, economic and military burden, is encouraging the more talented and diligent Israelis to leave the sinking Jewish ship. </p>
<p>Even if treating Israel as the country that embodies the ultimate evil in fact expresses a new and ugly incarnation of traditional anti-Semitism, which always viewed the Jews as the representative of all the world&#8217;s ills, the truth is still simple, but difficult to face: An Israel that does not allow the Palestinian situation to be resolved has effectively announced its own inexorable death, via the gradual destruction of the resources of knowledge and talent that have enabled it to develop and defend itself until now. In order to save Israel, we must immediately separate from the territories and their inhabitants.</p></blockquote>
<p><strong>Butler in her own words<br />
 	Judith Butler: As a Jew, I was taught it was ethically imperative to speak up 24/02/2010</strong><br />
 	<a href="http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1152017.html">Part one</a> 	<a href="http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1152018.html">Part two </a></p>
<blockquote><p>Philosopher, professor and author Judith Butler arrived in Israel this month, en route to the West Bank, where she was to give a seminar at Bir Zeit University, visit the theater in Jenin, and meet privately with friends and students.<br />
Why Israel-Palestine? Is this directly connected to your Jewishness? </p>
<p>As a Jew, I was taught that it was ethically imperative to speak up and to speak out against arbitrary state violence. That was part of what I learned when I learned about the Second World War and the concentration camps. There were those who would and could speak out against state racism and state violence, and it was imperative that we be able to speak out. Not just for Jews, but for any number of people. There was an entire idea of social justice that emerged for me from the consideration of the Nazi genocide. </p>
<p>I would also say that what became really hard for me is that if one wanted to criticize Israeli state violence &#8211; precisely because that as a Jew one is under obligation to criticize excessive state violence and state racism &#8211; then one is in a bind, because one is told that one is either self-hating as a Jew or engaging anti-Semitism. And yet for me, it comes out of a certain Jewish value of social justice. So how can I fulfill my obligation as a Jew to speak out against an injustice when, in speaking out against Israeli state and military injustice, I am accused of not being a good enough Jew or of being a self-hating Jew? This is the bind of my current situation. </p>
<p>Let me say one other thing about Jewish values. There are two things I took from Jewish philosophy and my Jewish formation that were really important for me&#8230; well there are many. There are many. Sitting shiva, for instance, explicit grieving. I thought it was the one of the most beautiful rituals of my youth. There were several people who died in my youth, and there were several moments when whole communities gathered in order to make sure that those who had suffered terrible losses were taken up and brought back into the community and given a way to affirm life again.<br />
So I agree with you. But I think we have to get over the idea that a state has to express a nation. And if we have a bi-national state, it&#8217;s expressing two nations. Only when bi-nationalism deconstructs the idea of a nation can we hope to think about what a state, what a polity might look like that would actually extend equality. It is no longer the question of &#8220;two peoples,&#8221; as Martin Buber put it. There is extraordinary complexity and intermixing among both the Jewish and the Palestinian populations. There will be those who say, &#8220;Ok, a state that expresses two cultural identities.&#8221; No. State should not be in the business of expressing cultural identity.<br />
I think that the BDS movement has taken several forms, and it is probably important to distinguish among them</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="http://www.thenation.com/doc/20100426/butler"><strong>More Butler from this Spring</strong></a></p>
<blockquote><p>Lastly, let me say this. You may feel fear in voting for this resolution. I was frightened coming here this evening. You may fear that you will seem anti-Semitic, that you cannot handle the appearance of being insensitive to Israel’s needs for self-defense, insensitive to the history of Jewish suffering. Perhaps it is best to remember the words of Primo Levi who survived a brutal internment at Auschwitz when he had the courage to oppose the Israeli bombings of southern Lebanon in the early 1980s. He openly criticized Menachem Begin, who directed the bombing of civilian centers, and he received letters asking him whether he cared at all about the spilling of Jewish blood. He wrote:<br />
I reply that the blood spilled pains me just as much as the blood spilled by all other human beings. But there are still harrowing letters. And I am tormented by them, because I know that Israel was founded by people like me, only less fortunate than me. Men with a number from Auschwitz tattooed on their arms, with no home nor homeland, escaping from the horrors of the Second World War who found in Israel a home and a homeland. I know all this. But I also know that this is Begin’s favorite defense. And I deny any validity to this defense.<br />
As the Israeli historian Idith Zertal makes clear, do not use this most atrocious historical suffering to legitimate military destructiveness–it is a cruel and twisted use of the history of suffering to defend the affliction of suffering on others.</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="http://blogs.ssrc.org/tif/2009/12/04/rethinking-secularism-the-power-of-religion-in-the-public-sphere/">Here is a video of further musing of Butler</a> about on Hannah Arendt And Israel delivered this past fall.<br />
For those interested, here is also an online discussion between her and Agamben on human rights.</p>
<p>I am less interested in the politics and more interested in the cultural weave. Haredi religion as entirely a choice of the heart without any social, cultural, or political ramifications. Rabbi Isaac Breuer influence? Prof Yeshaya Leibowitz? In the 1950&#8217;s Orthodox Rabbis separated between Torah and American democracy- keeping them apart. Greenfield claims to be following a diaspora model. Can it it be reformulated for a half century later?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/03/tzvia-greenfield-and-judith-butler/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>9</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tzvia Greenfield: Israel&#8217;s first female Haredi MK- Meretz Activist</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/17/tzvia-greenfield-peace-activist-leftist-israels-first-female-haredi-mk/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/17/tzvia-greenfield-peace-activist-leftist-israels-first-female-haredi-mk/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 18 Apr 2010 02:51:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[israel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[religious zionism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Meretz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tzvia Greenfield]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1146</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[From Haaretz- full version here Tzvia Greenfield. Israel&#8217;s first Haredi female to be elected to the Knesset, she is a fierce critic of her own community&#8217;s attitudes to the peace process and modernity; describing the Haredi community as being &#8220;incapable &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/17/tzvia-greenfield-peace-activist-leftist-israels-first-female-haredi-mk/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1163329.html">From Haaretz- full version here</a></p>
<p>Tzvia Greenfield. Israel&#8217;s first Haredi female to be elected to the Knesset, she is a fierce critic of her own community&#8217;s attitudes to the peace process and modernity; describing the Haredi community as being &#8220;incapable of compromise.&#8221; Yet she still lives in it, a resident of the Jerusalem suburb of Har Nof.</p>
<p>Of course, her horizons are far broader than the narrow vista of ultra-Orthodoxy. The 62-year-old, who has a doctorate in political philosophy from the Hebrew University, was elected on behalf of Meretz last November. She advocates a two-State solution based closely on the pre-1967 War borders; a self-proclaimed egalitarian, she’s in favour of women rabbis and religious pluralism.</p>
<p>The mother-of-five, who sent her children to national religious high-schools and both her sons to the army, arrives as expected wearing a sheitel (one that looks like a sheitel) and a long dress.</p>
<p>She then speaks candidly about her prospects of influencing change: she is unsure that Israel&#8217;s left can be revived &#8211; she&#8217;s not sure they can awake secular Israel from its &#8220;slumber&#8221;- and feels compelled to channel change in her own back-yard, despite disillusionment about the trenchant positions of the Haredi world, which her Austrian &#8220;ultra-Orthodox Zionist parents&#8221; brought her into.</p>
<p>She describes the &#8220;haredization&#8221; of parts of Jerusalem and Beit Shemesh as &#8220;killing&#8221; those places: &#8220;Once they take over a community no one else can live in &#8211; like in some parts of Jerusalem and Beit Shemesh &#8211; that&#8217;s unacceptable. That is something people won&#8217;t tolerate because they want to live their lives. One neighbour cannot impinge on the other&#8217;s rights; it&#8217;s true the Haredi community doesn&#8217;t understand its task in a democracy. It believes when its population grows in a territory, the whole area should be governed by its rules.</p>
<p>She added: &#8220;An essential part of adjustment is in being a minority; the problem is when they become a majority. They are already driving people out of Jerusalem and not just the secular &#8211; but the modern Orthodox; because they cannot tolerate this. If the Haredi community gets large enough we won&#8217;t see nice developments.&#8221;</p>
<p>Her non-interventionist liberal instincts means she defends its right to promote a school curriculum that bares little resemblance to the national model: she believes a &#8220;balanced&#8221; approach is necessary in seeking to bring the Haredi world into the modern age, without assaulting its delicate nuances. &#8220;Interfering in questions of education is particularly sensitive and fragile,&#8221; she argues. &#8220;Thinking from all sides, I think society has to ensure Haredim aren&#8217;t poor. Despite Israeli society’s investment it&#8217;s a very poor community.&#8221;</p>
<p>Can Meretz deliver change? &#8220;I&#8217;m not sure. I think the left all over Europe and particularly Israel has severely failed on many assignments and I think the left should profoundly reconsider its goals and how it goes about them. To me after years of being a peace activist it&#8217;s a shameful situation and I think it&#8217;s unacceptable not to look at ourselves.</p>
<p>Q and A</p>
<p><strong>Bearing in mind you say some religious people have difficulty with compromise how would you like to see change stemming from the religious world?</strong></p>
<p>Religious people have difficulty grasping essential ideas like peace, compromise and accepting others. These are difficult issues and they&#8217;ve got to be worked out.</p>
<p>I&#8217;m writing a book on the subject. I decided I had to write down what I think and that would be the best way to explain how one could retain ones religiosity and faithfulness to ones position and yet encourage profound changes.</p>
<p>I have one answer to your question. I think a religion ought to be concerned with human beings and not objects. Too often traditional religions have a great interest in objects and not enough in human beings. That has to be shifted completely. The emphasis and the concern should be entirely different and there are ways to do it.</p>
<p><strong>Do you think the demonstration of the human side of the Judaism has been lost?</strong></p>
<p>I think there is not enough concern about human beings, and I mean human beings in general, including non-Jews. As a religious person I believe that all human beings were created in the image of God.</p>
<p>What we&#8217;ve seen in Israel in the last thirty or forty years ever since the &#8217;67 War is a concern with land. That&#8217;s an object. It&#8217;s become the centre of attention for religious people and I think that&#8217;s a major mistake and I think that should be changed.</p>
<p><strong>Where do you stand on issues of religious pluralism and the rights of all sects of Judaism to have equal funding with regards to conversion programs and education?</strong></p>
<p>Of course I support pluralism. People have to make their choices and decide what&#8217;s for them. There&#8217;s no way the state should direct on what or how they should do things. Every citizen should be a free subject to make his or her decisions without any input by the state whatsoever.</p>
<p><strong>How would you, as a progressive Haredi, advocate it modernises its approach to self- governance?</strong></p>
<p>Education. Education is the answer to everything, The fact that it blocks general education to its community is part of the problem because they never really understand what is going on and make their own decision. I would try and allow these people to get education without breaking down the system altogether, without enforcing education on them in a way which cannot acceptable, not only for them, but even for me. I don?t believe in enforcing it brutally; it has to be done carefully.</p>
<p>The very fact it&#8217;s living in the modern world, is affecting it. We are talking about the younger generation that will make decisions about what they are doing. In both America and Israel.  They are re-evaluating the world that their parents have brought them into. We&#8217;re probably going to see changes in the next 20-30 years. After all, they do not want to be poor.</p>
<p>You hope that the secular and Haredi worlds can live side by side but at the moment even the modern Orthodox are getting annoyed with the Haredim as the recent riots in Beit Shemesh prove.</p>
<p>Once they take over a community no one else can live in &#8211; like in some parts of Jerusalem and Beit Shemesh &#8211; that&#8217;s unacceptable. That is something people won’t tolerate because they want to live their lives. One neighbor cannot impinge on the other&#8217;s rights; it&#8217;s true the Haredi community doesn&#8217;t understand its task in a democracy. It believes when its population grows in a territory the whole area should be governed by its rules.</p>
<p><strong>The Haredization of Jerusalem is already here &#8211; how can this situation be clawed back?</strong></p>
<p>The community is poor, uneducated and very militant &#8211; the combination is lethal. It will kill Jerusalem.</p>
<p><strong>How can the Haredi leadership recognise the need to modernise?</strong></p>
<p>There is one factor in favour of modernisation- poverty. Some of the leadership recognizes and is concerned by this. Although the politicians would recommend poverty should be paid for, the leaders have a deeper approach. Certain changes must occur. First women join professions. Later on some men join. Things will change. Young men will be encouraged to join colleges. Already now there are a couple of colleges where Haredi girls are accepted to law or commerce school.</p>
<p><strong>What do you think about the status of women in the Haredi world?</strong></p>
<p>The big issue here is a very delicate one. That is children. Large families thirty years ago was six children; now there&#8217;s 13 or 14 &#8211; from one wife. I believes the glorification of bringing as many children as possible is a definite way of ensuring women can&#8217;t bring their advantages into effect &#8211; subjugation.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s inconceivable for a woman to say to her husband, &#8220;I won&#8217;t have more than three children&#8221; &#8211; a cause for divorce. Inconceivable and non-existent.</p>
<p><strong>Do you think there should be Orthodox female rabbis?</strong></p>
<p>I&#8217;m all for it. I think if women want to serve as rabbis in religious function they should be given the right to do so. The issue of depriving women a religious position is part of deprivation of women from positions of power. Women don’t have equal rights in Judaism because they never had them in any field of life- a general result of subjugation.</p>
<p><strong>Why is there a lack of state involvement in social issues?</strong></p>
<p>The state has been run by conservatives who don&#8217;t want equal rights for women, Arabs, anyone; any progressive left issues. They want to sabotage these things.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/17/tzvia-greenfield-peace-activist-leftist-israels-first-female-haredi-mk/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>7</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
