<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>pew forum &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/tag/pew-forum/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2010 15:15:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='kavvanah.wordpress.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/c9f111237f93750b6b994fc5185d49c3?s=96&#038;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>pew forum &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>Millennial Data</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/18/millennial-data/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/18/millennial-data/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2010 13:34:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[sociology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[millenials]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pew forum]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=818</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Pew Forum has finally tabulated all the studies of the last few years and made their statement about the Millennial generation. No surprises. But what will it do to the community? Will Orthodoxy form a reactive ideology against the &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/18/millennial-data/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Pew Forum has finally tabulated all the studies of the last few years and made their statement about the Millennial generation. No surprises. But what will it do to the community? Will Orthodoxy form a reactive ideology against the younger generation? Will Orthodoxy gain an influx of those for whom the issue of Gay rights pushes them out of their liberal communities? Another point, we see the children of Evangelicals giving up Literalism, even while remaining in the fold.How will the break of literalism 47% to 53% play itself out? Debates in the classroom? Fights over which books to read?<br />
Anything else in full report worth noting? &#8211; <a href="http://pewforum.org/docs/?DocID=510">Full report here.</a></p>
<p><em>According to a new report by the Pew Forum on Religion and Public Life, the gap on some issues has widened into a chasm, notably on issues related to gay rights and tolerance.</em></p>
<p><em>&#8216;Young people are more accepting of homosexuality and evolution than are older people. They are also more comfortable with having a bigger government, and they are less concerned about Hollywood threatening their values,&#8217; said the report, which was released on Wednesday.<br />
For example, the report said that Pew&#8217;s massive 2007 US Religious Landscape Survey found young adults to be almost twice as likely to say homosexuality should be accepted by society as those 65 and older, 63 per cent versus 35 per cent. Overall in the 30+ age group only 47 per cent said homosexuality should be accepted. The report also said surveys showed that less than a third of Millennial adults saw Hollywood as a threat to their moral values compared to 44 per cent of those 30 and over. </em></p>
<p><em>Differences between young people and their elders today are also apparent in views of the Bible, although the differences are somewhat less pronounced. Overall, young people are slightly less inclined than those in older age groups to view the Bible as the literal word of God. Interestingly, age differences on this item are most dramatic among young evangelicals and are virtually nonexistent in other groups. Although younger evangelicals are just as likely as older evangelicals (and more likely than people in most other religious groups) to see the Bible as the word of God, they are less likely than older evangelicals to see it as the literal word of God. Less than half of young evangelicals interpret the Bible literally (47%), compared with 61% of evangelicals 30 and older.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/18/millennial-data/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rick Warren&#8217;s new agenda:what we can learn from it?</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/29/rick-warrens-new-agendawhat-we-can-learn-from-it/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/29/rick-warrens-new-agendawhat-we-can-learn-from-it/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2009 13:10:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[popular religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rabbis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sociology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[spirituality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pew forum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pew foundation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[purpose driven life]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=438</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Someone in the comments mentioned that my post was similar to a NYT op-ed and said it must be a meme going around. It is not a meme but that we all subscribe to the same list serves of religion &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/29/rick-warrens-new-agendawhat-we-can-learn-from-it/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Someone in the comments mentioned that my post was similar to a NYT op-ed and said it must be a meme going around. It is not a meme but that we all subscribe to the same list serves of religion information such as the Pew foundation that study and conduct surveys of religion in America. Orthodoxy, except for the truly sectarian, follows these trends as much as any other group does. So if you want to know the range of positions available at a given time they provide the guidelines. Orthodoxy will follow other similar conservative groups. Chief Rabbi Sacks is closer to Pope Benedict. NY Centrist Orthodoxy is closer to certain aspect of the Evangelicals and the Kiruv organizations are closest to other aspects of the Evangelicals.<br />
At the end of last month,<a href="http://pewforum.org/events/rss.php?EventID=221"> Pew held an interview with Rick Warren</a> to let journalists know where things are going.  Rick&#8217;s book, The Purpose Driven Life, is the best-selling nonfiction book in American history &#8211; over 30 million copies. That was the first quarter century of his career and corresponds to the religious turn in America. He has now turned to broader concerns. These are some of the directions and causes people will want from their Orthodoxy. Whoever gets there first will claim them</p>
<blockquote><p>We do training of what we call the three legs of the stool: business leadership, church leadership and public leadership in government.<br />
We have over 4,500 small groups. They meet in every city in Southern California.<br />
The second signature issue of our church we started in 1993, 10 years later, and it is called Celebrate Recovery. Celebrate Recovery is a Bible-based recovery program. It&#8217;s similar to AA but it&#8217;s built on the actual words of Jesus.<br />
The third signature issue we began in 2002, and that is our AIDS initiative for people infected and affected with AIDS.<br />
The fourth signature issue we began in 2003. It&#8217;s called the P.E.A.C.E. Plan. It&#8217;s a global humanitarian effort to take on the five biggest problems on the planet: poverty, disease, illiteracy, corruption and conflict. P.E.A.C.E. stands for Promote reconciliation, Equip ethical leaders, &#8220;A&#8221; is assist the poor, &#8220;C&#8221; is care for the sick and &#8220;E&#8221; is educate the next generation.</p></blockquote>
<p>Notice his working together with lay leadership and government agencies. He divides his Church into many focus groups “parents with a Downs child” “parents of an ADD child” “parents of twins.”<br />
His work with AA was done in Judaism by Rabbi Abraham Twerski and several elements of the Engaged Yeshivish world, not YU. Centrist Orthodoxy does not relish the thought of working with addictions as part of the rabbinate. Aids treatment is not part of the community at all.  Finally, the community does not make as its mission to fight poverty, disease, illiteracy, corruption, and conflict. This last one is where the future of American conservative religion lies.</p>
<blockquote><p>WARREN: the future of the world is not secularism. The future of the world is religious pluralism, and we must learn to get along. It is not secularism. There was the myth in the 20th century that if we just educate people they won&#8217;t need God anymore.<br />
I was the keynote speaker for ISNA, the Islamic Society of North America, which is the largest convention of Muslims. It was here in D.C. on the Fourth of July. There were 25,000 Muslims here in town, and they invited a non-Muslim to be the keynote speaker.</p></blockquote>
<p>This affirmation of religious pluralism from an exclusivist Evangelical Christian is where things are going. And unlike the 1980’s and 1990’s where Evangelicals said “woe is me- the secularists are after us;” Rick Warren is now boldly going out into the world and trying to put relgion in the public sphere (Don&#8217;t confuse his position with that of First Things and David Novak.) Many college students participate in interfaith events as part of the post 9//11 world, even Orthodox. We have had orthodox Jews and Muslims discussing difficulties in dietary laws and hair covering, Catholics and Orthodox Jews holding joint Friday night dinners, and groups of several faiths meeting to each talk about their experiences- not theology or doctrine but personal narratives.</p>
<blockquote><p>I have many, many who are gay leaders across the nation who have worked with me on AIDS. Kay and I have personally given millions of dollars &#8211; millions of dollars personally &#8211; to help people with HIV and AIDS. We&#8217;ve worked with all kinds of gay groups on these issues. I wrote those guys apologies and said, you guys know I didn&#8217;t mean this. Oh, we knew. We knew it, Rick.<br />
But all of the criticism came from people who didn&#8217;t know me &#8211; 100 percent. Not a single gay leader who knew me personally criticized me. Not one. All of it came from people who didn&#8217;t know me personally because I didn&#8217;t have the relationship. That goes back to this thing about if you don&#8217;t have the relationship, where do you know where that guy&#8217;s head is anyway? He said that. He didn&#8217;t correct it. Well, that&#8217;s not their fault; that&#8217;s my fault.</p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>My message is to the individual, and that is, every individual matters. I don&#8217;t care who you are or what you&#8217;ve done, what you claim to be or &#8211; you matter to God and you are loved unconditionally. You can&#8217;t make God stop loving you. Here&#8217;s my philosophy of life: If God gives me a choice to reject him or love him &#8211; because it&#8217;s not love if I&#8217;m forced to love him &#8211; if God gives me a choice to reject him or love him, then I&#8217;ve got to give everybody else that choice too. And that&#8217;s why I believe in America. I&#8217;ve got to give everybody the choice.</p></blockquote>
<p>This is his philosophy on GLBT issues as an evangelical. He does not support Gay marriage but would not support the anti-legislation either. The press and the blogs love to tear him apart from both sides. The web is filled with statements hinging on his every word to see what he accepts or rejects. In contrast,  Rev. Richard Cizik  who was Vice President for the National Association of Evangelicals and was  leading evangelicals toward ecology and global stewardship  (another role model for orthodoxy) expressed his support for same sex unions and that he was closer to supporting same sex marriage and was forced to resign from his leadership position.</p>
<blockquote><p>Melinda Gates, who was a friend of mine said, Rick, I get it. The church could be the distribution center for health care. I said, not only health care, for everything else. You can use it for education, you can use it &#8211; all five things that we&#8217;re talking about in the P.E.A.C.E. program. I said, let me give you an example.Then we started teaching them more things like how to dress a wound, all the way up to how to administer ARVs. Today, right now, I have 1,400 trained community health care workers &#8211; it will be over 1,500 by the end of December &#8211; in an area that had one doctor a year-and-a-half ago.</p></blockquote>
<p>Notice he is friends with confirmed agnostic Melinda and Bill Gates. And when he asks for money it is not to build churches or parochial institutions but to offer health care in Africa.  Young Jews like AJWS and Hazon.</p>
<blockquote><p>Third is I added up all that the church had paid me in 25 years and I gave it all back. I knew I was being put under the spotlight, and I never wanted anybody to think that I do what I do for money. I don&#8217;t. I do it because I love Jesus Christ. And I love people.<br />
We&#8217;re not going to change our lifestyle one bit. I still live in the same house I&#8217;ve lived in for 17 years. I drive a 10-year-old Ford truck. I bought my watch at Wal-Mart. I don&#8217;t own a boat, I don&#8217;t own a plane, I don&#8217;t own a vacation home. I didn&#8217;t want to be a televangelist. The second thing is seven years ago I stopped taking a salary from Saddleback Church, so I effectively retired.</p></blockquote>
<p><strong>See any Orthodox leaders going this route?</strong></p>
<blockquote><p>We lowered the age of the leadership body in our church by 16 years in one week. We had a group of pastors who have been with me pretty much since the start that we call our elders. Most of us are in our 50s, mid-50s, and we have led the church all these years. All along we&#8217;ve been mentoring the next generation, which is what I&#8217;m doing. I&#8217;m spending the rest of my life mentoring the next generation. We had a group of young guys who were in their 30s and a couple reaching 40, and in one week we turned over the leadership.</p></blockquote>
<p>This is important for the change in leadership style<a href="http:///kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/19/determine-your-rabbinical-age/">&#8211; see this quiz that I posted a while ago</a>.<strong>Take the Quiz</strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/29/rick-warrens-new-agendawhat-we-can-learn-from-it/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>6</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Many Americans Mix Multiple Faiths: Eastern &#038; New Age Beliefs Widespread</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/15/many-americans-mix-multiple-faiths-eastern-new-age-beliefs-widespread/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/15/many-americans-mix-multiple-faiths-eastern-new-age-beliefs-widespread/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2009 23:45:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Buddhism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[popular religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sociology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[spirituality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[azande]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[modern orthodoxy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[new age]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pew forum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rationality]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=366</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Last week, the Pew Forum has put out a report on how Americans believe in many contradictory things. Many Americans &#8220;Mix Multiple Faiths and that Eastern, New Age Beliefs Widespread&#8221; Some 24 percent of U.S. adults surveyed (including 22 percent &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/15/many-americans-mix-multiple-faiths-eastern-new-age-beliefs-widespread/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Last week, the <em>Pew Forum</em> has put out a report on how Americans believe in many contradictory things. Many Americans <a href="http://pewforum.org/docs/?DocID=490">&#8220;Mix Multiple Faiths and that Eastern, New Age Beliefs Widespread&#8221;</a></p>
<blockquote><p>Some 24 percent of U.S. adults surveyed (including 22 percent of those who identified themselves as Christians) say they believe in reincarnation — that people will be reborn in this world again and again. Other results of the Pew  Research Center survey:</p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>* Belief in Astrology: 25 percent<br />
* Seen or felt a ghost: Nearly 20 percent<br />
* Consulted a fortuneteller or a psychic: 15 percent</p>
<p>&#8220;The religious beliefs and practices of Americans do not fit neatly into conventional categories,&#8221; Pew analysts concluded. &#8220;Large numbers of Americans engage in multiple religious practices, mixing elements of diverse traditions. Many say they attend worship services of more than one faith or denomination — even when they are not traveling or going to special events like weddings and funerals. Many also blend Christianity with Eastern or New Age beliefs such as reincarnation, astrology and the presence of spiritual energy in physical objects.&#8221;</p>
<p>Nearly half (49 percent) said they have had a religious or mystical experience, defined as a &#8220;moment of sudden religious insight or awakening.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>Most this applies in equal percent, if not greater, to the Modern Orthodox community. There are several of us who have watched the local community list serve for several years and have noted the ever increasing magic and superstition.</p>
<p>To return to the discussion of rationality from below. If someone calls the Modern Orthodox community rational and the Yeshiva world superstitious then does it correspond to the facts? On one hand it does not since the modern community displays all the beliefs of the Pew Report. Are they saying they want to be rational and rather than engaging in rationality they say other are others are superstitious?  Or is it that modern Orthodox has reached a point where they have a rational public Judaism but a magical superstitious private life. Meaning that to treat Torah as irrational is no good, but to live a new age life is OK. Or is it just a denial of what people actually think?</p>
<p>Maimonides would not approve of any of these beliefs but he was willing to write off the masses or at least seek to change them minimally by fiat. But what is this rationality of modern orthodoxy that does not involve rational training. It is like the works of Chassidus that describe dvekus as a way to warm people’s hearts even if they are not having such an experience. (This is a whole Michel Certeau  discussion to be had here)</p>
<p>One way of looking at this is to return to the discussion of rationality of the 1970’s of Wilson-Barnes-Winch. who used the African Azande tribe described by EE Pritchard as their model. The Azande tribe knew that trees fall for natural causes but if someone is hurt it had to be witchcraft , this way they can speak of theodicy and meaning. But this case of the tribe of the Modern Orthodox is a bit tougher to unravel.. What is the first order causality and what is second order? Do they live in the world of their secular professions and suburban lives and then make a leap into a second order world of Torah and halakhah in order to make meaning in life and give order to a secular existence? Or do they live in the rational world of their professions and have a halakhah equally secular of the supernatural so they find solace in the supernatural, new age, and superstitious beliefs? Is Torah their primary cosmology or are the beliefs of the Pew study their cosmology? Do they get meaning that transcends their rationality from Torah or from superstition?</p>
<p>An alternate way to explain things might be to compare the orthodox community to religion in China, where Daoism, Confucianism and Buddhism exist simultaneously.  As Rav Lichtenstein, and others, have noted, halakhah functions as a proper order of life, providing education, hierarchy, values, and respect similar to Confucianism. Here is a possible extension after the Pew study, the superstition and new age functions like Daoism- it provided “scientific” explanations of sickness, of power and of magic.. People live surrounding themselves with forms of Daoism like Fung Shui and Chinese medicine. And finally, only some people, those more monastic and meditative, seek the greater explanatory force of Buddhism. So too here, while everyone does the ordered life of halakhah, the Jewish magic and new age is ever present in the community, while only some people go in for either philosophy or spirituality, akin to Buddhism, with their greater explanatory power but their greater removal from ordinary life.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/15/many-americans-mix-multiple-faiths-eastern-new-age-beliefs-widespread/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
