<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Reb Yudel, Ethan Tucker, and Dan Bern	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/02/27/reb-yudel-ethan-tucker-and-dan-bern/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/02/27/reb-yudel-ethan-tucker-and-dan-bern/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2011 04:46:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: BZ		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/02/27/reb-yudel-ethan-tucker-and-dan-bern/#comment-2725</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[BZ]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2011 04:46:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3167#comment-2725</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&lt;i&gt;Another distinction is that Pardes sees itself as a pluralistic institution that doesn’t take stands on the interpretation of halacha and doesn’t have expectations of it students&lt;/i&gt;

My understanding of Pardes is that this is not entirely accurate:  while it is correct that Pardes doesn&#039;t place expectations on what its students do when they&#039;re outside of the building, it doesn&#039;t claim to be pluralistic (though you have to be paying very close attention to catch this), and it does promote a particular approach to halacha as normative (though it doesn&#039;t enforce it).]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><i>Another distinction is that Pardes sees itself as a pluralistic institution that doesn’t take stands on the interpretation of halacha and doesn’t have expectations of it students</i></p>
<p>My understanding of Pardes is that this is not entirely accurate:  while it is correct that Pardes doesn&#8217;t place expectations on what its students do when they&#8217;re outside of the building, it doesn&#8217;t claim to be pluralistic (though you have to be paying very close attention to catch this), and it does promote a particular approach to halacha as normative (though it doesn&#8217;t enforce it).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: chakira		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/02/27/reb-yudel-ethan-tucker-and-dan-bern/#comment-2713</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[chakira]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 17:18:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3167#comment-2713</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/02/27/reb-yudel-ethan-tucker-and-dan-bern/#comment-2710&quot;&gt;Jon&lt;/a&gt;.

I the four articles as an opportunity to attack the programmatic vision as articulated in multiple forums and constantly reiterated by Tucker including in this talk. I do not think that is unfair.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/02/27/reb-yudel-ethan-tucker-and-dan-bern/#comment-2710">Jon</a>.</p>
<p>I the four articles as an opportunity to attack the programmatic vision as articulated in multiple forums and constantly reiterated by Tucker including in this talk. I do not think that is unfair.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Jon		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/02/27/reb-yudel-ethan-tucker-and-dan-bern/#comment-2710</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jon]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 05:57:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3167#comment-2710</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/02/27/reb-yudel-ethan-tucker-and-dan-bern/#comment-2698&quot;&gt;chakira&lt;/a&gt;.

... It was just a talk for some high-school kids.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/02/27/reb-yudel-ethan-tucker-and-dan-bern/#comment-2698">chakira</a>.</p>
<p>&#8230; It was just a talk for some high-school kids.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: MBG		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/02/27/reb-yudel-ethan-tucker-and-dan-bern/#comment-2709</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[MBG]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 22:51:15 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3167#comment-2709</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I have often felt that talking to Hadar types can be like talking to charedim.  It&#039;s obvious to them that they are doing the right thing, have picked the right battles, and have chosen the path of virtue.  Each speaks as if their lifestyle is self-justifying, ultimately tracing back to God in some loose way, resting on many unspoken assumptions that would be easy to challenge logically, but difficult to challenge vis a vis my specific interlocutor.  There is a similar emunah peshutah.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have often felt that talking to Hadar types can be like talking to charedim.  It&#8217;s obvious to them that they are doing the right thing, have picked the right battles, and have chosen the path of virtue.  Each speaks as if their lifestyle is self-justifying, ultimately tracing back to God in some loose way, resting on many unspoken assumptions that would be easy to challenge logically, but difficult to challenge vis a vis my specific interlocutor.  There is a similar emunah peshutah.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: chakira		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/02/27/reb-yudel-ethan-tucker-and-dan-bern/#comment-2708</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[chakira]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 21:56:40 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3167#comment-2708</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/02/27/reb-yudel-ethan-tucker-and-dan-bern/#comment-2704&quot;&gt;David S&lt;/a&gt;.

I do not think this maps onto strict or lenient. I am with Ethan Tucker when he says that he is not just a meikeil. I think it maps onto neoliberalism and thus I wonder at revelation&#039;s new role as the handmaiden of neoliberal values. Maybe there is some sittlichkeit they are extracting from Torah-- Why it is so deracinated....yelamdeinu Rabbeinu.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/02/27/reb-yudel-ethan-tucker-and-dan-bern/#comment-2704">David S</a>.</p>
<p>I do not think this maps onto strict or lenient. I am with Ethan Tucker when he says that he is not just a meikeil. I think it maps onto neoliberalism and thus I wonder at revelation&#8217;s new role as the handmaiden of neoliberal values. Maybe there is some sittlichkeit they are extracting from Torah&#8211; Why it is so deracinated&#8230;.yelamdeinu Rabbeinu.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Yonatan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/02/27/reb-yudel-ethan-tucker-and-dan-bern/#comment-2706</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Yonatan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 15:51:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3167#comment-2706</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I think that we should distinguish between laws that Hadar might find morally troubling (e.g. not counting women for a minyan or not saving the lives of gentiles on Shabbos) vs. other laws (e.g. Kashrus, Shabbos, Yom Kippur) which are just inconvenient. They do require adherence to the latter among their community.

I think Chakira &#038; AS are making most of this overly complicated.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think that we should distinguish between laws that Hadar might find morally troubling (e.g. not counting women for a minyan or not saving the lives of gentiles on Shabbos) vs. other laws (e.g. Kashrus, Shabbos, Yom Kippur) which are just inconvenient. They do require adherence to the latter among their community.</p>
<p>I think Chakira &amp; AS are making most of this overly complicated.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: David S		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/02/27/reb-yudel-ethan-tucker-and-dan-bern/#comment-2704</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[David S]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 13:32:32 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3167#comment-2704</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I would argue that the same issues apply to Charedi thinkers except in reverse.  They constantly change the tradition through the addition of new strictures that are designed to show how much more frum the true frusters are.  One need only look at outcomes to know that this is true.  There are Rabbis like Rabbi Tucker whose outcome may be loaded from the start to look for egalitarianism in the Torah.  There are also Rabbis for whom a strict interpretation of anything is also a foregone conclusion.  

People who can truly be objective are few and far between.  It seems to me that God created the world with diverse human beings.  He therefore wants diversity of thought.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I would argue that the same issues apply to Charedi thinkers except in reverse.  They constantly change the tradition through the addition of new strictures that are designed to show how much more frum the true frusters are.  One need only look at outcomes to know that this is true.  There are Rabbis like Rabbi Tucker whose outcome may be loaded from the start to look for egalitarianism in the Torah.  There are also Rabbis for whom a strict interpretation of anything is also a foregone conclusion.  </p>
<p>People who can truly be objective are few and far between.  It seems to me that God created the world with diverse human beings.  He therefore wants diversity of thought.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: chakira		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/02/27/reb-yudel-ethan-tucker-and-dan-bern/#comment-2702</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[chakira]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 03:26:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3167#comment-2702</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thanks for making me clarify. This is exactly the point I think I need to elucidate most. I think that the one reason too many problem is relevant here. In other words, if what I said about a pragmatic methodology leading to a moral epistemology is true, then why take the Torah detour? 

I hear the question about forms of life associated with Halakha, but isn&#039;t Tucker trying to open up just those forms of life? Is that not what he means when he says Torah demands something of everyone? 

I think maybe I think these texts are so rich that their applicability is maybe not going to be something quite so simple as not smoking on Saturday. It might be more a work of appropriation like Heidegger&#039;s discussion of fallenness or Gelassenheit. These are models that kind of come to mind, I am not sure about my hermeneutics and its political/real world implications.

Maybe I would say to Tucker: I personally am not committed to apply these texts one way or another. But in raising the stakes of your feminism by marrying it to Revelation, it raises the question, why stop there? Why hem in the radical critique at gender roles and not have a full blown social critique? Why does it map so neatly to corporate speak  and PC speak and that kind of utterly banal use of language? Does all this make you question this marriage of revelation and God to feminism and faux egalitarianism?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thanks for making me clarify. This is exactly the point I think I need to elucidate most. I think that the one reason too many problem is relevant here. In other words, if what I said about a pragmatic methodology leading to a moral epistemology is true, then why take the Torah detour? </p>
<p>I hear the question about forms of life associated with Halakha, but isn&#8217;t Tucker trying to open up just those forms of life? Is that not what he means when he says Torah demands something of everyone? </p>
<p>I think maybe I think these texts are so rich that their applicability is maybe not going to be something quite so simple as not smoking on Saturday. It might be more a work of appropriation like Heidegger&#8217;s discussion of fallenness or Gelassenheit. These are models that kind of come to mind, I am not sure about my hermeneutics and its political/real world implications.</p>
<p>Maybe I would say to Tucker: I personally am not committed to apply these texts one way or another. But in raising the stakes of your feminism by marrying it to Revelation, it raises the question, why stop there? Why hem in the radical critique at gender roles and not have a full blown social critique? Why does it map so neatly to corporate speak  and PC speak and that kind of utterly banal use of language? Does all this make you question this marriage of revelation and God to feminism and faux egalitarianism?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/02/27/reb-yudel-ethan-tucker-and-dan-bern/#comment-2700</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 03:00:13 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3167#comment-2700</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[So you are claiming that the pragmatic methodology presupposes a pragmatist moral epistemology - in which case who cares what you do with some old texts? Well, maybe the same reason that a Dworkin cites precedent. 

Or, maybe abandoning the language of halakhah means abandoning a form of life associated with it?

What are you suggesting instead; that texts should extract something from us, not just the other way around?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>So you are claiming that the pragmatic methodology presupposes a pragmatist moral epistemology &#8211; in which case who cares what you do with some old texts? Well, maybe the same reason that a Dworkin cites precedent. </p>
<p>Or, maybe abandoning the language of halakhah means abandoning a form of life associated with it?</p>
<p>What are you suggesting instead; that texts should extract something from us, not just the other way around?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: chakira		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/02/27/reb-yudel-ethan-tucker-and-dan-bern/#comment-2698</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[chakira]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 01:51:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3167#comment-2698</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Upon some reflection it seems to me that a latent pragmatics underlies Ethan Tucker&#039;s hermeneutics. It is a pragmatic approach which I find undervalues process in favor of preordained conclusions, much like a Bush era signing statement. In this case Tucker has taken a much commented upon (if less than fertile question) called &quot;is there an ethic outside of Halacha&quot; in its classic iteration of &quot;what would R Aharon do on a desert island? What would R Amital do?&quot; Rather than parsing multiple sources, Tucker will use his knowledge of Shu&quot;ttim to load the dice and mine for a certain conclusion which reflects preexisting values. This smacks of disingenousness  first, because Tucker is patently taking advantage of his greater facility with Shu&quot;ttim than his interlocutors to make a faux &quot;slam dunk&quot; case wrapped in a full blown jargon of authenticity. Second, because it conveniently plays upon his interlocutors&#039; lack of familiarity with a great(er) variety of texts, also a polyphonic cacophony, which scream the opposite conclusion. From Zoharic animadversions to goyyim to the Talmud&#039;s own discussion of what makes Torah something that people will see and think &quot;that is a cool way to live&quot; (Astrology) the texts go from palimpsest or metaphysics down to a very flat neo-liberal vision. That very neo-liberalism forms the crux of a second nascent criticism, perhaps more Marxist. Namely, that going to the Schechter of Bergen County and telling them that Torah does not only belong to TABC does not mean reclaiming Torah for &quot;the Jewish people.&quot; On the contrary. The message is, this is not just for one group of rich people. Even your slightly different group of rich people can get behind Torah. Now, if the Torah demands a vision of radical gender (and let&#039;s throw in racial) equality, we might ask, what demands does it then make for social egalitarianism, income inequality etc? Is the Torah only another bludgeon to be joined to feminism in extracting rents from normativity? Is Torah another closed circuit of self justifying discourse which allows us to congratulate ourselves on meeting some self imposed demands? All we know from Tucker is that Torah, like DE Shaw: &quot;do[es] not discriminate ...on the basis of race, color, religion, gender, pregnancy, national origin..., sexual orientation, marital status, disability, or any other category protected by law. Note that for us, this is more than just legal boilerplate. We are genuinely committed to these principles, which form an important part of our corporate culture, and are eager to hear from extraordinarily well qualified individuals having a wide range of backgrounds and personal characteristics.&quot;

Anyway if a pragmatic hermeneutics leads there, why not skip the extra reason called Torah and seek employment at one of the area&#039;s many fine financial and legal firms? By the way (paging Saadya Gaon) how did they manage to discern these eternal truths absent divine revelation?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Upon some reflection it seems to me that a latent pragmatics underlies Ethan Tucker&#8217;s hermeneutics. It is a pragmatic approach which I find undervalues process in favor of preordained conclusions, much like a Bush era signing statement. In this case Tucker has taken a much commented upon (if less than fertile question) called &#8220;is there an ethic outside of Halacha&#8221; in its classic iteration of &#8220;what would R Aharon do on a desert island? What would R Amital do?&#8221; Rather than parsing multiple sources, Tucker will use his knowledge of Shu&#8221;ttim to load the dice and mine for a certain conclusion which reflects preexisting values. This smacks of disingenousness  first, because Tucker is patently taking advantage of his greater facility with Shu&#8221;ttim than his interlocutors to make a faux &#8220;slam dunk&#8221; case wrapped in a full blown jargon of authenticity. Second, because it conveniently plays upon his interlocutors&#8217; lack of familiarity with a great(er) variety of texts, also a polyphonic cacophony, which scream the opposite conclusion. From Zoharic animadversions to goyyim to the Talmud&#8217;s own discussion of what makes Torah something that people will see and think &#8220;that is a cool way to live&#8221; (Astrology) the texts go from palimpsest or metaphysics down to a very flat neo-liberal vision. That very neo-liberalism forms the crux of a second nascent criticism, perhaps more Marxist. Namely, that going to the Schechter of Bergen County and telling them that Torah does not only belong to TABC does not mean reclaiming Torah for &#8220;the Jewish people.&#8221; On the contrary. The message is, this is not just for one group of rich people. Even your slightly different group of rich people can get behind Torah. Now, if the Torah demands a vision of radical gender (and let&#8217;s throw in racial) equality, we might ask, what demands does it then make for social egalitarianism, income inequality etc? Is the Torah only another bludgeon to be joined to feminism in extracting rents from normativity? Is Torah another closed circuit of self justifying discourse which allows us to congratulate ourselves on meeting some self imposed demands? All we know from Tucker is that Torah, like DE Shaw: &#8220;do[es] not discriminate &#8230;on the basis of race, color, religion, gender, pregnancy, national origin&#8230;, sexual orientation, marital status, disability, or any other category protected by law. Note that for us, this is more than just legal boilerplate. We are genuinely committed to these principles, which form an important part of our corporate culture, and are eager to hear from extraordinarily well qualified individuals having a wide range of backgrounds and personal characteristics.&#8221;</p>
<p>Anyway if a pragmatic hermeneutics leads there, why not skip the extra reason called Torah and seek employment at one of the area&#8217;s many fine financial and legal firms? By the way (paging Saadya Gaon) how did they manage to discern these eternal truths absent divine revelation?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
