<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Avi Sagi, Casualties of Worship—Reshit II	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/25/avi-sagi-casualties-of-worship%e2%80%94reshit-ii/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/25/avi-sagi-casualties-of-worship%e2%80%94reshit-ii/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 06 Nov 2010 22:42:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Tzvee		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/25/avi-sagi-casualties-of-worship%e2%80%94reshit-ii/#comment-1842</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tzvee]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2010 02:23:30 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2240#comment-1842</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Amen.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Amen.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/25/avi-sagi-casualties-of-worship%e2%80%94reshit-ii/#comment-1839</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 31 Oct 2010 23:27:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2240#comment-1839</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I offered up 4 possibilities....charediism which is in total respect of the nusach of the sidur, kabbalistic kavanot (suitably modernized or not) that changed the nusach from Ashkenaz to Sefard, and is used by balei madreigah everywhere, and an ambitious joyous  Conservative version, that adds nothing to the nusach but does eliminate piyutim and more. If you have better ideas how to speak to the millions of Jews who are leaving synagogue life, America is waiting. 

My fin de sie&#039;cle idea starts from the Kantian thesis  in his last crtique  that the closest we get to the sublime is by the apprehension of the beautiful. It need not have anything to do with the sidur or Judaism, though many a Jew from Sarah Bernhardt to Proust lived more meaningful  lives because of this ideal.  The Anglican-Catholic version from Chesterton to TS Eliott  to today&#039;s Radical Orthodoxy pumped some life into religion long after materialism was dominant. I see echoes of this Brideshead Revisited style in the yichus driven  wealthy  Orthodox families.  Reform prides itself on having aesthetically pleasing services.  For the most part I find the high- church of angels singing and an organ playing quite boring, and the Debbie Friedman low- church kumsitz style not much better. My point is that you have to put some backbone, some stulzkeit into these sad empty temples.

You have the last word.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I offered up 4 possibilities&#8230;.charediism which is in total respect of the nusach of the sidur, kabbalistic kavanot (suitably modernized or not) that changed the nusach from Ashkenaz to Sefard, and is used by balei madreigah everywhere, and an ambitious joyous  Conservative version, that adds nothing to the nusach but does eliminate piyutim and more. If you have better ideas how to speak to the millions of Jews who are leaving synagogue life, America is waiting. </p>
<p>My fin de sie&#8217;cle idea starts from the Kantian thesis  in his last crtique  that the closest we get to the sublime is by the apprehension of the beautiful. It need not have anything to do with the sidur or Judaism, though many a Jew from Sarah Bernhardt to Proust lived more meaningful  lives because of this ideal.  The Anglican-Catholic version from Chesterton to TS Eliott  to today&#8217;s Radical Orthodoxy pumped some life into religion long after materialism was dominant. I see echoes of this Brideshead Revisited style in the yichus driven  wealthy  Orthodox families.  Reform prides itself on having aesthetically pleasing services.  For the most part I find the high- church of angels singing and an organ playing quite boring, and the Debbie Friedman low- church kumsitz style not much better. My point is that you have to put some backbone, some stulzkeit into these sad empty temples.</p>
<p>You have the last word.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: tzvee		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/25/avi-sagi-casualties-of-worship%e2%80%94reshit-ii/#comment-1837</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tzvee]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 31 Oct 2010 21:06:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2240#comment-1837</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&quot;What makes some uses of prayer proper and others not?&quot; OK good, that is THE question and is amenable to answer once you agree on what you mean by &quot;jewish prayer&quot;. if you start from the premise that the siddur defines jewish prayer, then i can tell you what is in it and we can extrapolate from there the basic rules that govern its logic and canonical integrity. (and that is what i am doing in part in my current book project.) if you start from another mode of defining &quot;jewish prayer&quot; then it also behooves you to spell out some concrete brackets of logic and canon and it is desirable that you explain why you don&#039;t choose the siddur-model.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&#8220;What makes some uses of prayer proper and others not?&#8221; OK good, that is THE question and is amenable to answer once you agree on what you mean by &#8220;jewish prayer&#8221;. if you start from the premise that the siddur defines jewish prayer, then i can tell you what is in it and we can extrapolate from there the basic rules that govern its logic and canonical integrity. (and that is what i am doing in part in my current book project.) if you start from another mode of defining &#8220;jewish prayer&#8221; then it also behooves you to spell out some concrete brackets of logic and canon and it is desirable that you explain why you don&#8217;t choose the siddur-model.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/25/avi-sagi-casualties-of-worship%e2%80%94reshit-ii/#comment-1818</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2010 23:17:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2240#comment-1818</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Tzvee... I&#039;m not proposing a change in the nusach of tefila, nor is Sagi. We&#039;re talking about the correct kavanot or experiences that one should have during prayer, since ex hypothesi both petitionary and laudatory prayers are no longer in place. I was just throwing out what I consider plausible alternatives. If you look back at the history of kabbalah, all sorts of kavanot were quasi sexualized, for example in the work of the Ari z&quot;l. Many of mental yichudim use an accepted nusach attempt to join  the feminine and masculine aspects of the Godhead.  My larger point is that there is no essence to prayer, and there is no one way of using prayer in a post religious time that ought to be privileged. Most of the people Sagi mentions were never involved in the liturgical cycle, and now they are going to be used as poskim on how and with what ideations we ought to pray. C’mon. 

On a different topic, Dr. Brill has spoken at length on the relationship between evangelical styles and developments in Jewish congregational practices. I came across a Kol Nidre service that has the feel of a revivalist meeting. It combines different styles of music, with traditional liturgy under the leadership of a dramatic rabbi. My association was with the show Garrison Keillor and his Lake Woebegon ensemble put on at Ravinia. Like Bnei Jeshurin in NY, this combination of traditional nusach,  Carlebach songs, smooth jazz, mixed with a little Country and Western and a little foot stomping makes for an emotionally satisfying evening. (http://www.jewishjournal.com/kol_nidre.) Add in some leftist activism and it’s a winning formula that is scalable. Listen to the Rabbi Naomi Levy’s  sermon at 1:20 and read her write up in this week’s Forward Top Fifty. (http://forward.com/forward-50/ ) This woman has had her share of existential angst. Doesn’t mean that the entire congregation  must take existential leaps three times a day.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Tzvee&#8230; I&#8217;m not proposing a change in the nusach of tefila, nor is Sagi. We&#8217;re talking about the correct kavanot or experiences that one should have during prayer, since ex hypothesi both petitionary and laudatory prayers are no longer in place. I was just throwing out what I consider plausible alternatives. If you look back at the history of kabbalah, all sorts of kavanot were quasi sexualized, for example in the work of the Ari z&#8221;l. Many of mental yichudim use an accepted nusach attempt to join  the feminine and masculine aspects of the Godhead.  My larger point is that there is no essence to prayer, and there is no one way of using prayer in a post religious time that ought to be privileged. Most of the people Sagi mentions were never involved in the liturgical cycle, and now they are going to be used as poskim on how and with what ideations we ought to pray. C’mon. </p>
<p>On a different topic, Dr. Brill has spoken at length on the relationship between evangelical styles and developments in Jewish congregational practices. I came across a Kol Nidre service that has the feel of a revivalist meeting. It combines different styles of music, with traditional liturgy under the leadership of a dramatic rabbi. My association was with the show Garrison Keillor and his Lake Woebegon ensemble put on at Ravinia. Like Bnei Jeshurin in NY, this combination of traditional nusach,  Carlebach songs, smooth jazz, mixed with a little Country and Western and a little foot stomping makes for an emotionally satisfying evening. (<a href="http://www.jewishjournal.com/kol_nidre" rel="nofollow ugc">http://www.jewishjournal.com/kol_nidre</a>.) Add in some leftist activism and it’s a winning formula that is scalable. Listen to the Rabbi Naomi Levy’s  sermon at 1:20 and read her write up in this week’s Forward Top Fifty. (<a href="http://forward.com/forward-50/" rel="nofollow ugc">http://forward.com/forward-50/</a> ) This woman has had her share of existential angst. Doesn’t mean that the entire congregation  must take existential leaps three times a day.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: tzvee		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/25/avi-sagi-casualties-of-worship%e2%80%94reshit-ii/#comment-1816</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tzvee]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2010 15:12:37 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2240#comment-1816</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&quot;I also want to know why prayer can’t be used to deepen our sexual consciousness? There is an abundance of sexual imagery in the Zoharic literature waiting to be redeemed. ...What makes some uses of prayer proper and others not?&quot;

Religion functions according to knowable historical and social mechanisms. Regarding the questions you ask about sexuality and mystical imagery -- it is fair to say that the synagogue, i.e. the mechanism that govern Jewish prayer, has excluded over the millenia most mystical and sexual material from what it deems acceptable. That&#039;s on the surface - just read the (Orthodox) prayer book to see what is not there. Now if you propose to change that, consider how the services and the rabbis who govern them are resistant to even the smallest change, at least in the Orthodox instance. No chance a major shift as you suggest will occur in their institutionalized prayer. If you are satisfied to take your quest to Reconstructionist, Reform or even Conservatives, you have a better chance of an open reception and of finding some Jews with authority or influence who will consider changes that you wish to see &quot;proper&quot;. But why is it important to you to have &quot;prayer&quot; accomodate your needs for mystical and sexual expression? And likewise, we ought to ask Sagi, why is it legitimate to ask literature to speak about prayer? Neither the literary nor the religious expect prayer to be confused with literature.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&#8220;I also want to know why prayer can’t be used to deepen our sexual consciousness? There is an abundance of sexual imagery in the Zoharic literature waiting to be redeemed. &#8230;What makes some uses of prayer proper and others not?&#8221;</p>
<p>Religion functions according to knowable historical and social mechanisms. Regarding the questions you ask about sexuality and mystical imagery &#8212; it is fair to say that the synagogue, i.e. the mechanism that govern Jewish prayer, has excluded over the millenia most mystical and sexual material from what it deems acceptable. That&#8217;s on the surface &#8211; just read the (Orthodox) prayer book to see what is not there. Now if you propose to change that, consider how the services and the rabbis who govern them are resistant to even the smallest change, at least in the Orthodox instance. No chance a major shift as you suggest will occur in their institutionalized prayer. If you are satisfied to take your quest to Reconstructionist, Reform or even Conservatives, you have a better chance of an open reception and of finding some Jews with authority or influence who will consider changes that you wish to see &#8220;proper&#8221;. But why is it important to you to have &#8220;prayer&#8221; accomodate your needs for mystical and sexual expression? And likewise, we ought to ask Sagi, why is it legitimate to ask literature to speak about prayer? Neither the literary nor the religious expect prayer to be confused with literature.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/25/avi-sagi-casualties-of-worship%e2%80%94reshit-ii/#comment-1812</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 27 Oct 2010 20:50:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2240#comment-1812</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Why must a pragmatic question like how are we now going to use prayer be given an essentialist response? For Sagi, the essence of tefila according to X is Y, only to be followed by according to A it’s B, and so on, as we take this  little trip through the humanities. What goes on in our minds during actual prayer services both consciously and pre-consciously  is an empirical issue, and certainly not one thing. Minds wander in the strangest ways. Are these fragments related to prayer? How does Sagi know that in our post religious world we should use prayer as a sort of self reflexive medicated psychotherapy? The same goes for self expression and all the many other essences of prayer. How do we go from the purported fact that we are not  making real contact with the transcendental to everyone must now  use prayer  according to its essence, though no two people agree what this essence is?

All this talk of a phenomenological reconstruction is faced with the actual liturgy we use. We never say “My father, my king…” or “I sinned, I rebelled…” or “My subjective- self object  I call God, onto whom I project forever and ever.” It’s always the impersonal collective ‘we’. On Sagi’s views why do we need a tzibur? Simone Weill didn’t need a minyan , nor did Rosenzweig.

The 19th century saw many attempts at coming to terms emotionally with the feeling that there is no God.  The strongest response was the use of beauty and its sublime qualities as a substitute. What is common to  late- romanticism and early modernism is this almost ‘religious’ devotion to style and art. I want to know why prayer can’t be used for such aesthetic purposes? I also want to know why prayer can’t be used to deepen our sexual consciousness? There is an abundance of sexual imagery in the Zoharic literature waiting to be redeemed. And then there is always the old charedi standby, taking up a pre-modern attitude as a  protest against modernism and all the posts and post-posts .  What makes some uses of prayer proper and others not?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Why must a pragmatic question like how are we now going to use prayer be given an essentialist response? For Sagi, the essence of tefila according to X is Y, only to be followed by according to A it’s B, and so on, as we take this  little trip through the humanities. What goes on in our minds during actual prayer services both consciously and pre-consciously  is an empirical issue, and certainly not one thing. Minds wander in the strangest ways. Are these fragments related to prayer? How does Sagi know that in our post religious world we should use prayer as a sort of self reflexive medicated psychotherapy? The same goes for self expression and all the many other essences of prayer. How do we go from the purported fact that we are not  making real contact with the transcendental to everyone must now  use prayer  according to its essence, though no two people agree what this essence is?</p>
<p>All this talk of a phenomenological reconstruction is faced with the actual liturgy we use. We never say “My father, my king…” or “I sinned, I rebelled…” or “My subjective- self object  I call God, onto whom I project forever and ever.” It’s always the impersonal collective ‘we’. On Sagi’s views why do we need a tzibur? Simone Weill didn’t need a minyan , nor did Rosenzweig.</p>
<p>The 19th century saw many attempts at coming to terms emotionally with the feeling that there is no God.  The strongest response was the use of beauty and its sublime qualities as a substitute. What is common to  late- romanticism and early modernism is this almost ‘religious’ devotion to style and art. I want to know why prayer can’t be used for such aesthetic purposes? I also want to know why prayer can’t be used to deepen our sexual consciousness? There is an abundance of sexual imagery in the Zoharic literature waiting to be redeemed. And then there is always the old charedi standby, taking up a pre-modern attitude as a  protest against modernism and all the posts and post-posts .  What makes some uses of prayer proper and others not?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Shai Secunda		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/25/avi-sagi-casualties-of-worship%e2%80%94reshit-ii/#comment-1809</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shai Secunda]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2010 09:15:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2240#comment-1809</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The  shift in understanding Amichai strikes a chord with me.  In conversations I have had with (non-specialist) friends of my generation  (born during the 1970s) - especially in Israel, I have found that people are less likely to read Amichai as radically breaking with tradition. For myself, I have been particularly bewildered with the (once) standard consensus that  Amichai was a religious iconoclast who through his subversions completely detached himself from Judaism.   At an Amichai conference at Yale a few years ago, the only person who said things that really resonated with my reading of the poet was Leon Wiselter.  He spoke (and has written) about Amichai, especially in his final work, as creating a humanist midrashic structure and one which is not only a critique of religion. When I mentioned to some of the specialists at a dinner party after the session that as an Orthodox Jew I have found myself close to tears when reading &quot;Patuah Sagur Patuah,&quot; they did not know what I was talking about.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The  shift in understanding Amichai strikes a chord with me.  In conversations I have had with (non-specialist) friends of my generation  (born during the 1970s) &#8211; especially in Israel, I have found that people are less likely to read Amichai as radically breaking with tradition. For myself, I have been particularly bewildered with the (once) standard consensus that  Amichai was a religious iconoclast who through his subversions completely detached himself from Judaism.   At an Amichai conference at Yale a few years ago, the only person who said things that really resonated with my reading of the poet was Leon Wiselter.  He spoke (and has written) about Amichai, especially in his final work, as creating a humanist midrashic structure and one which is not only a critique of religion. When I mentioned to some of the specialists at a dinner party after the session that as an Orthodox Jew I have found myself close to tears when reading &#8220;Patuah Sagur Patuah,&#8221; they did not know what I was talking about.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/25/avi-sagi-casualties-of-worship%e2%80%94reshit-ii/#comment-1807</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2010 03:02:42 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2240#comment-1807</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I think both and more. It is an entire book of several diverse chapters condensed in an article. His discussion of prayer as self-expression seems to be his description, the poetry section is closing a gap, the treating prayer as an action is constructive philosophy of relgion.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think both and more. It is an entire book of several diverse chapters condensed in an article. His discussion of prayer as self-expression seems to be his description, the poetry section is closing a gap, the treating prayer as an action is constructive philosophy of relgion.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Jon		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/25/avi-sagi-casualties-of-worship%e2%80%94reshit-ii/#comment-1806</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jon]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2010 02:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2240#comment-1806</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This might not be particularly relevant, but do you think Sagi is describing what prayer is, or what prayer could be in the event of &quot;the death of God&quot;? That is to say, is he expressing his own views or trying to create common ground?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This might not be particularly relevant, but do you think Sagi is describing what prayer is, or what prayer could be in the event of &#8220;the death of God&#8221;? That is to say, is he expressing his own views or trying to create common ground?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
