<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Rabbi Immanuel Jakobovits and Christiaan Barnard	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2013 23:30:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: David Z		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7324</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[David Z]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2013 23:30:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5736#comment-7324</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7023&quot;&gt;noam stadlan&lt;/a&gt;.

I read “this would be set aside in cases where competent medical opinion deems any prospects of resuscitation, however remote, at all” not as referring to the heart, but to the &quot;living person&quot; as defined by Barnard (i.e. the brain).  So yes, if you can&#039;t transplant a heart that has stopped beating, heart transplants would not be an option in Judaism.  But I may just be reading it all wrong.
Does Jewish tradition really consider it murder when you try to save someone&#039;s life in a risky procedure but end up hastening his death???]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7023">noam stadlan</a>.</p>
<p>I read “this would be set aside in cases where competent medical opinion deems any prospects of resuscitation, however remote, at all” not as referring to the heart, but to the &#8220;living person&#8221; as defined by Barnard (i.e. the brain).  So yes, if you can&#8217;t transplant a heart that has stopped beating, heart transplants would not be an option in Judaism.  But I may just be reading it all wrong.<br />
Does Jewish tradition really consider it murder when you try to save someone&#8217;s life in a risky procedure but end up hastening his death???</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7063</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2012 07:43:51 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5736#comment-7063</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7043&quot;&gt;Alan Brill&lt;/a&gt;.

I imagine it has something to do with personal experience. Barnard as a doctor seeing many dying patients, and RIJ performing pastoral duties during his stints as a communal rabbi.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7043">Alan Brill</a>.</p>
<p>I imagine it has something to do with personal experience. Barnard as a doctor seeing many dying patients, and RIJ performing pastoral duties during his stints as a communal rabbi.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7043</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Nov 2012 12:21:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5736#comment-7043</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7042&quot;&gt;AS&lt;/a&gt;.

AS- so how do you read this closeness of terms between RIJ and Barnard?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7042">AS</a>.</p>
<p>AS- so how do you read this closeness of terms between RIJ and Barnard?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7042</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Nov 2012 10:34:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5736#comment-7042</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I don&#039;t want to get back into the debates I&#039;ve had on the topic. Instead it is worth pointing out that from the perspective of day-to-day medical practice/clinical bioethics/pastoral counseling the issues of futility, refusal and withdrawal of care is paramount, while the definition of death is a much rarer concern.

So while everyone seems to be aware of the major positions on brain death and organ donation, people are at a loss when it comes to the decisions that most of us will need to face at one time or another for ourselves or family members. It&#039;s not as sexy as brain death and organ donation, but it is much more relevant. As is the case in society generally, what is sorely lacking is a Jewish discourse on the &quot;good death&quot; and its implications for end of life care.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I don&#8217;t want to get back into the debates I&#8217;ve had on the topic. Instead it is worth pointing out that from the perspective of day-to-day medical practice/clinical bioethics/pastoral counseling the issues of futility, refusal and withdrawal of care is paramount, while the definition of death is a much rarer concern.</p>
<p>So while everyone seems to be aware of the major positions on brain death and organ donation, people are at a loss when it comes to the decisions that most of us will need to face at one time or another for ourselves or family members. It&#8217;s not as sexy as brain death and organ donation, but it is much more relevant. As is the case in society generally, what is sorely lacking is a Jewish discourse on the &#8220;good death&#8221; and its implications for end of life care.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: noam stadlan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7038</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[noam stadlan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Nov 2012 03:32:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5736#comment-7038</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Rav Tendler is echoing the position of Rav Moshe Feinstein at the time, who also described it as double murder.  However, Dr. Fred Rosner, writing in 1970, stated that he had a personal interview with Rav Moshe and that if the donor was &quot;absolutely and positively dead by all medical and Jewish legal criteria, then no murder of the donor would be involved and the removal of his heart or other organ to save another human life would be permitted.&quot;  Furthermore, &quot;when medical science will have progressed to the point where cardiac transplantation becomes an accepted therapeutic procedure..then the recipient would no longer be considered murdered.&quot;    This also accords with Rav Daniel Reifman&#039;s reading of Rav Moshe&#039;s teshuvot(available on the RCA blog). 

I think that the context of the opinions is very important.  For over 10 years the medical literature had been describing patients with an absent neurological exam, absent blood flow to the brain, and silent EEG&#039;s(prior to CT and MRI, these were the main options for obtaining data on brain function and anatomy while the patient was alive).  In addition, pathology reports on these patients were reporting widespread liquifactive necrosis(brains turning to mush).  These patients could be considered dead on two counts- loss of neurological function, and loss of circulation to the only organ that counted- the brain.  In addition, patients in this situation did not survive for very long(hours to days).  So if they weren&#039;t totally dead they were irreversibly very close to dead(this inevitability was used by some as being the same as dead). This was the mindset that CB and the medical establishment were coming from.

RIJ&#039;s starting point was the classic halachic definition of death(and the classic definition in society as well)- cessation of respiration and circulation(Rav Yehuda Aryeh d&#039;Modena&#039;s shita not being a commonly cited starting point).  He recognizes that they have to be modified to some extent to cover modern medical achievements(stating that if the person can be resuscitated then the classic definitions dont apply), but it seems to me that the halachic sources had not been developed to fully address all that technology could offer.  Similar to the secular medicolegal world, it took time and thinking to develop the  basis for recognizing brain death as a halachically valid definition of death (and I would note that R. JD Bleich&#039;s concept of vital motion was similarly absent early in the conversation until he introduced it.). (Dr. Rosner reviews a number of opinions from the 1960&#039;s and it seems that they are all trying to find precedents to apply- similar to RIJ).   It is to his credit that RIJ acknolwedged that modifications were necessary.  I think Michael&#039;s point is that if RIJ was familiar with the current discussions and scientific data, he would concur with R. Tendler or R. Steinberg.
I apologize for being lengthy but one note regarding the vagueness.  The inability to be specific can cast doubt on the unequivocal statement.  For example, one can state that death is the cessation of vital motion.  However, if one cannot give an exact definition of vital motion, nor give specifics as to how it&#039;s presence or absence can be ascertained, the adequacy of the definition can be questioned.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rav Tendler is echoing the position of Rav Moshe Feinstein at the time, who also described it as double murder.  However, Dr. Fred Rosner, writing in 1970, stated that he had a personal interview with Rav Moshe and that if the donor was &#8220;absolutely and positively dead by all medical and Jewish legal criteria, then no murder of the donor would be involved and the removal of his heart or other organ to save another human life would be permitted.&#8221;  Furthermore, &#8220;when medical science will have progressed to the point where cardiac transplantation becomes an accepted therapeutic procedure..then the recipient would no longer be considered murdered.&#8221;    This also accords with Rav Daniel Reifman&#8217;s reading of Rav Moshe&#8217;s teshuvot(available on the RCA blog). </p>
<p>I think that the context of the opinions is very important.  For over 10 years the medical literature had been describing patients with an absent neurological exam, absent blood flow to the brain, and silent EEG&#8217;s(prior to CT and MRI, these were the main options for obtaining data on brain function and anatomy while the patient was alive).  In addition, pathology reports on these patients were reporting widespread liquifactive necrosis(brains turning to mush).  These patients could be considered dead on two counts- loss of neurological function, and loss of circulation to the only organ that counted- the brain.  In addition, patients in this situation did not survive for very long(hours to days).  So if they weren&#8217;t totally dead they were irreversibly very close to dead(this inevitability was used by some as being the same as dead). This was the mindset that CB and the medical establishment were coming from.</p>
<p>RIJ&#8217;s starting point was the classic halachic definition of death(and the classic definition in society as well)- cessation of respiration and circulation(Rav Yehuda Aryeh d&#8217;Modena&#8217;s shita not being a commonly cited starting point).  He recognizes that they have to be modified to some extent to cover modern medical achievements(stating that if the person can be resuscitated then the classic definitions dont apply), but it seems to me that the halachic sources had not been developed to fully address all that technology could offer.  Similar to the secular medicolegal world, it took time and thinking to develop the  basis for recognizing brain death as a halachically valid definition of death (and I would note that R. JD Bleich&#8217;s concept of vital motion was similarly absent early in the conversation until he introduced it.). (Dr. Rosner reviews a number of opinions from the 1960&#8217;s and it seems that they are all trying to find precedents to apply- similar to RIJ).   It is to his credit that RIJ acknolwedged that modifications were necessary.  I think Michael&#8217;s point is that if RIJ was familiar with the current discussions and scientific data, he would concur with R. Tendler or R. Steinberg.<br />
I apologize for being lengthy but one note regarding the vagueness.  The inability to be specific can cast doubt on the unequivocal statement.  For example, one can state that death is the cessation of vital motion.  However, if one cannot give an exact definition of vital motion, nor give specifics as to how it&#8217;s presence or absence can be ascertained, the adequacy of the definition can be questioned.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7036</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Nov 2012 01:45:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5736#comment-7036</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7035&quot;&gt;Michael Feldstein&lt;/a&gt;.

Or you can say that this looks too much like Barnard and not enough like Yoma to count. Also RIJ was trying to produce an ethic not a halakhah. In addition, his guidance from Dayan Weiss was more about not prolonging a life and avoiding organ transplants.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7035">Michael Feldstein</a>.</p>
<p>Or you can say that this looks too much like Barnard and not enough like Yoma to count. Also RIJ was trying to produce an ethic not a halakhah. In addition, his guidance from Dayan Weiss was more about not prolonging a life and avoiding organ transplants.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Michael Feldstein		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7035</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Michael Feldstein]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Nov 2012 00:41:03 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5736#comment-7035</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I think what makes it interesting is that some of the same issues that were being debated more than 40 years ago are still being debated now.  The big difference, in my opinion, is that today we have much more sophisticated medical equipment and tests to accurately determine brain stem function and respiration, and that if RIJ were alive today he would (like Rabbi Tendler) believe that this information conclusively prove that brain stem death is halachic death.  I think RIJ wanted to believe this at the time, but the medical sophistication about brain stem death simply did not exist -- and prevented him from articulating this position clearly.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think what makes it interesting is that some of the same issues that were being debated more than 40 years ago are still being debated now.  The big difference, in my opinion, is that today we have much more sophisticated medical equipment and tests to accurately determine brain stem function and respiration, and that if RIJ were alive today he would (like Rabbi Tendler) believe that this information conclusively prove that brain stem death is halachic death.  I think RIJ wanted to believe this at the time, but the medical sophistication about brain stem death simply did not exist &#8212; and prevented him from articulating this position clearly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7034</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Nov 2012 00:24:24 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5736#comment-7034</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7033&quot;&gt;Michael Feldstein&lt;/a&gt;.

Rabbi Tendler wrote in 1968 (Tradition, Vol.9, No. 4), accusing Dr. Christian Barnard of committing double murder.
In 1990, he explained his reasoning as due to the fact that at the time &quot;Barnard was not only performing an experimental operation which hastened the death of his recipients, but also because he was dealing with donors who were cerebrally dead as opposed to brain dead. Cerebral death is not death according to Jewish law.&quot;

Michael, What makes this interesting? And do you think it changes the time of death debate in any way?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7033">Michael Feldstein</a>.</p>
<p>Rabbi Tendler wrote in 1968 (Tradition, Vol.9, No. 4), accusing Dr. Christian Barnard of committing double murder.<br />
In 1990, he explained his reasoning as due to the fact that at the time &#8220;Barnard was not only performing an experimental operation which hastened the death of his recipients, but also because he was dealing with donors who were cerebrally dead as opposed to brain dead. Cerebral death is not death according to Jewish law.&#8221;</p>
<p>Michael, What makes this interesting? And do you think it changes the time of death debate in any way?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Michael Feldstein		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7033</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Michael Feldstein]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Nov 2012 00:15:42 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5736#comment-7033</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This was REALLY interesting!  Thanks for finding it and posting it.  Do you know if Rabbi Tendler made any statements about the first heart transplant in 1967 (he was certainly teaching at YU at the time).]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This was REALLY interesting!  Thanks for finding it and posting it.  Do you know if Rabbi Tendler made any statements about the first heart transplant in 1967 (he was certainly teaching at YU at the time).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: zjb		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7029</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[zjb]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Nov 2012 17:40:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5736#comment-7029</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Reblogged this on &lt;a href=&quot;http://jewishphilosophyplace.wordpress.com/2012/11/14/4033/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;jewish philosophy place&lt;/a&gt; and commented: 
Add your thoughts here... (optional)]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Reblogged this on <a href="http://jewishphilosophyplace.wordpress.com/2012/11/14/4033/" rel="nofollow">jewish philosophy place</a> and commented:<br />
Add your thoughts here&#8230; (optional)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7028</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Nov 2012 17:28:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5736#comment-7028</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[If the first type of vagueness is due to a difficulty in the ostensive meaning.Your second form, in this case, is due to the lacuna of the text or the gap between the Talmud and current medicine.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If the first type of vagueness is due to a difficulty in the ostensive meaning.Your second form, in this case, is due to the lacuna of the text or the gap between the Talmud and current medicine.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Noam Stadlan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7027</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Noam Stadlan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Nov 2012 17:18:14 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5736#comment-7027</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7024&quot;&gt;Alan Brill&lt;/a&gt;.

I agree that in his practice CB was not stringent in his criteria for death and was a quality of life person(see description of the second heart transplant by Raymond Hoffenberg in BMJ 2001 1478-80). 

RIJ allows care to be withheld in patients who are alive according to all opinions.  I am not sure what support he obtains or needs from Rav Weiss on this point.  
To be more precise, there are at least two types of &#039;vagueness&#039; that frequently appear in many definitions of death.  One is illustrated by the quotes from RIJ&#039;s position, where a specific characteristic of life is not clearly identified.  The second type is where a clear and unequivocal statement is made, but the ramifications of the statement are not systemstically addressed- and therefore there is uncertainty in the application.  For example, circulation is identified as the vital characteristic of human life, but the role of artificial hearts or transplants are not addressed.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7024">Alan Brill</a>.</p>
<p>I agree that in his practice CB was not stringent in his criteria for death and was a quality of life person(see description of the second heart transplant by Raymond Hoffenberg in BMJ 2001 1478-80). </p>
<p>RIJ allows care to be withheld in patients who are alive according to all opinions.  I am not sure what support he obtains or needs from Rav Weiss on this point.<br />
To be more precise, there are at least two types of &#8216;vagueness&#8217; that frequently appear in many definitions of death.  One is illustrated by the quotes from RIJ&#8217;s position, where a specific characteristic of life is not clearly identified.  The second type is where a clear and unequivocal statement is made, but the ramifications of the statement are not systemstically addressed- and therefore there is uncertainty in the application.  For example, circulation is identified as the vital characteristic of human life, but the role of artificial hearts or transplants are not addressed.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7024</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Nov 2012 03:24:48 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5736#comment-7024</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7023&quot;&gt;noam stadlan&lt;/a&gt;.

I think that this is the article by Troug and Miller to which you refer. 
http://www.thehastingscenter.org/Publications/HCR/Detail.aspx?id=2822

To use your terminology of vagueness, RIJ was vague enough to be able to combine a reliance of Dayan Weiss (to whom RIJ turned for halakhic guidance) who rejected brain death with allowing passive euthanasia by only considering spontaneous respiration.

I read Barnard less as utilitarian and more as quality of life- similar to Ronald M Green. I also think that he would be, and was in practice, even more lenient than brain death. 

Update- [a 2006 account of the surgery based on the testimony of Marius Barnard (the brother of head surgeon Christiaan Barnard and one of only three witnesses to the excision of donor Denise Darvall’s heart) reveals that the surgical team debated whether or not to wait for the Darvall’s heart to stop beating of its own accord (they did not), but suggests that they were not similarly concerned by Darvall’s continued “labored breathing”; see Donald McRae, Every Second Counts: The Race to Transplant the First Human Heart (New York: G. P. Putnam’s Sons, 2006), pp. 191-2.  See also the account of Olivia Rose-Innes, daughter of Dr. Peter Rose-Innes, the neurosurgeon charged with diagnosing Darvall’s condition, who does not mention cessation of respiration as a necessary criterion for establishing brain death]]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/11/12/rabbi-immanuel-jakobovits-and-christiaan-barnard/#comment-7023">noam stadlan</a>.</p>
<p>I think that this is the article by Troug and Miller to which you refer.<br />
<a href="http://www.thehastingscenter.org/Publications/HCR/Detail.aspx?id=2822" rel="nofollow ugc">http://www.thehastingscenter.org/Publications/HCR/Detail.aspx?id=2822</a></p>
<p>To use your terminology of vagueness, RIJ was vague enough to be able to combine a reliance of Dayan Weiss (to whom RIJ turned for halakhic guidance) who rejected brain death with allowing passive euthanasia by only considering spontaneous respiration.</p>
<p>I read Barnard less as utilitarian and more as quality of life- similar to Ronald M Green. I also think that he would be, and was in practice, even more lenient than brain death. </p>
<p>Update- [a 2006 account of the surgery based on the testimony of Marius Barnard (the brother of head surgeon Christiaan Barnard and one of only three witnesses to the excision of donor Denise Darvall’s heart) reveals that the surgical team debated whether or not to wait for the Darvall’s heart to stop beating of its own accord (they did not), but suggests that they were not similarly concerned by Darvall’s continued “labored breathing”; see Donald McRae, Every Second Counts: The Race to Transplant the First Human Heart (New York: G. P. Putnam’s Sons, 2006), pp. 191-2.  See also the account of Olivia Rose-Innes, daughter of Dr. Peter Rose-Innes, the neurosurgeon charged with diagnosing Darvall’s condition, who does not mention cessation of respiration as a necessary criterion for establishing brain death]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
