<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Gadamer on Orthodoxy: Tradition as self-identity	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/09/gadamer-on-orthodoxy-tradition-as-self-identity/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/09/gadamer-on-orthodoxy-tradition-as-self-identity/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2009 23:43:52 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: chakira		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/09/gadamer-on-orthodoxy-tradition-as-self-identity/#comment-68</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[chakira]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2009 23:43:52 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=144#comment-68</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Gadamer is becoming a sort of red herring in this discussion. Gadamer believes what he does about tradition because he argues for tradition as a sort of reference point in anything we are going to understand, in order to get around the problem of performances vs originals. He does this by focusing on aesthetic appearance (reception aesthetics is really prefigured here) rather than Kant&#039;s product aesthetics (and anthropological ideal reception) as given in the third critique. The way he sidesteps Kant relies heavily on Heidegger, but Gadamer has a kind of twist, where understanding becomes the basic comportment of Dasein in the world. So we are refocusing on our activity as worlded understanders, rather than deworlded sort of evacuated aesthetes as Kant has (if you want, Agamben has a great critique of this anthropological type in Man without Qualities). Anyway the point is not to detach the art from the world, or the person from the world. This worldedness, or intersubjective sphere where I am sort of stuck, as Hegel could have told me, is now seen as tradition. So aesthetic appearance ends up being PLAYED (key term) against and with reference to tradition. In some sense, this understanding Dasein is a playing Dasein, one who plays the interplay of tradition and the new aesthetic appearance. So tradition is not closed, like playing with a bouncy ball, seemingly  anything can happen (at least with reference to the bouncy ball happenings, the ball will not turn into a squid, sorry to disappoint the children).
Why did I rehash this? Because I think people like Sagi are forgetting the key terms in MH which undergird this architectonic system. If you take the upshot of the play and tradition without the sort of assumption of Dasein, Heidegger hermeneutics and a refocusing on intrinsic question of Being, you sort of have an open tradition. That&#039;s great for people who want to be Modern Orthodox, but for those keeping score at home, it would not be Gadamer. Pulling just one thread from the vast Gadamarian tapestry, we see for example that Gadamer believes understanding is inevitable. Compare this to Sagi&#039;s pictures of rupture with and return to tradition. There is an entire step missing in Gadamer because you do not rupture with tradition, since you are a hermeneutical being, and thus always already understanding. So where would this rupture come from? If I say that Moshe Rabbeinu was a night club owner, I am already playing off the tradition, I am not leaving it somehow and returning when I admit that he actually led the Jews through the desert for forty years. Getting to the final question Sagi poses about horizons, there is no need for a family resemblance, there is just one tradition. Anyway I think we can say that Sagi does not equal Gadamer without getting into the problems with the latter which I may have inadvertently pointed out in this comment.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Gadamer is becoming a sort of red herring in this discussion. Gadamer believes what he does about tradition because he argues for tradition as a sort of reference point in anything we are going to understand, in order to get around the problem of performances vs originals. He does this by focusing on aesthetic appearance (reception aesthetics is really prefigured here) rather than Kant&#8217;s product aesthetics (and anthropological ideal reception) as given in the third critique. The way he sidesteps Kant relies heavily on Heidegger, but Gadamer has a kind of twist, where understanding becomes the basic comportment of Dasein in the world. So we are refocusing on our activity as worlded understanders, rather than deworlded sort of evacuated aesthetes as Kant has (if you want, Agamben has a great critique of this anthropological type in Man without Qualities). Anyway the point is not to detach the art from the world, or the person from the world. This worldedness, or intersubjective sphere where I am sort of stuck, as Hegel could have told me, is now seen as tradition. So aesthetic appearance ends up being PLAYED (key term) against and with reference to tradition. In some sense, this understanding Dasein is a playing Dasein, one who plays the interplay of tradition and the new aesthetic appearance. So tradition is not closed, like playing with a bouncy ball, seemingly  anything can happen (at least with reference to the bouncy ball happenings, the ball will not turn into a squid, sorry to disappoint the children).<br />
Why did I rehash this? Because I think people like Sagi are forgetting the key terms in MH which undergird this architectonic system. If you take the upshot of the play and tradition without the sort of assumption of Dasein, Heidegger hermeneutics and a refocusing on intrinsic question of Being, you sort of have an open tradition. That&#8217;s great for people who want to be Modern Orthodox, but for those keeping score at home, it would not be Gadamer. Pulling just one thread from the vast Gadamarian tapestry, we see for example that Gadamer believes understanding is inevitable. Compare this to Sagi&#8217;s pictures of rupture with and return to tradition. There is an entire step missing in Gadamer because you do not rupture with tradition, since you are a hermeneutical being, and thus always already understanding. So where would this rupture come from? If I say that Moshe Rabbeinu was a night club owner, I am already playing off the tradition, I am not leaving it somehow and returning when I admit that he actually led the Jews through the desert for forty years. Getting to the final question Sagi poses about horizons, there is no need for a family resemblance, there is just one tradition. Anyway I think we can say that Sagi does not equal Gadamer without getting into the problems with the latter which I may have inadvertently pointed out in this comment.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/09/gadamer-on-orthodoxy-tradition-as-self-identity/#comment-65</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2009 19:11:33 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=144#comment-65</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I think there are many issues here and this may not be a test case.
The Jofa case has the fact that it was one of the battle lines in the culture wars, so they could not have historical blindness. These who created supply side halkhah or libertarian halkhah saw themselves as the tradtion.
Second, they are caught up in the liberal side of the conservative-liberal divide and based it on the supersessionalism of liberal 1960&#039;s positions.
Third, as a more general comment. Much of Jewish studies on traditional texts is still in the retrival through philology mode of the 1860&#039;s.
Fourth, the community does not read theory- as Steven I. pointed out in a newspaper article - he found the feminist books never taken out from the library. 
Finally, to your question- even the historicism of Dilthy has not really been absorbed by the community - let alone the openess of later thinkers.

Andrew Louth- a very traditional Catholic who wishes to reclaim the neoplatonic mystical tradition offers some worthwhile thoughts on the reclaiming hte past. 
While I devoured Louth  in my studies on mysticism- the immediate connection is that Wordpress offered these posts to look at on this post.
Read the Louth and get back to the discussion here.
 http://avowofconversation.wordpress.com/2008/04/25/louth-on-gadamer-i/

http://avowofconversation.wordpress.com/2008/04/27/louth-on-gadamer-ii/]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think there are many issues here and this may not be a test case.<br />
The Jofa case has the fact that it was one of the battle lines in the culture wars, so they could not have historical blindness. These who created supply side halkhah or libertarian halkhah saw themselves as the tradtion.<br />
Second, they are caught up in the liberal side of the conservative-liberal divide and based it on the supersessionalism of liberal 1960&#8217;s positions.<br />
Third, as a more general comment. Much of Jewish studies on traditional texts is still in the retrival through philology mode of the 1860&#8217;s.<br />
Fourth, the community does not read theory- as Steven I. pointed out in a newspaper article &#8211; he found the feminist books never taken out from the library.<br />
Finally, to your question- even the historicism of Dilthy has not really been absorbed by the community &#8211; let alone the openess of later thinkers.</p>
<p>Andrew Louth- a very traditional Catholic who wishes to reclaim the neoplatonic mystical tradition offers some worthwhile thoughts on the reclaiming hte past.<br />
While I devoured Louth  in my studies on mysticism- the immediate connection is that WordPress offered these posts to look at on this post.<br />
Read the Louth and get back to the discussion here.<br />
 <a href="http://avowofconversation.wordpress.com/2008/04/25/louth-on-gadamer-i/" rel="nofollow ugc">http://avowofconversation.wordpress.com/2008/04/25/louth-on-gadamer-i/</a></p>
<p><a href="http://avowofconversation.wordpress.com/2008/04/27/louth-on-gadamer-ii/" rel="nofollow ugc">http://avowofconversation.wordpress.com/2008/04/27/louth-on-gadamer-ii/</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: chakira		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/09/gadamer-on-orthodoxy-tradition-as-self-identity/#comment-62</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[chakira]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2009 00:08:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=144#comment-62</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[One question which we are dancing around is the foreignness, and returnability-to of the past. Does hermeneutics render the past accessible by empathizing it (let&#039;s say Schleiermacher) or reliving it (Hegel) or do we see the past as foreclosed and inaccessible because of its high level of contingency and openness involved in some non teleological accounts of it (Derrida)?  This problem is academic for most people, but for those Orthodox Jews who wish to go back to the future, it is alive. Perhaps what we need is some kind of thought of futurity in Orthodoxy, more than a thought of reliving the old days. Even reading pamphlets from JOFA we see the evocation of the golden age of the 50s rather than any rigorous thought of anything which is to come. A side note, if we are so obsessed with the ethos of Hadesh Yameinu KeKedem we ironically make the past more inaccessible as it is effaced into futurity, while foreclosing the future within the limitedness of the momentary impasse. So where is the JOFA pamphlet which begins with an invocation of the fact that the 2050s could be better than the 1950s, and that even if Daniel Sperber does not discover the egal minyan of medieval Worms, we will still be ok?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One question which we are dancing around is the foreignness, and returnability-to of the past. Does hermeneutics render the past accessible by empathizing it (let&#8217;s say Schleiermacher) or reliving it (Hegel) or do we see the past as foreclosed and inaccessible because of its high level of contingency and openness involved in some non teleological accounts of it (Derrida)?  This problem is academic for most people, but for those Orthodox Jews who wish to go back to the future, it is alive. Perhaps what we need is some kind of thought of futurity in Orthodoxy, more than a thought of reliving the old days. Even reading pamphlets from JOFA we see the evocation of the golden age of the 50s rather than any rigorous thought of anything which is to come. A side note, if we are so obsessed with the ethos of Hadesh Yameinu KeKedem we ironically make the past more inaccessible as it is effaced into futurity, while foreclosing the future within the limitedness of the momentary impasse. So where is the JOFA pamphlet which begins with an invocation of the fact that the 2050s could be better than the 1950s, and that even if Daniel Sperber does not discover the egal minyan of medieval Worms, we will still be ok?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
