<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Christian Smith on Biblicism (and halakhah)	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/11/christian-smith-on-biblicism-and-halakhah/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/11/christian-smith-on-biblicism-and-halakhah/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2011 22:39:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/11/christian-smith-on-biblicism-and-halakhah/#comment-3529</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2011 22:39:30 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4009#comment-3529</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Michael Bernstein,
I think that Smith would even consider the normative approach as a solution. He is complaining about things like &quot;The Bible&#039;s guide to finance&quot; which does not see the distancization from the text.  He does not like the investing a sermon with fixing univocal meaning. Maimonides and Nahmanides offer both clarity and understanding of a hermeneutic,lacking in the handbook approach.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Michael Bernstein,<br />
I think that Smith would even consider the normative approach as a solution. He is complaining about things like &#8220;The Bible&#8217;s guide to finance&#8221; which does not see the distancization from the text.  He does not like the investing a sermon with fixing univocal meaning. Maimonides and Nahmanides offer both clarity and understanding of a hermeneutic,lacking in the handbook approach.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Michael Bernstein		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/11/christian-smith-on-biblicism-and-halakhah/#comment-3528</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Michael Bernstein]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2011 22:22:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4009#comment-3528</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It strikes me that the Biblicists (and their counterparts in the world of halakha) take what could be called a normative approach, seeing the sacred text as stamped with Divine authority, but subject to straightforward interpretation that makes clear the guidelines for proper behavior and belief.  The other approach would be an immanent approach in whuch the text is a meeting place between the human and the Divine and, as such, not reducible to any one meaning, especially one that would be characterized as &quot;peshat.&quot;.  To read Bible (or halakha) that way is to sacrifice doctrinal clarity for the depth of encounter with the Divine hrough the sacred text (or tradition).]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It strikes me that the Biblicists (and their counterparts in the world of halakha) take what could be called a normative approach, seeing the sacred text as stamped with Divine authority, but subject to straightforward interpretation that makes clear the guidelines for proper behavior and belief.  The other approach would be an immanent approach in whuch the text is a meeting place between the human and the Divine and, as such, not reducible to any one meaning, especially one that would be characterized as &#8220;peshat.&#8221;.  To read Bible (or halakha) that way is to sacrifice doctrinal clarity for the depth of encounter with the Divine hrough the sacred text (or tradition).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Larry		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/11/christian-smith-on-biblicism-and-halakhah/#comment-3526</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Larry]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2011 06:03:31 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4009#comment-3526</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I don&#039;t see how moving to the Catholic Church is going to solve any problems long-term. You&#039;ve escaped from the worst excesses of trying to project the emotional experience of perceived Truth on to a specific collection of ancient texts that, on close analysis, have multiple meanings and agendas. (The emotional perception of having perceived the deeper and absolute truth would seem to be a certain set of brain circuits.)
But affirming to a Church, no matter how Catholic, means giving the truth claims to either a set of committees, or an institution... and the implicit notion that the Absolute Divine, the Allegedly Omnipotent and Omnibenevolent, could think of no better institution to leave to his followers than an institution which opposed democracy, human rights, and the prosecution of child molesters.

The really interesting question is why Smith is so adamantly refusing to identity as liberal, even as he works through the same contradictions that led so many generations of his theological predecessors to conclude, no matter how reluctantly, that there is no Absolute divinity or truth in recorded revelation and human institutions, no matter how much Holiness might be experienced there.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I don&#8217;t see how moving to the Catholic Church is going to solve any problems long-term. You&#8217;ve escaped from the worst excesses of trying to project the emotional experience of perceived Truth on to a specific collection of ancient texts that, on close analysis, have multiple meanings and agendas. (The emotional perception of having perceived the deeper and absolute truth would seem to be a certain set of brain circuits.)<br />
But affirming to a Church, no matter how Catholic, means giving the truth claims to either a set of committees, or an institution&#8230; and the implicit notion that the Absolute Divine, the Allegedly Omnipotent and Omnibenevolent, could think of no better institution to leave to his followers than an institution which opposed democracy, human rights, and the prosecution of child molesters.</p>
<p>The really interesting question is why Smith is so adamantly refusing to identity as liberal, even as he works through the same contradictions that led so many generations of his theological predecessors to conclude, no matter how reluctantly, that there is no Absolute divinity or truth in recorded revelation and human institutions, no matter how much Holiness might be experienced there.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Larry Yudelson		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/11/christian-smith-on-biblicism-and-halakhah/#comment-3520</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Larry Yudelson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 14 Aug 2011 23:15:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4009#comment-3520</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[EJ,

Note the increasing number of post-high school yeshivas that specialize in things other than Nezikin and Nashim.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>EJ,</p>
<p>Note the increasing number of post-high school yeshivas that specialize in things other than Nezikin and Nashim.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: HS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/11/christian-smith-on-biblicism-and-halakhah/#comment-3516</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[HS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 14 Aug 2011 17:22:30 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4009#comment-3516</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I certainly see commonality with Orthodoxy in &quot;Complete Coverage.&quot;  I know successful Orthodox businessmen who consult their rebbe before closing any major transaction.  

&quot;Internal Harmony&quot; is ignorance, no different from the uneducated lay looking upon Hasidim and the Pennsylvania Dutch, and concluding they are the same religious sect.  Similarly, I find no difference between Niels Bohr&#039;s quantum mechanics and Richard Feynman&#039;s quantum mechanics.   Bohr and Feynman seem pretty harmonious to me.    

But professional physicists, who know better, would find strange an attempt to locate the &quot;hacha b&#039;mai askinan&quot; that enables harmonization of Bohr and Feynman.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I certainly see commonality with Orthodoxy in &#8220;Complete Coverage.&#8221;  I know successful Orthodox businessmen who consult their rebbe before closing any major transaction.  </p>
<p>&#8220;Internal Harmony&#8221; is ignorance, no different from the uneducated lay looking upon Hasidim and the Pennsylvania Dutch, and concluding they are the same religious sect.  Similarly, I find no difference between Niels Bohr&#8217;s quantum mechanics and Richard Feynman&#8217;s quantum mechanics.   Bohr and Feynman seem pretty harmonious to me.    </p>
<p>But professional physicists, who know better, would find strange an attempt to locate the &#8220;hacha b&#8217;mai askinan&#8221; that enables harmonization of Bohr and Feynman.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/11/christian-smith-on-biblicism-and-halakhah/#comment-3514</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 14 Aug 2011 02:46:29 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4009#comment-3514</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I think I agree with your thesis if I understand it correctly, to wit that  the criticism levelled against the Evangelical use of scripture also applies to similar uses of halacha. Nevertheless it seems to me there are profound differences between halacha and the Christian use of the bible. The Torah we  have came from places far away and from cultures and times very different from ours. This makes the Talmud strange, uncanny in a way. What is say Soteh about? Who would act like this? What is taharos about....how does impurity travel? For every mitzvah that seems natural and of moral import, there are many more that are pretty much incomprehensible. The tragedy and greatness of Orthodoxy is that however strange a halacha should be, no mitzva, no text gets left behind, whether there are satisfying apologetics or not. The upshot is the content of Torah is not very pliable, you can discard it, throw it overboard, but you can’t turn it anything you want. There is no way to go from Seder Nashim to a charitable mission in Togo, or from Seder Nezikin into liberal or conservative politics. Torah in its broad outlines is recalcitrant, it says what it says, and we try to learn this in all its detail even when it doesn’t fit our secular or modern views.
Not so Evangelical Christianity. This is brought out, though not in the clearest way, in a book you recommended to us at the beginning of this blog, “America’s God” by Mark Knoll. The Protestant churches created the American version of Protestant theology by incorporating important features of American life. They grew to  favour a republic, though the European Protestants supported monarchies; they eventually opposed slavery, and found support for both these doctrines in the Bible. Until today I have no idea whether Orthodoxy is republican, in favour of separation of church and state with all that entails,  or not. Chasidic rebbes and heads of yeshivoth inherit their positions. We continue to talk of the melech hamashiach. Would the Vilna Gaon have encouraged the American revolution, would the Bais Halevi or Reb Shlomo Kluger have been opposed to slavery and in favour of the Civil War? Who knows? The Evangelicals have much more freedom to create a religion that mirrors their beliefs, because they are much more at liberty to begin with the present.
I was pleased to see Stanley Hauerwas, who is apparently an important Protestant theologian,  makes a similar point in an article I stumbled across on the internet. 
http://www.abc.net.au/religion/articles/2011/08/08/2947368.htm]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think I agree with your thesis if I understand it correctly, to wit that  the criticism levelled against the Evangelical use of scripture also applies to similar uses of halacha. Nevertheless it seems to me there are profound differences between halacha and the Christian use of the bible. The Torah we  have came from places far away and from cultures and times very different from ours. This makes the Talmud strange, uncanny in a way. What is say Soteh about? Who would act like this? What is taharos about&#8230;.how does impurity travel? For every mitzvah that seems natural and of moral import, there are many more that are pretty much incomprehensible. The tragedy and greatness of Orthodoxy is that however strange a halacha should be, no mitzva, no text gets left behind, whether there are satisfying apologetics or not. The upshot is the content of Torah is not very pliable, you can discard it, throw it overboard, but you can’t turn it anything you want. There is no way to go from Seder Nashim to a charitable mission in Togo, or from Seder Nezikin into liberal or conservative politics. Torah in its broad outlines is recalcitrant, it says what it says, and we try to learn this in all its detail even when it doesn’t fit our secular or modern views.<br />
Not so Evangelical Christianity. This is brought out, though not in the clearest way, in a book you recommended to us at the beginning of this blog, “America’s God” by Mark Knoll. The Protestant churches created the American version of Protestant theology by incorporating important features of American life. They grew to  favour a republic, though the European Protestants supported monarchies; they eventually opposed slavery, and found support for both these doctrines in the Bible. Until today I have no idea whether Orthodoxy is republican, in favour of separation of church and state with all that entails,  or not. Chasidic rebbes and heads of yeshivoth inherit their positions. We continue to talk of the melech hamashiach. Would the Vilna Gaon have encouraged the American revolution, would the Bais Halevi or Reb Shlomo Kluger have been opposed to slavery and in favour of the Civil War? Who knows? The Evangelicals have much more freedom to create a religion that mirrors their beliefs, because they are much more at liberty to begin with the present.<br />
I was pleased to see Stanley Hauerwas, who is apparently an important Protestant theologian,  makes a similar point in an article I stumbled across on the internet.<br />
<a href="http://www.abc.net.au/religion/articles/2011/08/08/2947368.htm" rel="nofollow ugc">http://www.abc.net.au/religion/articles/2011/08/08/2947368.htm</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/11/christian-smith-on-biblicism-and-halakhah/#comment-3510</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2011 00:06:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4009#comment-3510</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Actually in the second half of the book, Smith wants to go back to positions like Rav Soloveitchik or Karl Barth. He find&#039;s treating the text as an aspiration, a sensibility, a philosophy, or an insight to be the correct approach. These approaches acknowledge the complexity of hearing the divine voice in the sun set. Smith differentiates this from the current generation that speaks of instruction manuals with its realism and univocal directions, unaware that God does not speak like a Home Depot manual. 
Smith can live with Thomistic, Kantian, or Existential truth, not home manuals.
Smith is actually the idealist who wants to go back to the Christian equivalents of Rabbis Soloveitchik, Lichtenstein, or Amital who taught a multi-valence approach and taught a method that has to be personally applied by the individual, knowing that others  will not arrive at the same conclusions. He would like Newman, Barth, and Aquinas. He does not like phrases like the &quot;Torah view of the stock market.&quot; But he would like &quot;cultivating a personality of Torah values.&quot; As long as the latter would understand that there are alternate choices to one&#039;s own. He does not like those who troll for halakhic factoids as singular Biblicist truths by which to beat others up.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Actually in the second half of the book, Smith wants to go back to positions like Rav Soloveitchik or Karl Barth. He find&#8217;s treating the text as an aspiration, a sensibility, a philosophy, or an insight to be the correct approach. These approaches acknowledge the complexity of hearing the divine voice in the sun set. Smith differentiates this from the current generation that speaks of instruction manuals with its realism and univocal directions, unaware that God does not speak like a Home Depot manual.<br />
Smith can live with Thomistic, Kantian, or Existential truth, not home manuals.<br />
Smith is actually the idealist who wants to go back to the Christian equivalents of Rabbis Soloveitchik, Lichtenstein, or Amital who taught a multi-valence approach and taught a method that has to be personally applied by the individual, knowing that others  will not arrive at the same conclusions. He would like Newman, Barth, and Aquinas. He does not like phrases like the &#8220;Torah view of the stock market.&#8221; But he would like &#8220;cultivating a personality of Torah values.&#8221; As long as the latter would understand that there are alternate choices to one&#8217;s own. He does not like those who troll for halakhic factoids as singular Biblicist truths by which to beat others up.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Larry Yudelson		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/11/christian-smith-on-biblicism-and-halakhah/#comment-3509</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Larry Yudelson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2011 23:07:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4009#comment-3509</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[What they have in common is the belief that the holy scripture provides both an insight into God&#039;s mind and solution to the problems of how to live.

In Ish Hahalacha, the Halachic perception of the world is qualitatively better than the scientific or the aesthetic. The Halachic Man sees the sun going down and the ears in his head hear a Divine Command to daven Mincha.

20 years ago, I interviewed American kids studying in yeshiva in Israel. What motivates them? The answer: Studying Talmud is as close as they can come to understanding the Mind of God.

I forget the exact context in which I heard this line in the name of a modern-to-right Orthodox Jews: &quot;How would God create the world and not include an instruction manual?&quot; The logic is that underlying solo scriptorum: Wouldn&#039;t an omniscient benevolent God tell us what to do? And the Bible -- or, in our case, the Talmud, is a venerable book that claims to do just that.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What they have in common is the belief that the holy scripture provides both an insight into God&#8217;s mind and solution to the problems of how to live.</p>
<p>In Ish Hahalacha, the Halachic perception of the world is qualitatively better than the scientific or the aesthetic. The Halachic Man sees the sun going down and the ears in his head hear a Divine Command to daven Mincha.</p>
<p>20 years ago, I interviewed American kids studying in yeshiva in Israel. What motivates them? The answer: Studying Talmud is as close as they can come to understanding the Mind of God.</p>
<p>I forget the exact context in which I heard this line in the name of a modern-to-right Orthodox Jews: &#8220;How would God create the world and not include an instruction manual?&#8221; The logic is that underlying solo scriptorum: Wouldn&#8217;t an omniscient benevolent God tell us what to do? And the Bible &#8212; or, in our case, the Talmud, is a venerable book that claims to do just that.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Geoffrey Stern		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/11/christian-smith-on-biblicism-and-halakhah/#comment-3508</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Geoffrey Stern]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2011 22:56:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4009#comment-3508</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The social phenomenon of Biblicism parallels the way those with very strong and narrow opinions troll the internet for opinions and &quot;facts&quot; that mirror and support their own bias.  Not enough research has been done to analyze how the internet has changed research and fact finding and how we learn and think.  Learning and newsgathering have become a modern form of apologetics and polemic rather than true learning and informed enlightenment.  As they say... &quot;You can change the facts, but you can&#039;t change opinions&quot;.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The social phenomenon of Biblicism parallels the way those with very strong and narrow opinions troll the internet for opinions and &#8220;facts&#8221; that mirror and support their own bias.  Not enough research has been done to analyze how the internet has changed research and fact finding and how we learn and think.  Learning and newsgathering have become a modern form of apologetics and polemic rather than true learning and informed enlightenment.  As they say&#8230; &#8220;You can change the facts, but you can&#8217;t change opinions&#8221;.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/11/christian-smith-on-biblicism-and-halakhah/#comment-3507</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2011 21:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4009#comment-3507</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/11/christian-smith-on-biblicism-and-halakhah/#comment-3506&quot;&gt;IH&lt;/a&gt;.

We can ask him afterward. That might be a good interview. In the meantime, it worked reasonably well for his &lt;em&gt;American Evangelicalism: Embattled and Thriving&lt;/em&gt;. Maybe we should go back to that volume and see where the 1998 paradigm fit and did not fit.  The closer we are to certain political and sociological issues it works, the closer we are to pure theological issues it fits less well. He would see Biblicism and univocal texts as a social question and not a theological one. There have been several studies of specific issues comparing the two communities.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/11/christian-smith-on-biblicism-and-halakhah/#comment-3506">IH</a>.</p>
<p>We can ask him afterward. That might be a good interview. In the meantime, it worked reasonably well for his <em>American Evangelicalism: Embattled and Thriving</em>. Maybe we should go back to that volume and see where the 1998 paradigm fit and did not fit.  The closer we are to certain political and sociological issues it works, the closer we are to pure theological issues it fits less well. He would see Biblicism and univocal texts as a social question and not a theological one. There have been several studies of specific issues comparing the two communities.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: IH		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/11/christian-smith-on-biblicism-and-halakhah/#comment-3506</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[IH]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2011 21:13:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4009#comment-3506</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[And does Smith concur?  I.e. is it a reasonable jump to make in interpreting his thesis?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>And does Smith concur?  I.e. is it a reasonable jump to make in interpreting his thesis?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/11/christian-smith-on-biblicism-and-halakhah/#comment-3505</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2011 20:58:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4009#comment-3505</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/11/christian-smith-on-biblicism-and-halakhah/#comment-3504&quot;&gt;IH&lt;/a&gt;.

Yes, you misunderstood. That is exactly what I said NOT to compare. DOnt compare our use of the bIble, rather their use of Bble to our use of Hazal and halakhah. Commonsense of Talmud wins over literal readings. Commonsense and democratic means without history or philosophy et al and we treat halakhah with that unselfish-conscious commonsense. We treat the Rambam, SA MB, or even a newsletter with a solo scriptura sense.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/11/christian-smith-on-biblicism-and-halakhah/#comment-3504">IH</a>.</p>
<p>Yes, you misunderstood. That is exactly what I said NOT to compare. DOnt compare our use of the bIble, rather their use of Bble to our use of Hazal and halakhah. Commonsense of Talmud wins over literal readings. Commonsense and democratic means without history or philosophy et al and we treat halakhah with that unselfish-conscious commonsense. We treat the Rambam, SA MB, or even a newsletter with a solo scriptura sense.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: IH		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/11/christian-smith-on-biblicism-and-halakhah/#comment-3504</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[IH]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2011 20:51:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4009#comment-3504</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[On first reading, I do not see how you conclude &quot;most of his comments apply equally well to the way the halakhah is used and the Orthodox high view of the Talmud.&quot;.

Some examples:

1.  Commonsense Hermeneutics:  Pshat wins in Tanach: I think not.
2.  Democratic Perspicuity: e.g. Shir ha&#039;Shirim?  Kohelet?
3.  Solo Scriptura: no need for Rambam&#039;s 13 Ikkarim?  (Or, Mishneh Torah. Tur and SA for that matter.)

Also, as I was reading the passage starting &quot;Many of those Biblicists establishing certainty&quot;, I was thinking the opposite of what he intended.  In Judaism, it seems to be the more RW Orthodox, the more one holds the view Smith ascribes to &quot;Biblicists&quot;.

Have I mis-understood?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>On first reading, I do not see how you conclude &#8220;most of his comments apply equally well to the way the halakhah is used and the Orthodox high view of the Talmud.&#8221;.</p>
<p>Some examples:</p>
<p>1.  Commonsense Hermeneutics:  Pshat wins in Tanach: I think not.<br />
2.  Democratic Perspicuity: e.g. Shir ha&#8217;Shirim?  Kohelet?<br />
3.  Solo Scriptura: no need for Rambam&#8217;s 13 Ikkarim?  (Or, Mishneh Torah. Tur and SA for that matter.)</p>
<p>Also, as I was reading the passage starting &#8220;Many of those Biblicists establishing certainty&#8221;, I was thinking the opposite of what he intended.  In Judaism, it seems to be the more RW Orthodox, the more one holds the view Smith ascribes to &#8220;Biblicists&#8221;.</p>
<p>Have I mis-understood?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
