<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Absence of Mind- Marilynne Robinson  1 of 3 posts	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/20/absence-of-mind-marilynne-robinson-1-of-3-posts/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/20/absence-of-mind-marilynne-robinson-1-of-3-posts/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2011 22:40:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Pegasus		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/20/absence-of-mind-marilynne-robinson-1-of-3-posts/#comment-3957</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pegasus]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2011 22:40:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1694#comment-3957</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Her point is not that the mind is &quot;autonomous and independent entity&quot; but that the mind is an authentic phenomenon - just as the brain is - and that its many functions which go beyond the basic functions of seeking food and reproducing as espoused by the most reductive Evolutionary Theoriticians, are valid areas of exploration in their own right. She does so not by categorically stating that the opposing views are &#039;wrong&#039;, but by pointing out the flaws in their analysis/ interpretation of the subjective experience and even objective approach to Mind and by exposing how their discourse fails to do justice or even account for what is going on. They fail to take into account interiority, or the fact that our lives are &#039;happy&#039; or &#039;sad&#039;, &#039;fulfilled&#039; or &#039;unfulfilled&#039; outside of their remit. Explaining themselves in terms of what they are not doesn&#039;t answer the fundamental question: why do we have them and why is what goes on in them so important? To find even possible answers, she argues, we have to drop our condescending attitude towards other ways of thinking and look at what is there.

She doesn&#039;t espouse dualism. She never denies the connection of the mind to the body or biological processes, she merely states that the vast panoply of experience the human mind - whatever its origins or nature - has to offer, as well as its rich legacy in terms of past and present culture, cannot be ignored or dismissed even by the most strident materialist approach. Saying that the sense of Self is &#039;an illusion&#039; doesn&#039;t account for why the illusion is there, nor does it get round the fact that we live and die with it and work out our destinies in its context. Saying its &#039;an illusion&#039; is therefore basically unhelpful, as even if one were to &#039;prove&#039; it (how would one? As an illusion has to be experienced by something, so we are stuck in an infinite regress of consciousness and &#039;illusory&#039; Self-hoods), of what actual use would that be to us?

These are the points she seems to be making, it seems to me. I don&#039;t agree that she has to prove that Mind is not an &#039;epiphenomenon&#039;. Why? Its not a consensus view and as a view it holds immense problems (such as why evolve such a thing?). Her point is that even if it WERE an epiphenomenon, we still have to live with it and it still remains our field of experience, with all the complex matrices of emotional and mental meaning that involves.

The last thing Marilynne Robinson is is strident.  By couching the debate in these confrontational terms, it appears to me to evading her questions and arguments by reframing the discussion, rather than addressing what she actually says.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Her point is not that the mind is &#8220;autonomous and independent entity&#8221; but that the mind is an authentic phenomenon &#8211; just as the brain is &#8211; and that its many functions which go beyond the basic functions of seeking food and reproducing as espoused by the most reductive Evolutionary Theoriticians, are valid areas of exploration in their own right. She does so not by categorically stating that the opposing views are &#8216;wrong&#8217;, but by pointing out the flaws in their analysis/ interpretation of the subjective experience and even objective approach to Mind and by exposing how their discourse fails to do justice or even account for what is going on. They fail to take into account interiority, or the fact that our lives are &#8216;happy&#8217; or &#8216;sad&#8217;, &#8216;fulfilled&#8217; or &#8216;unfulfilled&#8217; outside of their remit. Explaining themselves in terms of what they are not doesn&#8217;t answer the fundamental question: why do we have them and why is what goes on in them so important? To find even possible answers, she argues, we have to drop our condescending attitude towards other ways of thinking and look at what is there.</p>
<p>She doesn&#8217;t espouse dualism. She never denies the connection of the mind to the body or biological processes, she merely states that the vast panoply of experience the human mind &#8211; whatever its origins or nature &#8211; has to offer, as well as its rich legacy in terms of past and present culture, cannot be ignored or dismissed even by the most strident materialist approach. Saying that the sense of Self is &#8216;an illusion&#8217; doesn&#8217;t account for why the illusion is there, nor does it get round the fact that we live and die with it and work out our destinies in its context. Saying its &#8216;an illusion&#8217; is therefore basically unhelpful, as even if one were to &#8216;prove&#8217; it (how would one? As an illusion has to be experienced by something, so we are stuck in an infinite regress of consciousness and &#8216;illusory&#8217; Self-hoods), of what actual use would that be to us?</p>
<p>These are the points she seems to be making, it seems to me. I don&#8217;t agree that she has to prove that Mind is not an &#8216;epiphenomenon&#8217;. Why? Its not a consensus view and as a view it holds immense problems (such as why evolve such a thing?). Her point is that even if it WERE an epiphenomenon, we still have to live with it and it still remains our field of experience, with all the complex matrices of emotional and mental meaning that involves.</p>
<p>The last thing Marilynne Robinson is is strident.  By couching the debate in these confrontational terms, it appears to me to evading her questions and arguments by reframing the discussion, rather than addressing what she actually says.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/20/absence-of-mind-marilynne-robinson-1-of-3-posts/#comment-1347</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Jul 2010 05:51:26 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1694#comment-1347</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[No, she specifically does not want to get into the current arguments in phil of mind,  nor should she. It&#039;s not as if there is really some new problem here. A cause is a cause is a cause, whether it is material, psychological, neurological, evolutionary, etc. People who get really excited about these questions seem to forget that they are entirely theoretical in the sense that they do not intersect with practical reasoning at all. From the pragmatic perspective we all have some degree of practical agency and we cannot help but think otherwise. To think otherwise is to dispense with practical reason. And this is why for Kant, God is absented from the first critique but returns in the second. 

The argument, such that it is, is that we exist as subjective consciousnesses with practical agency. That is the explananda. From there you can move to whatever metaphysical apparatus or deflationary account you prefer. Her critique is in making the latter move instead of the former.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>No, she specifically does not want to get into the current arguments in phil of mind,  nor should she. It&#8217;s not as if there is really some new problem here. A cause is a cause is a cause, whether it is material, psychological, neurological, evolutionary, etc. People who get really excited about these questions seem to forget that they are entirely theoretical in the sense that they do not intersect with practical reasoning at all. From the pragmatic perspective we all have some degree of practical agency and we cannot help but think otherwise. To think otherwise is to dispense with practical reason. And this is why for Kant, God is absented from the first critique but returns in the second. </p>
<p>The argument, such that it is, is that we exist as subjective consciousnesses with practical agency. That is the explananda. From there you can move to whatever metaphysical apparatus or deflationary account you prefer. Her critique is in making the latter move instead of the former.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/20/absence-of-mind-marilynne-robinson-1-of-3-posts/#comment-1346</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 21 Jul 2010 21:58:50 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1694#comment-1346</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Her core argument is like  the argument for theism that goes (premise) God exists, (conclusion) God exists. Valid, but not helpful since he who doubts the conclusion would doubt the premise. Robinson argues we have real subjective experiences, therefore the experiences we have are real.
She says science cannot do justice to the flow of consciousness. For that we need language and folk psychology that describe the contents of this flow from within. This is true, we need writers and poets and ordinary people and even, if she insists, Eckhart Tolle. Yes, scientists might be helped in deepening their humanity by having a night seder in James Joyce. What she needs to show is that we have minds that are not epiphenomena. This topic is central to current discussions in philosophy. The alternative is that only our neural states are real causing us to have thoughts, but we are not creating these thoughts ex-nihilo. Robinson does nothing to disprove this latter view. We now know that neurons fire before the conscious intention or action, which is a difficulty for the view of the mind as autonomous and independent entity. David Chalmers a maven on this topic has catalogued 18000 recent papers on this topic.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Her core argument is like  the argument for theism that goes (premise) God exists, (conclusion) God exists. Valid, but not helpful since he who doubts the conclusion would doubt the premise. Robinson argues we have real subjective experiences, therefore the experiences we have are real.<br />
She says science cannot do justice to the flow of consciousness. For that we need language and folk psychology that describe the contents of this flow from within. This is true, we need writers and poets and ordinary people and even, if she insists, Eckhart Tolle. Yes, scientists might be helped in deepening their humanity by having a night seder in James Joyce. What she needs to show is that we have minds that are not epiphenomena. This topic is central to current discussions in philosophy. The alternative is that only our neural states are real causing us to have thoughts, but we are not creating these thoughts ex-nihilo. Robinson does nothing to disprove this latter view. We now know that neurons fire before the conscious intention or action, which is a difficulty for the view of the mind as autonomous and independent entity. David Chalmers a maven on this topic has catalogued 18000 recent papers on this topic.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
