<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Passover haggadah &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/tag/passover-haggadah/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Apr 2010 19:48:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='kavvanah.wordpress.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/c9f111237f93750b6b994fc5185d49c3?s=96&#038;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>Passover haggadah &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>Haggadot 2010</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/29/haggadot-2010/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/29/haggadot-2010/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 29 Apr 2010 19:48:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[holidays]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[artscroll]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gra]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[haggadah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jonathan Sacks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Passover haggadah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tabory]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1201</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I never got around to posting this after Passover, so Pesah Sheni reminded me to get this posted ASAP. All of these are impressions from their use at the table, not in depth studies. JPS Tabory- he is an expert &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/29/haggadot-2010/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I never got around to posting this after Passover, so Pesah Sheni reminded me to get this posted ASAP. All of these are impressions from their use at the table, not in depth studies. </p>
<p>JPS Tabory- he is an expert on the topic and I like his scholarly articles on the Pasover  seder but was disappointed with the haggadah. I blame it more on the editor.  There are points where the comment on the bottom states “Popular theories are not true”  without giving his own opinion. For a popular haggadah just to state that others are false is not good editing.  The introduction was more trendy in scholarship than I expected, cutting edge debates around Israel Yuval’s work and whether  Christianity is the source of the Haggadah and not visa versa. I would have liked more of the basics from his scholarship. And of course he discusses “Pour out they love upon the gentiles.”</p>
<p>This year, I listened to Jonathan Sacks through someone else reading from its comments.  Sacks quotes Primo Levi on the same page as the Hartman’s Haggadah, we have noted in the past his reliance on Hartman’s but the Primo Levi is also quoted in the classic Schoken haggadah by Nachum Glatzer. Sacks was consistently in favor of community at the expense of faithless spirituality and individualism. He even manages to twist a Kotzker statement about letting God into one heart into the need to affirm the future of the community. I was most piqued by his statements about the need for the hope of Jewish history and peoplehood- and the message of the haggadah is not the details of Temple law. Having been acculturated into Brisker appreciation for Temple law- this was unexpected. His language of peoplehood and continuity sounded like a 1950’s Conservative haggadah, I pulled one or two off the shelf, finding the sentiment, but I could not find Sacks exact language</p>
<p>The Carlebach Haggadah was more Holocaust oriented than I remembered. </p>
<p>The  MM Kasher Haggadah where everything is explained as messianic and golly gee whiz we can have a return to the Temple does not seem as innocuous anymore.</p>
<p>Marge Piercy’s mix of Jewish renewal, poetry, and foodie recipes is a nice gift for right person.</p>
<p>The Artscroll Vilna Gaon Haggadah remain a gem for conveying the traditional Lithuanian understanding of the Haggadah. &#8220;Zekher Yetziat mitzrayim as a chance for unending Talmud Torah.&#8221; The Haggadah was not actually written by the Gra. When the Gra died in 1797 – he left behind 10 official books- 8 of them in Kabbalah. There were some early fragments of the Gra on the Haggdah published in 1813 but  in the 1850’s there was a full commentary created. Most people knew the Gra only through this accessible entry point of the haggadh. When ordinary rabbis quoted the Gra this was the volume that they could understand. The volume had an effect on the nusach of the haggadah both on Russian printings and on the American Hebrew Publishing company. I could pick issues with the translation but is nice to have some real Torah transalted.</p>
<p>But I wonder why they don’t translate the Nesivos Haggadah?  The Haggadah Maaseh Nissim of  Rabbi Yaakov Lorberbaum called by his legal commentary Netivot was the major shaper of Eastern European drush on the Haggadah. All these people claiming to wait the view of the mesorah of eastern Europe are not referring to anything spoken at the seder in Europe if they don’t have the Maasah Nissim. </p>
<p>On the other hand, Artscroll did waste their time putting a pile of haggadahs from various contemporary gedolim that are gibberish. I don’t blame the rabbanim and I wont list which ones. But they are quite a few that were sent out as fundraisers by various yeshivas that have vorts that the reader cannot tell if the gadol is telling over the Gra? Differing with the Gra? Offering his own approach to the Gra? Collections of random butchered quotes of Aharonim that only a high pitched tenth grader proving he is stark could love. They should have done the Nesivos instead.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/29/haggadot-2010/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>8</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Marc-Alain Ouaknin, Haggadah</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/20/marc-alain-ouaknin-haggadah/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/20/marc-alain-ouaknin-haggadah/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2010 01:15:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[liturgy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ritual]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[elijah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[idolatry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Levinas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[marc alain ouaknin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Passover haggadah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Talmud]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[yachatz]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=979</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[One of the most interesting commentaries on the haggadah of the last decade was the one by Rabbi Marc-Alain Ouaknin, Haggadah: The Passover Story (Paperback) Ouaknin, a follower of Levinas and Lacan who teaches at Bar Ilan, when he is &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/20/marc-alain-ouaknin-haggadah/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One of the most interesting commentaries on the haggadah of the last decade was the one by<br />
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Haggadah-Passover-Rabbi-Marc-Alain-Ouaknin/dp/2843232538/ref=tmm_pap_title_0">Rabbi Marc-Alain Ouaknin, Haggadah: The Passover Story</a> (Paperback)</p>
<p>Ouaknin, a follower of Levinas and Lacan who teaches at Bar Ilan, when he is not busy writing profitable coffee table books, does some serious engagement with contemporary French thought, especially in his <strong>The Burnt Book.</strong><em>  For him, the Talmudic project of the Eastern European beit midrash  has no closure, ever changing, ever forgetful and driven by desire. He freely mixes R. Hayyim of Volozhin, Rav Nahman, Reb Zadok with psychoanalysis, symbolist poetry, and semiotics. Ouaknin has a reading of Judaism as indeterminacy. “Man must reject the illusion of thinking that life is already written and the way is drawn.”  He are various fragments from the web that give some indiation of his approach to the Passover haggadah.</p>
<p>My favorite section is his explanation of Yachatz, breaking the middle matzah, as the Lacanian Real sending us on our quest through the seder for our ever receding Real , creating a symbolic order in the Lacan sense. Breaking the matzah creates an open space for our symbolic registry to occur. We are throw in the seder just as we are thrown into our quest for the recovery of the real.</p>
<p>On the telling of the Passover story, he writes:<br />
“The words of telling emerge from that break, from the empty place left between the two pieces of matzah.”<br />
The act of telling the story of the Exodus occurs through an exchange of conversation and ideas. We take the one whole matzah and break it in half because discussion and conversation occur when there is a minimum of two — me and the other. </p>
<p>On opening the door for Elijah, Ouaknin quotes the story in which Elijah goes alone to a cave on Mount Horev in the desert. God brings a great wind, and then an earthquake, and then a fire—but God was not in any of these. Instead, after the fire, he finds God in ‘a still, small voice.’ (1 Kings 19:11-13) Ouaknin comments that one must reach the level of Elijah, self-forgetfulness in the desert.</p>
<p></em><em>One must have sharpened one’s hearing, to be led to the absolute level of attention, to become capable of perceiving such a tenuous breath. One must have sounded oneself, have explored oneself in the darkest places of consciousness, to the furthest of thoughts, to have made the circuit of one’s inner domain many times, in constantly growing but nevertheless tightening circles, so as to attain the intimate desert of self-forgetfulness, to be able to be stroked lightly, touched, visited by such an inaudible sigh.<br />
The point of concluding the seder with opening the door for Elijah is to signify that this journey in ‘the intimate desert of self-forgetfulness’ is the ultimate intention of the seder. While we aim to find ourselves on seder night, to reconnect with the story of our people and see ourselves as having personally left Egypt, remembering who we are paradoxically requires losing ourselves at the same time.</em></p>
<p>For his approach to “my forefathers worshiped idols” he quotes J.L. Marion about idols as false forms that distort reality and fill in the gap between us and the divine.<br />
<em>What the idol tries to reduce is the gap and the withdrawal of the divine… Filling in for the absence of the divinity, the idol brings the divine within reach, ensures its presence, and, eventually, distorts it. Its completion finishes the divine off… The idol lacks the distance that identifies and authenticates the divine as such–as that which does not belong to us, but which happens to us. (Ouaknin, The Burnt Book, p. 65)</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/20/marc-alain-ouaknin-haggadah/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
