<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Chief Rabbi di Segni on the Jewish Catholic Encounter	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/17/chief-rabbi-desegni-on-the-jewish-catholic-encounter/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/17/chief-rabbi-desegni-on-the-jewish-catholic-encounter/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2010 04:29:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: chakira		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/17/chief-rabbi-desegni-on-the-jewish-catholic-encounter/#comment-439</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[chakira]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2010 01:05:36 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=574#comment-439</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I think we have found the nafka minah of using someone like Gadamer to describe Halakha (per earlier Sagi discussion). Even when the explicit text says we can not understand the other because of ontological difference, or because the other is almost demonic, dialog is still happening. This is coming close to the &quot;performative contradiction&quot; of Habermas vis a vis his opponents; if you debate him, he wins, cause he said its all about debate.

Still I think Di Segni is different, more like mechirat chametz. No, we cannot understand each other at all. But we can &quot;provisionally&quot; act as if we do, and tally up the differences after dialog (or Passover).]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think we have found the nafka minah of using someone like Gadamer to describe Halakha (per earlier Sagi discussion). Even when the explicit text says we can not understand the other because of ontological difference, or because the other is almost demonic, dialog is still happening. This is coming close to the &#8220;performative contradiction&#8221; of Habermas vis a vis his opponents; if you debate him, he wins, cause he said its all about debate.</p>
<p>Still I think Di Segni is different, more like mechirat chametz. No, we cannot understand each other at all. But we can &#8220;provisionally&#8221; act as if we do, and tally up the differences after dialog (or Passover).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/17/chief-rabbi-desegni-on-the-jewish-catholic-encounter/#comment-438</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2010 20:02:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=574#comment-438</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Dont contort di Segni into the Procrustean bed of YU terms. He is neither reading, referring, nor developing any ideas of Rabbi Soloveitchik.  In addition, Rabbi di Segni certainly believes we can dialogue and understand one another.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dont contort di Segni into the Procrustean bed of YU terms. He is neither reading, referring, nor developing any ideas of Rabbi Soloveitchik.  In addition, Rabbi di Segni certainly believes we can dialogue and understand one another.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Arie Folger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/01/17/chief-rabbi-desegni-on-the-jewish-catholic-encounter/#comment-437</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arie Folger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2010 19:50:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=574#comment-437</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Very interesting. I have met R&#039;Di Seigni several times, and am pleased to find out more about his thought. I find myself right at home, having been saying some of the same things, though more gently, and have discovered that people like the idea of not chucking out exclusivist claims, but either setting them aside or having each faith that wants to be part of public discourse argue from within why it can work hand in hand - and under what circumstances - with unbelievers. I took that latter idea from R&#039; Jonathan Sacks&#039; Dignity of Difference, though I think in the second half of that book he veered from those ideas towards a more principled pluralism. Unfortunately, his dissertation is in Italian, so I can&#039;t read that.

I feel that Di Seigni is building on some ideas R&#039;Soloveitchik stated in Confrontation, but has done so by being more explicitly theological and historical in a way that R&#039; Soloveitchik may have intentionally wanted to stay away from in that paper. What do you think?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Very interesting. I have met R&#8217;Di Seigni several times, and am pleased to find out more about his thought. I find myself right at home, having been saying some of the same things, though more gently, and have discovered that people like the idea of not chucking out exclusivist claims, but either setting them aside or having each faith that wants to be part of public discourse argue from within why it can work hand in hand &#8211; and under what circumstances &#8211; with unbelievers. I took that latter idea from R&#8217; Jonathan Sacks&#8217; Dignity of Difference, though I think in the second half of that book he veered from those ideas towards a more principled pluralism. Unfortunately, his dissertation is in Italian, so I can&#8217;t read that.</p>
<p>I feel that Di Seigni is building on some ideas R&#8217;Soloveitchik stated in Confrontation, but has done so by being more explicitly theological and historical in a way that R&#8217; Soloveitchik may have intentionally wanted to stay away from in that paper. What do you think?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
