<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Korach &#038; Moses&#8217; Meritocracy	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/06/27/korach-moses-meritocracy/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/06/27/korach-moses-meritocracy/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Aug 2012 02:00:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: reddotsg		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/06/27/korach-moses-meritocracy/#comment-6631</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[reddotsg]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 12 Aug 2012 02:00:32 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5282#comment-6631</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Reblogged this on &lt;a href=&quot;http://reddotsg.wordpress.com/2012/08/12/28/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Reddotsg&#039;s Blog&lt;/a&gt; and commented: 
Imagine a nation run as a meritocracy, where leaders rose to the top as they proved that they were brighter, more motivated, more assertive — true “leaders,” in every sense of the word.... Read on?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Reblogged this on <a href="http://reddotsg.wordpress.com/2012/08/12/28/" rel="nofollow">Reddotsg&#039;s Blog</a> and commented:<br />
Imagine a nation run as a meritocracy, where leaders rose to the top as they proved that they were brighter, more motivated, more assertive — true “leaders,” in every sense of the word&#8230;. Read on?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Eliezer Abrahamson		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/06/27/korach-moses-meritocracy/#comment-5824</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eliezer Abrahamson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 03 Jul 2012 17:25:38 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5282#comment-5824</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[While the Mei HaShiloach does acknowledge that Korach&#039;s argument had an element of truth in it, the Mei HaShiloach is not saying that Korach&#039;s argument was actually valid, in principle, and his error was &quot;merely a matter of timing.&quot; The point made by the Mei HaShiloach is that Korach was, indeed, motivated by his own desire for honor, for if his true motivation had been that &quot;the entire community is holy&quot; then he would protested earlier when the Leviim had been elevated. The fact that Korach first raised this argument only after he personally had been passed over demonstrated that his motivation was purely selfish. Thus, his own argument, which was only a means - &quot;ofen&quot; - to his true end, was turned back upon him.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>While the Mei HaShiloach does acknowledge that Korach&#8217;s argument had an element of truth in it, the Mei HaShiloach is not saying that Korach&#8217;s argument was actually valid, in principle, and his error was &#8220;merely a matter of timing.&#8221; The point made by the Mei HaShiloach is that Korach was, indeed, motivated by his own desire for honor, for if his true motivation had been that &#8220;the entire community is holy&#8221; then he would protested earlier when the Leviim had been elevated. The fact that Korach first raised this argument only after he personally had been passed over demonstrated that his motivation was purely selfish. Thus, his own argument, which was only a means &#8211; &#8220;ofen&#8221; &#8211; to his true end, was turned back upon him.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/06/27/korach-moses-meritocracy/#comment-5672</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2012 15:15:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5282#comment-5672</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I have been reading the many obituaries and appreciations of Nora Ephron in the NY Times, Forward  and elsewhere, all favorable , all dazzled by her empathy, natural warmth and talent. She brings to mind a second , more benign conception of meritocracy, where our social world is  a large family where everybody is within two degrees of separation, and where we support and help each other. My impression is that many industries and professions work for the most part as an old “boy” network. We see these relations in academia, the clergy, medicine, law, Silicon Valley,  Hollywood. It might not be the old WASP establishment, but it is a long way from the impersonal, entrenched bureaucracy of Kafka and Hayes. 
The Korach affair can be darshened as an intrafamily  brouhaha that threatened the network of governance. “Our Crowds” work against a background murmur of gossip, but open rebellion is not the way… we all know that, maybe because we know what happened with Korach.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have been reading the many obituaries and appreciations of Nora Ephron in the NY Times, Forward  and elsewhere, all favorable , all dazzled by her empathy, natural warmth and talent. She brings to mind a second , more benign conception of meritocracy, where our social world is  a large family where everybody is within two degrees of separation, and where we support and help each other. My impression is that many industries and professions work for the most part as an old “boy” network. We see these relations in academia, the clergy, medicine, law, Silicon Valley,  Hollywood. It might not be the old WASP establishment, but it is a long way from the impersonal, entrenched bureaucracy of Kafka and Hayes.<br />
The Korach affair can be darshened as an intrafamily  brouhaha that threatened the network of governance. “Our Crowds” work against a background murmur of gossip, but open rebellion is not the way… we all know that, maybe because we know what happened with Korach.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Yossi		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/06/27/korach-moses-meritocracy/#comment-5669</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Yossi]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2012 12:38:24 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5282#comment-5669</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Why a &quot;crisis of followership&quot;?  If people are more cynical, it&#039;s NOT because they like to pretend they are better than everybody else.  It&#039;s because, perhaps, they are tired of being lied to.  They are tired of the charade in Washington where the competing parties pretend to fight for the benefit of the &quot;people&quot;.  What really happens is that a few monied interests take care of themselves and leave the rest of us to twist in the wind.  How can we trust  government after the Gulf of Tonkin non-Incident, Watergate,  etc... etc..?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Why a &#8220;crisis of followership&#8221;?  If people are more cynical, it&#8217;s NOT because they like to pretend they are better than everybody else.  It&#8217;s because, perhaps, they are tired of being lied to.  They are tired of the charade in Washington where the competing parties pretend to fight for the benefit of the &#8220;people&#8221;.  What really happens is that a few monied interests take care of themselves and leave the rest of us to twist in the wind.  How can we trust  government after the Gulf of Tonkin non-Incident, Watergate,  etc&#8230; etc..?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
