<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: An Open Letter to America’s Christian Zionists From David P. Gushee and Glen H. Stassen	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/26/an-open-letter-to-america%e2%80%99s-christian-zionists-from-david-p-gushee-and-glen-h-stassen/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/26/an-open-letter-to-america%e2%80%99s-christian-zionists-from-david-p-gushee-and-glen-h-stassen/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2011 11:27:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/26/an-open-letter-to-america%e2%80%99s-christian-zionists-from-david-p-gushee-and-glen-h-stassen/#comment-3644</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2011 11:27:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4175#comment-3644</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It seems to me that mainstream evangelicals have always tended to read the Bible politically, so this looks like a marked retreat from that way of seeing it. The Bible is not so much about God&#039;s relationship with various groups who have political identities (&quot;We will leave it to God to sort out with the Jewish people of the modern state of Israel the very complex terms of his covenant with them&quot;) but is now about &quot;God’s clearly revealed moral will,&quot; which is universal.

All the talk about Abraham&#039;s many children and the fact that Israel never had full control of the land is an attempt to discredit the political messages that evangelicals have been taking from the bible, but by itself it it puts forward no positive vision of how God wants the world to be organized (which used to include the idea that peace would come after some type of cataclysm). It is now rather vague calls for universal peace and justice which becomes the basis for a new political vision that displaces everything else. 

Along similar lines one sees attempts to try to align American evangelicals with political movements more concerned with promoting social justice and less with those seeking to maintain conservative christian social values. Both, it seems to me, tend to minimize Christianity itself as a political identity and instead advance it as a personal mandate to promote &quot;God&#039;s clearly revealed moral will.&quot; These have succeed mostly with the younger generation of evangelicals - and I suspect the same will be true here.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It seems to me that mainstream evangelicals have always tended to read the Bible politically, so this looks like a marked retreat from that way of seeing it. The Bible is not so much about God&#8217;s relationship with various groups who have political identities (&#8220;We will leave it to God to sort out with the Jewish people of the modern state of Israel the very complex terms of his covenant with them&#8221;) but is now about &#8220;God’s clearly revealed moral will,&#8221; which is universal.</p>
<p>All the talk about Abraham&#8217;s many children and the fact that Israel never had full control of the land is an attempt to discredit the political messages that evangelicals have been taking from the bible, but by itself it it puts forward no positive vision of how God wants the world to be organized (which used to include the idea that peace would come after some type of cataclysm). It is now rather vague calls for universal peace and justice which becomes the basis for a new political vision that displaces everything else. </p>
<p>Along similar lines one sees attempts to try to align American evangelicals with political movements more concerned with promoting social justice and less with those seeking to maintain conservative christian social values. Both, it seems to me, tend to minimize Christianity itself as a political identity and instead advance it as a personal mandate to promote &#8220;God&#8217;s clearly revealed moral will.&#8221; These have succeed mostly with the younger generation of evangelicals &#8211; and I suspect the same will be true here.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
