<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Could Louis Jacobs have been accepted?	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/03/could-louis-jacobs-have-been-accepted/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/03/could-louis-jacobs-have-been-accepted/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2013 05:33:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/03/could-louis-jacobs-have-been-accepted/#comment-8006</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2013 05:33:32 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6080#comment-8006</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/03/could-louis-jacobs-have-been-accepted/#comment-8005&quot;&gt;Zach Mann&lt;/a&gt;.

Thank you for the corrections. Can you find the Jacob&#039;s citation and praise of Agus?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/03/could-louis-jacobs-have-been-accepted/#comment-8005">Zach Mann</a>.</p>
<p>Thank you for the corrections. Can you find the Jacob&#8217;s citation and praise of Agus?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Zach Mann		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/03/could-louis-jacobs-have-been-accepted/#comment-8005</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Zach Mann]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2013 05:30:20 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6080#comment-8005</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Absolutely fascinating post, Professor Brill.  I never came across any connection between Agus and Seidel in my research, but it sounds like a particularly fruitful one to pursue, so thank you.  I hesitate to nitpick, but you write above that both Agus and Bokser transferred to JTS, but this is only true of Bokser.  Agus received his semikha from Moshe Soloveitchik and remained an Orthodox rabbi (at least on paper) until 1945-1946.  Incidentally, Agus took a pulpit in Chicago at the behest of Bernard Revel in 1940-1941 and it was there that he most likely came under the influence of Solomon Goldman.  Goldman&#039;s influence probably played a large part in inspiring Agus to join the Rabbinical Assembly in 1945 and his decision to reorganize his congregation in Dayton, Ohio, under Conservative auspices. Agus also felt very close to Bernard Revel but did not see eye-to-eye with Samuel Belkin, so Revel&#039;s passing may have eased Agus&#039; conscience and allowed him to make the leap officially.  Agus&#039; closeness to Goldman and the fact that, as Leo Jung&#039;s research assistant, he studied the question of the halakhic necessity of mekhitza, help explain Agus&#039; deep involvement with the various mekhitza cases and the Responsum on the Sabbath, and make them that much more fraught with meaning.  If Agus played such an important role in defining Conservative Judaism at midcentury in contradistinction to Orthodoxy, it was in part because of this background, and because he was trained in philosophy and theology which was fairly uncommon at the time, so he was particularly interested in articulating the difference between Orthodoxy and Conservatism on the level of ideas.  (He also played an important role in making a Conservative audience aware of Orthodox theologians they might not have otherwise - R&#039; Kook, as you mention, and (J.D.) Soloveitchik, in addition to helping to introduce English audiences to Rosenzweig and Buber.)  To the subject of your post, defining the one necessarily involved defining the other, so Agus needed to define &quot;Orthodoxy&quot; for the purposes of rejecting it - he usually equated it with acceptance of Biblical &quot;literalism,&quot; but his break with Orthodoxy had just as much if not more to do with halakhic reasoning and a perceived lack of intellectual honesty within Orthodoxy than attitudes towards Biblical criticism in particular. Not that I am in any way implying you argue otherwise.  Oh - and many years later, Louis Jacobs saw Agus as a like-minded thinker who shared his own &quot;Liberal Supernaturalism.&quot;]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Absolutely fascinating post, Professor Brill.  I never came across any connection between Agus and Seidel in my research, but it sounds like a particularly fruitful one to pursue, so thank you.  I hesitate to nitpick, but you write above that both Agus and Bokser transferred to JTS, but this is only true of Bokser.  Agus received his semikha from Moshe Soloveitchik and remained an Orthodox rabbi (at least on paper) until 1945-1946.  Incidentally, Agus took a pulpit in Chicago at the behest of Bernard Revel in 1940-1941 and it was there that he most likely came under the influence of Solomon Goldman.  Goldman&#8217;s influence probably played a large part in inspiring Agus to join the Rabbinical Assembly in 1945 and his decision to reorganize his congregation in Dayton, Ohio, under Conservative auspices. Agus also felt very close to Bernard Revel but did not see eye-to-eye with Samuel Belkin, so Revel&#8217;s passing may have eased Agus&#8217; conscience and allowed him to make the leap officially.  Agus&#8217; closeness to Goldman and the fact that, as Leo Jung&#8217;s research assistant, he studied the question of the halakhic necessity of mekhitza, help explain Agus&#8217; deep involvement with the various mekhitza cases and the Responsum on the Sabbath, and make them that much more fraught with meaning.  If Agus played such an important role in defining Conservative Judaism at midcentury in contradistinction to Orthodoxy, it was in part because of this background, and because he was trained in philosophy and theology which was fairly uncommon at the time, so he was particularly interested in articulating the difference between Orthodoxy and Conservatism on the level of ideas.  (He also played an important role in making a Conservative audience aware of Orthodox theologians they might not have otherwise &#8211; R&#8217; Kook, as you mention, and (J.D.) Soloveitchik, in addition to helping to introduce English audiences to Rosenzweig and Buber.)  To the subject of your post, defining the one necessarily involved defining the other, so Agus needed to define &#8220;Orthodoxy&#8221; for the purposes of rejecting it &#8211; he usually equated it with acceptance of Biblical &#8220;literalism,&#8221; but his break with Orthodoxy had just as much if not more to do with halakhic reasoning and a perceived lack of intellectual honesty within Orthodoxy than attitudes towards Biblical criticism in particular. Not that I am in any way implying you argue otherwise.  Oh &#8211; and many years later, Louis Jacobs saw Agus as a like-minded thinker who shared his own &#8220;Liberal Supernaturalism.&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Paul Shaviv		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/03/could-louis-jacobs-have-been-accepted/#comment-7964</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Paul Shaviv]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2013 02:20:39 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6080#comment-7964</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/03/could-louis-jacobs-have-been-accepted/#comment-7957&quot;&gt;Ben Elton&lt;/a&gt;.

I take your point about LJ&#039;s personality - but he was far more blunt in print than (generally) in public speech, and it is (I believe) certainly the case that he was shy. &quot;Humble&quot;? -- maybe not.  But he was not a rabble-rousing orator by any means, and I still think that the story would have been different had he had a more extrovert personality. Another factor worth considering is his northern, Manchester background; I think that he had a characteristically North-of-England bluntness, and I think that the Manchester tradition of non-conformism also figured in the whole picture of his personality and style.
Regarding Steve Bayme&#039;s comment (below) about LJ&#039;s religious belief / status in 1973 -- by that time the controversy was over bar the shouting, and he had -- in the views of some -- been backed into a corner which required him to defend a series of views that he might not otherwise have made the focus of his life.  He was certainly not Reform; not only was he a convinced defender of the halakhic system, but he turned down opportunities to become the head of the Leo Baeck College in London because he did not want to identify with their theology.  &#039;Conservative&#039;?  What did the term mean in London at that time?  As he maintained, and has has been discussed, the old United Synagogue (UK) spanned the USA dividing line between Left-wing Orthodox and right-wing Conservative.  (For old Anglo-Jews like myself, who remembers the Rev. Isaac Livingstone, minister of the Golders Green Synagogue for decades, who would proudly carry his umbrella to and from shul on shabbat morning along an eruv-less GG Road? Or Rev. Leslie Hardman of Hendon Synagogue; or Saul Amias of Edgware?  All legendary pastoral leaders -- but hardly Orthodox by any present-day definition.

Enough of memory lane -- sorry, Alan, for taking the comments away from your focus!]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/03/could-louis-jacobs-have-been-accepted/#comment-7957">Ben Elton</a>.</p>
<p>I take your point about LJ&#8217;s personality &#8211; but he was far more blunt in print than (generally) in public speech, and it is (I believe) certainly the case that he was shy. &#8220;Humble&#8221;? &#8212; maybe not.  But he was not a rabble-rousing orator by any means, and I still think that the story would have been different had he had a more extrovert personality. Another factor worth considering is his northern, Manchester background; I think that he had a characteristically North-of-England bluntness, and I think that the Manchester tradition of non-conformism also figured in the whole picture of his personality and style.<br />
Regarding Steve Bayme&#8217;s comment (below) about LJ&#8217;s religious belief / status in 1973 &#8212; by that time the controversy was over bar the shouting, and he had &#8212; in the views of some &#8212; been backed into a corner which required him to defend a series of views that he might not otherwise have made the focus of his life.  He was certainly not Reform; not only was he a convinced defender of the halakhic system, but he turned down opportunities to become the head of the Leo Baeck College in London because he did not want to identify with their theology.  &#8216;Conservative&#8217;?  What did the term mean in London at that time?  As he maintained, and has has been discussed, the old United Synagogue (UK) spanned the USA dividing line between Left-wing Orthodox and right-wing Conservative.  (For old Anglo-Jews like myself, who remembers the Rev. Isaac Livingstone, minister of the Golders Green Synagogue for decades, who would proudly carry his umbrella to and from shul on shabbat morning along an eruv-less GG Road? Or Rev. Leslie Hardman of Hendon Synagogue; or Saul Amias of Edgware?  All legendary pastoral leaders &#8212; but hardly Orthodox by any present-day definition.</p>
<p>Enough of memory lane &#8212; sorry, Alan, for taking the comments away from your focus!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/03/could-louis-jacobs-have-been-accepted/#comment-7963</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2013 20:50:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6080#comment-7963</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/03/could-louis-jacobs-have-been-accepted/#comment-7962&quot;&gt;Shaya&lt;/a&gt;.

Shaya- yes, I know. But you may be interested in reading the book in English. It is on the VBM list serve - I have subscribed for the entire course. It is a good read but does not really get too near the fundamental problems. Rather, it introduced the issues in a safe religious context.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/03/could-louis-jacobs-have-been-accepted/#comment-7962">Shaya</a>.</p>
<p>Shaya- yes, I know. But you may be interested in reading the book in English. It is on the VBM list serve &#8211; I have subscribed for the entire course. It is a good read but does not really get too near the fundamental problems. Rather, it introduced the issues in a safe religious context.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Shaya		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/03/could-louis-jacobs-have-been-accepted/#comment-7962</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shaya]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2013 20:44:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6080#comment-7962</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Rabbi brill, you might want to note Rav Amnon bazak&#039;s new book on bible critism from the Har Etzion school. He just advertised it on his facebook today (&quot;Ad Hayom Hazeh&quot; , Yediot Sfarim press).]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rabbi brill, you might want to note Rav Amnon bazak&#8217;s new book on bible critism from the Har Etzion school. He just advertised it on his facebook today (&#8220;Ad Hayom Hazeh&#8221; , Yediot Sfarim press).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Steven Bayme		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/03/could-louis-jacobs-have-been-accepted/#comment-7961</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Steven Bayme]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2013 20:07:42 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6080#comment-7961</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Alan-First-rate piece and analysis. Surprising degree of evolution in Jacobs’s thinking.
 
 In the meantime, for what they are worth are some comments and reactions:
 
 
 1)      Whether you are correct in characterizing Agus’s invoking of Rosenzweig as “falsely” is somewhat questionable.  Rosenzweig’s citation here of Wellhausen and the Samaritan text suggest he may well have been referencing historical criticism. Certainly an entire generation, if not two, of Conservative rabbis understood Rosenzweig as legitimating historical criticism while revering the authority of the text as the one we have. Is there a Rosenzweig scholar since Agus who took issue with this interpretation of Rosenzweig?
 
 2)      The core of Jacobs’s quest is for an Orthodoxy that is intellectually compelling. Biblical criticism remains central to that quest. If one claims that acceptance of Biblical criticism crosses a line that places you outside the pale of Orthodoxy, you then have to ask how should the Orthodox Jew relate to questions of multiple sources, anachronisms, and historical error, to say nothing of morally troubling episodes. No shortage of these in either last week’s parshiot or this week’s. What troubles me is that in the Orthodoxy of today people are faithfully attending shul and never raising questions of this sort, even when they are obvious-e.g. on a moral level the war against the Midianites and on an historical level the Yair ben Menashe affair.
 
 3)      The Jacobs affair one would think would have stirred greater controversy here in the States. It appears to have caused barely a ripple. In 1965 the late Charles Liebman predicted that Modern Orthodoxy would soon be torn apart over Biblical criticism. Instead we have seen the triumph of the ArtScroll and its pathetic inability to distinguish peshat and derash. The closest we came to  an American parallel is probably the 1966 Greenberg/Lichtenstein debate, but even there the entire focus-both contemporaneously and in historical memory- was over negiah and premarital intimacy. Greenberg’s comments on Biblical criticism in the initial interview elicited virtually no reaction or comment.
 
 4)      If one accepts your conclusion, that Jacobs indeed was Conservative if not Reform by 1973, the question becomes one of the limits of Orthodox dissent and of rabbinic authority. Does intellectual honesty compel one to shed one’s Orthodoxy or can Orthodoxy tolerate some level of deviant belief in the light of intellectually compelling evidence and argument? Given the absence generally of Conservative communities where these questions are taken seriously (Hadar is a noteworthy exception), is it unacceptable to declare oneself an Orthodox Jew by practice who chooses, quite logically, to identify with an Orthodox community? Last, Orthodoxy has never drawn strict lines to its theological right (pace David Berger). Can it not handle questions on its Left by saying, “legitimate questions, Orthodox Jews have always believed otherwise, but if we take modern culture seriously, we cannot afford to ignore findings of modern scholarship; that is what distinguishes us from the Haredi world”?
 
 5)      I was fascinated by your description of Rabbi Seidel. Interesting that his name has disappeared from the official histories of YU.
 
 
 
 Again, really interesting paper. Would love to see and read more.
 
 
 
 Best,
 
 Stevce
 
 Steven Bayme, Ph.D
 National Director
 William Petschek Contemporary Jewish Life Department
]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Alan-First-rate piece and analysis. Surprising degree of evolution in Jacobs’s thinking.</p>
<p> In the meantime, for what they are worth are some comments and reactions:</p>
<p> 1)      Whether you are correct in characterizing Agus’s invoking of Rosenzweig as “falsely” is somewhat questionable.  Rosenzweig’s citation here of Wellhausen and the Samaritan text suggest he may well have been referencing historical criticism. Certainly an entire generation, if not two, of Conservative rabbis understood Rosenzweig as legitimating historical criticism while revering the authority of the text as the one we have. Is there a Rosenzweig scholar since Agus who took issue with this interpretation of Rosenzweig?</p>
<p> 2)      The core of Jacobs’s quest is for an Orthodoxy that is intellectually compelling. Biblical criticism remains central to that quest. If one claims that acceptance of Biblical criticism crosses a line that places you outside the pale of Orthodoxy, you then have to ask how should the Orthodox Jew relate to questions of multiple sources, anachronisms, and historical error, to say nothing of morally troubling episodes. No shortage of these in either last week’s parshiot or this week’s. What troubles me is that in the Orthodoxy of today people are faithfully attending shul and never raising questions of this sort, even when they are obvious-e.g. on a moral level the war against the Midianites and on an historical level the Yair ben Menashe affair.</p>
<p> 3)      The Jacobs affair one would think would have stirred greater controversy here in the States. It appears to have caused barely a ripple. In 1965 the late Charles Liebman predicted that Modern Orthodoxy would soon be torn apart over Biblical criticism. Instead we have seen the triumph of the ArtScroll and its pathetic inability to distinguish peshat and derash. The closest we came to  an American parallel is probably the 1966 Greenberg/Lichtenstein debate, but even there the entire focus-both contemporaneously and in historical memory- was over negiah and premarital intimacy. Greenberg’s comments on Biblical criticism in the initial interview elicited virtually no reaction or comment.</p>
<p> 4)      If one accepts your conclusion, that Jacobs indeed was Conservative if not Reform by 1973, the question becomes one of the limits of Orthodox dissent and of rabbinic authority. Does intellectual honesty compel one to shed one’s Orthodoxy or can Orthodoxy tolerate some level of deviant belief in the light of intellectually compelling evidence and argument? Given the absence generally of Conservative communities where these questions are taken seriously (Hadar is a noteworthy exception), is it unacceptable to declare oneself an Orthodox Jew by practice who chooses, quite logically, to identify with an Orthodox community? Last, Orthodoxy has never drawn strict lines to its theological right (pace David Berger). Can it not handle questions on its Left by saying, “legitimate questions, Orthodox Jews have always believed otherwise, but if we take modern culture seriously, we cannot afford to ignore findings of modern scholarship; that is what distinguishes us from the Haredi world”?</p>
<p> 5)      I was fascinated by your description of Rabbi Seidel. Interesting that his name has disappeared from the official histories of YU.</p>
<p> Again, really interesting paper. Would love to see and read more.</p>
<p> Best,</p>
<p> Stevce</p>
<p> Steven Bayme, Ph.D<br />
 National Director<br />
 William Petschek Contemporary Jewish Life Department</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/03/could-louis-jacobs-have-been-accepted/#comment-7959</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2013 18:23:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6080#comment-7959</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/03/could-louis-jacobs-have-been-accepted/#comment-7943&quot;&gt;moshe&lt;/a&gt;.

I am sorry, but no. I wanted to outline the theological dividing lines not those who tried to respond with schoalrship. He was not received in scholarly circles but was highly praised in Mizrachi circles.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/03/could-louis-jacobs-have-been-accepted/#comment-7943">moshe</a>.</p>
<p>I am sorry, but no. I wanted to outline the theological dividing lines not those who tried to respond with schoalrship. He was not received in scholarly circles but was highly praised in Mizrachi circles.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/03/could-louis-jacobs-have-been-accepted/#comment-7958</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2013 18:14:46 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6080#comment-7958</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/03/could-louis-jacobs-have-been-accepted/#comment-7957&quot;&gt;Ben Elton&lt;/a&gt;.

I removed from the blog version the following below that was in the original paper. My question was about his theology not about Rabbi Brodie or the United Synagogue. 
And as I wrote in the post &quot;Some of these [latter] views were already expressed orally since 1958, and he was in conversation with the NY JTSA to become part of their rabbinical faculty.&quot; I was not doing a history between looking at the theological contours.

1.	Orthodox and Liberalism
Liberal Christianity, broadly speaking , is an undogmatic method of understanding God through the use of scripture by applying the same modern hermeneutics used to understand any ancient writings.  Liberal Christianity does not claim to be a belief structure, and as such is not dependent upon any Church dogma or creedal statements. The word liberal in liberal Christianity denotes a characteristic willingness to interpret scripture without any preconceived notion of inerrancy of scripture or the correctness of Church dogma

The theology of liberal Christianity was prominent in the Biblical criticism of the 19th and 20th centuries. The Bible is non-propositional. This means that the Bible is not considered a collection of factual statements, but instead an anthology that documents the human authors&#039; beliefs and feelings about God at the time of its writing—within a historical or cultural context. Bible are metaphorical or ‘myth based’.
Higher critics, such as Johann Eichhorn and David Strauss, denied the inspiration and inerrancy of the Bible. Moses didn’t write the Pentateuch Most famous theologians of the  20th century are Bultman and Tillich “Liberalism at its best is more likely to say, ‘We certainly ought to honor the richness of the Christian past and appreciate the vast contribution it makes to our lives, but finally we must live by our best modern conclusions.  

Orthodox theology, broadly speaking , is a dogmatic method of understanding God through the reading of scripture  with a special hermeneutic, different than the way one reads any ancient writings. Texts are read through tradition, authorial bodies, and via prior understandings. Orthodoxy has a clear belief structure dependent upon any dogma and creedal statements. The word Orthodox means a characteristic unwillingness to interpret scripture without any consideration of the correctness of dogma. Perceived changes to the tradition are due to God’s revelation not contingent history

Orthodox theology when asked  “When the consensus of the best contemporary minds differs markedly from the most precious teachings of the past, which do we follow?  To which do we give primary allegiance, the past or the present?” The orthodox answer is always that  “We ought to listen to the hypotheses of the present and take from them what we can, but ultimately the truth has been given to us in the past, and the acceptance of that is our ultimate obligation.  Everything the contemporary world might say must be judged by its conformity to biblical revelation.”  Important orthodox theologians include Karl Barth, The Niebuhrs, Cardinal Ratzinger, and John Henry Newman.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/03/could-louis-jacobs-have-been-accepted/#comment-7957">Ben Elton</a>.</p>
<p>I removed from the blog version the following below that was in the original paper. My question was about his theology not about Rabbi Brodie or the United Synagogue.<br />
And as I wrote in the post &#8220;Some of these [latter] views were already expressed orally since 1958, and he was in conversation with the NY JTSA to become part of their rabbinical faculty.&#8221; I was not doing a history between looking at the theological contours.</p>
<p>1.	Orthodox and Liberalism<br />
Liberal Christianity, broadly speaking , is an undogmatic method of understanding God through the use of scripture by applying the same modern hermeneutics used to understand any ancient writings.  Liberal Christianity does not claim to be a belief structure, and as such is not dependent upon any Church dogma or creedal statements. The word liberal in liberal Christianity denotes a characteristic willingness to interpret scripture without any preconceived notion of inerrancy of scripture or the correctness of Church dogma</p>
<p>The theology of liberal Christianity was prominent in the Biblical criticism of the 19th and 20th centuries. The Bible is non-propositional. This means that the Bible is not considered a collection of factual statements, but instead an anthology that documents the human authors&#8217; beliefs and feelings about God at the time of its writing—within a historical or cultural context. Bible are metaphorical or ‘myth based’.<br />
Higher critics, such as Johann Eichhorn and David Strauss, denied the inspiration and inerrancy of the Bible. Moses didn’t write the Pentateuch Most famous theologians of the  20th century are Bultman and Tillich “Liberalism at its best is more likely to say, ‘We certainly ought to honor the richness of the Christian past and appreciate the vast contribution it makes to our lives, but finally we must live by our best modern conclusions.  </p>
<p>Orthodox theology, broadly speaking , is a dogmatic method of understanding God through the reading of scripture  with a special hermeneutic, different than the way one reads any ancient writings. Texts are read through tradition, authorial bodies, and via prior understandings. Orthodoxy has a clear belief structure dependent upon any dogma and creedal statements. The word Orthodox means a characteristic unwillingness to interpret scripture without any consideration of the correctness of dogma. Perceived changes to the tradition are due to God’s revelation not contingent history</p>
<p>Orthodox theology when asked  “When the consensus of the best contemporary minds differs markedly from the most precious teachings of the past, which do we follow?  To which do we give primary allegiance, the past or the present?” The orthodox answer is always that  “We ought to listen to the hypotheses of the present and take from them what we can, but ultimately the truth has been given to us in the past, and the acceptance of that is our ultimate obligation.  Everything the contemporary world might say must be judged by its conformity to biblical revelation.”  Important orthodox theologians include Karl Barth, The Niebuhrs, Cardinal Ratzinger, and John Henry Newman.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Ben Elton		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/03/could-louis-jacobs-have-been-accepted/#comment-7957</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Elton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2013 18:02:31 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6080#comment-7957</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I disagree that that the moment of LJ&#039;s separation from Orthodoxy was 1964-5. We Have Reason to Believe (1957) made statements about Sefer Daniel that offended Grunfeld but Epstein, Cohen and Brodie would have agreed with. However, the latter disagreed sharply about what LJ said about the Pentateuch in WHRTB. It was those comments which led to LJ&#039;s exclusion from Anglo-Orthodoxy in 1959, when he was denied the Principalship of Jews&#039; College. That process was completed in 1964 with the foundation of the New London Synagogue, but it began well before.

Some revision needs to be done about the view of LJ as shy and humble. In his reviews, for example of Lamm&#039;s &#039;Faith and Doubt&#039;, he is very strident, even arrogant. He was fond of the phrase &#039;no thinking person&#039; would disagree with him. Lamm is a thinking person!]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I disagree that that the moment of LJ&#8217;s separation from Orthodoxy was 1964-5. We Have Reason to Believe (1957) made statements about Sefer Daniel that offended Grunfeld but Epstein, Cohen and Brodie would have agreed with. However, the latter disagreed sharply about what LJ said about the Pentateuch in WHRTB. It was those comments which led to LJ&#8217;s exclusion from Anglo-Orthodoxy in 1959, when he was denied the Principalship of Jews&#8217; College. That process was completed in 1964 with the foundation of the New London Synagogue, but it began well before.</p>
<p>Some revision needs to be done about the view of LJ as shy and humble. In his reviews, for example of Lamm&#8217;s &#8216;Faith and Doubt&#8217;, he is very strident, even arrogant. He was fond of the phrase &#8216;no thinking person&#8217; would disagree with him. Lamm is a thinking person!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Paul Shaviv		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/03/could-louis-jacobs-have-been-accepted/#comment-7952</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Paul Shaviv]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 07 Jul 2013 02:27:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6080#comment-7952</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In addition -- expanding on point #4 -- the lay leadership of the United Synagogue had changed.  When LJ was barred by Israel Brodie from the Principalship of Jews College, most of the J/Coll Board resigned -- representing the old Anglo-Jewish gentry.  (The college never recovered).  At roughly the samr time, leadership of the US passed from the &#039;gentry&#039; -- in this case, Ewen Montagu, who succeeded the legendary Sir Robert Waley Cohen - to the &#039;new&#039; community, represented by millionaire Sir Isaac Wolfson (himself observant).  Despite, perhaps, what I wrote above, the old-style leaders - out of touch with the community - while always careful to respect the Orthodoxy of the clergy (Robert Waley Cohen vs C R Hertz, and Dayan Abramsky), were essentially gentlemen, and held that the treatment of Louis Jacobs had &#039;not been cricket&#039;.  

None of this bears on the issue of whether LJ would have been able to be theologically &#039;accepted&#039;; it really addresses the question of whether he could have remained in the pulpit of the United Synagogue.  For what it&#039;s worth, Immanuel Jakobovits said to me that if he had been C R at the time, &quot;the Jacobs affair would never have been allowed to come to [this]&quot;.  However, a recent work by Meir Persoff records extracts from LJ&#039;s diary which indicate unsuccessful &#039;reaching out&#039; by IJ before taking up office.

Finally - LJ&#039;s personality -- shy, humble, academic - was also a factor.  He was not a fiery orator, and he did not seek to be a leader of a new movement - he saw himself as genuinely Orthodox (&quot;Minhag Anglia&quot;). Had he have had a more outgoing personality, the outcome(s) may also have been different.

The whole Jacobs affair was a turning point in Anglo-Jewry. Personally - I think it was catastrophic.  Many people think the opposite.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In addition &#8212; expanding on point #4 &#8212; the lay leadership of the United Synagogue had changed.  When LJ was barred by Israel Brodie from the Principalship of Jews College, most of the J/Coll Board resigned &#8212; representing the old Anglo-Jewish gentry.  (The college never recovered).  At roughly the samr time, leadership of the US passed from the &#8216;gentry&#8217; &#8212; in this case, Ewen Montagu, who succeeded the legendary Sir Robert Waley Cohen &#8211; to the &#8216;new&#8217; community, represented by millionaire Sir Isaac Wolfson (himself observant).  Despite, perhaps, what I wrote above, the old-style leaders &#8211; out of touch with the community &#8211; while always careful to respect the Orthodoxy of the clergy (Robert Waley Cohen vs C R Hertz, and Dayan Abramsky), were essentially gentlemen, and held that the treatment of Louis Jacobs had &#8216;not been cricket&#8217;.  </p>
<p>None of this bears on the issue of whether LJ would have been able to be theologically &#8216;accepted&#8217;; it really addresses the question of whether he could have remained in the pulpit of the United Synagogue.  For what it&#8217;s worth, Immanuel Jakobovits said to me that if he had been C R at the time, &#8220;the Jacobs affair would never have been allowed to come to [this]&#8221;.  However, a recent work by Meir Persoff records extracts from LJ&#8217;s diary which indicate unsuccessful &#8216;reaching out&#8217; by IJ before taking up office.</p>
<p>Finally &#8211; LJ&#8217;s personality &#8212; shy, humble, academic &#8211; was also a factor.  He was not a fiery orator, and he did not seek to be a leader of a new movement &#8211; he saw himself as genuinely Orthodox (&#8220;Minhag Anglia&#8221;). Had he have had a more outgoing personality, the outcome(s) may also have been different.</p>
<p>The whole Jacobs affair was a turning point in Anglo-Jewry. Personally &#8211; I think it was catastrophic.  Many people think the opposite.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Paul Shaviv		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/03/could-louis-jacobs-have-been-accepted/#comment-7948</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Paul Shaviv]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2013 23:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6080#comment-7948</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thank you for an interesting post.  May I suggest that missing here (although perhaps not in the longer paper) is the British context - and Louis Jacobs was VERY British!   The United Synagogue itself was founded as a Jewish version of the Anglican Church, and had many Anglican characterisitics until 1967 (part the Six Day War, part the accession of Lord Jakobovits).  Factors which play into this discussion may include (but are not limited to):

1. LJ himself, in one of his memoirs, recognises that his position would eventually have become untenable given the changes (the Artscroll revolution) which were on the horizon in UK Orthodoxy as elsewhere. (Compare the United Synagogue rabbinate today with that of, say, 1965).
2.  There is no doubt that there were other Rabbis and &#039;Ministers&#039; occupying pulpits in the US who were just as radical in their theology as LJ - especially in the New West End Synagogue, which was a &#039;society&#039; shul long regarded as out of the mainstream.
3.  The great fear of the Beth Din was that LJ was regarded as a contender for the &#039;glittering prizes&#039; of Anglo-Jewry -- the Principalship of Jews College and perhaps the Chief Rabbinate.  They might have been prepared to leave him at the NWE, out of harm&#039;s way -- but they could not risk him in either of those two key positions.  They also feared his possible influence on the yeshivah world, as LJ was wholly a product of Manchester Yeshivah and Gateshead Kollel -- he did not go to university until he came to London (where his first post was at &#039;Munk&#039;s&#039; - the Breuer&#039;s of London).  At the famous meeting of rabbis around the time of the &quot;affair&quot;, called by Israel Brodie, Brodie made a point of saying to the Gateshead rabbanim (who turned out, exceptionally, to support Brodie) &quot;This man comes from among you, not from us&quot;.
4.  The lay leadership of the US have a long, British tradition of abdicating all leadership and decision-making to the Beth Din; so Sir Isaac Wolfson went along with the &#039;excommunication&#039;.
5.  The question of whether his theology (a defence of non-fundamentalist halachic observance) would have been defensible or viable in the Anglo-Jewish community is moot, because Anglo-Jewry has never had any interest in theology!  Other than LJ, (and in a different way, and more recently, Lord Sacks) the UK is something of a desert for Judaism.  Jews College was never the incubator of thinkers and scholars that YU or JTS became, and Jewish Studies at Universities in the UK exist in total isolation from the community, most of whom are unaware that such faculties exist!

Anyway -- shabbat is coming......]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thank you for an interesting post.  May I suggest that missing here (although perhaps not in the longer paper) is the British context &#8211; and Louis Jacobs was VERY British!   The United Synagogue itself was founded as a Jewish version of the Anglican Church, and had many Anglican characterisitics until 1967 (part the Six Day War, part the accession of Lord Jakobovits).  Factors which play into this discussion may include (but are not limited to):</p>
<p>1. LJ himself, in one of his memoirs, recognises that his position would eventually have become untenable given the changes (the Artscroll revolution) which were on the horizon in UK Orthodoxy as elsewhere. (Compare the United Synagogue rabbinate today with that of, say, 1965).<br />
2.  There is no doubt that there were other Rabbis and &#8216;Ministers&#8217; occupying pulpits in the US who were just as radical in their theology as LJ &#8211; especially in the New West End Synagogue, which was a &#8216;society&#8217; shul long regarded as out of the mainstream.<br />
3.  The great fear of the Beth Din was that LJ was regarded as a contender for the &#8216;glittering prizes&#8217; of Anglo-Jewry &#8212; the Principalship of Jews College and perhaps the Chief Rabbinate.  They might have been prepared to leave him at the NWE, out of harm&#8217;s way &#8212; but they could not risk him in either of those two key positions.  They also feared his possible influence on the yeshivah world, as LJ was wholly a product of Manchester Yeshivah and Gateshead Kollel &#8212; he did not go to university until he came to London (where his first post was at &#8216;Munk&#8217;s&#8217; &#8211; the Breuer&#8217;s of London).  At the famous meeting of rabbis around the time of the &#8220;affair&#8221;, called by Israel Brodie, Brodie made a point of saying to the Gateshead rabbanim (who turned out, exceptionally, to support Brodie) &#8220;This man comes from among you, not from us&#8221;.<br />
4.  The lay leadership of the US have a long, British tradition of abdicating all leadership and decision-making to the Beth Din; so Sir Isaac Wolfson went along with the &#8216;excommunication&#8217;.<br />
5.  The question of whether his theology (a defence of non-fundamentalist halachic observance) would have been defensible or viable in the Anglo-Jewish community is moot, because Anglo-Jewry has never had any interest in theology!  Other than LJ, (and in a different way, and more recently, Lord Sacks) the UK is something of a desert for Judaism.  Jews College was never the incubator of thinkers and scholars that YU or JTS became, and Jewish Studies at Universities in the UK exist in total isolation from the community, most of whom are unaware that such faculties exist!</p>
<p>Anyway &#8212; shabbat is coming&#8230;&#8230;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: e. pruzhaner (@pruzhaner)		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/03/could-louis-jacobs-have-been-accepted/#comment-7944</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[e. pruzhaner (@pruzhaner)]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2013 04:52:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6080#comment-7944</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[ר&#039; חיים הירשענזאהן, מלכי בקדש ב&#039; עמ&#039; 216: אמנם נורא הוא המצב של העוסקים בבקורת התנ״ך וביחוד בהחלק הנקרא אצלם בשם ״בקורת הגבוה״, בונים להם מגדל ושמים בשמים פיהם, כופרים בתורה שלא מדעת תורה, ואין חכמה ואין עצה ואין תבונה לטעון להכופר בתורת עמו, כי הכופר בה לא עליה יחשב, ומה לו ולעמו]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ר&#8217; חיים הירשענזאהן, מלכי בקדש ב&#8217; עמ&#8217; 216: אמנם נורא הוא המצב של העוסקים בבקורת התנ״ך וביחוד בהחלק הנקרא אצלם בשם ״בקורת הגבוה״, בונים להם מגדל ושמים בשמים פיהם, כופרים בתורה שלא מדעת תורה, ואין חכמה ואין עצה ואין תבונה לטעון להכופר בתורת עמו, כי הכופר בה לא עליה יחשב, ומה לו ולעמו</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: moshe		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/03/could-louis-jacobs-have-been-accepted/#comment-7943</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[moshe]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2013 01:12:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6080#comment-7943</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In the full version, do you discuss at all the work of Hayyim Heller (1878-1960) and his reception by the scholarly world?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the full version, do you discuss at all the work of Hayyim Heller (1878-1960) and his reception by the scholarly world?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
