<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Suburban Religion: The Divine Commodity-Skye Jethani	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/27/the-divine-commodity-skye-jethani/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/27/the-divine-commodity-skye-jethani/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Dec 2010 09:44:59 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Jeff Wild		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/27/the-divine-commodity-skye-jethani/#comment-2228</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jeff Wild]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 26 Dec 2010 09:44:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1388#comment-2228</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Where do you suggest I find out more about Rav Dessler and Michtav Me’Eliyahu in English?
For some reason I didn&#039;t see the Feldheim &lt;i&gt;Strive for Truth!&lt;/i&gt; translation when I first searched. I assume that is a good place to start. Others?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Where do you suggest I find out more about Rav Dessler and Michtav Me’Eliyahu in English?<br />
For some reason I didn&#8217;t see the Feldheim <i>Strive for Truth!</i> translation when I first searched. I assume that is a good place to start. Others?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/27/the-divine-commodity-skye-jethani/#comment-1101</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2010 13:15:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1388#comment-1101</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I think that the underlying issue is that when popular religion loses the ability to critique (or simply refuses to critique) capitalist/ consumerist culture then it will end up mirroring it.

Above all else, consumerism has promoted the idea that you can buy a prefabricated identity by associating with a brand or a lifestyle. Modern religion has done something similar by mimicking the branding concept.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think that the underlying issue is that when popular religion loses the ability to critique (or simply refuses to critique) capitalist/ consumerist culture then it will end up mirroring it.</p>
<p>Above all else, consumerism has promoted the idea that you can buy a prefabricated identity by associating with a brand or a lifestyle. Modern religion has done something similar by mimicking the branding concept.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: H Sragow		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/27/the-divine-commodity-skye-jethani/#comment-1099</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[H Sragow]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2010 03:20:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1388#comment-1099</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Personally, I would be unsatisfied with a religion that confuses God and community;  excuses the moral lapses of the big donors; or sees its purpose as simply self-perpetuation.  But in the long-term, those characteristcs don&#039;t govern the triumph of one religious stream over another.  Rather, Darwin governs (or, if you prefer, marketing governs).  

The more pluralistic our society becomes, the more people will view religions (to say nothing of streams within a religion) as interchangeable.  That growing segment will not choose a religion on the basis of the substantive differences between the &quot;religious products&quot;; they discern few real distinctions.   Flashiness wins, ease of adoption wins, and the power of brand association wins.   

As religious institutions represent a smaller portion of the educational background of Americans, more will choose a religion (or choose no religion) on the basis of non-religious values.  Catholic school attendance, for example, has dropped by more than 50% over the last 30 years (see http://cara.georgetown.edu/bulletin/index.htm).  So I would say yes, if people are taught that they need a life coach, many of those students  will indeed want their religion to be a life coach.      

Whether this is &quot;good,&quot; and whether we can do anything about it, are entirely different questions.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Personally, I would be unsatisfied with a religion that confuses God and community;  excuses the moral lapses of the big donors; or sees its purpose as simply self-perpetuation.  But in the long-term, those characteristcs don&#8217;t govern the triumph of one religious stream over another.  Rather, Darwin governs (or, if you prefer, marketing governs).  </p>
<p>The more pluralistic our society becomes, the more people will view religions (to say nothing of streams within a religion) as interchangeable.  That growing segment will not choose a religion on the basis of the substantive differences between the &#8220;religious products&#8221;; they discern few real distinctions.   Flashiness wins, ease of adoption wins, and the power of brand association wins.   </p>
<p>As religious institutions represent a smaller portion of the educational background of Americans, more will choose a religion (or choose no religion) on the basis of non-religious values.  Catholic school attendance, for example, has dropped by more than 50% over the last 30 years (see <a href="http://cara.georgetown.edu/bulletin/index.htm" rel="nofollow ugc">http://cara.georgetown.edu/bulletin/index.htm</a>).  So I would say yes, if people are taught that they need a life coach, many of those students  will indeed want their religion to be a life coach.      </p>
<p>Whether this is &#8220;good,&#8221; and whether we can do anything about it, are entirely different questions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/27/the-divine-commodity-skye-jethani/#comment-1098</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2010 01:41:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1388#comment-1098</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/27/the-divine-commodity-skye-jethani/#comment-1096&quot;&gt;H Sragow&lt;/a&gt;.

Howie,
&lt;em&gt;the vast majority of people want religion-lite, &lt;/em&gt;

Is there any idea of needing to do anything? achieve anything? Is it Ok to confuse God and community? Is there anything one can do that would be not acceptable to do?
Rick Warren asks for commitment as soon you attend one service. Or is religion just a lifestyle coach?

Jonathan,
Which one should be tackled first? Why?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/27/the-divine-commodity-skye-jethani/#comment-1096">H Sragow</a>.</p>
<p>Howie,<br />
<em>the vast majority of people want religion-lite, </em></p>
<p>Is there any idea of needing to do anything? achieve anything? Is it Ok to confuse God and community? Is there anything one can do that would be not acceptable to do?<br />
Rick Warren asks for commitment as soon you attend one service. Or is religion just a lifestyle coach?</p>
<p>Jonathan,<br />
Which one should be tackled first? Why?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Jonathan Hirsch		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/27/the-divine-commodity-skye-jethani/#comment-1097</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jonathan Hirsch]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2010 01:35:36 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1388#comment-1097</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Has any Modern Orthodox leader /thinker attempted to address this issue in a meaningful way ?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Has any Modern Orthodox leader /thinker attempted to address this issue in a meaningful way ?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: H Sragow		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/27/the-divine-commodity-skye-jethani/#comment-1096</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[H Sragow]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 31 May 2010 04:26:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1388#comment-1096</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I don&#039;t think anyone has consciously set out to convert a religion into a &quot;cruise ship&quot; model.  But modern marketing techniques have been used in religious enterprises worldwide (sometimes consciously, some without realizing).  And no surprise -- religious enterprises utilizing concepts like demographic niche, social marketing, and multi-media experience  -- let&#039;s say, the ilk of Rick Warren&#039;s megachurch -- have been very successful in gathering adherents.  

Religious institutions slower to adopt these practices -- let&#039;s say mainline Protestant denominations  -- have lost membership.  

Certainly there are some people who want their religion to be a search -- and micro-marketers will serve that niche.  But if the vast majority of people want religion-lite, they will gravitate towards the clergy and institutions providing it.

Even those institutions providing a more sophisticated &quot;religious product&quot; to the niche that wants it, need to market themselves, and make sure their target audience knows where to purchase the product.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I don&#8217;t think anyone has consciously set out to convert a religion into a &#8220;cruise ship&#8221; model.  But modern marketing techniques have been used in religious enterprises worldwide (sometimes consciously, some without realizing).  And no surprise &#8212; religious enterprises utilizing concepts like demographic niche, social marketing, and multi-media experience  &#8212; let&#8217;s say, the ilk of Rick Warren&#8217;s megachurch &#8212; have been very successful in gathering adherents.  </p>
<p>Religious institutions slower to adopt these practices &#8212; let&#8217;s say mainline Protestant denominations  &#8212; have lost membership.  </p>
<p>Certainly there are some people who want their religion to be a search &#8212; and micro-marketers will serve that niche.  But if the vast majority of people want religion-lite, they will gravitate towards the clergy and institutions providing it.</p>
<p>Even those institutions providing a more sophisticated &#8220;religious product&#8221; to the niche that wants it, need to market themselves, and make sure their target audience knows where to purchase the product.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/27/the-divine-commodity-skye-jethani/#comment-1085</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 28 May 2010 18:27:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1388#comment-1085</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A little rant:  Whatever the sin of consumerism might be, it is not an essential feature of suburbia. Suburbs are these days are generally poorer  than the center. 
The same level of expenditure look different depending on the frame and economic class. When people are in the early stages of assimilation and  are  nouveau riche, the consumption looks particularly conspicuous. There is something about face to face societies that aggravates  this sort of complaint. Later in the acculturation cycle many   attempt a &quot;modest&quot; shabby chic  lifestyle. It takes even more money  to make your garden/life look untended, and &quot;natural.&quot;
One can see the class divisions and inequalities in income very clearly Pesach cruise time. One finds oneself next to some very heimish, simple guy that just put out $75000 to have his family together for  Pesach. If he had spent the money on a Jaguar everyone would be shushing &quot; take a look at...&quot; The complaint of too much gashmiyus is many times a complaint about inequality.
The idea that the correct way is the monastic, ascetic way doesn&#039;t travel well, because it frequently comes with the religious demand to give more money to the rabbinical class. But the Orthodox rich do support the rabbinical class, so somehow they are exempt.  Besides, the majority of Orthodox Jews struggle to pay for tuition and basic necessities. Does R. Schwartz have any clever ideas? 
In short, the musar that &quot;they&quot; are consuming  too much needs more context and elaboration.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A little rant:  Whatever the sin of consumerism might be, it is not an essential feature of suburbia. Suburbs are these days are generally poorer  than the center.<br />
The same level of expenditure look different depending on the frame and economic class. When people are in the early stages of assimilation and  are  nouveau riche, the consumption looks particularly conspicuous. There is something about face to face societies that aggravates  this sort of complaint. Later in the acculturation cycle many   attempt a &#8220;modest&#8221; shabby chic  lifestyle. It takes even more money  to make your garden/life look untended, and &#8220;natural.&#8221;<br />
One can see the class divisions and inequalities in income very clearly Pesach cruise time. One finds oneself next to some very heimish, simple guy that just put out $75000 to have his family together for  Pesach. If he had spent the money on a Jaguar everyone would be shushing &#8221; take a look at&#8230;&#8221; The complaint of too much gashmiyus is many times a complaint about inequality.<br />
The idea that the correct way is the monastic, ascetic way doesn&#8217;t travel well, because it frequently comes with the religious demand to give more money to the rabbinical class. But the Orthodox rich do support the rabbinical class, so somehow they are exempt.  Besides, the majority of Orthodox Jews struggle to pay for tuition and basic necessities. Does R. Schwartz have any clever ideas?<br />
In short, the musar that &#8220;they&#8221; are consuming  too much needs more context and elaboration.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
