<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Asking the Big Questions  today on a college campus	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/12/asking-the-big-questions-today-on-a-college-campus/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/12/asking-the-big-questions-today-on-a-college-campus/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2011 06:47:59 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Isaac Shalev (@rejewvenator)		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/12/asking-the-big-questions-today-on-a-college-campus/#comment-3628</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Isaac Shalev (@rejewvenator)]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2011 06:47:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4106#comment-3628</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Orthodox life radically narrows the arena within which human choice is permitted to function. The intention is to limit choices to only those options that are compatible with &quot;the good life.&quot; Paradoxically, however, part of living the good life appears to be making meaningful choices about what the life is. Orthodoxy&#039;s slow leak of meaning, and its preference for Torah uBaseball over Torah Umada, is at least in part related to the fact that Orthodoxy won&#039;t allow for the sanctification of new values or ideas that emerge from the interplay of Torah and Mada... so you may as well eat chulent, go to shul, have 4-6 kids, be a doctor/lawyer/banker and watch the Yankees.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Orthodox life radically narrows the arena within which human choice is permitted to function. The intention is to limit choices to only those options that are compatible with &#8220;the good life.&#8221; Paradoxically, however, part of living the good life appears to be making meaningful choices about what the life is. Orthodoxy&#8217;s slow leak of meaning, and its preference for Torah uBaseball over Torah Umada, is at least in part related to the fact that Orthodoxy won&#8217;t allow for the sanctification of new values or ideas that emerge from the interplay of Torah and Mada&#8230; so you may as well eat chulent, go to shul, have 4-6 kids, be a doctor/lawyer/banker and watch the Yankees.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: L		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/12/asking-the-big-questions-today-on-a-college-campus/#comment-3615</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[L]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 18 Sep 2011 11:49:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4106#comment-3615</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[If exploring issues of meaning doesn’t impact one’s life (present and future), then it’s simply a waste of time. The point is to figure out how to live according to what we take away from that exploration, to enable values to drive our actions. You quote im ain akshav, which is about doing, not sitting around thinking.

I agree that the particular philosophers you mention do not directly address the situations you’ve raised. However, a well-developed personal concept around life’s potential for meaning could inform issues that could arise out of these circumstances, and help one identify possibilities to inject meaning into the mundane.

Most obvious to me is your example of the parent-teacher meeting. Someone with a deep personal sense of meaning would, I hope, inquire not only about the child’s grades, but also about his moral/character development. 

Also clearly connected to issues of meaning are your dreams of buying the big house. The search for meaning won’t help you decide which mortgage to take out, though it should inform an internal conversation about whether the philosophical “good life” is one in which you buy that house, or one where you consider other alternatives. 

Even the carpool can be connected to issues of meaning. For example, developing one’s own sense around inclusivity might inform the composition of your carpool. As a collective activity, carpooling provides opportunities for values-based interactions with others. And a strong sense of personal meaning could certainly inform what you choose to talk about in the course of the ride. 

The problem is that we’ve divorced study and intellectual inquiry from lived meaning, reducing life to what’s most practical or convenient at the moment. You point out after college “other things take priority,” but we don’t need to let these other things edge out our deepest longings. Why succumb to this emptiness? There’s a hunger for more principles in with the daily practice/observance, and for spiritual leaders who can connect the two. That’s what the rabbi discussed in the post seems to be attempting to do.

As the next generation graduates to join extant communities and to create new ones, perhaps those who’ve been through programs like this will go on shape communities of meaning consonant with their values, and not simply accept existing “lifestyle enclaves.”]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If exploring issues of meaning doesn’t impact one’s life (present and future), then it’s simply a waste of time. The point is to figure out how to live according to what we take away from that exploration, to enable values to drive our actions. You quote im ain akshav, which is about doing, not sitting around thinking.</p>
<p>I agree that the particular philosophers you mention do not directly address the situations you’ve raised. However, a well-developed personal concept around life’s potential for meaning could inform issues that could arise out of these circumstances, and help one identify possibilities to inject meaning into the mundane.</p>
<p>Most obvious to me is your example of the parent-teacher meeting. Someone with a deep personal sense of meaning would, I hope, inquire not only about the child’s grades, but also about his moral/character development. </p>
<p>Also clearly connected to issues of meaning are your dreams of buying the big house. The search for meaning won’t help you decide which mortgage to take out, though it should inform an internal conversation about whether the philosophical “good life” is one in which you buy that house, or one where you consider other alternatives. </p>
<p>Even the carpool can be connected to issues of meaning. For example, developing one’s own sense around inclusivity might inform the composition of your carpool. As a collective activity, carpooling provides opportunities for values-based interactions with others. And a strong sense of personal meaning could certainly inform what you choose to talk about in the course of the ride. </p>
<p>The problem is that we’ve divorced study and intellectual inquiry from lived meaning, reducing life to what’s most practical or convenient at the moment. You point out after college “other things take priority,” but we don’t need to let these other things edge out our deepest longings. Why succumb to this emptiness? There’s a hunger for more principles in with the daily practice/observance, and for spiritual leaders who can connect the two. That’s what the rabbi discussed in the post seems to be attempting to do.</p>
<p>As the next generation graduates to join extant communities and to create new ones, perhaps those who’ve been through programs like this will go on shape communities of meaning consonant with their values, and not simply accept existing “lifestyle enclaves.”</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Arie Folger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/12/asking-the-big-questions-today-on-a-college-campus/#comment-3613</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arie Folger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2011 22:07:36 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4106#comment-3613</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Ideally, you are right, but to quote from one of the blog master&#039;s papers, Torah uMadda is a great ideal, but in the suburbs, we really need Torah veBaseball or Torah im Dougies. (citing from memory).

In college, many people do tend to form communities around intellectual principles or interests, but once people settle down, other things take priority. When you have the luxury of residential college, a minor point in a philosophical exploration can take very large proportions, and to an extent, that&#039;s good, because im ein akhshav, eimatai, that&#039;s the time to explore those issues. But people&#039;s needs are radically different when building a community where to belong to for the long term.

Think about it, What&#039;s Kierkegaard&#039;s view on car pooling? What does Levinas have to say about parent-teacher meetings? And what can Sartre tell you about the kind of mortgage you should take for that six bedroom home you&#039;ve been dreaming of?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ideally, you are right, but to quote from one of the blog master&#8217;s papers, Torah uMadda is a great ideal, but in the suburbs, we really need Torah veBaseball or Torah im Dougies. (citing from memory).</p>
<p>In college, many people do tend to form communities around intellectual principles or interests, but once people settle down, other things take priority. When you have the luxury of residential college, a minor point in a philosophical exploration can take very large proportions, and to an extent, that&#8217;s good, because im ein akhshav, eimatai, that&#8217;s the time to explore those issues. But people&#8217;s needs are radically different when building a community where to belong to for the long term.</p>
<p>Think about it, What&#8217;s Kierkegaard&#8217;s view on car pooling? What does Levinas have to say about parent-teacher meetings? And what can Sartre tell you about the kind of mortgage you should take for that six bedroom home you&#8217;ve been dreaming of?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: L		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/12/asking-the-big-questions-today-on-a-college-campus/#comment-3612</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[L]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2011 21:46:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4106#comment-3612</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[To Arie Folger -
You seem to be suggesting that community-building somehow rules out intellectual exploration. There are many communities where intellectual discourse around important questions of meaning are the glue that binds, the stuff that challenges members to engage with one another at a deeper level. Hopefully the students in this program will draw on their experience to build communities that stimulate the intellect and nurture meaning-making as much as they provide for meals, minyanim, and carpools.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>To Arie Folger &#8211;<br />
You seem to be suggesting that community-building somehow rules out intellectual exploration. There are many communities where intellectual discourse around important questions of meaning are the glue that binds, the stuff that challenges members to engage with one another at a deeper level. Hopefully the students in this program will draw on their experience to build communities that stimulate the intellect and nurture meaning-making as much as they provide for meals, minyanim, and carpools.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: HS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/12/asking-the-big-questions-today-on-a-college-campus/#comment-3607</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[HS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2011 02:21:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4106#comment-3607</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[HUC&#039;s Eugene Borowitz wrote &quot;Choosing a Sex Ethic: A Jewish Inquiry&quot; (Schocken, 1970), covering many of the same topics from an ethical perspective, and he does a fair job looking at traditional halachic sources too.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>HUC&#8217;s Eugene Borowitz wrote &#8220;Choosing a Sex Ethic: A Jewish Inquiry&#8221; (Schocken, 1970), covering many of the same topics from an ethical perspective, and he does a fair job looking at traditional halachic sources too.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Arie Folger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/12/asking-the-big-questions-today-on-a-college-campus/#comment-3606</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arie Folger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2011 22:31:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4106#comment-3606</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Isn&#039;t the disappointment you describe - and which may again be looming over this new program - not inherently the result of the very different things that allow one to engage in intellectual speculation, on the one hand, and building a community, on the other hand? Is it perhaps that the guy with the funny cards has a better grasp of the dynamics of social interactions than the guy who is going to ask a kind of question in a kind of way that may almost by definition make the establishment of a mainstream community (i.e., not an academic institute, a community, where people settle, have jobs in professions and trades, have kids, educate them, car pool, worship, etc.) an insurmountable challenge?

After all, two major reasons why college students like to engage in these intellectual pursuits is because they have the time and are footloose, not tied long term to any community, yet, don&#039;t you think so?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Isn&#8217;t the disappointment you describe &#8211; and which may again be looming over this new program &#8211; not inherently the result of the very different things that allow one to engage in intellectual speculation, on the one hand, and building a community, on the other hand? Is it perhaps that the guy with the funny cards has a better grasp of the dynamics of social interactions than the guy who is going to ask a kind of question in a kind of way that may almost by definition make the establishment of a mainstream community (i.e., not an academic institute, a community, where people settle, have jobs in professions and trades, have kids, educate them, car pool, worship, etc.) an insurmountable challenge?</p>
<p>After all, two major reasons why college students like to engage in these intellectual pursuits is because they have the time and are footloose, not tied long term to any community, yet, don&#8217;t you think so?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/12/asking-the-big-questions-today-on-a-college-campus/#comment-3605</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2011 18:38:38 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4106#comment-3605</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The questions are excellent, the best. I doubt if the educators- rabbis have worked out a coherent answer. If they have, they should let the rest of us know, since most people find these questions extraordinary difficult. One problem is that giving an answer to one question might be inadequate because it would limit the answers elsewhere. We also lack criteria of  
adequacy, what are the constraints on a possible answer. Must it be acceptable to Orthodox Jews, all Jews, ideal observer Jews? Can it be very different from traditional answers? These days whenever  someone tries to put together a big story, they don’t get very far. In contemporary Jewish life, no good intellectual deed goes unpunished. What did Greenberg accomplish other than marginalize his position within Orthodoxy? There are other similar examples. I don’t buy into the idea that the questions even without answers are worthwhile. Questions are easy, answers that allow others to solidify their own intuitions are difficult.
Here is a four word answer. I received an email today that was signed Rosh Kolel Yeshivat Oheiv Kesef vrodeif Nashim. Cute. If we now parse the first as living the good life, either as satisfying basic needs or utilities, and the second part as loving beauty, we have the outlines of a perfectionist theory of Judaism. Judaism exists to help us achieve the good life and pursue beauty, ( that includes the beauty mathematicians see in certain theorems), and perfection. It’s an answer that satisfies the aristocratic aspect of Judaism, seeing Talmudists and Kabbalists as achieving ever more perfect levels of spiritual and intellectual understanding, etc. Trouble is I have no reason to believe this answer that is a good one for our post holocaust times. What I am trying to say is that I don’t know how to tell what is a good answer and what is an inadequate answer. If that is true, why ask the questions?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The questions are excellent, the best. I doubt if the educators- rabbis have worked out a coherent answer. If they have, they should let the rest of us know, since most people find these questions extraordinary difficult. One problem is that giving an answer to one question might be inadequate because it would limit the answers elsewhere. We also lack criteria of<br />
adequacy, what are the constraints on a possible answer. Must it be acceptable to Orthodox Jews, all Jews, ideal observer Jews? Can it be very different from traditional answers? These days whenever  someone tries to put together a big story, they don’t get very far. In contemporary Jewish life, no good intellectual deed goes unpunished. What did Greenberg accomplish other than marginalize his position within Orthodoxy? There are other similar examples. I don’t buy into the idea that the questions even without answers are worthwhile. Questions are easy, answers that allow others to solidify their own intuitions are difficult.<br />
Here is a four word answer. I received an email today that was signed Rosh Kolel Yeshivat Oheiv Kesef vrodeif Nashim. Cute. If we now parse the first as living the good life, either as satisfying basic needs or utilities, and the second part as loving beauty, we have the outlines of a perfectionist theory of Judaism. Judaism exists to help us achieve the good life and pursue beauty, ( that includes the beauty mathematicians see in certain theorems), and perfection. It’s an answer that satisfies the aristocratic aspect of Judaism, seeing Talmudists and Kabbalists as achieving ever more perfect levels of spiritual and intellectual understanding, etc. Trouble is I have no reason to believe this answer that is a good one for our post holocaust times. What I am trying to say is that I don’t know how to tell what is a good answer and what is an inadequate answer. If that is true, why ask the questions?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Elli		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/09/12/asking-the-big-questions-today-on-a-college-campus/#comment-3600</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Elli]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2011 09:14:54 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4106#comment-3600</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Though not often perceived as such, early Jewish sources do seem to acknowledge the existence of genders other than male and female. In the MIshna, you have the tumtum and androgynous. In Navi, you have the saris. Contemporary discussions should probably begin with serious engagement of those constructions.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Though not often perceived as such, early Jewish sources do seem to acknowledge the existence of genders other than male and female. In the MIshna, you have the tumtum and androgynous. In Navi, you have the saris. Contemporary discussions should probably begin with serious engagement of those constructions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
