<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Shalhevet’s Modern Orthodox Education	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/26/shalhevet%e2%80%99s-modern-orthodox-education/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/26/shalhevet%e2%80%99s-modern-orthodox-education/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2011 12:42:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Larry Yudelson		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/26/shalhevet%e2%80%99s-modern-orthodox-education/#comment-3364</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Larry Yudelson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2011 12:42:51 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3816#comment-3364</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[And then there&#039;s this:

Our school, Shalhevet High School, is raffling a once-in-a-life time grand prize as a fund-raiser for the senior class trip to the &quot;March of the Living&quot; in Poland and Israel.  
 
A trip to LA to see Taylor Swift in concert August 23rd.
http://winanlatrip2seetayloraug23.webs.com/
 

The grand prize includes:
 
* airfare from a major U.S. city
* two nights at a Beverly Hills hotel
* two top-priced Taylor Swift Speak Now concert tickets
 
AND 
 
* a $150. shopping spree with a Hollywood stylist
* two hair and make-up make-overs at a Beverly Hills salon
* two photo shoots with a celebrity photographer
* two 48-hour Starline &quot;hop-on hop-off&quot; double decker tour bus passes
* Lunch at 20th Century Fox Studios
 
PLUS
 
gift certificates to local restaurants
gift certificates to local ice cream/frozen yogurt stores
gift certificates to a coffee shop
50. certificate for Speak Now Tour souvenirs at the Staples Center
A &quot;Welcome to Hollywood&quot; gift bag waiting at the hotel
 
and more to be announced!!!!! 
 
 http://winanlatrip2seetayloraug23.webs.com/
 
Facebook: Win A Trip To See Taylor Swift In Hollywood  
Twitter: TaylorLAraffle 
 
 
Please forward this to everyone you know - especially friends &#038; relatives with Taylor Swift fans!!!
 
thank you!]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>And then there&#8217;s this:</p>
<p>Our school, Shalhevet High School, is raffling a once-in-a-life time grand prize as a fund-raiser for the senior class trip to the &#8220;March of the Living&#8221; in Poland and Israel.  </p>
<p>A trip to LA to see Taylor Swift in concert August 23rd.<br />
<a href="http://winanlatrip2seetayloraug23.webs.com/" rel="nofollow ugc">http://winanlatrip2seetayloraug23.webs.com/</a></p>
<p>The grand prize includes:</p>
<p>* airfare from a major U.S. city<br />
* two nights at a Beverly Hills hotel<br />
* two top-priced Taylor Swift Speak Now concert tickets</p>
<p>AND </p>
<p>* a $150. shopping spree with a Hollywood stylist<br />
* two hair and make-up make-overs at a Beverly Hills salon<br />
* two photo shoots with a celebrity photographer<br />
* two 48-hour Starline &#8220;hop-on hop-off&#8221; double decker tour bus passes<br />
* Lunch at 20th Century Fox Studios</p>
<p>PLUS</p>
<p>gift certificates to local restaurants<br />
gift certificates to local ice cream/frozen yogurt stores<br />
gift certificates to a coffee shop<br />
50. certificate for Speak Now Tour souvenirs at the Staples Center<br />
A &#8220;Welcome to Hollywood&#8221; gift bag waiting at the hotel</p>
<p>and more to be announced!!!!! </p>
<p> <a href="http://winanlatrip2seetayloraug23.webs.com/" rel="nofollow ugc">http://winanlatrip2seetayloraug23.webs.com/</a></p>
<p>Facebook: Win A Trip To See Taylor Swift In Hollywood<br />
Twitter: TaylorLAraffle </p>
<p>Please forward this to everyone you know &#8211; especially friends &amp; relatives with Taylor Swift fans!!!</p>
<p>thank you!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Larry Yudelson		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/26/shalhevet%e2%80%99s-modern-orthodox-education/#comment-3363</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Larry Yudelson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2011 12:40:57 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3816#comment-3363</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[One anecdotal data point: My niece transferred into Shalhevet last year as a junior. When I saw her a couple of weeks ago, she had picked up and started reading the Guide to the Perplexed. I hadn&#039;t previously known her to be reading seforim in her spare time.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One anecdotal data point: My niece transferred into Shalhevet last year as a junior. When I saw her a couple of weeks ago, she had picked up and started reading the Guide to the Perplexed. I hadn&#8217;t previously known her to be reading seforim in her spare time.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Arie Folger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/26/shalhevet%e2%80%99s-modern-orthodox-education/#comment-3353</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arie Folger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2011 12:49:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3816#comment-3353</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I see a very big difference in how Talmud &#038; Halakha are approached on the one hand, and Tanakh on the other. The Talmuyd &#038; Halakha curriculum seems daring yet traditional, while in Tanakh, the traditional approach seems tacked on, to be yotze. It seems to portray Biblical Criticism as the true approach, to which some Orthodox thinkers can offer a homiletical response. Has the same ring as apologetics (undeservedly for R&#039;Yoel Bin Nun et al., undeservedly for the traditional approach, and undeservedly for apologetics in general, which deserve a bit less of a bad rap).

So one question the authors have to ask is, what kind of Modern Orthodoxy do they want to impart to their students.

And of course, the remark above about how the curriculum breathes two very different definitions of MO is true, too.

I love to see the final product - the curriculum and the students 5 years later.

That said, itś a daring idea, and I hope it contributes to &#039;hinukh.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I see a very big difference in how Talmud &amp; Halakha are approached on the one hand, and Tanakh on the other. The Talmuyd &amp; Halakha curriculum seems daring yet traditional, while in Tanakh, the traditional approach seems tacked on, to be yotze. It seems to portray Biblical Criticism as the true approach, to which some Orthodox thinkers can offer a homiletical response. Has the same ring as apologetics (undeservedly for R&#8217;Yoel Bin Nun et al., undeservedly for the traditional approach, and undeservedly for apologetics in general, which deserve a bit less of a bad rap).</p>
<p>So one question the authors have to ask is, what kind of Modern Orthodoxy do they want to impart to their students.</p>
<p>And of course, the remark above about how the curriculum breathes two very different definitions of MO is true, too.</p>
<p>I love to see the final product &#8211; the curriculum and the students 5 years later.</p>
<p>That said, itś a daring idea, and I hope it contributes to &#8216;hinukh.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: David		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/26/shalhevet%e2%80%99s-modern-orthodox-education/#comment-3335</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[David]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2011 13:04:20 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3816#comment-3335</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As co-authors of the Tanakh and Talmud sections of Shalhevet’s curriculum project, we wanted to express our appreciation for the open and exciting discussion that has taken place thus far on this blog. Many of the comments discussed here pertain to very real questions that we’ve had to grapple with as we craft this program, and we certainly hope that continued discussion here about how to address these issues will improve the curriculum as a whole.
 
We also felt the need to further describe our goals and approach so that our continued discussion can proceed constructively. First, we’d stress that the write-up on Shalhevet&#039;s website is a dated and incomplete draft of the project, and that much progress has been made to it since the document was posted. We were glad to see, however, that even from this rough outline, readers were able to glean important information about our methods and goals. Also, while our Judaic studies principal is a YCT graduate and we invite members of that institution to contribute valuable insight to this curriculum, the lead authors of the project are graduates of Yeshiva University and RIETS, and this project will be continuing next year with support from Yeshiva University&#039;s Center for the Jewish Future and Yeshiva University&#039;s Legacy Heritage Fellowship.
 
A couple of additional points:
•	Our primary goal throughout this project has been to communicate the relevancy of our tradition within the modern world. Today’s students are indeed bored; the thought of poring over ancient texts in a difficult language is simply not what most modern high school students want to do. Students are often thrust into gemarah learning with little to no introduction, and while they&#039;re taught how to learn Talmud, it’s seldom explained to them why they should. They’re rarely taught about the role of Talmud study in shaping Jewish tradition throughout history or introduced to the individual who composed the particular text that they’re struggling over. At the end of the day, our goal is to connect students to Jewish learning via an approach that does not simply start with “Keitzad Haregel” Rashi&#039;s commentary and a couple of Tosafot. It is an approach that communicates the beauty of Torah in a modern world and thereby invites today’s students to develop a continuing relationship with it - and is has been a tremendous help to us in addressing this challenge within our school.

•	At the same time, the issue of traditional modes of learning has been a central one that we’ve tried to address in this project. Again, ultimately, this curriculum is not just about modern orthodox philosophy – although it is certainly about that as well. At its advanced stages, the curriculum envisions a transition back towards more “traditional” learning – continuing the applied modes of analysis through traditional studies of Talmudic tractates. Further, the curriculum remains an entirely text based approach – while we may not be treating entire tractates, our primary texts still consist of individual gemaras, as well as selected texts from rishonim and achronim, in addition to articles from Torah and scholarly journals. 

•	While the details of any educational curriculum obviously must be tailored to a specific student body, this project has thus far seen an overwhelming response from our students – an interest in engaging text, an excitement for the exploration of sources, and the development of critical skills in learning. Our goal has been to ensure that students will no longer be able to simply claim that the sacred texts and heritage before them are arcane or irrelevant, and we&#039;ve been encouraged by the powerful response from within our student body thus far and will be continuing to develop tools to track it. We see a changing reality every day within our students and within their connection to Jewish tradition – expressed in casual encounters (students exclaiming “I can&#039;t believe we did not know this&quot; and “So, halakhic thinking does make sense!” - not the reactions to Torah learning that we were used to hearing in high school), as well as through their ability to think critically about complex contemporary issues relating to the halakhic process (on ordaining women: “we learned that halakhic thinking is a process and that various textual factors and precedents need to be considered to resolve this issue”) - for us, these responses have gone a long way towards answering the questions of how to put it into practice or connect this dream to the reality within our school.

•	At the end of the day, we certainly agree with the notion expressed in the blog that any curriculum is limited by its communicators – a teacher armed with this curriculum who cannot connect to his or her students will not be more effective than a teacher who cannot effectively develop a meaningful relationship with the students, no matter what particular text he or she is teaching. Our hope, however, is that this project will help the right teacher do an even better job of connecting his or her students to Jewish learning, identity and values. 

Thank you again for engaging in this discussion with us, and we look forward to receiving additional responses from Kavvanah&#039;s readers. In particular, if any readers are interested in more specific details about course choices or materials, we&#039;d be happy to provide more information and would welcome continued discussion.

Sincerely, 

Noam L. Weissman
David P. Stein]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As co-authors of the Tanakh and Talmud sections of Shalhevet’s curriculum project, we wanted to express our appreciation for the open and exciting discussion that has taken place thus far on this blog. Many of the comments discussed here pertain to very real questions that we’ve had to grapple with as we craft this program, and we certainly hope that continued discussion here about how to address these issues will improve the curriculum as a whole.</p>
<p>We also felt the need to further describe our goals and approach so that our continued discussion can proceed constructively. First, we’d stress that the write-up on Shalhevet&#8217;s website is a dated and incomplete draft of the project, and that much progress has been made to it since the document was posted. We were glad to see, however, that even from this rough outline, readers were able to glean important information about our methods and goals. Also, while our Judaic studies principal is a YCT graduate and we invite members of that institution to contribute valuable insight to this curriculum, the lead authors of the project are graduates of Yeshiva University and RIETS, and this project will be continuing next year with support from Yeshiva University&#8217;s Center for the Jewish Future and Yeshiva University&#8217;s Legacy Heritage Fellowship.</p>
<p>A couple of additional points:<br />
•	Our primary goal throughout this project has been to communicate the relevancy of our tradition within the modern world. Today’s students are indeed bored; the thought of poring over ancient texts in a difficult language is simply not what most modern high school students want to do. Students are often thrust into gemarah learning with little to no introduction, and while they&#8217;re taught how to learn Talmud, it’s seldom explained to them why they should. They’re rarely taught about the role of Talmud study in shaping Jewish tradition throughout history or introduced to the individual who composed the particular text that they’re struggling over. At the end of the day, our goal is to connect students to Jewish learning via an approach that does not simply start with “Keitzad Haregel” Rashi&#8217;s commentary and a couple of Tosafot. It is an approach that communicates the beauty of Torah in a modern world and thereby invites today’s students to develop a continuing relationship with it &#8211; and is has been a tremendous help to us in addressing this challenge within our school.</p>
<p>•	At the same time, the issue of traditional modes of learning has been a central one that we’ve tried to address in this project. Again, ultimately, this curriculum is not just about modern orthodox philosophy – although it is certainly about that as well. At its advanced stages, the curriculum envisions a transition back towards more “traditional” learning – continuing the applied modes of analysis through traditional studies of Talmudic tractates. Further, the curriculum remains an entirely text based approach – while we may not be treating entire tractates, our primary texts still consist of individual gemaras, as well as selected texts from rishonim and achronim, in addition to articles from Torah and scholarly journals. </p>
<p>•	While the details of any educational curriculum obviously must be tailored to a specific student body, this project has thus far seen an overwhelming response from our students – an interest in engaging text, an excitement for the exploration of sources, and the development of critical skills in learning. Our goal has been to ensure that students will no longer be able to simply claim that the sacred texts and heritage before them are arcane or irrelevant, and we&#8217;ve been encouraged by the powerful response from within our student body thus far and will be continuing to develop tools to track it. We see a changing reality every day within our students and within their connection to Jewish tradition – expressed in casual encounters (students exclaiming “I can&#8217;t believe we did not know this&#8221; and “So, halakhic thinking does make sense!” &#8211; not the reactions to Torah learning that we were used to hearing in high school), as well as through their ability to think critically about complex contemporary issues relating to the halakhic process (on ordaining women: “we learned that halakhic thinking is a process and that various textual factors and precedents need to be considered to resolve this issue”) &#8211; for us, these responses have gone a long way towards answering the questions of how to put it into practice or connect this dream to the reality within our school.</p>
<p>•	At the end of the day, we certainly agree with the notion expressed in the blog that any curriculum is limited by its communicators – a teacher armed with this curriculum who cannot connect to his or her students will not be more effective than a teacher who cannot effectively develop a meaningful relationship with the students, no matter what particular text he or she is teaching. Our hope, however, is that this project will help the right teacher do an even better job of connecting his or her students to Jewish learning, identity and values. </p>
<p>Thank you again for engaging in this discussion with us, and we look forward to receiving additional responses from Kavvanah&#8217;s readers. In particular, if any readers are interested in more specific details about course choices or materials, we&#8217;d be happy to provide more information and would welcome continued discussion.</p>
<p>Sincerely, </p>
<p>Noam L. Weissman<br />
David P. Stein</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Israel FRAC		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/26/shalhevet%e2%80%99s-modern-orthodox-education/#comment-3333</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Israel FRAC]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2011 04:21:24 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3816#comment-3333</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Clearly written for parents and donors, much to all our regret.
Nevertheless, praise the initiative. At this point, praise almost any out of the box initiative.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Clearly written for parents and donors, much to all our regret.<br />
Nevertheless, praise the initiative. At this point, praise almost any out of the box initiative.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Jonathan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/26/shalhevet%e2%80%99s-modern-orthodox-education/#comment-3332</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jonathan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2011 01:43:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3816#comment-3332</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It is nice to teach Modern Orthodoxy but they should teach those thinkers and their ideas in  historical context .]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It is nice to teach Modern Orthodoxy but they should teach those thinkers and their ideas in  historical context .</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Jonathan Baker		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/26/shalhevet%e2%80%99s-modern-orthodox-education/#comment-3324</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jonathan Baker]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2011 11:53:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3816#comment-3324</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[ki-sarita:
They tried a women&#039;s davening group at Ramaz when I was in HS (early 1980s), but the girls that went, just treated it as another excuse to shmooze, just like they did every other day on the women&#039;s side of the mechitza (grr - girls can talk all they want, but when boys do, they get sent to the vice-principal&#039;s office - enforcement should be egalitarian).

&quot;strongest tie is to be yodeah sefer and a talmid chacham&quot; - which won&#039;t come without a lot of post-HS reading and learning, and most people won&#039;t get there at all.  So is it better to instill a love of traditional learning so that they can try for a goal that most won&#039;t reach, or is it better to give them ammunition for social situations?

Ramaz was mostly straightforward what I call &quot;conceptual&quot; learning in the Talmud classes - talk the issue out, from all perspectives, then see how that maps onto the various opinions in the text.  We didn&#039;t &quot;learn how to learn&quot; - that was apparently left for the post-HS year, but the post-HS year was far from universal at that point, and since I wasn&#039;t all that frum, and was tired of Jewish classes, I just wanted to go to college and then to work.  So I had to teach myself, years later, how to learn a sugya.  Also took a lot of Talmud classes at Lincoln Square Synagogue.

I have a Stoliner friend, who went to Chaim Berlin, who said he had the same problem - he realized when he was 16, that they weren&#039;t teaching him how to learn, they were using the &quot;conceptual&quot; method, so he too sat with dictionaries and taught himself how to learn a sugya.  So it&#039;s not just an MO thing.

The closest Ramaz came to Shalhevet&#039;s programmatic &quot;contemporary issues&quot; learning was 10th grade, the &quot;prepare for the social pressures of college&quot; year.  We did Yishayahu and Yirmiyahu in Navi, focussing on the real meaning of the messianic passages, so as to be able to resist missionaries in college.  We even read R Aryeh Kaplan&#039;s &quot;The Real Messiah&quot; as a text.  Judaism class with R&#039; Jack Bieler was contemporary Jewish sociology, warning us against the twin evils of &quot;intermarriage and assimilation&quot;.

Anyway - philosophy?  in lower grades of HS?  Until I was in my 30s, philosophy put me to sleep.  I somewhat regret not having taken Kant in college when a bunch of my friends did, but I wasn&#039;t read for it then.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ki-sarita:<br />
They tried a women&#8217;s davening group at Ramaz when I was in HS (early 1980s), but the girls that went, just treated it as another excuse to shmooze, just like they did every other day on the women&#8217;s side of the mechitza (grr &#8211; girls can talk all they want, but when boys do, they get sent to the vice-principal&#8217;s office &#8211; enforcement should be egalitarian).</p>
<p>&#8220;strongest tie is to be yodeah sefer and a talmid chacham&#8221; &#8211; which won&#8217;t come without a lot of post-HS reading and learning, and most people won&#8217;t get there at all.  So is it better to instill a love of traditional learning so that they can try for a goal that most won&#8217;t reach, or is it better to give them ammunition for social situations?</p>
<p>Ramaz was mostly straightforward what I call &#8220;conceptual&#8221; learning in the Talmud classes &#8211; talk the issue out, from all perspectives, then see how that maps onto the various opinions in the text.  We didn&#8217;t &#8220;learn how to learn&#8221; &#8211; that was apparently left for the post-HS year, but the post-HS year was far from universal at that point, and since I wasn&#8217;t all that frum, and was tired of Jewish classes, I just wanted to go to college and then to work.  So I had to teach myself, years later, how to learn a sugya.  Also took a lot of Talmud classes at Lincoln Square Synagogue.</p>
<p>I have a Stoliner friend, who went to Chaim Berlin, who said he had the same problem &#8211; he realized when he was 16, that they weren&#8217;t teaching him how to learn, they were using the &#8220;conceptual&#8221; method, so he too sat with dictionaries and taught himself how to learn a sugya.  So it&#8217;s not just an MO thing.</p>
<p>The closest Ramaz came to Shalhevet&#8217;s programmatic &#8220;contemporary issues&#8221; learning was 10th grade, the &#8220;prepare for the social pressures of college&#8221; year.  We did Yishayahu and Yirmiyahu in Navi, focussing on the real meaning of the messianic passages, so as to be able to resist missionaries in college.  We even read R Aryeh Kaplan&#8217;s &#8220;The Real Messiah&#8221; as a text.  Judaism class with R&#8217; Jack Bieler was contemporary Jewish sociology, warning us against the twin evils of &#8220;intermarriage and assimilation&#8221;.</p>
<p>Anyway &#8211; philosophy?  in lower grades of HS?  Until I was in my 30s, philosophy put me to sleep.  I somewhat regret not having taken Kant in college when a bunch of my friends did, but I wasn&#8217;t read for it then.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ki sarita		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/26/shalhevet%e2%80%99s-modern-orthodox-education/#comment-3321</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ki sarita]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2011 23:55:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3816#comment-3321</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[huh? feminism, jewish and not, occupied a big part of my thoughts as a teenager, drugs very little.
and feminism has PLENTY to offer to the discussion of sex relationships and marriage!]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>huh? feminism, jewish and not, occupied a big part of my thoughts as a teenager, drugs very little.<br />
and feminism has PLENTY to offer to the discussion of sex relationships and marriage!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/26/shalhevet%e2%80%99s-modern-orthodox-education/#comment-3320</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2011 22:29:37 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3816#comment-3320</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I didn’t much care for this curriculum for the same reasons that were discussed in the earlier comments. There is no stronger tie than to be a yodeah sefer and a  talmid chacham. There was one particular idea that I found really distasteful. “While examining the role of women in Halachic life, we will study prominent religious thinkers such as Rabbi Sperber, Rabbi Henkin, Rabbi Soloveitchik, Rabbi Berkowitz and Rabbi Meiselman.” Here are teenagers with so many life issues yet to be solved. They need to think about dating or not, shomer negiah or not, how to develop a relationship and how to create a good marriage. There will face sex, drugs and non-frum lifestyles should they attend a secular college. Jewish feminism and its opponents doesn’t confront these issues. What is needed is a ruv with some intelligence and flexibility to discuss a course in value clarification, and present a livable Orthodox perspective. Movies and  the 19th century shiduchim novels from Jane Austin thru Henry James would all be of value. If they pick up some romantic ideas all the better.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I didn’t much care for this curriculum for the same reasons that were discussed in the earlier comments. There is no stronger tie than to be a yodeah sefer and a  talmid chacham. There was one particular idea that I found really distasteful. “While examining the role of women in Halachic life, we will study prominent religious thinkers such as Rabbi Sperber, Rabbi Henkin, Rabbi Soloveitchik, Rabbi Berkowitz and Rabbi Meiselman.” Here are teenagers with so many life issues yet to be solved. They need to think about dating or not, shomer negiah or not, how to develop a relationship and how to create a good marriage. There will face sex, drugs and non-frum lifestyles should they attend a secular college. Jewish feminism and its opponents doesn’t confront these issues. What is needed is a ruv with some intelligence and flexibility to discuss a course in value clarification, and present a livable Orthodox perspective. Movies and  the 19th century shiduchim novels from Jane Austin thru Henry James would all be of value. If they pick up some romantic ideas all the better.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: zjb		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/26/shalhevet%e2%80%99s-modern-orthodox-education/#comment-3308</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[zjb]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2011 02:53:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3816#comment-3308</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[i teach this stuff for a living, the modern stuff obviously more than the classical materials, so i hate to say it: the curriculum sounds like a bore. not because the contents aren&#039;t interesting to me, but because it sounds like a program, somebody else&#039;s program being forcibly imposed upon students across an entire curriculum. 

i guess what i see are a bunch of names, waved around like a philosophical talisman. what i don&#039;t see is how any of these bluechip names in the history of jewish and western thought are supposed to address in an organic way the current questions that a student or groups of students might form for themselves about the world or worlds that they themselves inhabit. 

i hope it works, but the whole thing looks too top-heavy and perhaps ideologically driven. i guess this is true of all educational programs. but the program at hand is too specialized to be of general interest beyond the kids who find themselves drawn to philosophy. i think it would be better to just learn gemara or dostoyevsky without all the appratus, which to my mind requires a more organic, bottom-up type of directional movement. 

in my opinion, philosophy, unlike literature (including &quot;jewish literature,&quot; including talmud and midrash), is best pursued as an elective, and perhaps even sparingly at the high school level. maybe because what makes philosophy special is that it actually requires broad exposure to non-philosophical contents such as literature, history, math, and science.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>i teach this stuff for a living, the modern stuff obviously more than the classical materials, so i hate to say it: the curriculum sounds like a bore. not because the contents aren&#8217;t interesting to me, but because it sounds like a program, somebody else&#8217;s program being forcibly imposed upon students across an entire curriculum. </p>
<p>i guess what i see are a bunch of names, waved around like a philosophical talisman. what i don&#8217;t see is how any of these bluechip names in the history of jewish and western thought are supposed to address in an organic way the current questions that a student or groups of students might form for themselves about the world or worlds that they themselves inhabit. </p>
<p>i hope it works, but the whole thing looks too top-heavy and perhaps ideologically driven. i guess this is true of all educational programs. but the program at hand is too specialized to be of general interest beyond the kids who find themselves drawn to philosophy. i think it would be better to just learn gemara or dostoyevsky without all the appratus, which to my mind requires a more organic, bottom-up type of directional movement. </p>
<p>in my opinion, philosophy, unlike literature (including &#8220;jewish literature,&#8221; including talmud and midrash), is best pursued as an elective, and perhaps even sparingly at the high school level. maybe because what makes philosophy special is that it actually requires broad exposure to non-philosophical contents such as literature, history, math, and science.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Isaac Shalev		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/26/shalhevet%e2%80%99s-modern-orthodox-education/#comment-3305</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Isaac Shalev]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2011 00:22:32 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3816#comment-3305</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I&#039;m not sure what MO curriculum looks like nowadays. When I was in school, I&#039;m not sure that there was a curriculum. Each rebbe would pick a masechet of gemara and start teaching some of it. We&#039;d also pick a sefer of chumash and learn it with rashi and selected others, and the same for Navi. There was no study of method or derech ha-limmud, no organizing ideas, no real exploration - just a forced march through some sifrei kodesh. It was only in 11th grade, when we began to prepare for the Bechina Yerushalmit (the Jerusalem exam), and the up to 9 college credits that came with it, that we started having some organized learning, at least in Nach. We learned the selection stories of the major Nevi&#039;im and compared them. We studied their most famous prophecies and learned about parallel and chiastic poetic structures. 

In short, I&#039;m delighted that there&#039;s structure and purpose, because I was not well-served by my school. I didn&#039;t learn how to learn (from my school) and I didn&#039;t really learn any important ideas either. I did get a great secular education though - where there was curriculum. Seems like we should be able to do better than that.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m not sure what MO curriculum looks like nowadays. When I was in school, I&#8217;m not sure that there was a curriculum. Each rebbe would pick a masechet of gemara and start teaching some of it. We&#8217;d also pick a sefer of chumash and learn it with rashi and selected others, and the same for Navi. There was no study of method or derech ha-limmud, no organizing ideas, no real exploration &#8211; just a forced march through some sifrei kodesh. It was only in 11th grade, when we began to prepare for the Bechina Yerushalmit (the Jerusalem exam), and the up to 9 college credits that came with it, that we started having some organized learning, at least in Nach. We learned the selection stories of the major Nevi&#8217;im and compared them. We studied their most famous prophecies and learned about parallel and chiastic poetic structures. </p>
<p>In short, I&#8217;m delighted that there&#8217;s structure and purpose, because I was not well-served by my school. I didn&#8217;t learn how to learn (from my school) and I didn&#8217;t really learn any important ideas either. I did get a great secular education though &#8211; where there was curriculum. Seems like we should be able to do better than that.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/26/shalhevet%e2%80%99s-modern-orthodox-education/#comment-3303</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2011 19:44:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3816#comment-3303</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The contrast between the two 12th grade philosophy/Jewish thought classes is interesting. The first sees MO as a community that defines itself via three areas of engagement with modernity. The second says that MO is not about community, it is about the individual&#039;s struggle with Western thought. Here we go again.

If the question is whether it would &quot;work&quot; I would need to understand what the goal was. If it&#039;s simply &quot;what would happen&quot; I suppose the answer is you would bore 80 percent of the kids. Unless high school kids are now much more interested in the issues that drive a mostly rarefied discourse, I don&#039;t really see the point.

It does seem to me that the best outcomes usually come about when a school gives kids a bit of independent access to texts. If you really want to know how existentialism figures into modern Jewish thought you can figure it out later if that ever interests you. If you want to figure out a gemara you are going to be stuck with whatever artscroll gives you because you never had to prepare a sugya.

I&#039;m not sure how the &quot;great ideas&quot; pedagogical model became the preferred way to inculcate MO values. Instead, I would really like to see a HS curriculum based on the great books model for both Jewish and secular curricula. Let kids learn how to read/learn on parallel tracks with sustained engagement  and then give them the space to hash things out. (I had a mostly crappy HS education, but in a sense the traditional yeshivish gemara curriculum, with a some modification, is really a great books approach. You live with it until you get it or hate it.) But what do I know. I&#039;ve never had to control a classroom or deal with the actual concerns and limited attention span of the contemporary teen. (I&#039;ve had my share of experience with apathetic college kids; a far lesser burden.)]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The contrast between the two 12th grade philosophy/Jewish thought classes is interesting. The first sees MO as a community that defines itself via three areas of engagement with modernity. The second says that MO is not about community, it is about the individual&#8217;s struggle with Western thought. Here we go again.</p>
<p>If the question is whether it would &#8220;work&#8221; I would need to understand what the goal was. If it&#8217;s simply &#8220;what would happen&#8221; I suppose the answer is you would bore 80 percent of the kids. Unless high school kids are now much more interested in the issues that drive a mostly rarefied discourse, I don&#8217;t really see the point.</p>
<p>It does seem to me that the best outcomes usually come about when a school gives kids a bit of independent access to texts. If you really want to know how existentialism figures into modern Jewish thought you can figure it out later if that ever interests you. If you want to figure out a gemara you are going to be stuck with whatever artscroll gives you because you never had to prepare a sugya.</p>
<p>I&#8217;m not sure how the &#8220;great ideas&#8221; pedagogical model became the preferred way to inculcate MO values. Instead, I would really like to see a HS curriculum based on the great books model for both Jewish and secular curricula. Let kids learn how to read/learn on parallel tracks with sustained engagement  and then give them the space to hash things out. (I had a mostly crappy HS education, but in a sense the traditional yeshivish gemara curriculum, with a some modification, is really a great books approach. You live with it until you get it or hate it.) But what do I know. I&#8217;ve never had to control a classroom or deal with the actual concerns and limited attention span of the contemporary teen. (I&#8217;ve had my share of experience with apathetic college kids; a far lesser burden.)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: YDT		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/26/shalhevet%e2%80%99s-modern-orthodox-education/#comment-3302</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[YDT]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2011 16:56:36 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3816#comment-3302</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As with most high school curricula, this sounds like an idealistic dream with no connection to reality. Furthermore, often the curriculum itself is not important, rather the time devoted to the topic; a 45 minute class or even an hour and half class on Talmudic Jurisprudence is unlikely to meet the noble goals set out in this curriculum. As to the curriculum itself, it seems like an indoctrination to modern orthodox thought (as understood by the administration). Lastly, and in my opinion most importantly, this curriculum does not seem to provide students with the basic skills required in Jewish studies developed by years of systematic and intensive study, instead students are exposed to Jewish studies haphazardly through hand-picked topics without the depth and breadth of the entire Jewish corpus.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As with most high school curricula, this sounds like an idealistic dream with no connection to reality. Furthermore, often the curriculum itself is not important, rather the time devoted to the topic; a 45 minute class or even an hour and half class on Talmudic Jurisprudence is unlikely to meet the noble goals set out in this curriculum. As to the curriculum itself, it seems like an indoctrination to modern orthodox thought (as understood by the administration). Lastly, and in my opinion most importantly, this curriculum does not seem to provide students with the basic skills required in Jewish studies developed by years of systematic and intensive study, instead students are exposed to Jewish studies haphazardly through hand-picked topics without the depth and breadth of the entire Jewish corpus.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
