<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: The Message of the Holocaust is not the avoidance of Cyber-Bullying	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/05/24/the-message-of-the-holocaust-is-not-the-avoidance-of-cyber-bullying/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/05/24/the-message-of-the-holocaust-is-not-the-avoidance-of-cyber-bullying/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 May 2011 17:29:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: chakira		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/05/24/the-message-of-the-holocaust-is-not-the-avoidance-of-cyber-bullying/#comment-3100</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[chakira]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2011 17:29:39 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3602#comment-3100</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/05/24/the-message-of-the-holocaust-is-not-the-avoidance-of-cyber-bullying/#comment-3099&quot;&gt;AS&lt;/a&gt;.

I think this does not contradict what I said re agency and efficacy.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/05/24/the-message-of-the-holocaust-is-not-the-avoidance-of-cyber-bullying/#comment-3099">AS</a>.</p>
<p>I think this does not contradict what I said re agency and efficacy.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/05/24/the-message-of-the-holocaust-is-not-the-avoidance-of-cyber-bullying/#comment-3099</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2011 16:22:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3602#comment-3099</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/05/24/the-message-of-the-holocaust-is-not-the-avoidance-of-cyber-bullying/#comment-3094&quot;&gt;chakira&lt;/a&gt;.

Should the holocaust never be used to expand the bounds of the moral imagination? Without it would we think that society could turn on itself so quickly?  I think that &quot;lessons&quot; we learn are from the perpetrators, not the victims. There is no lofty ideal , only the notion that a society that does not fight certain tendencies is probably more likely to succumb to them.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/05/24/the-message-of-the-holocaust-is-not-the-avoidance-of-cyber-bullying/#comment-3094">chakira</a>.</p>
<p>Should the holocaust never be used to expand the bounds of the moral imagination? Without it would we think that society could turn on itself so quickly?  I think that &#8220;lessons&#8221; we learn are from the perpetrators, not the victims. There is no lofty ideal , only the notion that a society that does not fight certain tendencies is probably more likely to succumb to them.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Larry Yudelson		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/05/24/the-message-of-the-holocaust-is-not-the-avoidance-of-cyber-bullying/#comment-3096</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Larry Yudelson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2011 07:52:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3602#comment-3096</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[While I might personally prefer a nihilistic lesson from the Shoah, the reality is that people need to find meaning in events. The evils of cyberbullying may be a cloying lesson, but it offers certain ethical advantages over the competing narrative of victimhood granting license to victimize others.

The role of the ADL as both promoting and embodying these two responses to the Shoah should not be underestimated. They are invested both in &quot;Teaching Tolerance&quot; and embracing a morality-free Israeli survivalism.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>While I might personally prefer a nihilistic lesson from the Shoah, the reality is that people need to find meaning in events. The evils of cyberbullying may be a cloying lesson, but it offers certain ethical advantages over the competing narrative of victimhood granting license to victimize others.</p>
<p>The role of the ADL as both promoting and embodying these two responses to the Shoah should not be underestimated. They are invested both in &#8220;Teaching Tolerance&#8221; and embracing a morality-free Israeli survivalism.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: chakira		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/05/24/the-message-of-the-holocaust-is-not-the-avoidance-of-cyber-bullying/#comment-3094</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[chakira]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2011 03:38:51 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3602#comment-3094</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I am really upset by the language of a message to the holocaust. Its more Hegelian magical thinking where the wounds of spirit heal without leaving a trace. If there was a message to the Holocaust it would assume that the people there were somehow spiritually incorporated into our self consciousness and now we are learning from their peregrinations. The problem of agency strikes me as central here viz. If you were given the choice between teaching even the loftiest ideal to help prevent future genocides, or not suffering genocide in the here and now and maybe putting off the lesson, a sane rational person would choose the latter. Now maybe there is something here that happens despite the lack of agency. Like &quot;Hey, maybe despite all this we can recuperate something from this mess.&quot; Nice impulse, since you are the one still alive. But aren&#039;t you then instrumentalizing the death of the other for your own therapeutic needs?  As Doctor Melfi said to Tony Soprano: how many people have to die for your personal growth? Assumedly, furthermore, fictional scenarios or thought experiments could carry the same or even roughly similar argumentative or persuasive weight to Holocaust stories in teaching you how to not bully, be a better Jew or not commit genocide. Maybe they do not pack the same punch, but there must be some ratio of persuasiveness to justifying genocide post facto (and I would assume the number would be set pretty low by most people). 

I think that these problems of agency and viable alternatives render the narrative where we recuperate from the holocaust either morally dubious or at least unnecessary. We can still of course ask what Holocaust rhetoric says about those who invoke it. Why raise the stakes as such and drag dead children into your argument? Maybe it cannot stand and fall on its own merits.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I am really upset by the language of a message to the holocaust. Its more Hegelian magical thinking where the wounds of spirit heal without leaving a trace. If there was a message to the Holocaust it would assume that the people there were somehow spiritually incorporated into our self consciousness and now we are learning from their peregrinations. The problem of agency strikes me as central here viz. If you were given the choice between teaching even the loftiest ideal to help prevent future genocides, or not suffering genocide in the here and now and maybe putting off the lesson, a sane rational person would choose the latter. Now maybe there is something here that happens despite the lack of agency. Like &#8220;Hey, maybe despite all this we can recuperate something from this mess.&#8221; Nice impulse, since you are the one still alive. But aren&#8217;t you then instrumentalizing the death of the other for your own therapeutic needs?  As Doctor Melfi said to Tony Soprano: how many people have to die for your personal growth? Assumedly, furthermore, fictional scenarios or thought experiments could carry the same or even roughly similar argumentative or persuasive weight to Holocaust stories in teaching you how to not bully, be a better Jew or not commit genocide. Maybe they do not pack the same punch, but there must be some ratio of persuasiveness to justifying genocide post facto (and I would assume the number would be set pretty low by most people). </p>
<p>I think that these problems of agency and viable alternatives render the narrative where we recuperate from the holocaust either morally dubious or at least unnecessary. We can still of course ask what Holocaust rhetoric says about those who invoke it. Why raise the stakes as such and drag dead children into your argument? Maybe it cannot stand and fall on its own merits.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/05/24/the-message-of-the-holocaust-is-not-the-avoidance-of-cyber-bullying/#comment-3093</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2011 22:55:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3602#comment-3093</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/05/24/the-message-of-the-holocaust-is-not-the-avoidance-of-cyber-bullying/#comment-3092&quot;&gt;Larry Yudelson&lt;/a&gt;.

Part of the tri-faith rhetoric was that they were all democratic and needed to fight communism and fascism by engaging in war. War was religiously mandated a necessary evil to fight greater evil.  They did not think pop-sociology was going to defeat fascism. 
And even Woody Guthrie only made sense by actual combat not symbolic singing of songs.
&lt;blockquote&gt;following the Nazi invasion of the Soviet Union and the Japanese assault of Pearl Harbor, Woody’s guitar became adorned with the hand-painted epitaph, THIS MACHINE KILLS FASCISTS, a slogan which held great metaphoric power. In the face of World War Two, the group separated as most members were drafted or anxiously enlisted. The fight against fascism took on massive proporations, especially for those on the Left. Woody joined the Merchant Marine, offering two tours of duty, and then was briefly drafted into the Army as well.&lt;/blockquote&gt;]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/05/24/the-message-of-the-holocaust-is-not-the-avoidance-of-cyber-bullying/#comment-3092">Larry Yudelson</a>.</p>
<p>Part of the tri-faith rhetoric was that they were all democratic and needed to fight communism and fascism by engaging in war. War was religiously mandated a necessary evil to fight greater evil.  They did not think pop-sociology was going to defeat fascism.<br />
And even Woody Guthrie only made sense by actual combat not symbolic singing of songs.</p>
<blockquote><p>following the Nazi invasion of the Soviet Union and the Japanese assault of Pearl Harbor, Woody’s guitar became adorned with the hand-painted epitaph, THIS MACHINE KILLS FASCISTS, a slogan which held great metaphoric power. In the face of World War Two, the group separated as most members were drafted or anxiously enlisted. The fight against fascism took on massive proporations, especially for those on the Left. Woody joined the Merchant Marine, offering two tours of duty, and then was briefly drafted into the Army as well.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Larry Yudelson		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/05/24/the-message-of-the-holocaust-is-not-the-avoidance-of-cyber-bullying/#comment-3092</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Larry Yudelson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2011 22:49:11 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3602#comment-3092</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[But wait. Wasn&#039;t the pluralism of Tri-Faith America and the National Conference of Christians and Jews an explicit rebuke of Fascism, even before the Holocaust?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>But wait. Wasn&#8217;t the pluralism of Tri-Faith America and the National Conference of Christians and Jews an explicit rebuke of Fascism, even before the Holocaust?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
