<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Sliding to the Left?	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/sliding-to-the-left/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/sliding-to-the-left/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2011 17:49:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Micha Berger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/sliding-to-the-left/#comment-3329</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Micha Berger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2011 15:54:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3801#comment-3329</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/sliding-to-the-left/#comment-3323&quot;&gt;Charles&lt;/a&gt;.

CJF is YU&#039;s attempt to appeal to the hinterlands, the same places where NCYI&#039;s attempt to avoid YCT grads from taking YI positions isn&#039;t going over too well. But what RIETS is producing, particularly now that R&#039; Herschel Schachter is &quot;the&quot; shiur to get into, is to the right of where RIETS was in my day. (Not my own shiur; R&#039; Dovid Lifshitz&#039;s talmidim were always off the right of the mainstream...)]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/sliding-to-the-left/#comment-3323">Charles</a>.</p>
<p>CJF is YU&#8217;s attempt to appeal to the hinterlands, the same places where NCYI&#8217;s attempt to avoid YCT grads from taking YI positions isn&#8217;t going over too well. But what RIETS is producing, particularly now that R&#8217; Herschel Schachter is &#8220;the&#8221; shiur to get into, is to the right of where RIETS was in my day. (Not my own shiur; R&#8217; Dovid Lifshitz&#8217;s talmidim were always off the right of the mainstream&#8230;)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Micha Berger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/sliding-to-the-left/#comment-3328</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Micha Berger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2011 15:51:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3801#comment-3328</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/sliding-to-the-left/#comment-3327&quot;&gt;Larry Yudelson&lt;/a&gt;.

Great point!]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/sliding-to-the-left/#comment-3327">Larry Yudelson</a>.</p>
<p>Great point!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Larry Yudelson		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/sliding-to-the-left/#comment-3327</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Larry Yudelson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2011 14:48:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3801#comment-3327</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/sliding-to-the-left/#comment-3319&quot;&gt;Micha Berger&lt;/a&gt;.

I would caution that a sample of MTA and TABC students may not find half-shabbos observance because I suspect it to be a very gendered thing. In my observation of a very small, very unscientific sampling of both a TABC boy and a Frisch girl, the boy connects to his friends by playing basketball; the girl by texting.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/sliding-to-the-left/#comment-3319">Micha Berger</a>.</p>
<p>I would caution that a sample of MTA and TABC students may not find half-shabbos observance because I suspect it to be a very gendered thing. In my observation of a very small, very unscientific sampling of both a TABC boy and a Frisch girl, the boy connects to his friends by playing basketball; the girl by texting.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Charles		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/sliding-to-the-left/#comment-3323</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Charles]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2011 10:19:40 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3801#comment-3323</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[you all are forgetting that even in YU there is now  a significant left trend - with the CJF placing women in synagogues as full time scholars, with over a 1000 students a year engaged in service learning around the world and many of those becoming the new YU rabbinical students, as well as the fact that CJF is engaging the reform and conservative leadership and creating a safe place for orthodox rabbis to continue to grow irrespective of their smicha]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>you all are forgetting that even in YU there is now  a significant left trend &#8211; with the CJF placing women in synagogues as full time scholars, with over a 1000 students a year engaged in service learning around the world and many of those becoming the new YU rabbinical students, as well as the fact that CJF is engaging the reform and conservative leadership and creating a safe place for orthodox rabbis to continue to grow irrespective of their smicha</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Chaim I. Waxman		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/sliding-to-the-left/#comment-3322</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chaim I. Waxman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2011 06:42:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3801#comment-3322</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The article by Yehuda Turetsky and me emphasized the tentative nature of our suggestions.  I &quot;contend&quot; nothing; we explicitly inserted a question mark in our main title – “Sliding to the Left?”; we reject neither the thesis of Sam Heilman nor my own earlier argument about &quot;haredization&quot; -- though I do elsewhere now argue that &quot;humrazation&quot; is a much more appropriate term for the phenomenon; we also suggest that &quot;that American Orthodox Jewry is much more heterogeneous than the above-cited observers perceived&quot;; we think that the heterogeneity of American Orthodoxy is part of broader American social and cultural patters; and we state explicitly that a &quot;deeper, more detailed analysis of American Modern Orthodoxy requires much more extensive empirical data, including but not limited to a representative sample of the norms, values and thoughts of members, in addition to rabbis, of Modern Orthodox congregations across the country.&quot;  
The &quot;dropping out of orthodoxy altogether&quot; is a very interesting phenomenon; so too are the dropping out of Conservative and Reform Judaism, the dropping out of Judaism, and many others, interesting phenomena.  They just are not what we were studying.  We were looking at those who identify as Orthodox Jews.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The article by Yehuda Turetsky and me emphasized the tentative nature of our suggestions.  I &#8220;contend&#8221; nothing; we explicitly inserted a question mark in our main title – “Sliding to the Left?”; we reject neither the thesis of Sam Heilman nor my own earlier argument about &#8220;haredization&#8221; &#8212; though I do elsewhere now argue that &#8220;humrazation&#8221; is a much more appropriate term for the phenomenon; we also suggest that &#8220;that American Orthodox Jewry is much more heterogeneous than the above-cited observers perceived&#8221;; we think that the heterogeneity of American Orthodoxy is part of broader American social and cultural patters; and we state explicitly that a &#8220;deeper, more detailed analysis of American Modern Orthodoxy requires much more extensive empirical data, including but not limited to a representative sample of the norms, values and thoughts of members, in addition to rabbis, of Modern Orthodox congregations across the country.&#8221;<br />
The &#8220;dropping out of orthodoxy altogether&#8221; is a very interesting phenomenon; so too are the dropping out of Conservative and Reform Judaism, the dropping out of Judaism, and many others, interesting phenomena.  They just are not what we were studying.  We were looking at those who identify as Orthodox Jews.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Micha Berger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/sliding-to-the-left/#comment-3319</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Micha Berger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2011 20:29:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3801#comment-3319</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Rabbi Dr Brill, I don&#039;t think you took sufficient time to read my posts. Maybe you overestimated the clarity with which I write?

1- I said that with the Rav&#039;s death, one side slid to the right, and the other to the left. The side that slid to the right took the majority of communal structures, forcing Open Orthodoxy to build his own. I don&#039;t think either is actually perpetuating the MO that the Rav taught.

2- Going beyond what I said, I didn&#039;t intend that as a value judgment, but as a historical statement. It could well be that the MO of a few decades ago addressed a need that today&#039;s society doesn&#039;t face. The fact that there isn&#039;t a sizable community sticking with it would give some indication that it&#039;s true. Which modification is holier? Which is healthier? I didn&#039;t touch that issue.

3- Yes, I did call those who supported SCA as being to the left of the Rav. That&#039;s not saying they would have gone as far was 21st cent Open O.

3- What I wrote elsewhere is that I don&#039;t think &quot;half Shabbos&quot; is sustainable in large O communities outside of Open O. I actually think the majority of kids who are texting on Shabbos who attend MTA or TABC are either violating Shabbos more generally, or will be in the next few weeks. And I say that as someone who has a dozen or more teenagers at my home on the typical Shabbos afternoon, in various states between Mod-O and not-currently-O, and asked them if they knew kids who basically tried to keep Shabbos but can&#039;t keep away from texting and their Facebook app. They haven&#039;t heard of &quot;Half Shabbos&quot;, neither the term nor the concept. And if you search around on-line, this is the consistent result of such experiments. So I figure the phenomenon is localized in geography or community-space.

So, I have to guess what population would have such teens, some group that doesn&#039;t overlap with my six teens&#039; pools of friends. What came to mind were communities that aren&#039;t as judgmental, that don&#039;t force you to choose between complete compliance and affiliation: (1) Smaller out of town communities, (2) Open Orthodoxy. ((3) Lubavitch -- but only WRT the not-yet-frum; they&#039;re relatively less judgmental of their own kids&#039; choices, but this far.)

But I said this because my &quot;spies&quot; in Teaneck, MTA, JEC, do NOT see what you, R&#039; Burg, [R&#039; Pelocovitz] your anonymous educator friend, etc... are speaking of. (My home neighborhood doesn&#039;t have a sizable MO population. Too many kids entirely off the derekh and willing to use their phones on Shabbos, though...) Trying to find conditions that *don&#039;t* match the typical Teaneck kid is what brought me to ask about Open O, not trying to *identify* the two.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rabbi Dr Brill, I don&#8217;t think you took sufficient time to read my posts. Maybe you overestimated the clarity with which I write?</p>
<p>1- I said that with the Rav&#8217;s death, one side slid to the right, and the other to the left. The side that slid to the right took the majority of communal structures, forcing Open Orthodoxy to build his own. I don&#8217;t think either is actually perpetuating the MO that the Rav taught.</p>
<p>2- Going beyond what I said, I didn&#8217;t intend that as a value judgment, but as a historical statement. It could well be that the MO of a few decades ago addressed a need that today&#8217;s society doesn&#8217;t face. The fact that there isn&#8217;t a sizable community sticking with it would give some indication that it&#8217;s true. Which modification is holier? Which is healthier? I didn&#8217;t touch that issue.</p>
<p>3- Yes, I did call those who supported SCA as being to the left of the Rav. That&#8217;s not saying they would have gone as far was 21st cent Open O.</p>
<p>3- What I wrote elsewhere is that I don&#8217;t think &#8220;half Shabbos&#8221; is sustainable in large O communities outside of Open O. I actually think the majority of kids who are texting on Shabbos who attend MTA or TABC are either violating Shabbos more generally, or will be in the next few weeks. And I say that as someone who has a dozen or more teenagers at my home on the typical Shabbos afternoon, in various states between Mod-O and not-currently-O, and asked them if they knew kids who basically tried to keep Shabbos but can&#8217;t keep away from texting and their Facebook app. They haven&#8217;t heard of &#8220;Half Shabbos&#8221;, neither the term nor the concept. And if you search around on-line, this is the consistent result of such experiments. So I figure the phenomenon is localized in geography or community-space.</p>
<p>So, I have to guess what population would have such teens, some group that doesn&#8217;t overlap with my six teens&#8217; pools of friends. What came to mind were communities that aren&#8217;t as judgmental, that don&#8217;t force you to choose between complete compliance and affiliation: (1) Smaller out of town communities, (2) Open Orthodoxy. ((3) Lubavitch &#8212; but only WRT the not-yet-frum; they&#8217;re relatively less judgmental of their own kids&#8217; choices, but this far.)</p>
<p>But I said this because my &#8220;spies&#8221; in Teaneck, MTA, JEC, do NOT see what you, R&#8217; Burg, [R&#8217; Pelocovitz] your anonymous educator friend, etc&#8230; are speaking of. (My home neighborhood doesn&#8217;t have a sizable MO population. Too many kids entirely off the derekh and willing to use their phones on Shabbos, though&#8230;) Trying to find conditions that *don&#8217;t* match the typical Teaneck kid is what brought me to ask about Open O, not trying to *identify* the two.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/sliding-to-the-left/#comment-3318</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2011 19:22:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3801#comment-3318</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/sliding-to-the-left/#comment-3316&quot;&gt;Micha Berger&lt;/a&gt;.

Micha, 
You are doing more to build a historic and sociological base for Open Orthodoxy then anyone I know. They should pay you as their PR person. Here you calling all the old time rabbis who were not on the right, all the 1950&#039;s and 1960&#039;s Torah UMAdda rabbis as Open Orthodoxy. You are calling Rabbis like Rabbi President Belkin who supported the SCA as Open Orthodoxy. 
And elsewhere you have called the kids who may text on shabbos who go to TABC and MTA who live in Teaneck as Open Orthodox.   You are pre-dating it and making it an eternal struggle in YU granting it eternal importance. 
I did not know that you were such a supporter.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/sliding-to-the-left/#comment-3316">Micha Berger</a>.</p>
<p>Micha,<br />
You are doing more to build a historic and sociological base for Open Orthodoxy then anyone I know. They should pay you as their PR person. Here you calling all the old time rabbis who were not on the right, all the 1950&#8217;s and 1960&#8217;s Torah UMAdda rabbis as Open Orthodoxy. You are calling Rabbis like Rabbi President Belkin who supported the SCA as Open Orthodoxy.<br />
And elsewhere you have called the kids who may text on shabbos who go to TABC and MTA who live in Teaneck as Open Orthodox.   You are pre-dating it and making it an eternal struggle in YU granting it eternal importance.<br />
I did not know that you were such a supporter.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Micha Berger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/sliding-to-the-left/#comment-3316</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Micha Berger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2011 19:09:13 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3801#comment-3316</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I agree with &quot;ej&quot;... I read the trends as indicating a splitting of Modern Orthodoxy. National Conference of Young Israel and the RCA are Mod-O institutions that are trying to minimize (eliminate?) association with Yeshivat Chovevei Torah. This is what primarily motivated the creation of the IRF -- YCT grads and those sympathetic to their viewpoint weren&#039;t welcome anywhere else.

While YU, the OU, and the RCA appear to be firmly on the rightward drifting side of the trend, this split seems to be running down the middle of the Young Israel movement. Somewhere between the greater NY and other densely Orthodox areas, including the NCYI central office, and the rank and file YI in the rest of the country. Thus causing stories like &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.yucommentator.com/2.2828/leaking-ship-young-israel-on-the-rocks-1.297626&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Leaking Ship: Young Israel On The Rocks&lt;/a&gt;&quot; in the YU Commentator (Charlie Quinn, Dec 2007).

Rav Soloveichi, the Rav, was really the only thing that anchored Mod O together. Even when the right slide further right, fealty to their rebbe kept the slide from denying the basics of Mod-O. Under R&#039; Herschel Schachter, Torah uMaddah (Torah and [Academic] Knowledge) has become Torah uParanasah (Torah and making a living). Ideologically, the Rav&#039;s notion that secular knowledge is inherently holy because it is knowledge is no longer echoing down the halls of RIETS.

On the other hand, the same could be said of the leftward travels of some of his other students. When the Rav was alive, Open Orthodoxy had to have significant limits not now in effect; his guidelines on joining the SCA don&#039;t only obligate one in preserving the sanctity of the unified Jewish community when it came to matters of fate, it also prohibited one in uniting with heterodox movements and their leaders on matters of destiny. On pragmatics, survival, and dealing with the outside yes; on spirituality and internal matters, no.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I agree with &#8220;ej&#8221;&#8230; I read the trends as indicating a splitting of Modern Orthodoxy. National Conference of Young Israel and the RCA are Mod-O institutions that are trying to minimize (eliminate?) association with Yeshivat Chovevei Torah. This is what primarily motivated the creation of the IRF &#8212; YCT grads and those sympathetic to their viewpoint weren&#8217;t welcome anywhere else.</p>
<p>While YU, the OU, and the RCA appear to be firmly on the rightward drifting side of the trend, this split seems to be running down the middle of the Young Israel movement. Somewhere between the greater NY and other densely Orthodox areas, including the NCYI central office, and the rank and file YI in the rest of the country. Thus causing stories like &#8220;<a href="http://www.yucommentator.com/2.2828/leaking-ship-young-israel-on-the-rocks-1.297626" rel="nofollow">Leaking Ship: Young Israel On The Rocks</a>&#8221; in the YU Commentator (Charlie Quinn, Dec 2007).</p>
<p>Rav Soloveichi, the Rav, was really the only thing that anchored Mod O together. Even when the right slide further right, fealty to their rebbe kept the slide from denying the basics of Mod-O. Under R&#8217; Herschel Schachter, Torah uMaddah (Torah and [Academic] Knowledge) has become Torah uParanasah (Torah and making a living). Ideologically, the Rav&#8217;s notion that secular knowledge is inherently holy because it is knowledge is no longer echoing down the halls of RIETS.</p>
<p>On the other hand, the same could be said of the leftward travels of some of his other students. When the Rav was alive, Open Orthodoxy had to have significant limits not now in effect; his guidelines on joining the SCA don&#8217;t only obligate one in preserving the sanctity of the unified Jewish community when it came to matters of fate, it also prohibited one in uniting with heterodox movements and their leaders on matters of destiny. On pragmatics, survival, and dealing with the outside yes; on spirituality and internal matters, no.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/sliding-to-the-left/#comment-3315</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2011 19:05:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3801#comment-3315</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/sliding-to-the-left/#comment-3314&quot;&gt;yehudah&lt;/a&gt;.

Eli Clark thought that there are people, on what he calls the left,, that think that the right drops off of Modern Orthodoxy into becoming haredi. Heilman was not too far from that position in his sliding to the right. And go look at Waxman&#039;s 1997 article.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/sliding-to-the-left/#comment-3314">yehudah</a>.</p>
<p>Eli Clark thought that there are people, on what he calls the left,, that think that the right drops off of Modern Orthodoxy into becoming haredi. Heilman was not too far from that position in his sliding to the right. And go look at Waxman&#8217;s 1997 article.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: yehudah		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/sliding-to-the-left/#comment-3314</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[yehudah]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2011 18:59:51 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3801#comment-3314</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[this seems to miss an important point - the real slide to the left is about dropping out of orthodoxy altogether, and is a significant phenomenon in both the states and israel. the slide to the right, however, is never defined that way.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>this seems to miss an important point &#8211; the real slide to the left is about dropping out of orthodoxy altogether, and is a significant phenomenon in both the states and israel. the slide to the right, however, is never defined that way.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/sliding-to-the-left/#comment-3313</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2011 15:21:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3801#comment-3313</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Ben, 
That is my point in saying I dont use these categories... 
Those who speak of right and left treat Orthodox Judaism as a polity and try to lobby for one side.  I dont like that language at all. They also read everyone as if they are also treating it as a polity.
I posted this to let people know since so many others out there in our time think of Torah as a political caucus.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ben,<br />
That is my point in saying I dont use these categories&#8230;<br />
Those who speak of right and left treat Orthodox Judaism as a polity and try to lobby for one side.  I dont like that language at all. They also read everyone as if they are also treating it as a polity.<br />
I posted this to let people know since so many others out there in our time think of Torah as a political caucus.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Ben Pincus		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/sliding-to-the-left/#comment-3311</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Pincus]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2011 14:19:42 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3801#comment-3311</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I think this topic is moronic. Orthodox Judaism is among other things a culture and a society. It is not a polity. And if it is sliding one way or the other? What should I do about it? Tell my Rabbi what opinions to have? Start being more lenient in my own practice to level the playing field? Take on a chumrah to further strengthen the &#039;slide to the right?&#039; Should I opt out of Torah observance because frum culture or society changed in a way I don&#039;t like? How silly it all is. The only thing this topic can do is cause people to worry needlessly about something they can and should do absolutely nothing about. Here&#039;s my sage advice: serve Hashem as best you can and look for ways to improve that service. ]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think this topic is moronic. Orthodox Judaism is among other things a culture and a society. It is not a polity. And if it is sliding one way or the other? What should I do about it? Tell my Rabbi what opinions to have? Start being more lenient in my own practice to level the playing field? Take on a chumrah to further strengthen the &#8216;slide to the right?&#8217; Should I opt out of Torah observance because frum culture or society changed in a way I don&#8217;t like? How silly it all is. The only thing this topic can do is cause people to worry needlessly about something they can and should do absolutely nothing about. Here&#8217;s my sage advice: serve Hashem as best you can and look for ways to improve that service. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Jonathan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/sliding-to-the-left/#comment-3304</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jonathan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2011 22:52:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3801#comment-3304</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I think he is right outside of a few places ,YU Roshei Yeshiva have little influence on the broader Modern Orthodox Community .Perhaps the appointments of Rabbi&#039;s  Goldin &#038; Weil support this idea]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think he is right outside of a few places ,YU Roshei Yeshiva have little influence on the broader Modern Orthodox Community .Perhaps the appointments of Rabbi&#8217;s  Goldin &amp; Weil support this idea</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
