<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>tu beshevat &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/tag/tu-beshevat/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2010 06:23:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='kavvanah.wordpress.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/c9f111237f93750b6b994fc5185d49c3?s=96&#038;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>tu beshevat &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>Rabbi Morgenstern and Meditation</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/09/rabbi-morgenstern-and-meditation/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/09/rabbi-morgenstern-and-meditation/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2010 04:28:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Hasidism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kabbalah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Neo-Hasidism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[popular religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rabbis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[spirituality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ashlag]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Derech yihud]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[derekh yihud]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rav Itchie Mayer Morgenstern]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sheva Eynayim]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tu beshevat]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yitzhak Meir Moregenstern]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[YM Erlanger]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=751</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When someone mentions Jewish meditation to me the first thing I think of are the Haredi Kabbalitic mediators. I think of Y.M Erlanger who in his Sheva Eynayim and in classes in Heimishe Yeshivos is teaching Hasidut combined with Abulafia &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/09/rabbi-morgenstern-and-meditation/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When someone mentions Jewish meditation to me the first thing I think of are the Haredi Kabbalitic mediators. I think of Y.M Erlanger who in his <em>Sheva Eynayim</em> and in classes in Heimishe Yeshivos is teaching Hasidut combined with Abulafia and I think of Yitzhak Meir Moregenstern who is reorganizing early Kabbalah, Ramak, Ari, and Abulafia as Hasidut.  Erlanger’s starts with the statements in <em>Sefer Habesht al Hatorah </em>and introduces ever more esoteric material and at the end of the last volume, he introduces Abulafia with a warning that the material that he is about to teach is not for everyone, and not everyone should enter the Pardes, and even if you do enter this may not be for you. In contrast, Rabbi  Morgenstern called Rav Itchie Mayer Morgenstern starts everyone on the real stuff.</p>
<p>R. Morgenstern is a Haredi descendant of the Kotzker and lived most of his life in England and has moved to Jerusalem and set up a Beit Midrash. You can find videos of him teaching and singing with Anglos on the web.  See<a href="http://dixieyid.blogspot.com/2007/11/rav-itchie-mayer-shalosh-sheudos.html"> here,</a> <a href="http://dixieyid.blogspot.com/2007/05/chochma-vs-bina-practical_30.html">here </a>and <a href="http://dixieyid.blogspot.com/2007/05/chochma-vs-bina-practical.html">here.</a><br />
He has attached a real following. He gives weekly public shiurim in kavvanot, in Komarno, and Ramhal. He has an email list serve for his Torah, his kabbalah, and for assorted teachings (Hebrew, English, and Yiddish).  Send an email here to subscribe tc7@neto.bezeqint.net </p>
<p>He seems to have read some generic books on “How to Meditate” or “Meditation for Everyone” and in his work <em>Derekh Yihud</em> he reorganizes traditional  kabbalistic practices into an order that reflects the general mediation world. The topics are sitting, breathing, visualizing, creating an avir in front of one, colors, and  a unified vision.  He freely takes pieces of Abulafia, Ramak,  and early kabbalah to create a Jewish meditation manual in line with the non-Jewish ones. The work <em>Derekh Yihud</em> opens up a new path of reorganizing the older materials based on modern principles.</p>
<p>I see him as potentially the future.  Rav Ashlag wrote in the 1930’s and took the meditation, medieval worldview and fantasy out of the Kabbalah and replaced it was science, communism, Schopenhauer, and a closed system. Now everything from the Kabbalah Centre to Bnai Baruch to Michael Leitman are his spiritual descendents. Rabbi Morgensten is teaching the young grandchildren of the Rebbes and many  in Kolel and he also accepts the varied pneumatics of Jerusalem as his students.  When all those students take their positions as Rebbes, Ramim, and teachers then the meditation format of breathing and visualization will be the tradition.  If the trend continues,  in 2050 this will be mainstream Kabbalah. </p>
<p>I had originally planned this post before my computer crash when I received the following two weeks ago. It offers a concise taste of <em>Derekh Yihud.</em> Morgenstern advises to close the eyes and see the hidden lights  in order to achieve bliss. One turns from this world to the airspace and achieves a vision of the Throne. Lights, then hidden mind, and finally the source of the soul and the Throne.</p>
<blockquote><p>
When a Jew spends time in hisbodedus before his Creator, he closes his eyes so as not to be enticed by the illusory pleasures of this world because he doesn’t want to be connected to them.<br />
When he closes his eyes in this way, he is able to see the brilliant hues that are rooted in the “hidden mind” of Mocha Sesima’ah, and he begins to derive pleasure from spiritual reality, from the fact that Hashem is revealed through a myriad of shades and hues of dveikus. He starts to feel Hashem’s light and glory within himself, and how all of the pleasures of this world are null and void, are like a mere sliver of light, compared with the delight of dveikus that is a composite of all possible forms of bliss.</p>
<p>So when a person seals his vision against the illusory nature of this world, he rises to the place of the “airspace” and its “membrane,” which is really the source of the human soul and its throne of glory. In that place it can be said, “From my flesh, I see G-d.” One begins to enjoy a vision of the ultimate Kisei HaKavod upon which the “form of a person sat.”<br />
The final three plagues parallel these three states of dveikus:<br />
First, a person must meditate and be misboded on the expansive Binah light of Hashem.<br />
Then he must ascend to the place of the “hidden mind” which is the counterpart of the holy darkness of turning aside from this-worldly concerns to receive “light in all his dwellings.” With this, he destroys the klippah of the impure firstborn and rises further to the place of the “membrane of the airspace” and the “airspace” itself which correlates to the level of the Da’as of Atik and which reveals to him the source of his neshamah that “sits upon the throne.”<br />
 “It is revealed and known before Your Kisei HaKavod&#8230;” Meaning, through coming to the level of the Kisei HaKavod, we are able to subdue all of the klippos and utterly “smite Egypt through their firstborns.”</p></blockquote>
<p>This past week he sent out a special Tu beShevat essay. He opens the essay stating that was asked why Hayyim Vital did not mention TuBeshevat and answers in the name of R. Haayim Cohen that it is a hidden quality. And when pressed why does everyone do it today? He turns to R. Aharon Halevi of Strashelye explaining that since we are lesser today everyone learns Kabbalah since they do not grasp the real depth anyway.  The essay is a running account of his Torah and the questions he received Tu Beshevat-Shabbat Shrah. There are many interesting points in it including -We are told of the joy from the recent publishing  of Vital’s alchemy and magic.</p>
<p>Copyright © 2010 Alan Brill • All Rights Reserved</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/02/09/rabbi-morgenstern-and-meditation/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>31</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
