<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Why Maimonides Matters &#8211; Kenneth Hart Green- Part I	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/18/why-maimonides-matters-kenneth-hart-green-part-i/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/18/why-maimonides-matters-kenneth-hart-green-part-i/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2013 23:15:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: moti		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/18/why-maimonides-matters-kenneth-hart-green-part-i/#comment-8047</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[moti]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2013 23:15:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6093#comment-8047</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/18/why-maimonides-matters-kenneth-hart-green-part-i/#comment-8035&quot;&gt;Saul Shajnfeld&lt;/a&gt;.

I want to take issue with one thing in Saul Shajnfeld&#039;s comment. You say, &#039;Rambam says that Judaism requires emunah in Hashem. But emunah—by itself—is not a faculty or tool that has any usefulness in apprehending emes—the truth.&#039;

But I think the notion of emunah / faith that you&#039;re referring to is foreign to the Guide of the Perplexed, in fact it&#039;s directly ridiculed in Part 1 Chapter 50.

The word &#039;emunah&#039; in different forms was used by translator&#039;s of the Guide and the Commentary on the Mishnah to translate the Arabic i&#039;tiqad. In Mishneh Torah, written in Hebrew, in the parallel sections, the Rambam used the verb לידע.

There is no faith in the sense of a mental trick or leap in the Rambam, only striving to understand. On that point at least, I don&#039;t think your issue is an issue with Maimonides.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/18/why-maimonides-matters-kenneth-hart-green-part-i/#comment-8035">Saul Shajnfeld</a>.</p>
<p>I want to take issue with one thing in Saul Shajnfeld&#8217;s comment. You say, &#8216;Rambam says that Judaism requires emunah in Hashem. But emunah—by itself—is not a faculty or tool that has any usefulness in apprehending emes—the truth.&#8217;</p>
<p>But I think the notion of emunah / faith that you&#8217;re referring to is foreign to the Guide of the Perplexed, in fact it&#8217;s directly ridiculed in Part 1 Chapter 50.</p>
<p>The word &#8217;emunah&#8217; in different forms was used by translator&#8217;s of the Guide and the Commentary on the Mishnah to translate the Arabic i&#8217;tiqad. In Mishneh Torah, written in Hebrew, in the parallel sections, the Rambam used the verb לידע.</p>
<p>There is no faith in the sense of a mental trick or leap in the Rambam, only striving to understand. On that point at least, I don&#8217;t think your issue is an issue with Maimonides.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Saul Shajnfeld		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/18/why-maimonides-matters-kenneth-hart-green-part-i/#comment-8035</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Saul Shajnfeld]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2013 17:40:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6093#comment-8035</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A question for Professor Green:

Please forgive it if my questions are simpleminded—I’m not an expert on Rambam.  I was raised as an Orthodox Jew.  I am interested in how Rambam would react to Jewish heretics (“kofrim”) if he were alive today.

1. I believe that Rambam requires ostracism of kofrim.  While Aristotle confronted Judaism with difficult philosophical problems in Rambam’s day, the number of problems we are confronted with today greatly surpasses those in his day.  The questionable authorship of the Torah—raised by Higher Criticism, historical errors, anachronisms, contradictions, the use of Hebrew, etc.—has been acknowledged to be severely problematic by such prominent frum thinkers as R. Mordechai Breuer and R. David Weiss Halivni, among others.  Their attempts to salvage the idea of a divine Torah are questionable at best.

The problem of theodicy still is with us, despite the creative imaginative abilities of fundamentalists, whose bag of tricks include such unfalsifiable concepts as olam haba, gilgulim and hester panim.  All such concepts could have been used just as easily to defend “false gods” like Ba’al, Moloch, etc.

Like the idol-gods that Tehillim ridicules as having ears but not hearing (i.e., being impotent), Hashem has failed us at every turn: the first Churban; the second Churban, when Jewish blood was flowing like a river; the Crusades; The Inquisition; the Pogroms of Russia and Eastern Europe; and finally, the Holocaust.  Hashem was nowhere to be found.  Talk about impotence.

Scientific and archaeological discoveries continue to clash with literal Torah.  And, following Rambam, Judaism keeps “reinterpreting,” allegorizing and retrenching.  The latest victim is Noah’s flood.  Its historicity having been discredited by almost every discipline, a 2009 article in the RCA’s journal Tradition makes the absurd claim that Hashem incorporated into the Torah a mythological Babylonian epic.  What will be identified next as a myth—the story of Avraham Avinu?  

And how are we allowed to reinterpret so freely when our entire belief system rests on an allegedly “unbroken chain of tradition?”  Not a single member of Chazal or Rishon ever questioned the historicity of the flood.  We were taught that it’s what Moshe taught B’nei Yisra’el.  Does our mesorah go “poof” with every new discovery?  Is it, too, unreliable?

Orthodoxy talks about Hashem’s grand design.  But science shows us that 50% of human embryos in the U.S. never make it to live births (they are expelled as deformed embryos and fetuses), and many of those that do are deformed or dysfunctional.  A company producing radios that had to throw out 50% of their finished products as inoperable would be adjudged incompetent, and would fail.  Hashem, the incompetent designer?  The answer, of course, is evolution.  Not design, but meandering.

So a six-day creation is now 13.7 billion years.  Adam is a mythical being, as homo sapiens is between 50,00 and 200,000 year old.  We are descended from ape-like creatures (human embryos still have full-length tails), not separately created.  One Orthodox rabbi tells us that the first 11 chapters of Genesis are all myth.

And many, many more problems for the believer.  So, were Rambam alive today, would he advocate one retrenching after another?  Or would he act like the intellectually honest genius he was, and be an agnostic, probably teaching at MIT or Harvard?

There are just so many hits that a belief system can take before the neon sign flashes, “GAME OVER.”  But to believing Jews, it will never flash.  They have emunah.

2. Rambam says that Judaism requires emunah in Hashem.  But emunah—by itself—is not a faculty or tool that has any usefulness in apprehending emes—the truth.  And we can see the value and usefulness of emunah as a tool for reaching truth simply by noting that over three billion Christians, Moslems and Hindus use emunah to &quot;know&quot; the &quot;truths&quot; of, respectively, Christianity, Islam and Hinduism.  Using emunah to determine truth is like using a hammer to determine the distance to the moon.  Not a useful tool for that purpose.  Emunah is a hefker velt: it is based on early indoctrination, and it takes you wherever you want to go.  Didn&#039;t Rambam realize that?

It is easier and more rational for a thoughtful, educated Jew today to be a heretic that to be a believer.  So, my question is: what do you think that Rambam would say if he were alive today?  Would he ostracize kofrim for the crime of using their intelligence, and for the crime of rejecting an obviously useless thing like emunah?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A question for Professor Green:</p>
<p>Please forgive it if my questions are simpleminded—I’m not an expert on Rambam.  I was raised as an Orthodox Jew.  I am interested in how Rambam would react to Jewish heretics (“kofrim”) if he were alive today.</p>
<p>1. I believe that Rambam requires ostracism of kofrim.  While Aristotle confronted Judaism with difficult philosophical problems in Rambam’s day, the number of problems we are confronted with today greatly surpasses those in his day.  The questionable authorship of the Torah—raised by Higher Criticism, historical errors, anachronisms, contradictions, the use of Hebrew, etc.—has been acknowledged to be severely problematic by such prominent frum thinkers as R. Mordechai Breuer and R. David Weiss Halivni, among others.  Their attempts to salvage the idea of a divine Torah are questionable at best.</p>
<p>The problem of theodicy still is with us, despite the creative imaginative abilities of fundamentalists, whose bag of tricks include such unfalsifiable concepts as olam haba, gilgulim and hester panim.  All such concepts could have been used just as easily to defend “false gods” like Ba’al, Moloch, etc.</p>
<p>Like the idol-gods that Tehillim ridicules as having ears but not hearing (i.e., being impotent), Hashem has failed us at every turn: the first Churban; the second Churban, when Jewish blood was flowing like a river; the Crusades; The Inquisition; the Pogroms of Russia and Eastern Europe; and finally, the Holocaust.  Hashem was nowhere to be found.  Talk about impotence.</p>
<p>Scientific and archaeological discoveries continue to clash with literal Torah.  And, following Rambam, Judaism keeps “reinterpreting,” allegorizing and retrenching.  The latest victim is Noah’s flood.  Its historicity having been discredited by almost every discipline, a 2009 article in the RCA’s journal Tradition makes the absurd claim that Hashem incorporated into the Torah a mythological Babylonian epic.  What will be identified next as a myth—the story of Avraham Avinu?  </p>
<p>And how are we allowed to reinterpret so freely when our entire belief system rests on an allegedly “unbroken chain of tradition?”  Not a single member of Chazal or Rishon ever questioned the historicity of the flood.  We were taught that it’s what Moshe taught B’nei Yisra’el.  Does our mesorah go “poof” with every new discovery?  Is it, too, unreliable?</p>
<p>Orthodoxy talks about Hashem’s grand design.  But science shows us that 50% of human embryos in the U.S. never make it to live births (they are expelled as deformed embryos and fetuses), and many of those that do are deformed or dysfunctional.  A company producing radios that had to throw out 50% of their finished products as inoperable would be adjudged incompetent, and would fail.  Hashem, the incompetent designer?  The answer, of course, is evolution.  Not design, but meandering.</p>
<p>So a six-day creation is now 13.7 billion years.  Adam is a mythical being, as homo sapiens is between 50,00 and 200,000 year old.  We are descended from ape-like creatures (human embryos still have full-length tails), not separately created.  One Orthodox rabbi tells us that the first 11 chapters of Genesis are all myth.</p>
<p>And many, many more problems for the believer.  So, were Rambam alive today, would he advocate one retrenching after another?  Or would he act like the intellectually honest genius he was, and be an agnostic, probably teaching at MIT or Harvard?</p>
<p>There are just so many hits that a belief system can take before the neon sign flashes, “GAME OVER.”  But to believing Jews, it will never flash.  They have emunah.</p>
<p>2. Rambam says that Judaism requires emunah in Hashem.  But emunah—by itself—is not a faculty or tool that has any usefulness in apprehending emes—the truth.  And we can see the value and usefulness of emunah as a tool for reaching truth simply by noting that over three billion Christians, Moslems and Hindus use emunah to &#8220;know&#8221; the &#8220;truths&#8221; of, respectively, Christianity, Islam and Hinduism.  Using emunah to determine truth is like using a hammer to determine the distance to the moon.  Not a useful tool for that purpose.  Emunah is a hefker velt: it is based on early indoctrination, and it takes you wherever you want to go.  Didn&#8217;t Rambam realize that?</p>
<p>It is easier and more rational for a thoughtful, educated Jew today to be a heretic that to be a believer.  So, my question is: what do you think that Rambam would say if he were alive today?  Would he ostracize kofrim for the crime of using their intelligence, and for the crime of rejecting an obviously useless thing like emunah?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Lawrence Kaplan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/18/why-maimonides-matters-kenneth-hart-green-part-i/#comment-8034</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lawrence Kaplan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2013 16:22:33 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6093#comment-8034</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[To add to George&#039;s list: Not to mention Krochmal, Shay Ish Horowitz, and others. 

On the other hand, in his essay &quot;Cohen and Maimonides&quot; Strauss make some very cogent  criticisms of Cohen, particularly  with regard to the latter&#039;s interpretation of Maimonides&#039; attributes of action.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>To add to George&#8217;s list: Not to mention Krochmal, Shay Ish Horowitz, and others. </p>
<p>On the other hand, in his essay &#8220;Cohen and Maimonides&#8221; Strauss make some very cogent  criticisms of Cohen, particularly  with regard to the latter&#8217;s interpretation of Maimonides&#8217; attributes of action.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Micha Berger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/18/why-maimonides-matters-kenneth-hart-green-part-i/#comment-8029</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Micha Berger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2013 02:09:11 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6093#comment-8029</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/18/why-maimonides-matters-kenneth-hart-green-part-i/#comment-8016&quot;&gt;Micha Berger&lt;/a&gt;.

I wrote: &quot;Leo Strauss took the topic of esoterica and used it to turn the Moreh into a Rorschach Test.&quot;

By which I mean his use of Maimonides&#039; 7th reason for contradictions in the text to dismiss parts of the Guide itself as hiding esoterica. Not the topic here (#2) of esoterica in the Torah. As phrased here, there is nothing novel -- the notion that the Torah is constantly mined for messages to each generation and milieu is fundamental to accepting the notion of an Oral Torah.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/18/why-maimonides-matters-kenneth-hart-green-part-i/#comment-8016">Micha Berger</a>.</p>
<p>I wrote: &#8220;Leo Strauss took the topic of esoterica and used it to turn the Moreh into a Rorschach Test.&#8221;</p>
<p>By which I mean his use of Maimonides&#8217; 7th reason for contradictions in the text to dismiss parts of the Guide itself as hiding esoterica. Not the topic here (#2) of esoterica in the Torah. As phrased here, there is nothing novel &#8212; the notion that the Torah is constantly mined for messages to each generation and milieu is fundamental to accepting the notion of an Oral Torah.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: George Y. Kohler		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/18/why-maimonides-matters-kenneth-hart-green-part-i/#comment-8026</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[George Y. Kohler]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2013 19:58:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6093#comment-8026</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&quot;Prior to Strauss, Maimonides was viewed as an antiquated medieval figure—though revered by a select group of scholars for his achievements which occurred in the distant past—but nevertheless not particularly relevant to modern Judaism, never mind to modern people in general...&quot;
This is as wrong as can be. Just read Hermann Cohen&#039;s &quot;Religion of Reason out of the sources of Judaism&quot; (1918) and you will find how much Maimonides was thought to be relevant for modern Jewish theology. In fact the entire German Reform Movement of the 19th Century apopted Maimonides&#039; thought for their modernizing purposes.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&#8220;Prior to Strauss, Maimonides was viewed as an antiquated medieval figure—though revered by a select group of scholars for his achievements which occurred in the distant past—but nevertheless not particularly relevant to modern Judaism, never mind to modern people in general&#8230;&#8221;<br />
This is as wrong as can be. Just read Hermann Cohen&#8217;s &#8220;Religion of Reason out of the sources of Judaism&#8221; (1918) and you will find how much Maimonides was thought to be relevant for modern Jewish theology. In fact the entire German Reform Movement of the 19th Century apopted Maimonides&#8217; thought for their modernizing purposes.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Micha Berger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/18/why-maimonides-matters-kenneth-hart-green-part-i/#comment-8016</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Micha Berger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2013 14:34:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6093#comment-8016</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Leo Strauss took the topic of esoterica and used it to turn the Moreh into a Rorschach Test.

I think the Rambam&#039;s meta-issues are of interest, but don&#039;t overplay it. The Rambam fit Jewish Thought to Natural Philosophy, not science. It is more equal of a choice to decide whether to listen to a Babylonian amora&#039;s discussion of qemei&#039;os that work or of sheidim or a Greek philosopher&#039;s conclusion that they respectively couldn&#039;t work and don&#039;t exist. Aristotilian thought barely advanced in the 1,500 years before the Rambam; part of what gave it such an aura of authority. With science comes two things: evidence based conclusions and a spirit of progress.

So the parallel challenge facing us isn&#039;t really the same thing.

In terms of mesorah, his philosophy is a distinct minority view. Not that there is a halachic process with regard to Jewish Thought, but it&#039;s still worth noting. The Rambam so embraced Aristotilianism that he understood the connection between G-d and Creation to be Thought -- and thus the connection from us created being to G-d to be thought. Ethics and morality, or even a personal relationship with G-d, the ideas which most of us would feel more comfortable making the measure of man, become handmaidens to intellectual development (in the case of ethics and morality) or dismissed as impossible (in his vision G-d is not a Person to whom you can relate). And those aren&#039;t only ideas we&#039;re more comfortable with, and were the centerpieces of Jewish Thought for the past 250 years, they&#039;re also the language Chazal talk in.

I disagree with but understand the tradition that has students skip the first 4 chapters of Maimonides&#039; Code and of the Guide. (And the first section of R&#039; Bachya ibn Paquda&#039;s Chovos haLavavos for the same reason.) We simply aren&#039;t perplexed by Aristotilian questions and wouldn&#039;t be happy with Aistotilian answers. So I can see someone asking why we should bother opening those questions.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Leo Strauss took the topic of esoterica and used it to turn the Moreh into a Rorschach Test.</p>
<p>I think the Rambam&#8217;s meta-issues are of interest, but don&#8217;t overplay it. The Rambam fit Jewish Thought to Natural Philosophy, not science. It is more equal of a choice to decide whether to listen to a Babylonian amora&#8217;s discussion of qemei&#8217;os that work or of sheidim or a Greek philosopher&#8217;s conclusion that they respectively couldn&#8217;t work and don&#8217;t exist. Aristotilian thought barely advanced in the 1,500 years before the Rambam; part of what gave it such an aura of authority. With science comes two things: evidence based conclusions and a spirit of progress.</p>
<p>So the parallel challenge facing us isn&#8217;t really the same thing.</p>
<p>In terms of mesorah, his philosophy is a distinct minority view. Not that there is a halachic process with regard to Jewish Thought, but it&#8217;s still worth noting. The Rambam so embraced Aristotilianism that he understood the connection between G-d and Creation to be Thought &#8212; and thus the connection from us created being to G-d to be thought. Ethics and morality, or even a personal relationship with G-d, the ideas which most of us would feel more comfortable making the measure of man, become handmaidens to intellectual development (in the case of ethics and morality) or dismissed as impossible (in his vision G-d is not a Person to whom you can relate). And those aren&#8217;t only ideas we&#8217;re more comfortable with, and were the centerpieces of Jewish Thought for the past 250 years, they&#8217;re also the language Chazal talk in.</p>
<p>I disagree with but understand the tradition that has students skip the first 4 chapters of Maimonides&#8217; Code and of the Guide. (And the first section of R&#8217; Bachya ibn Paquda&#8217;s Chovos haLavavos for the same reason.) We simply aren&#8217;t perplexed by Aristotilian questions and wouldn&#8217;t be happy with Aistotilian answers. So I can see someone asking why we should bother opening those questions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: moti		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/18/why-maimonides-matters-kenneth-hart-green-part-i/#comment-8015</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[moti]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2013 04:37:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6093#comment-8015</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Two separate topics are combined here: &#039;why maimonides matters&#039; and &#039;why leo strauss matters&#039;. Maimonides has engaged people in every generation--you see the imprint of the &#039;guide&#039; everywhere--even, strongly, among people who reacted against it, like the kabbalists. Yes, I guess it was always an elite pursuit but I don&#039;t know if it&#039;s accurate to say that Leo Strauss &#039;changed all of that&#039;. His mysterious treatments of Maimonides have probably, unfortunately, caused ordinary people to turn back after having an urge to look into Maimonides--people who who would have benefited from some of the great religious ideas of the Guide.

Re: &quot;no one has proved Strauss wrong about Maimonides’ esotericism&quot;--that seems like a straw man. Esoteric readings of the Guide started right from ibn Tibbon and they&#039;re there in the standard commentaries printed in the common hebrew edition. Perhaps Strauss made the topic interesting or respectable for academics to pursue, I don&#039;t know, and that would be an interesting contribution. But the products of Strauss&#039;s reading--the interpretations he arrived at--are a separate matter, as is the proportion to take in, between exotericism and esotericism, in approaching the Guide and presenting it to interested readers.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Two separate topics are combined here: &#8216;why maimonides matters&#8217; and &#8216;why leo strauss matters&#8217;. Maimonides has engaged people in every generation&#8211;you see the imprint of the &#8216;guide&#8217; everywhere&#8211;even, strongly, among people who reacted against it, like the kabbalists. Yes, I guess it was always an elite pursuit but I don&#8217;t know if it&#8217;s accurate to say that Leo Strauss &#8216;changed all of that&#8217;. His mysterious treatments of Maimonides have probably, unfortunately, caused ordinary people to turn back after having an urge to look into Maimonides&#8211;people who who would have benefited from some of the great religious ideas of the Guide.</p>
<p>Re: &#8220;no one has proved Strauss wrong about Maimonides’ esotericism&#8221;&#8211;that seems like a straw man. Esoteric readings of the Guide started right from ibn Tibbon and they&#8217;re there in the standard commentaries printed in the common hebrew edition. Perhaps Strauss made the topic interesting or respectable for academics to pursue, I don&#8217;t know, and that would be an interesting contribution. But the products of Strauss&#8217;s reading&#8211;the interpretations he arrived at&#8211;are a separate matter, as is the proportion to take in, between exotericism and esotericism, in approaching the Guide and presenting it to interested readers.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
