<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Exorcisms of Personality Traits and Hidden Scandal	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/12/exorcisms-of-personality-traits/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/12/exorcisms-of-personality-traits/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Jul 2010 18:01:55 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Yonatan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/12/exorcisms-of-personality-traits/#comment-1329</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Yonatan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 16 Jul 2010 18:01:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1664#comment-1329</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I actually enjoyed reading American Exorcism two years ago and I think that several points need to be made:

1) We should distinguish between &quot;deliverance&quot; &#038; full blown &quot;exorcisms&quot;. While the latter is considered far more extreme, the world of Pentacostalism accepts the belief (akin to many Jewish communities historically) that their world is filled with demons and that these demons need to be removed.  It&#039;s not a single demon afflicing you, but many dark forces. 

Deliverance often takes place many times (like a series of medical treatments). 

2) One cannot separate deliverance &#038; exorcisms as it is currently practiced in America from Pentacostalism &#038; Pentacostal Culture/Theology. 

It is a world with a strong sense of presence of a very immanent God along with forces of good and evil. Additionally, one cannot separate deliverance from such practices as healing, speaking in tongues &#038; prophecy.

3) One cannot make a strong distinction between therapy vs. deliverance, as they often accompany each other as complimentary treatments, akin to medicine &#038; alternative medicines.

As an aside, when I was explaining deliverance to my wife, she said that it made a lot of sense and would probably be very healing way of dealing with past traumas.

4) Lastly, I don&#039;t think that one could make such a strong distinction for internal vs. external sources of problems, as many used Freudianism as a way of claiming that they were not responsible for their flaws or claimed societal responsibility for their problems. 

I have wondered for a while why Exorcism &#038; Deliverance was not more prominent in Jewish Renewal Circles.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I actually enjoyed reading American Exorcism two years ago and I think that several points need to be made:</p>
<p>1) We should distinguish between &#8220;deliverance&#8221; &amp; full blown &#8220;exorcisms&#8221;. While the latter is considered far more extreme, the world of Pentacostalism accepts the belief (akin to many Jewish communities historically) that their world is filled with demons and that these demons need to be removed.  It&#8217;s not a single demon afflicing you, but many dark forces. </p>
<p>Deliverance often takes place many times (like a series of medical treatments). </p>
<p>2) One cannot separate deliverance &amp; exorcisms as it is currently practiced in America from Pentacostalism &amp; Pentacostal Culture/Theology. </p>
<p>It is a world with a strong sense of presence of a very immanent God along with forces of good and evil. Additionally, one cannot separate deliverance from such practices as healing, speaking in tongues &amp; prophecy.</p>
<p>3) One cannot make a strong distinction between therapy vs. deliverance, as they often accompany each other as complimentary treatments, akin to medicine &amp; alternative medicines.</p>
<p>As an aside, when I was explaining deliverance to my wife, she said that it made a lot of sense and would probably be very healing way of dealing with past traumas.</p>
<p>4) Lastly, I don&#8217;t think that one could make such a strong distinction for internal vs. external sources of problems, as many used Freudianism as a way of claiming that they were not responsible for their flaws or claimed societal responsibility for their problems. </p>
<p>I have wondered for a while why Exorcism &amp; Deliverance was not more prominent in Jewish Renewal Circles.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/12/exorcisms-of-personality-traits/#comment-1324</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Jul 2010 13:18:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1664#comment-1324</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[There is autonomy in the sense of being bound or not bound to various sets of norms. Then there is autonomy as a sense of personal causal efficacy. We are talking about the latter, and in that sense Orthodox Jews see themselves as fully autonomous, and are not pre-modern. 

By move away from spirit possession I&#039;m referring to the apparent epidemic of possession in 16th-early 17th century Safed and related circles followed by its almost complete disappearance. 

And these were individual cases, not presumably intentionally cultivated, nor did they occur collectively among groups. This is quite different from mass speaking in tongues or being overcome by the spirit where there are clear and pronounced social-psychological effects.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There is autonomy in the sense of being bound or not bound to various sets of norms. Then there is autonomy as a sense of personal causal efficacy. We are talking about the latter, and in that sense Orthodox Jews see themselves as fully autonomous, and are not pre-modern. </p>
<p>By move away from spirit possession I&#8217;m referring to the apparent epidemic of possession in 16th-early 17th century Safed and related circles followed by its almost complete disappearance. </p>
<p>And these were individual cases, not presumably intentionally cultivated, nor did they occur collectively among groups. This is quite different from mass speaking in tongues or being overcome by the spirit where there are clear and pronounced social-psychological effects.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/12/exorcisms-of-personality-traits/#comment-1321</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Jul 2010 02:20:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1664#comment-1321</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[No one is really autonomous, but most everyone is not walking around with a 3000 year tradition of writing down more and more rules to govern behavior. Orthodoxy has the same split between conscious and unconscious ideation as the rest of humanity  plus a superego on steroids. We are less autonomous than Protestants who feel reading the bible and deciding ethical questions are personal.

Evangelical charismatics are not necessary for demonic possesion, but in its absence, cases are much less frequent. I don&#039;t know what you are referring to when you speak of Orthodoxy&#039;s move away from demonic possesion? When  did Orthodoxy ever move toward demonic possesion? A story about Reb Elchanan Wasserman or a play by Ansky is not a moving towards.

In a Catholic charismatic church with a monthly healing mass, fifty people can come forward out of a congregation of a few hundred, most all will fall to the ground whether or not they will it,and of those five or so people praying on their behalf maybe two will talk in tongues involuntarily. A case of serious demonic possesion every few years is quite normal. To the best of my knowledge even the most forlorn shtetl west of the Hudson does not have cases of demonic posession every two-three years.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>No one is really autonomous, but most everyone is not walking around with a 3000 year tradition of writing down more and more rules to govern behavior. Orthodoxy has the same split between conscious and unconscious ideation as the rest of humanity  plus a superego on steroids. We are less autonomous than Protestants who feel reading the bible and deciding ethical questions are personal.</p>
<p>Evangelical charismatics are not necessary for demonic possesion, but in its absence, cases are much less frequent. I don&#8217;t know what you are referring to when you speak of Orthodoxy&#8217;s move away from demonic possesion? When  did Orthodoxy ever move toward demonic possesion? A story about Reb Elchanan Wasserman or a play by Ansky is not a moving towards.</p>
<p>In a Catholic charismatic church with a monthly healing mass, fifty people can come forward out of a congregation of a few hundred, most all will fall to the ground whether or not they will it,and of those five or so people praying on their behalf maybe two will talk in tongues involuntarily. A case of serious demonic possesion every few years is quite normal. To the best of my knowledge even the most forlorn shtetl west of the Hudson does not have cases of demonic posession every two-three years.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/12/exorcisms-of-personality-traits/#comment-1314</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2010 11:22:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1664#comment-1314</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/12/exorcisms-of-personality-traits/#comment-1311&quot;&gt;ej&lt;/a&gt;.

No one is really autonomous - we realize that this is the driving myth of modernity. Nonetheless, religious Jews today are just as invested in this idea because they believe in their personal efficacy to effect change in the world and in themselves. Being bound to some extent by tradition and culture is pretty par for the course for everyone. Dr. Brill was pointing to the rejection of this notion of autonomy.

If you are only looking at the Zohar and Ari then you are missing the actual accounts of demon possession and exorcism in many other sources. Look at them and it becomes apparent that they were often airing shameful secrets that could not otherwise be spoken  And there is no indication that I&#039;ve seen that many of those who were infected were participants in a charismatic tradition. You seem to mistake what happens to come to mind when you think of demonic possession and exorcism (evangelical charismatics) as necessary conditions for its instantiation when this is simply not the case. 

I think it is clear that for Orthodoxy much of the move away from spirit possession, as Dr. Brill alluded, simply has to do with society moving to psycho-dynamic or behaviorist conceptions of the psyche.

My previous question was why return to demonic causes when there are all sorts of other external factors that could be blamed instead?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/12/exorcisms-of-personality-traits/#comment-1311">ej</a>.</p>
<p>No one is really autonomous &#8211; we realize that this is the driving myth of modernity. Nonetheless, religious Jews today are just as invested in this idea because they believe in their personal efficacy to effect change in the world and in themselves. Being bound to some extent by tradition and culture is pretty par for the course for everyone. Dr. Brill was pointing to the rejection of this notion of autonomy.</p>
<p>If you are only looking at the Zohar and Ari then you are missing the actual accounts of demon possession and exorcism in many other sources. Look at them and it becomes apparent that they were often airing shameful secrets that could not otherwise be spoken  And there is no indication that I&#8217;ve seen that many of those who were infected were participants in a charismatic tradition. You seem to mistake what happens to come to mind when you think of demonic possession and exorcism (evangelical charismatics) as necessary conditions for its instantiation when this is simply not the case. </p>
<p>I think it is clear that for Orthodoxy much of the move away from spirit possession, as Dr. Brill alluded, simply has to do with society moving to psycho-dynamic or behaviorist conceptions of the psyche.</p>
<p>My previous question was why return to demonic causes when there are all sorts of other external factors that could be blamed instead?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/12/exorcisms-of-personality-traits/#comment-1311</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Jul 2010 17:12:54 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1664#comment-1311</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[You are conflating a bunch of ideas. Religious  Jews are not fully autonomous even without possession by demons  because we are born Jews, and our Torah and culture are handed down from previous generations. We are not told to leave home to create our own way. Second externalization and  projection. If you want to be really careful about not projecting, every strongly held belief about others should be examined for possible projection of some inner ambivalence, much like certain vegetables are inspected for bugs. Nothing directly to do with exorcism which involves both externalization and possession by a demon because of  a subsequent re-internalization.
For exorcisms to be common  I think you need an acceptance  of being moved by the Holy Spirit, and its consequences shaking, falling to the floor, speaking in tongues and more. Jews do not come from such a charismatic tradition. Jews do talk of demons,  but it is a speculation that all such talk comes from being unable to talk of the sin. The Zohar and the Ari talk up a storm on the sin  of masturbation and how it creates demons in the world. No exorcisms, but teshuva, fasting and repentance are recommended. The same with current Orthodoxy and homosexuality and the abuse of minors. So far no dibukim have been sighted.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>You are conflating a bunch of ideas. Religious  Jews are not fully autonomous even without possession by demons  because we are born Jews, and our Torah and culture are handed down from previous generations. We are not told to leave home to create our own way. Second externalization and  projection. If you want to be really careful about not projecting, every strongly held belief about others should be examined for possible projection of some inner ambivalence, much like certain vegetables are inspected for bugs. Nothing directly to do with exorcism which involves both externalization and possession by a demon because of  a subsequent re-internalization.<br />
For exorcisms to be common  I think you need an acceptance  of being moved by the Holy Spirit, and its consequences shaking, falling to the floor, speaking in tongues and more. Jews do not come from such a charismatic tradition. Jews do talk of demons,  but it is a speculation that all such talk comes from being unable to talk of the sin. The Zohar and the Ari talk up a storm on the sin  of masturbation and how it creates demons in the world. No exorcisms, but teshuva, fasting and repentance are recommended. The same with current Orthodoxy and homosexuality and the abuse of minors. So far no dibukim have been sighted.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/12/exorcisms-of-personality-traits/#comment-1307</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Jul 2010 11:59:50 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1664#comment-1307</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[So at what point does a religious group decide that it&#039;s caused by demons instead of projecting the perceived malady onto the evils of communism, materialism, secularism, feminism, humanism, etc? There are all sorts of non-magical externalized explanations available. What spells the end of &quot;autonomous modernity&quot;? perhaps it is the recognition that these forces are so pervasive that their presence is not recognized as causally salient.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>So at what point does a religious group decide that it&#8217;s caused by demons instead of projecting the perceived malady onto the evils of communism, materialism, secularism, feminism, humanism, etc? There are all sorts of non-magical externalized explanations available. What spells the end of &#8220;autonomous modernity&#8221;? perhaps it is the recognition that these forces are so pervasive that their presence is not recognized as causally salient.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
