<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Prof Brian Klug on Revelation and Torah from Heaven	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/18/prof-brian-klug-on-revelation-and-torah-from-heaven/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/18/prof-brian-klug-on-revelation-and-torah-from-heaven/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2013 04:34:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: George Brieger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/18/prof-brian-klug-on-revelation-and-torah-from-heaven/#comment-7892</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[George Brieger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2013 04:34:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6041#comment-7892</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Professor, I watched the video you linked about Wittgenstein, and believe I understand generally the later Wittgenstein&#039;s understanding of words  playing a role, particularly words in a religious context. The short piece I quoted from Prof. Klug appears to state that the word &quot;belief&quot; in a religious context works differently from the way it works in most every day speech.  In this he is following Wittgenstein. 

Where I think you are incorrect is when you write that Klug (or Wittgenstein)  would disagree with the statement that as a historical matter, in the world of facts, the Pentateuch is most unlikely to have been given at Sinai. Unless you are saying that the philosopher is like an ostrich, who is ignorant of the field of Bible studies or rejects the scholarly consensus in the field, or is incapable occasionally of playing a game of checkers (in addition to the game of the philosophy of religion). Or is he like an intellectual plumber, totally unconcerned with the actual history of the primary sacred text at the center of his religion? Notice I did not use the term &quot;belief&quot; in the previous three sentences. 

Then, as I think we agree, when considering the word &quot;belief&quot; (and its synonyms) in the religious sense, he can decide to play the religious language game, in which historical facts (and metaphysical reality) are deemed irrelevant.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Professor, I watched the video you linked about Wittgenstein, and believe I understand generally the later Wittgenstein&#8217;s understanding of words  playing a role, particularly words in a religious context. The short piece I quoted from Prof. Klug appears to state that the word &#8220;belief&#8221; in a religious context works differently from the way it works in most every day speech.  In this he is following Wittgenstein. </p>
<p>Where I think you are incorrect is when you write that Klug (or Wittgenstein)  would disagree with the statement that as a historical matter, in the world of facts, the Pentateuch is most unlikely to have been given at Sinai. Unless you are saying that the philosopher is like an ostrich, who is ignorant of the field of Bible studies or rejects the scholarly consensus in the field, or is incapable occasionally of playing a game of checkers (in addition to the game of the philosophy of religion). Or is he like an intellectual plumber, totally unconcerned with the actual history of the primary sacred text at the center of his religion? Notice I did not use the term &#8220;belief&#8221; in the previous three sentences. </p>
<p>Then, as I think we agree, when considering the word &#8220;belief&#8221; (and its synonyms) in the religious sense, he can decide to play the religious language game, in which historical facts (and metaphysical reality) are deemed irrelevant.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Joebug		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/18/prof-brian-klug-on-revelation-and-torah-from-heaven/#comment-7873</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joebug]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2013 21:31:22 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6041#comment-7873</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This is all very well if you accept Wittgenstein and his idea of language games, or perhaps similarly if you accept post-structuralism. Then I think Prof Klug has a reasonable and in many ways attractive argument.
However, the point of all of this, and of similar discussions on the blog such as Prof Ross&#039; recent post is that modernity presents a huge challenge to belief. Twisting the argument, people live their lives in that language game.
Or more seriously, they don&#039;t accept Wittgenstein&#039;s ideas, they sit with a common sense or modernist or positivist (increasingly the dominant language game, discourse..) conception of the world. They don&#039;t see languages as incommensurable as Prof Klug suggests, they see them as having independent meaning and the capacity for translation and cognitive understanding and discussion - and of course many philosophers agree with them and not Wittgenstein (ask Daniel Dennet for example).
Prof Klug writes &quot;There is no paradox about that! By the same token, there is nothing paradoxical about disbelieving the historical claim that the Torah was given to Moses from heaven – what would it even mean to believe this? – and believing it as a point of faith. &quot; Fine for Wittgenstein, but not very persuasive for most moderns. It&#039;s fine if you want to be regarded as obscurantist and don&#039;t care - that&#039;s the argument after all, but most people do care, and I doubt your argument will persuade them otherwise - and after all, isn&#039;t that the point - to find a resolution of the clash with modernity? But really you should give more cognizance to the fact that it&#039;s not working for anyone apart from a few selected people in the academy.
And further, isn&#039;t the problem as well that the Torah and the Mesorah actively proclaim themselves as being within a scientific world view - that&#039;s what I picked up very clearly at Hasmonean :) - we proclaim a faith based on history - much much more so than Christianity or any other religion...and that&#039;s part of the problem I think for Prof Klug and Wittgenstein as well.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is all very well if you accept Wittgenstein and his idea of language games, or perhaps similarly if you accept post-structuralism. Then I think Prof Klug has a reasonable and in many ways attractive argument.<br />
However, the point of all of this, and of similar discussions on the blog such as Prof Ross&#8217; recent post is that modernity presents a huge challenge to belief. Twisting the argument, people live their lives in that language game.<br />
Or more seriously, they don&#8217;t accept Wittgenstein&#8217;s ideas, they sit with a common sense or modernist or positivist (increasingly the dominant language game, discourse..) conception of the world. They don&#8217;t see languages as incommensurable as Prof Klug suggests, they see them as having independent meaning and the capacity for translation and cognitive understanding and discussion &#8211; and of course many philosophers agree with them and not Wittgenstein (ask Daniel Dennet for example).<br />
Prof Klug writes &#8220;There is no paradox about that! By the same token, there is nothing paradoxical about disbelieving the historical claim that the Torah was given to Moses from heaven – what would it even mean to believe this? – and believing it as a point of faith. &#8221; Fine for Wittgenstein, but not very persuasive for most moderns. It&#8217;s fine if you want to be regarded as obscurantist and don&#8217;t care &#8211; that&#8217;s the argument after all, but most people do care, and I doubt your argument will persuade them otherwise &#8211; and after all, isn&#8217;t that the point &#8211; to find a resolution of the clash with modernity? But really you should give more cognizance to the fact that it&#8217;s not working for anyone apart from a few selected people in the academy.<br />
And further, isn&#8217;t the problem as well that the Torah and the Mesorah actively proclaim themselves as being within a scientific world view &#8211; that&#8217;s what I picked up very clearly at Hasmonean 🙂 &#8211; we proclaim a faith based on history &#8211; much much more so than Christianity or any other religion&#8230;and that&#8217;s part of the problem I think for Prof Klug and Wittgenstein as well.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/18/prof-brian-klug-on-revelation-and-torah-from-heaven/#comment-7872</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2013 16:12:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6041#comment-7872</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Here are three applications of the use of religious language. The first is by Father Guido Sarducci and involves answers to the question of the immortality of the soul, aliyas neshamot, reward and punishment and gilgulim. I understand these ideas, or I think I do, as did the audience. No deep background picture here, no special use of religious language but a calculation any storekeeper would understand. No one  believes this in the sense of a life commitment, but the story  lingers and  becomes part of other such  ideas that influence our behavior in part, even when we know it is not true in a literal way. What choice is there but to understand these sentences in a fundamentalist way? https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zp3aAvorZcw
The second example is an impromptu  remark using religious language by the Lubavitcher Rebbe that is unsettling, yet  simple to understand, not exactly empirical though there might be neurological empirical traces that would support his claim. I can’t speak for others but this idea will remain with me, but there is no particular  need to embrace this idea with a passion. https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fBjUmj95r6g
And finally a nigun combined with body language, again involving the Lubavitcher but there are many such examples. Here we have some form of religious communication, but not using a full blown language.  There is nothing to believe. https://www.youtube.com/watch?NR=1&#038;v=EW6cTS2XrV8&#038;feature=endscreen

How would Wittgenstein’s approach to the “logic of religious questions” understand these three examples?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here are three applications of the use of religious language. The first is by Father Guido Sarducci and involves answers to the question of the immortality of the soul, aliyas neshamot, reward and punishment and gilgulim. I understand these ideas, or I think I do, as did the audience. No deep background picture here, no special use of religious language but a calculation any storekeeper would understand. No one  believes this in the sense of a life commitment, but the story  lingers and  becomes part of other such  ideas that influence our behavior in part, even when we know it is not true in a literal way. What choice is there but to understand these sentences in a fundamentalist way? <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zp3aAvorZcw" rel="nofollow ugc">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zp3aAvorZcw</a><br />
The second example is an impromptu  remark using religious language by the Lubavitcher Rebbe that is unsettling, yet  simple to understand, not exactly empirical though there might be neurological empirical traces that would support his claim. I can’t speak for others but this idea will remain with me, but there is no particular  need to embrace this idea with a passion. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fBjUmj95r6g" rel="nofollow ugc">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fBjUmj95r6g</a><br />
And finally a nigun combined with body language, again involving the Lubavitcher but there are many such examples. Here we have some form of religious communication, but not using a full blown language.  There is nothing to believe. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?NR=1&#038;v=EW6cTS2XrV8&#038;feature=endscreen" rel="nofollow ugc">https://www.youtube.com/watch?NR=1&#038;v=EW6cTS2XrV8&#038;feature=endscreen</a></p>
<p>How would Wittgenstein’s approach to the “logic of religious questions” understand these three examples?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Joseph		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/18/prof-brian-klug-on-revelation-and-torah-from-heaven/#comment-7870</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joseph]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2013 02:54:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6041#comment-7870</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thank you, Prof. Brill, for graciously forwarding my question, and Prof. Klug, for your taking the time to provide a very thoughtful response.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thank you, Prof. Brill, for graciously forwarding my question, and Prof. Klug, for your taking the time to provide a very thoughtful response.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Joshua Skootsky		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/18/prof-brian-klug-on-revelation-and-torah-from-heaven/#comment-7869</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joshua Skootsky]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2013 23:00:36 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6041#comment-7869</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/18/prof-brian-klug-on-revelation-and-torah-from-heaven/#comment-7864&quot;&gt;ruvie&lt;/a&gt;.

Ruvie, Ma&#039;amad Har Sinai is not a historical fact that we can prove to people who don&#039;t believe it. If it was, we would have done that, and we wouldn&#039;t be having this discussion. So, we have a situation where we, believers, believe 100% that it occurred, but we can&#039;t prove it to other people. A &quot;historical fact&quot; would be something that we could know and prove to other people, because it is objectively demonstrable to be true. There are very few historical facts.

I also think Prof. Klug is expressing a belief that Heavenly Torah can come from heaven to earth, so it isn&#039;t proper to accuse him of not believing in the possibility of God revealing Himself to humans.

Quite right that we believe in God and the Torah for reasons unrelated to history. We believe because of our mesorah, which is our story of how things happened, and it is to our mesorah that we commit ourselves.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/18/prof-brian-klug-on-revelation-and-torah-from-heaven/#comment-7864">ruvie</a>.</p>
<p>Ruvie, Ma&#8217;amad Har Sinai is not a historical fact that we can prove to people who don&#8217;t believe it. If it was, we would have done that, and we wouldn&#8217;t be having this discussion. So, we have a situation where we, believers, believe 100% that it occurred, but we can&#8217;t prove it to other people. A &#8220;historical fact&#8221; would be something that we could know and prove to other people, because it is objectively demonstrable to be true. There are very few historical facts.</p>
<p>I also think Prof. Klug is expressing a belief that Heavenly Torah can come from heaven to earth, so it isn&#8217;t proper to accuse him of not believing in the possibility of God revealing Himself to humans.</p>
<p>Quite right that we believe in God and the Torah for reasons unrelated to history. We believe because of our mesorah, which is our story of how things happened, and it is to our mesorah that we commit ourselves.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/18/prof-brian-klug-on-revelation-and-torah-from-heaven/#comment-7868</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2013 22:42:58 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6041#comment-7868</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/18/prof-brian-klug-on-revelation-and-torah-from-heaven/#comment-7865&quot;&gt;Joseph&lt;/a&gt;.

I emailed your question to Prof. Klug and he graciously replied. Everything below is from him.

Which brings me to the interesting comment and thoughtful question posed by your commentator. Here is my (rather hurried) response. It is not so much my intention to draw a line between reason and revelation as to distinguish between the kind of reasoning employed for the purposes of scientific discourse and the kind that enters into thinking about about God, the soul and so on (in a religious idiom). I accept that this is not made clear enough in the paper and it is certainly not developed there. 

On the other hand, I hope that at no point do I suggest that reason is all of a piece and that it is categorically different from revelation, since that is not what I think. The commentator observes that &quot;a common medieval Jewish approach was to state that both reason and revelation have their roots in the Divine and must be made to agree with each other&quot;. Yes, but the crucial question here (as I say in both the first and third sections of the paper) is this: how should the &#039;agreement&#039; or accommodation be made between the kind of &#039;reason&#039; that we find in science and the language of revelation? 
As I read Wittgenstein, light on this question is shed by his thought -- and that is what I set out to show in the paper. I do not think that Wittgenstein&#039;s approach lends itself more to elucidating Christianity rather than Judaism, since the argument in the paper goes via considerations of the very logic of religious language rather than the doctrines of any particular faith. (This is not reflected in the extracts on the blog but I think it is clear in the paper.)  It does not go via &quot;Jewish sources&quot;; the final question is asking for a different paper, with a different aim, from the one I wrote.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/18/prof-brian-klug-on-revelation-and-torah-from-heaven/#comment-7865">Joseph</a>.</p>
<p>I emailed your question to Prof. Klug and he graciously replied. Everything below is from him.</p>
<p>Which brings me to the interesting comment and thoughtful question posed by your commentator. Here is my (rather hurried) response. It is not so much my intention to draw a line between reason and revelation as to distinguish between the kind of reasoning employed for the purposes of scientific discourse and the kind that enters into thinking about about God, the soul and so on (in a religious idiom). I accept that this is not made clear enough in the paper and it is certainly not developed there. </p>
<p>On the other hand, I hope that at no point do I suggest that reason is all of a piece and that it is categorically different from revelation, since that is not what I think. The commentator observes that &#8220;a common medieval Jewish approach was to state that both reason and revelation have their roots in the Divine and must be made to agree with each other&#8221;. Yes, but the crucial question here (as I say in both the first and third sections of the paper) is this: how should the &#8216;agreement&#8217; or accommodation be made between the kind of &#8216;reason&#8217; that we find in science and the language of revelation?<br />
As I read Wittgenstein, light on this question is shed by his thought &#8212; and that is what I set out to show in the paper. I do not think that Wittgenstein&#8217;s approach lends itself more to elucidating Christianity rather than Judaism, since the argument in the paper goes via considerations of the very logic of religious language rather than the doctrines of any particular faith. (This is not reflected in the extracts on the blog but I think it is clear in the paper.)  It does not go via &#8220;Jewish sources&#8221;; the final question is asking for a different paper, with a different aim, from the one I wrote.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/18/prof-brian-klug-on-revelation-and-torah-from-heaven/#comment-7867</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2013 21:59:12 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6041#comment-7867</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/18/prof-brian-klug-on-revelation-and-torah-from-heaven/#comment-7866&quot;&gt;JJ&lt;/a&gt;.

No, Klug did not say anything about the historic matter at Sinai. That is the work of historian or the hypothetical video camera. In this approach, any statement of evidence based history is not belief.  Historical language and religious language are two separate realms, separate language games with separate rules. One cannot use the rules of checkers in playing chess.
For Klug, the problem of fundamentalism is not the ignoring of historical and scientific evidence by the religious, rather the thinking that religious language is of the same game as history and science.  Read the short introductions that I linked to.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/18/prof-brian-klug-on-revelation-and-torah-from-heaven/#comment-7866">JJ</a>.</p>
<p>No, Klug did not say anything about the historic matter at Sinai. That is the work of historian or the hypothetical video camera. In this approach, any statement of evidence based history is not belief.  Historical language and religious language are two separate realms, separate language games with separate rules. One cannot use the rules of checkers in playing chess.<br />
For Klug, the problem of fundamentalism is not the ignoring of historical and scientific evidence by the religious, rather the thinking that religious language is of the same game as history and science.  Read the short introductions that I linked to.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: JJ		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/18/prof-brian-klug-on-revelation-and-torah-from-heaven/#comment-7866</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[JJ]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2013 21:43:42 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6041#comment-7866</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/18/prof-brian-klug-on-revelation-and-torah-from-heaven/#comment-7863&quot;&gt;Alan Brill&lt;/a&gt;.

From the section &quot;What is Belief? What is the Difference between Scientific and Religious Belief?&quot;: &quot;...there is nothing paradoxical about disbelieving the historical claim that the Torah was given to Moses from heaven – what would it even mean to believe this? – and believing it as a point of faith. This is a measure of the difference in meaning between ‘believe’ and ‘believe’ – a difference in the work being done – when the same word is used in these two different contexts.&quot;   

So Klug appears to acknowledge that as a historical matter, in the world of facts, the Torah was not given at Sinai. (“what would it even mean to believe this?”) But then he re-interprets the word “belief” when used in a religious context to mean something like “commitment” or “alignment.” With this interpretation of “belief” he then affirms his commitment of Torah MinHashamayim. Am I understanding him correctly?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/18/prof-brian-klug-on-revelation-and-torah-from-heaven/#comment-7863">Alan Brill</a>.</p>
<p>From the section &#8220;What is Belief? What is the Difference between Scientific and Religious Belief?&#8221;: &#8220;&#8230;there is nothing paradoxical about disbelieving the historical claim that the Torah was given to Moses from heaven – what would it even mean to believe this? – and believing it as a point of faith. This is a measure of the difference in meaning between ‘believe’ and ‘believe’ – a difference in the work being done – when the same word is used in these two different contexts.&#8221;   </p>
<p>So Klug appears to acknowledge that as a historical matter, in the world of facts, the Torah was not given at Sinai. (“what would it even mean to believe this?”) But then he re-interprets the word “belief” when used in a religious context to mean something like “commitment” or “alignment.” With this interpretation of “belief” he then affirms his commitment of Torah MinHashamayim. Am I understanding him correctly?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Joseph		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/18/prof-brian-klug-on-revelation-and-torah-from-heaven/#comment-7865</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joseph]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2013 20:58:58 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6041#comment-7865</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&quot;Reason and belief are two separate categories. Alternately, scientific belief is based on evidence and religious belief is based on the role it has in my life...In this sense of ‘belief’, what Wittgenstein says about Christianity applies equally to Judaism: &lt;em&gt;Christianity is not based on a historical truth, but presents us with a (historical) narrative &#038; says: now believe! But not believe this report with the belief that is appropriate to a historical report, – but rather: believe, through thick &#038; thin &#038; you can do this only as the outcome of a life. &lt;/em&gt;&quot; -- 

While a common classical Christian approach was to treat revelation as separate from reason, a common medieval Jewish approach was to state that both reason and revelation have their roots in the Divine and must be made to agree with each other. In this case, Prof. Klug jumps straight from Wittgenstein, who came from a  Christian cultural background, into Judaism, but, to use a term he himself used, the jump is &quot;glib&quot; - partly because he fails to ground Wittgenstein&#039;s theories in classical Jewish sources. What Jewish sources does he have to back up his interpretation of Torah min-ha-Shamayim?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&#8220;Reason and belief are two separate categories. Alternately, scientific belief is based on evidence and religious belief is based on the role it has in my life&#8230;In this sense of ‘belief’, what Wittgenstein says about Christianity applies equally to Judaism: <em>Christianity is not based on a historical truth, but presents us with a (historical) narrative &amp; says: now believe! But not believe this report with the belief that is appropriate to a historical report, – but rather: believe, through thick &amp; thin &amp; you can do this only as the outcome of a life. </em>&#8221; &#8212; </p>
<p>While a common classical Christian approach was to treat revelation as separate from reason, a common medieval Jewish approach was to state that both reason and revelation have their roots in the Divine and must be made to agree with each other. In this case, Prof. Klug jumps straight from Wittgenstein, who came from a  Christian cultural background, into Judaism, but, to use a term he himself used, the jump is &#8220;glib&#8221; &#8211; partly because he fails to ground Wittgenstein&#8217;s theories in classical Jewish sources. What Jewish sources does he have to back up his interpretation of Torah min-ha-Shamayim?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ruvie		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/18/prof-brian-klug-on-revelation-and-torah-from-heaven/#comment-7864</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ruvie]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2013 18:05:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6041#comment-7864</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&quot;religious statements are entirely outside the realm of evidence&quot;
is torah min hashamayim a religious statement or an historical fact (or belief in that fact) that his religious implications? or are we really reinterpreting what the misnah originally meant to make it acceptable to what we think we know or suspect today?

do not understand how this helps religious jews:
&quot;we can say that the doctrine of Torah from heaven makes the following demand on us: embrace the idea with a passion – ‘believe, through thick &#038; thin’ – or leave it be, but don’t ask for the evidence. It is not a hypothesis or theory.&quot; if you don&#039;t believe God&#039;s involvement or of an historical fact(possibility) then how do you get to the vigor stuff?

this post reminds of the saying: its not that i believe in God and go to church but i go to church therefore i believe in God.

like the concluding remark. for whatever reason i believe he is on the right road.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&#8220;religious statements are entirely outside the realm of evidence&#8221;<br />
is torah min hashamayim a religious statement or an historical fact (or belief in that fact) that his religious implications? or are we really reinterpreting what the misnah originally meant to make it acceptable to what we think we know or suspect today?</p>
<p>do not understand how this helps religious jews:<br />
&#8220;we can say that the doctrine of Torah from heaven makes the following demand on us: embrace the idea with a passion – ‘believe, through thick &amp; thin’ – or leave it be, but don’t ask for the evidence. It is not a hypothesis or theory.&#8221; if you don&#8217;t believe God&#8217;s involvement or of an historical fact(possibility) then how do you get to the vigor stuff?</p>
<p>this post reminds of the saying: its not that i believe in God and go to church but i go to church therefore i believe in God.</p>
<p>like the concluding remark. for whatever reason i believe he is on the right road.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/18/prof-brian-klug-on-revelation-and-torah-from-heaven/#comment-7863</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2013 17:02:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6041#comment-7863</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/18/prof-brian-klug-on-revelation-and-torah-from-heaven/#comment-7862&quot;&gt;JJ&lt;/a&gt;.

No, because he would not agree with your first line. Religion and history are fundamentally two separate realms.

The first half is an intro to his life and the second half starting at 12 minutes explain his views. The video does a great job. Dont assume that Prof. Krug as a specialist on Wittgenstein agrees with all the details of the film. The film is more agnostic, Krug in this paper is more theist. 
http://youtu.be/JFzfOXsOymk]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/18/prof-brian-klug-on-revelation-and-torah-from-heaven/#comment-7862">JJ</a>.</p>
<p>No, because he would not agree with your first line. Religion and history are fundamentally two separate realms.</p>
<p>The first half is an intro to his life and the second half starting at 12 minutes explain his views. The video does a great job. Dont assume that Prof. Krug as a specialist on Wittgenstein agrees with all the details of the film. The film is more agnostic, Krug in this paper is more theist.<br />
<iframe class='youtube-player' width='500' height='282' src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/JFzfOXsOymk?version=3&#038;rel=1&#038;fs=1&#038;autohide=2&#038;showsearch=0&#038;showinfo=1&#038;iv_load_policy=1&#038;wmode=transparent' allowfullscreen='true' style='border:0;'></iframe></p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: JJ		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/06/18/prof-brian-klug-on-revelation-and-torah-from-heaven/#comment-7862</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[JJ]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2013 16:51:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6041#comment-7862</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In the interest of clarify of thinking about Torah and about its history (and in the interest of saving a lot of ink and trees), wouldn&#039;t it be simpler for Mr. Klug to just write something like:
1. The notion that the Pentateuch was given at Sinai is conradicted by  historical facts and I therefore reject it.
2. In this I agree with Rabbi Jacobs and the scholarly consensus. 
3. The Pentateuch is considered a primary sacred text in Judaism and I embrace the Jewish religion for reasons unrelated to the Pentateuch&#039;s historical origins.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the interest of clarify of thinking about Torah and about its history (and in the interest of saving a lot of ink and trees), wouldn&#8217;t it be simpler for Mr. Klug to just write something like:<br />
1. The notion that the Pentateuch was given at Sinai is conradicted by  historical facts and I therefore reject it.<br />
2. In this I agree with Rabbi Jacobs and the scholarly consensus.<br />
3. The Pentateuch is considered a primary sacred text in Judaism and I embrace the Jewish religion for reasons unrelated to the Pentateuch&#8217;s historical origins.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
