<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Pregnancy Ethics in Israel and Japan&#8212;Updated by AS	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/24/pregnancy-ethics-in-israel-and-japan/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/24/pregnancy-ethics-in-israel-and-japan/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 May 2010 02:02:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: MBG		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/24/pregnancy-ethics-in-israel-and-japan/#comment-1059</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[MBG]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2010 02:02:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1333#comment-1059</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/24/pregnancy-ethics-in-israel-and-japan/#comment-1058&quot;&gt;Alan Brill&lt;/a&gt;.

I don&#039;t know if this responds to your interests, but here are some of my own anecdotes...

My experience has been  that there is a profound lack of any distinct conceptions of childbirth, and probably pregnancy also,  in the so-called MO world.  The model of childbirth was the standard American medical model (again I think this helps rabbis avoid having to fully answer, and take responsibility for, difficult questions) and I was really at a loss to see any vision of gestation at all.  Pregnancy talk among the women I know from shul was about ultrasounds, prenatal yoga, and eating sushi while pregnant, and was very much like pregnancy talk with other yuppies.  I basically never heard about any of the (alleged) minhagim one can read about in yeshivish pamphlets, and nothing about introspection or self-improvement for the baby&#039;s spiritual sake.
Perhaps I just didn&#039;t know where to look, but i think the MO adoption of what was previously a male model of religiosity (e.g., learning and synagogue attendance) as a quasi-gender-neutral norm has really cut off thinking about a lot of woman-specific ideas.   
The only area in which i felt any push-back against the standard conceptions of my secular counterparts was the idea that halacha can still ask physically difficult things of pregnant women (eg, fasting) - whereas i found in secular society a horror that (white, non-poor) pregnant ladies, especially in the third trimester, could be asked to do anything other than sit on the couch gestating.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/24/pregnancy-ethics-in-israel-and-japan/#comment-1058">Alan Brill</a>.</p>
<p>I don&#8217;t know if this responds to your interests, but here are some of my own anecdotes&#8230;</p>
<p>My experience has been  that there is a profound lack of any distinct conceptions of childbirth, and probably pregnancy also,  in the so-called MO world.  The model of childbirth was the standard American medical model (again I think this helps rabbis avoid having to fully answer, and take responsibility for, difficult questions) and I was really at a loss to see any vision of gestation at all.  Pregnancy talk among the women I know from shul was about ultrasounds, prenatal yoga, and eating sushi while pregnant, and was very much like pregnancy talk with other yuppies.  I basically never heard about any of the (alleged) minhagim one can read about in yeshivish pamphlets, and nothing about introspection or self-improvement for the baby&#8217;s spiritual sake.<br />
Perhaps I just didn&#8217;t know where to look, but i think the MO adoption of what was previously a male model of religiosity (e.g., learning and synagogue attendance) as a quasi-gender-neutral norm has really cut off thinking about a lot of woman-specific ideas.<br />
The only area in which i felt any push-back against the standard conceptions of my secular counterparts was the idea that halacha can still ask physically difficult things of pregnant women (eg, fasting) &#8211; whereas i found in secular society a horror that (white, non-poor) pregnant ladies, especially in the third trimester, could be asked to do anything other than sit on the couch gestating.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/24/pregnancy-ethics-in-israel-and-japan/#comment-1058</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2010 23:27:11 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1333#comment-1058</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[MBG= I have heard that besides the outsourcing, the Hasidic community itself has a vision of the fetus that encourages it.  There is lots of good material in the &quot;mother in Israel&quot; post. As long as we speak about axiological ideas we avoid the actual reality of the porcess, we also obscure the conceptions of motherhood, fetus, and childbirth.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>MBG= I have heard that besides the outsourcing, the Hasidic community itself has a vision of the fetus that encourages it.  There is lots of good material in the &#8220;mother in Israel&#8221; post. As long as we speak about axiological ideas we avoid the actual reality of the porcess, we also obscure the conceptions of motherhood, fetus, and childbirth.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: MBG		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/24/pregnancy-ethics-in-israel-and-japan/#comment-1056</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[MBG]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2010 16:51:40 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1333#comment-1056</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A friend of mine was doing an OB rotation at a hospital frequented by chassidim.  A doctor she was working for was apparently very pro-abortion and prided herself on, e.g., creative interpretations of statutes to allow abortions later in pregnancy.  Said doctor explicitly told my friend she thought disabled babies should be aborted, and that she would lie to chassidic women about the severity of their fetus&#039; birth defects so that the women would get abortions.  

At some point I began to wonder (pure speculation) whether there was some complicity on the part of the chassidim.  Something like, they see abortion as permitted if the fetus is X, but not Y.  But they might also want to abort for Y, so if the doctor says X they don&#039;t ask too many questions about whether it really might be only Y.  Or even collusion - that they may know it&#039;s Y, but the doctor says what she knows they need to hear to &quot;allow&quot; abortion.  

I have no basis for believing this occured in the context of abortions, but I wondered because the general idea of privileging the words of the doctor over the factual situation they do or do not represent does happen.  Example:  I also had heard the folowing from another friend, a grandmother:  when she was having her kids (presumably in the 70s) the way to &quot;get a heter&quot; for contraception was for the husband to tell the doctor that his wife was so stressed out she was hitting the kids (or maybe that the husband was afraid she would).  The doctor would say she had to stop having kids, and the husband would bring that &quot;psak&quot; back to the rabbi.  

By outsourcing a lie to a doctor people can invest it with enough &quot;expert&quot; authority to feel that the psak that results from the lie is legitimate.  This is related to to AS&#039;s point about the unconscious reflection of dominant values - perhaps just a more exteme example of how it occurs.

On AS&#039;s point re: able bodied jews, it seems to me that rav aviner&#039;s psak is about as explicit on that as it could be]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A friend of mine was doing an OB rotation at a hospital frequented by chassidim.  A doctor she was working for was apparently very pro-abortion and prided herself on, e.g., creative interpretations of statutes to allow abortions later in pregnancy.  Said doctor explicitly told my friend she thought disabled babies should be aborted, and that she would lie to chassidic women about the severity of their fetus&#8217; birth defects so that the women would get abortions.  </p>
<p>At some point I began to wonder (pure speculation) whether there was some complicity on the part of the chassidim.  Something like, they see abortion as permitted if the fetus is X, but not Y.  But they might also want to abort for Y, so if the doctor says X they don&#8217;t ask too many questions about whether it really might be only Y.  Or even collusion &#8211; that they may know it&#8217;s Y, but the doctor says what she knows they need to hear to &#8220;allow&#8221; abortion.  </p>
<p>I have no basis for believing this occured in the context of abortions, but I wondered because the general idea of privileging the words of the doctor over the factual situation they do or do not represent does happen.  Example:  I also had heard the folowing from another friend, a grandmother:  when she was having her kids (presumably in the 70s) the way to &#8220;get a heter&#8221; for contraception was for the husband to tell the doctor that his wife was so stressed out she was hitting the kids (or maybe that the husband was afraid she would).  The doctor would say she had to stop having kids, and the husband would bring that &#8220;psak&#8221; back to the rabbi.  </p>
<p>By outsourcing a lie to a doctor people can invest it with enough &#8220;expert&#8221; authority to feel that the psak that results from the lie is legitimate.  This is related to to AS&#8217;s point about the unconscious reflection of dominant values &#8211; perhaps just a more exteme example of how it occurs.</p>
<p>On AS&#8217;s point re: able bodied jews, it seems to me that rav aviner&#8217;s psak is about as explicit on that as it could be</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: tesyaa		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/24/pregnancy-ethics-in-israel-and-japan/#comment-1053</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tesyaa]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2010 14:56:40 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1333#comment-1053</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Amnio is refused much more than ultrasound because of the high risk (relatively speaking) of it inducing abortion.  Ultrasound has no such risk, or an immeasurably small one.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Amnio is refused much more than ultrasound because of the high risk (relatively speaking) of it inducing abortion.  Ultrasound has no such risk, or an immeasurably small one.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/24/pregnancy-ethics-in-israel-and-japan/#comment-1045</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2010 18:35:11 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1333#comment-1045</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[AS-
Thank you so much for another wonderful comment- I am debating whether to make it into its own post. It does not read like one but it has the gravity of a post. 
Update- It became part of the post.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>AS-<br />
Thank you so much for another wonderful comment- I am debating whether to make it into its own post. It does not read like one but it has the gravity of a post.<br />
Update- It became part of the post.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Arie Folger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/24/pregnancy-ethics-in-israel-and-japan/#comment-1043</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arie Folger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2010 16:23:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1333#comment-1043</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/24/pregnancy-ethics-in-israel-and-japan/#comment-1042&quot;&gt;Alan Brill&lt;/a&gt;.

&lt;blockquote&gt;about theoretical discussion, we have witnessed a move from the 1970′s where MO argued how different it was than the Christians to the current approach is how close we are despite the halakhic exceptions.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

True. That should be right up your current professional alley. Would the reason not be that once upon a time, for the Western Jew, the threatening other was a Christian, while nowadays it is the hypersecular &#060;insert popular cause&#062; rights activist?
Nowadays, interfaith activity may increasingly be seen as a way to stem the tide of secularism.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/24/pregnancy-ethics-in-israel-and-japan/#comment-1042">Alan Brill</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>about theoretical discussion, we have witnessed a move from the 1970′s where MO argued how different it was than the Christians to the current approach is how close we are despite the halakhic exceptions.</p></blockquote>
<p>True. That should be right up your current professional alley. Would the reason not be that once upon a time, for the Western Jew, the threatening other was a Christian, while nowadays it is the hypersecular &lt;insert popular cause&gt; rights activist?<br />
Nowadays, interfaith activity may increasingly be seen as a way to stem the tide of secularism.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/24/pregnancy-ethics-in-israel-and-japan/#comment-1042</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2010 16:17:24 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1333#comment-1042</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/24/pregnancy-ethics-in-israel-and-japan/#comment-1041&quot;&gt;Arie Folger&lt;/a&gt;.

Sorry, I am not implying anything at all about pesak. Wrong blog. I know the book is not about religious Israelis, that is why it provides a great starting window on society. 

Your insight about Rabbi Eliyashiv is correct.
&lt;em&gt;I am now also less surprised at R’Eliyashiv’s view prohibiting amniosynthesis outright. The Israeli medical establishment is obviously strongly tilting in favor of aborting disabled foetuses.&lt;/em&gt;
On the contrary about theoretical discussion, we have witnessed a move from the 1970&#039;s where MO argued how different it was than the Christians to the current approach is how close we are despite the halakhic exceptions. The articles by the talking heads in journals have changed the most and reflect the culture wars. 
If there is a gap, it is between pesak and actual practice, and one gets a sense that it runs counter the pesak- but we will never get a truthful statistic.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/24/pregnancy-ethics-in-israel-and-japan/#comment-1041">Arie Folger</a>.</p>
<p>Sorry, I am not implying anything at all about pesak. Wrong blog. I know the book is not about religious Israelis, that is why it provides a great starting window on society. </p>
<p>Your insight about Rabbi Eliyashiv is correct.<br />
<em>I am now also less surprised at R’Eliyashiv’s view prohibiting amniosynthesis outright. The Israeli medical establishment is obviously strongly tilting in favor of aborting disabled foetuses.</em><br />
On the contrary about theoretical discussion, we have witnessed a move from the 1970&#8217;s where MO argued how different it was than the Christians to the current approach is how close we are despite the halakhic exceptions. The articles by the talking heads in journals have changed the most and reflect the culture wars.<br />
If there is a gap, it is between pesak and actual practice, and one gets a sense that it runs counter the pesak- but we will never get a truthful statistic.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Arie Folger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/05/24/pregnancy-ethics-in-israel-and-japan/#comment-1041</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arie Folger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2010 16:01:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1333#comment-1041</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The blurb is thought provoking. However, nowhere does the article indicate it is about religious Israelis.

Additionally, it would seem that whereas in the US amniosynthesis is meant primarily as a way for the mother to know some crucial facts about the health of her baby (she may want to keep a disabled child but wants to be prepared and informed), the Israeli scene painted in the article shows that obstetricians performing amniosynthesis already assume that there may be something wrong and that that will lead to an abortion. That surely impacts who chooses amniosynthesis, and skews the results of any poll of women seeking that test.

I am now also less surprised at R&#039;Eliyashiv&#039;s view prohibiting amniosynthesis outright. The Israeli medical establishment is obviously strongly tilting in favor of aborting disabled foetuses.
However, quite a number of MO rabbinical figures, particularly the noteworthy poskim (not to make a judgment call, let&#039;s just define these as those who are commonly perceived as those one turns to with the difficult halakhic issues), harbor serious intellectual reservations regarding these lenient views. In YU, R&#039; Moshe Feinstein&#039;s view on abortion was given much more consideration than R&#039; Eliezer Waldenberg&#039;s. The same goes for end of life issues.

While you may reasonably posit cultural osmosis regarding the incorporation of experiences in reaching practical psak, I think that regarding the academic analysis of the sources, the process is a lot more (but not entirely) objective, biased only to tradition (i.e., what was done in recent historical memory). Hence, I believe it is an error to consider possible cultural influence from Evangelicals, but to leave the academic convictions of internal opinion leaders out.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The blurb is thought provoking. However, nowhere does the article indicate it is about religious Israelis.</p>
<p>Additionally, it would seem that whereas in the US amniosynthesis is meant primarily as a way for the mother to know some crucial facts about the health of her baby (she may want to keep a disabled child but wants to be prepared and informed), the Israeli scene painted in the article shows that obstetricians performing amniosynthesis already assume that there may be something wrong and that that will lead to an abortion. That surely impacts who chooses amniosynthesis, and skews the results of any poll of women seeking that test.</p>
<p>I am now also less surprised at R&#8217;Eliyashiv&#8217;s view prohibiting amniosynthesis outright. The Israeli medical establishment is obviously strongly tilting in favor of aborting disabled foetuses.<br />
However, quite a number of MO rabbinical figures, particularly the noteworthy poskim (not to make a judgment call, let&#8217;s just define these as those who are commonly perceived as those one turns to with the difficult halakhic issues), harbor serious intellectual reservations regarding these lenient views. In YU, R&#8217; Moshe Feinstein&#8217;s view on abortion was given much more consideration than R&#8217; Eliezer Waldenberg&#8217;s. The same goes for end of life issues.</p>
<p>While you may reasonably posit cultural osmosis regarding the incorporation of experiences in reaching practical psak, I think that regarding the academic analysis of the sources, the process is a lot more (but not entirely) objective, biased only to tradition (i.e., what was done in recent historical memory). Hence, I believe it is an error to consider possible cultural influence from Evangelicals, but to leave the academic convictions of internal opinion leaders out.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
