<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: David Barton and Orthodox Historiography	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/15/david-barton-and-orthodox-historiography/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/15/david-barton-and-orthodox-historiography/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Jul 2011 15:15:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: IH		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/15/david-barton-and-orthodox-historiography/#comment-3357</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[IH]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 08 Jul 2011 15:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3707#comment-3357</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[So, helicoptering up, are there any articles comparing/contrasting the doctrine of Original Intent (as implemented by Justice Scalia) with the doctrine of Halacha as a self-contained abstract system (as implemented by the RYBS acolytes)?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>So, helicoptering up, are there any articles comparing/contrasting the doctrine of Original Intent (as implemented by Justice Scalia) with the doctrine of Halacha as a self-contained abstract system (as implemented by the RYBS acolytes)?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Arie Folger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/15/david-barton-and-orthodox-historiography/#comment-3356</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arie Folger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 08 Jul 2011 12:18:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3707#comment-3356</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Moshe Shoshan&#039;s first remark is spot on, and I&#039;d go even further (while disagreeing with his second point). You cite:
&lt;blockquote&gt;On one side are purveyors of a rich and complex view of the past, including most historians who have written and debated fiercely about the founding era. The “other side” is a group of ideological entrepreneurs who have created an alternate intellectual universe based on a historical fundamentalism. In their drive to create a usable past, they show little respect for the past as a foreign country.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The thing is, the rich and complex view of the past has a tendency of getting in the way of national narratives, and in fact often, through its attempt at being unbiased (which may really mean having a different bias - oy, postmodernism ;-)), actually precludes many kinds of value judgements. A simplified, perhaps even oversimplified account of history may fail to account for certain contradictions and other tensions, but it does so intentionally.

Take for example Navi. Navi is not history. It contains history, but it isn&#039;t history, it&#039;s prophecy. In this debate, when I say it&#039;s prophecy, I really want to emphasize that Navi is ideological. The book of Judges is not a full account of the history of the period, and is not nearly chronological. It is, instead, an ideological account meant to encourage people to see history through the ideological eyeglasses of the prophet. Its purpose is to argue that rather than make Joshua&#039;s conquest a success by settling the land and finishing off the conquest, Israel has fallen to the greatest depths of Canaanite immorality, deeply intertwined with its idolatry. Nowadays, there are historians who challenge the common understanding of Canaan. My response? Sure, you can, and Tanakh chose not to, because it made an ideological value judgement, in line with the Divine revelation in the Torah; it takes a stand. Objective, academic historians would want to provide us with a fuller picture, whenever possible, and insofar as it relates to the purely historical, that&#039;s fine, but it cannot and should not be seen as a source of values or ideology. (however, there are people who hold an ideology of turning amoral scientific research, whether in the exact sciences or in the humanities, into a set of values - that, too is an ideology, a set of meta-value judgements).

Back to Barton, that kind of writing recognizes that in order to produce a useful narrative, history needs to be simplified and interpreted. We may not agree with his ideology, and a legitimate question to confront Barton with is what space does he leave, in a de facto multicultural nation, for competing narratives. Can there be room for mutual debate and recognition?

Of course, given what I just wrote, the corollary is that those who use academic historians to produce a narrative, are also simplifying history, in a way that suits them.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Moshe Shoshan&#8217;s first remark is spot on, and I&#8217;d go even further (while disagreeing with his second point). You cite:</p>
<blockquote><p>On one side are purveyors of a rich and complex view of the past, including most historians who have written and debated fiercely about the founding era. The “other side” is a group of ideological entrepreneurs who have created an alternate intellectual universe based on a historical fundamentalism. In their drive to create a usable past, they show little respect for the past as a foreign country.</p></blockquote>
<p>The thing is, the rich and complex view of the past has a tendency of getting in the way of national narratives, and in fact often, through its attempt at being unbiased (which may really mean having a different bias &#8211; oy, postmodernism ;-)), actually precludes many kinds of value judgements. A simplified, perhaps even oversimplified account of history may fail to account for certain contradictions and other tensions, but it does so intentionally.</p>
<p>Take for example Navi. Navi is not history. It contains history, but it isn&#8217;t history, it&#8217;s prophecy. In this debate, when I say it&#8217;s prophecy, I really want to emphasize that Navi is ideological. The book of Judges is not a full account of the history of the period, and is not nearly chronological. It is, instead, an ideological account meant to encourage people to see history through the ideological eyeglasses of the prophet. Its purpose is to argue that rather than make Joshua&#8217;s conquest a success by settling the land and finishing off the conquest, Israel has fallen to the greatest depths of Canaanite immorality, deeply intertwined with its idolatry. Nowadays, there are historians who challenge the common understanding of Canaan. My response? Sure, you can, and Tanakh chose not to, because it made an ideological value judgement, in line with the Divine revelation in the Torah; it takes a stand. Objective, academic historians would want to provide us with a fuller picture, whenever possible, and insofar as it relates to the purely historical, that&#8217;s fine, but it cannot and should not be seen as a source of values or ideology. (however, there are people who hold an ideology of turning amoral scientific research, whether in the exact sciences or in the humanities, into a set of values &#8211; that, too is an ideology, a set of meta-value judgements).</p>
<p>Back to Barton, that kind of writing recognizes that in order to produce a useful narrative, history needs to be simplified and interpreted. We may not agree with his ideology, and a legitimate question to confront Barton with is what space does he leave, in a de facto multicultural nation, for competing narratives. Can there be room for mutual debate and recognition?</p>
<p>Of course, given what I just wrote, the corollary is that those who use academic historians to produce a narrative, are also simplifying history, in a way that suits them.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Fred		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/15/david-barton-and-orthodox-historiography/#comment-3253</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Fred]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2011 22:28:51 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3707#comment-3253</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Applebaum&#039;s idea is very interesting. Similarly it may be pointed out that unlike Evangelicals, Artscroll does not do a sola scriptura reading of the sources. It&#039;s paraphrase, paraphrase, paraphrase and only the vaguest of citations and no bibliographies. Yet the whole feel of it is mesorah. &quot;This is how R. Gedalyah Schorr gave over to us that it was like,&quot; or &quot;This is how R. Aharon Kotler understands the parsha.&quot; and that&#039;s supposed to trump precise readings of the sources.

Although the text isn&#039;t from Artscroll, when Lakewood Cheder retracted their promotional book My Uncle the Netziv they said, regarding what they felt was the true Netziv that it was not as in the book, but &quot;as related to us by his revered talmidim, the ones who knew him best.&quot; It&#039;s not clear, to be sure, which of the Netziv&#039;s revered talmidim related this to them in the 1980s. But]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Applebaum&#8217;s idea is very interesting. Similarly it may be pointed out that unlike Evangelicals, Artscroll does not do a sola scriptura reading of the sources. It&#8217;s paraphrase, paraphrase, paraphrase and only the vaguest of citations and no bibliographies. Yet the whole feel of it is mesorah. &#8220;This is how R. Gedalyah Schorr gave over to us that it was like,&#8221; or &#8220;This is how R. Aharon Kotler understands the parsha.&#8221; and that&#8217;s supposed to trump precise readings of the sources.</p>
<p>Although the text isn&#8217;t from Artscroll, when Lakewood Cheder retracted their promotional book My Uncle the Netziv they said, regarding what they felt was the true Netziv that it was not as in the book, but &#8220;as related to us by his revered talmidim, the ones who knew him best.&#8221; It&#8217;s not clear, to be sure, which of the Netziv&#8217;s revered talmidim related this to them in the 1980s. But</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/15/david-barton-and-orthodox-historiography/#comment-3213</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Jun 2011 13:25:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3707#comment-3213</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[First, the compartmentalization and specialization of knowledge creates the vacuum that allows these views (along with anti-evolution and anti climate science fare) to take a foothold in the culture. Academics expect everyone to be acculturated to respect expertise because no one has the ability to evaluate every sphere of specialized  knowledge.

But without a theology  positing that the autonomy of religious knowledge cuts both ways (both immune from empiricism and apart from it) the religious worldview still promotes the idea of having an all encompassing god-conscious view of the world in which there isn&#039;t really room to throw up one&#039;s hands and say OK, I&#039;ll take their word for it, especially when their view is godless (which can easily get construed as anti-instead of non-religious).]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>First, the compartmentalization and specialization of knowledge creates the vacuum that allows these views (along with anti-evolution and anti climate science fare) to take a foothold in the culture. Academics expect everyone to be acculturated to respect expertise because no one has the ability to evaluate every sphere of specialized  knowledge.</p>
<p>But without a theology  positing that the autonomy of religious knowledge cuts both ways (both immune from empiricism and apart from it) the religious worldview still promotes the idea of having an all encompassing god-conscious view of the world in which there isn&#8217;t really room to throw up one&#8217;s hands and say OK, I&#8217;ll take their word for it, especially when their view is godless (which can easily get construed as anti-instead of non-religious).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Moshe Shoshan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/06/15/david-barton-and-orthodox-historiography/#comment-3202</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Moshe Shoshan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2011 12:03:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3707#comment-3202</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[
These questions are important not just for understanding Artscroll but for understanding the entire tradition of Jewish historical storytelling going back at least to Chazal.

For me, one of the central questions in evaluating a figure like Barton is, does he believe his own story, is he a huckster in the grand american tradition or something in between?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>These questions are important not just for understanding Artscroll but for understanding the entire tradition of Jewish historical storytelling going back at least to Chazal.</p>
<p>For me, one of the central questions in evaluating a figure like Barton is, does he believe his own story, is he a huckster in the grand american tradition or something in between?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
