<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Key findings of the Avi Chai report on young Jewish leaders	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/12/key-findings-of-the-avi-chai-report-on-young-jewish-leaders/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/12/key-findings-of-the-avi-chai-report-on-young-jewish-leaders/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Apr 2010 15:23:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: evanstonjew		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/12/key-findings-of-the-avi-chai-report-on-young-jewish-leaders/#comment-822</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[evanstonjew]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Apr 2010 15:23:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1105#comment-822</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I fully agree with your sketch.

This Pesach one of the Mahrits to be was mezakeh our  group seder with a dvar torah on the importance of actually doing something. And in a conversation, this young women, who I have seen grow up and become an accomplished twenties something, tells me with a wink in her eye, &quot;You know there is more to be done than blogging.&quot; Hearing this gave me great joy.  To use one of their favorite expressions, I hope she and her friends make a difference.

A non frum friend tells me that he sees the same phenomena. He put it this way...&quot;These kids see low lying fruit everywhere, there for the taking. The parents even when liberal and activist left much to be done. They dream of  small changes at the margin.&quot; 

Evanston is admittedly a liberal place, but it is still remarkable how many kids go into social service professions. Few MBA&#039;s, many teachers of autistic children etc. Nachis. 

I have nothing much to add at this point to the Kugel discussions.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I fully agree with your sketch.</p>
<p>This Pesach one of the Mahrits to be was mezakeh our  group seder with a dvar torah on the importance of actually doing something. And in a conversation, this young women, who I have seen grow up and become an accomplished twenties something, tells me with a wink in her eye, &#8220;You know there is more to be done than blogging.&#8221; Hearing this gave me great joy.  To use one of their favorite expressions, I hope she and her friends make a difference.</p>
<p>A non frum friend tells me that he sees the same phenomena. He put it this way&#8230;&#8221;These kids see low lying fruit everywhere, there for the taking. The parents even when liberal and activist left much to be done. They dream of  small changes at the margin.&#8221; </p>
<p>Evanston is admittedly a liberal place, but it is still remarkable how many kids go into social service professions. Few MBA&#8217;s, many teachers of autistic children etc. Nachis. </p>
<p>I have nothing much to add at this point to the Kugel discussions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/12/key-findings-of-the-avi-chai-report-on-young-jewish-leaders/#comment-812</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Apr 2010 03:47:26 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1105#comment-812</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/12/key-findings-of-the-avi-chai-report-on-young-jewish-leaders/#comment-811&quot;&gt;evanstonjew&lt;/a&gt;.

I dont think that they will have the wide cultural palette that you describe. They will start with the self, DIY, and conscience, then work on social change.  They are likely to be the start of a new American Jewry not connected to Europe anymore. They are beyond your spectral post-holocaust recursions.  They have social universalism and they are light on textuality but strong on the new media. They are creating a whole new generation of liberal clergy that wants to reach people instead of worrying about their own learning. I am not sure how we are going to measure success, they are not using the old indicators.   
What are your thoughts on the Kugel-Bible issues?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/12/key-findings-of-the-avi-chai-report-on-young-jewish-leaders/#comment-811">evanstonjew</a>.</p>
<p>I dont think that they will have the wide cultural palette that you describe. They will start with the self, DIY, and conscience, then work on social change.  They are likely to be the start of a new American Jewry not connected to Europe anymore. They are beyond your spectral post-holocaust recursions.  They have social universalism and they are light on textuality but strong on the new media. They are creating a whole new generation of liberal clergy that wants to reach people instead of worrying about their own learning. I am not sure how we are going to measure success, they are not using the old indicators.<br />
What are your thoughts on the Kugel-Bible issues?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: evanstonjew		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/12/key-findings-of-the-avi-chai-report-on-young-jewish-leaders/#comment-811</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[evanstonjew]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Apr 2010 00:16:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1105#comment-811</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[My conjecture is these group differ from both Reform and Orthodox in a signicant way. Orthodox are trying to bring people to Orthodoxy. The rest is bells and whistles. Reform Temples have an appreciation of a diverse Jewish culture, but for them the issue is that whatever takes place should be centered around the temple, a kiruv to a bldg. as it were.

So far this generation has shown convincingly how they can translate into practise their committment to bring about social change. And they may well believe that Jewish peoplehood means the celebration of a rich diverse Jewish culture. I agree. What I question is whether this post- denominational generation have the inner resources to create such a culture. Will they celebrate Yiddish, Hebrew, Talmudic literature, Jewish Studies or all of the above. Somehow to me a culture is more than working out a lecture series at the 92nd Street Y.I hope these young people can come up with good answers. The previous generation outside of Orthodoxy were not very successful.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My conjecture is these group differ from both Reform and Orthodox in a signicant way. Orthodox are trying to bring people to Orthodoxy. The rest is bells and whistles. Reform Temples have an appreciation of a diverse Jewish culture, but for them the issue is that whatever takes place should be centered around the temple, a kiruv to a bldg. as it were.</p>
<p>So far this generation has shown convincingly how they can translate into practise their committment to bring about social change. And they may well believe that Jewish peoplehood means the celebration of a rich diverse Jewish culture. I agree. What I question is whether this post- denominational generation have the inner resources to create such a culture. Will they celebrate Yiddish, Hebrew, Talmudic literature, Jewish Studies or all of the above. Somehow to me a culture is more than working out a lecture series at the 92nd Street Y.I hope these young people can come up with good answers. The previous generation outside of Orthodoxy were not very successful.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Arie Folger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/12/key-findings-of-the-avi-chai-report-on-young-jewish-leaders/#comment-810</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arie Folger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2010 15:26:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1105#comment-810</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/12/key-findings-of-the-avi-chai-report-on-young-jewish-leaders/#comment-809&quot;&gt;Alan Brill&lt;/a&gt;.

This reminds me of a conversation I had with a rabbi, whose wife, after years of volunteer rebbetzenry, wanted to rejoin the work force, and needed to translate her parochial activities into resume lines that are relevant in the wider world.

However, getting back to the main point, this means that we cannot infer the likelihood of day school graduates remaining Orthodox from the Avi Chai statistic.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/12/key-findings-of-the-avi-chai-report-on-young-jewish-leaders/#comment-809">Alan Brill</a>.</p>
<p>This reminds me of a conversation I had with a rabbi, whose wife, after years of volunteer rebbetzenry, wanted to rejoin the work force, and needed to translate her parochial activities into resume lines that are relevant in the wider world.</p>
<p>However, getting back to the main point, this means that we cannot infer the likelihood of day school graduates remaining Orthodox from the Avi Chai statistic.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/12/key-findings-of-the-avi-chai-report-on-young-jewish-leaders/#comment-809</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2010 15:17:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1105#comment-809</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It is totally selection biased. However it is the same selection criteria used for Wexner, Dorot, and graduate school admissions. I have written lots of recommendation letters and they always ask for these criteria. The formal capacity, resume lines, and external activity is the criteria for leadership. The giver of the shiur would be at a disadvantage.  Yes, it only reflects those working in the wider world and who can convert it into a resume line.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It is totally selection biased. However it is the same selection criteria used for Wexner, Dorot, and graduate school admissions. I have written lots of recommendation letters and they always ask for these criteria. The formal capacity, resume lines, and external activity is the criteria for leadership. The giver of the shiur would be at a disadvantage.  Yes, it only reflects those working in the wider world and who can convert it into a resume line.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Arie Folger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/12/key-findings-of-the-avi-chai-report-on-young-jewish-leaders/#comment-808</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arie Folger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2010 08:43:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1105#comment-808</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&lt;blockquote&gt;Notice the day school graduates did not remain Orthodox, so that Orthodoxy’s remains at the 10% mark.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
This may or may not be correct, but I would be very wary of selection bias. Before this statistic can be considered meaningful, I would want to know whether the kind of leadership they were looking for is &quot;naturally&quot; more attractive - for better or for worse - to the less observant public. For example, social action has, for decades, been a focus of the more liberal institutions.

Do these causes also disproportionally affect the less observant day school students, perhaps because despite being less observant, they have happily been conditioned for a much more intensive Jewish identity? 

And does a businessman who gives a popular shiur in his shul, but holds no clerical office, nor is he involved in a formal capacity in an organization, fall outside the definition used by Avi Chai, and may he yet be an up and coming leader? Same for a businessman who is very committed to a cause, but does so without formalities.

I don&#039;t dismiss the findings, I just want the statisticians to tell us about any possible selection bias.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Notice the day school graduates did not remain Orthodox, so that Orthodoxy’s remains at the 10% mark.</p></blockquote>
<p>This may or may not be correct, but I would be very wary of selection bias. Before this statistic can be considered meaningful, I would want to know whether the kind of leadership they were looking for is &#8220;naturally&#8221; more attractive &#8211; for better or for worse &#8211; to the less observant public. For example, social action has, for decades, been a focus of the more liberal institutions.</p>
<p>Do these causes also disproportionally affect the less observant day school students, perhaps because despite being less observant, they have happily been conditioned for a much more intensive Jewish identity? </p>
<p>And does a businessman who gives a popular shiur in his shul, but holds no clerical office, nor is he involved in a formal capacity in an organization, fall outside the definition used by Avi Chai, and may he yet be an up and coming leader? Same for a businessman who is very committed to a cause, but does so without formalities.</p>
<p>I don&#8217;t dismiss the findings, I just want the statisticians to tell us about any possible selection bias.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
