<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Is there a Post-Orthodox Judaism that Corresponds to Post Evangelical?	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/19/is-there-a-post-orthodox-judaism-that-corresponds-to-post-evangelical/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/19/is-there-a-post-orthodox-judaism-that-corresponds-to-post-evangelical/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Dec 2012 16:36:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Michael Makovi		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/19/is-there-a-post-orthodox-judaism-that-corresponds-to-post-evangelical/#comment-519</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Michael Makovi]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2010 12:49:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=293#comment-519</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I learned in Machon Meir for three years, so I had a lot of contact with converts and 18-35 year old &lt;i&gt;ba&#039;alei teshuva&lt;/i&gt;. A lot of them bought the general &lt;i&gt;Hardal&lt;/i&gt; party line, and I won&#039;t speak about them.

But there&#039;s another section of them. These people are committed to strict Orthodox Judaism, but they are most dissatisfied with either the lack of intellectual depth, or with the offensive positions taken by mainstream Orthodoxy.For example, many of my friends were extremely disgusted by the &lt;i&gt;Hardal&lt;/i&gt; attitude on Christianity, finding it akin to racism and bigotry.Others are repulsed by any number of other issues. For example, many are disgusted by the lifestyle and opinions of the &lt;i&gt;Haredim&lt;/i&gt;, and how the Modern Orthodox and &lt;i&gt;Hardalim&lt;/i&gt; are inching ever closer to the &lt;i&gt;Haredim&lt;/i&gt;.

I have a friend that she wanted to be Orthodox ever since she was a little girl, and finally, when she became an adult, she was able to do so. However, she quickly realized that for many, Orthodoxy is an excuse to defenestrate your brain and surrender your free will, and she wanted none of this. In the end, my friend has a rather individualistic and eclectic approach to &lt;i&gt;halakhah&lt;/i&gt;. Don&#039;t misunderstand; she &lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;does&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt; strictly keep &lt;i&gt;halakhah&lt;/i&gt;. But after seeing so many rabbis out there make so many ridiculous and absurd rulings, she is skeptical of her obligation to &lt;i&gt;asei lekha rav&lt;/i&gt;. She definitely learns halakhic texts very sincerely and seriously, but in the end, she accepts what she herself finds personally reasonable.

Other friends of mine find their own path. Several people I know, for example, have realized that most rabbis out there haven&#039;t a clue, and so they&#039;ve instead turned to the Rambam and chosen the &lt;i&gt;Mishneh Torah&lt;/i&gt; as their &lt;i&gt;qitzur&lt;/i&gt;. If no one today has his head on straight, then they find someone who did.
]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I learned in Machon Meir for three years, so I had a lot of contact with converts and 18-35 year old <i>ba&#8217;alei teshuva</i>. A lot of them bought the general <i>Hardal</i> party line, and I won&#8217;t speak about them.</p>
<p>But there&#8217;s another section of them. These people are committed to strict Orthodox Judaism, but they are most dissatisfied with either the lack of intellectual depth, or with the offensive positions taken by mainstream Orthodoxy.For example, many of my friends were extremely disgusted by the <i>Hardal</i> attitude on Christianity, finding it akin to racism and bigotry.Others are repulsed by any number of other issues. For example, many are disgusted by the lifestyle and opinions of the <i>Haredim</i>, and how the Modern Orthodox and <i>Hardalim</i> are inching ever closer to the <i>Haredim</i>.</p>
<p>I have a friend that she wanted to be Orthodox ever since she was a little girl, and finally, when she became an adult, she was able to do so. However, she quickly realized that for many, Orthodoxy is an excuse to defenestrate your brain and surrender your free will, and she wanted none of this. In the end, my friend has a rather individualistic and eclectic approach to <i>halakhah</i>. Don&#8217;t misunderstand; she <i><b>does</b></i> strictly keep <i>halakhah</i>. But after seeing so many rabbis out there make so many ridiculous and absurd rulings, she is skeptical of her obligation to <i>asei lekha rav</i>. She definitely learns halakhic texts very sincerely and seriously, but in the end, she accepts what she herself finds personally reasonable.</p>
<p>Other friends of mine find their own path. Several people I know, for example, have realized that most rabbis out there haven&#8217;t a clue, and so they&#8217;ve instead turned to the Rambam and chosen the <i>Mishneh Torah</i> as their <i>qitzur</i>. If no one today has his head on straight, then they find someone who did.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Abacaxi Mamao		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/19/is-there-a-post-orthodox-judaism-that-corresponds-to-post-evangelical/#comment-330</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Abacaxi Mamao]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2009 23:54:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=293#comment-330</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Interesting. I grew up Orthodox and am still mostly observant, but more and more, I identify as simply &quot;observant&quot; or even post-Orthodox. This is due to many reasons, but one important one is the Orthodox community&#039;s different social values from mine. The gap is particularly big in NYC and environs. I also take issue with the materialism, anti-intellectualism, and halakhic dishonesty that I see. It&#039;s not even like those things are balanced by a warm, loving, or caring community, as far as my experiences go.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Interesting. I grew up Orthodox and am still mostly observant, but more and more, I identify as simply &#8220;observant&#8221; or even post-Orthodox. This is due to many reasons, but one important one is the Orthodox community&#8217;s different social values from mine. The gap is particularly big in NYC and environs. I also take issue with the materialism, anti-intellectualism, and halakhic dishonesty that I see. It&#8217;s not even like those things are balanced by a warm, loving, or caring community, as far as my experiences go.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/19/is-there-a-post-orthodox-judaism-that-corresponds-to-post-evangelical/#comment-319</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2009 13:25:51 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=293#comment-319</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[appolus- thanks for your comment. I have some future posts in mind on the emergent Church. 
When there was an arranged meeting back in 2006 between Emergents and what looked like their Jewish counterparts - the Christian side noted that the Jews think they are entirely still within the institutions and that the Jews were not interested in theory and theology to explain what they do and feel- they just wanted music and experience.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>appolus- thanks for your comment. I have some future posts in mind on the emergent Church.<br />
When there was an arranged meeting back in 2006 between Emergents and what looked like their Jewish counterparts &#8211; the Christian side noted that the Jews think they are entirely still within the institutions and that the Jews were not interested in theory and theology to explain what they do and feel- they just wanted music and experience.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: appolus		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/19/is-there-a-post-orthodox-judaism-that-corresponds-to-post-evangelical/#comment-315</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[appolus]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2009 22:00:58 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=293#comment-315</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Hi Guys, perhapa a few words from a Christian might help? :) There is a serious move afoot in Christianity, worldwide, to reject what they may call &quot;the establsihed church.&quot; This would include, denominations, non-denominations and the emergent church. I guess to put it into plain language, those who have had a real encounter, an epiphany so to speak, with God, no longer are able to stay within mainstream Christianity. Are these people orhtodox in what they believe? Very much so. Yet, they have found that they have nothing in common with what may be termed &quot;Cultural Christianity.&quot; The reason 80-90% of college kids walk away is because they only had tradition, they only had what their parents raised them with.  Yet, unless one can cry with King David &quot;As the deer panteth for the waterbrooks so my soul longeth after thee,&quot; then one is walking away from a mental assent to an abstract truth. There is a coming reformation of Christianity which will redefine what it means to be Christian. It will be based on a hunger and thirst for the presence of God. A seeking of the &quot;shekinah glory,&quot; or the manifest presence of God. Nothing else will satisfy. 
Psalm 51:11  Cast me not away from Your presence, and take not Your Holy Spirit from me. 
Psalm 51:12  Restore to me the joy of Your salvation, and uphold me with a willing spirit. 

People are seeking the reality of God. And while tradition has its place, if one only has tradition and not relationship, then what does one really have?
I understand that this is a Christian comment, yet perhaps we may see some parrallels?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hi Guys, perhapa a few words from a Christian might help? 🙂 There is a serious move afoot in Christianity, worldwide, to reject what they may call &#8220;the establsihed church.&#8221; This would include, denominations, non-denominations and the emergent church. I guess to put it into plain language, those who have had a real encounter, an epiphany so to speak, with God, no longer are able to stay within mainstream Christianity. Are these people orhtodox in what they believe? Very much so. Yet, they have found that they have nothing in common with what may be termed &#8220;Cultural Christianity.&#8221; The reason 80-90% of college kids walk away is because they only had tradition, they only had what their parents raised them with.  Yet, unless one can cry with King David &#8220;As the deer panteth for the waterbrooks so my soul longeth after thee,&#8221; then one is walking away from a mental assent to an abstract truth. There is a coming reformation of Christianity which will redefine what it means to be Christian. It will be based on a hunger and thirst for the presence of God. A seeking of the &#8220;shekinah glory,&#8221; or the manifest presence of God. Nothing else will satisfy.<br />
Psalm 51:11  Cast me not away from Your presence, and take not Your Holy Spirit from me.<br />
Psalm 51:12  Restore to me the joy of Your salvation, and uphold me with a willing spirit. </p>
<p>People are seeking the reality of God. And while tradition has its place, if one only has tradition and not relationship, then what does one really have?<br />
I understand that this is a Christian comment, yet perhaps we may see some parrallels?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/19/is-there-a-post-orthodox-judaism-that-corresponds-to-post-evangelical/#comment-299</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 25 Dec 2009 19:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=293#comment-299</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[84-86, It was connected to Inside-Outside, he wrote a few op-eds about Orthodoxy not solving agunah, misogyny, and not what he expected with Leo Jung and Emmanuel Rackman. This was during the WPG battles. He continued to attend the mehitza minyan in Palm Springs, but was disapponted. Maybe I will dig up some of the op-eds.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>84-86, It was connected to Inside-Outside, he wrote a few op-eds about Orthodoxy not solving agunah, misogyny, and not what he expected with Leo Jung and Emmanuel Rackman. This was during the WPG battles. He continued to attend the mehitza minyan in Palm Springs, but was disapponted. Maybe I will dig up some of the op-eds.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: lawrence kaplan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/19/is-there-a-post-orthodox-judaism-that-corresponds-to-post-evangelical/#comment-296</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lawrence kaplan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 25 Dec 2009 18:44:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=293#comment-296</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Alan:  Herman Wouk renounced Orthodoxy for right-wing Conservatism.  Really? When did this happen?  I consider myself fairly knowledgeable, but never heard of it.
Not only did it not make  a splah; it did not make a whisper.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Alan:  Herman Wouk renounced Orthodoxy for right-wing Conservatism.  Really? When did this happen?  I consider myself fairly knowledgeable, but never heard of it.<br />
Not only did it not make  a splah; it did not make a whisper.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Yonatan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/19/is-there-a-post-orthodox-judaism-that-corresponds-to-post-evangelical/#comment-223</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Yonatan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2009 17:57:51 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=293#comment-223</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[These numbers do not address the Emergent Church movement which allows its members to reject Megachurch Evangelism, but accept some for of Orthodox-ish Christianity.

I suppose that Minyanim play a similar role for many ex-Orthodox.

Also, as Christian Smith points out in American Evengelicals, many people who are described as &quot;ex-evangelicals&quot; still have Orthodox beliefs, but just don&#039;t attend Church.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>These numbers do not address the Emergent Church movement which allows its members to reject Megachurch Evangelism, but accept some for of Orthodox-ish Christianity.</p>
<p>I suppose that Minyanim play a similar role for many ex-Orthodox.</p>
<p>Also, as Christian Smith points out in American Evengelicals, many people who are described as &#8220;ex-evangelicals&#8221; still have Orthodox beliefs, but just don&#8217;t attend Church.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/19/is-there-a-post-orthodox-judaism-that-corresponds-to-post-evangelical/#comment-192</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2009 06:03:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=293#comment-192</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/19/is-there-a-post-orthodox-judaism-that-corresponds-to-post-evangelical/#comment-185&quot;&gt;evanstonjew&lt;/a&gt;.

evanstonjew-
A variety of disconnected thoughts - not to be joined. I am not sure that there are similar reasons. there seems to be many things going on. Internal Orthodox debates are not occurring for the same reasons as Neusner&#039;s op-ed.. People are forever switching right and left. People often go back to the faith of their youth. Arguments need a fertile ground.- when Herman Wouk renounced his Orthodoxy for right wing Conservatisim- it did not make a splash because of the orthodox triumphalism of the time and becuase the Conservative movement was becoming liberal and had little use for a 1950&#039;s right wing author.e are in an age of turning liberal that is reversing the course of the 80&#039;s and 90&#039;s.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/19/is-there-a-post-orthodox-judaism-that-corresponds-to-post-evangelical/#comment-185">evanstonjew</a>.</p>
<p>evanstonjew-<br />
A variety of disconnected thoughts &#8211; not to be joined. I am not sure that there are similar reasons. there seems to be many things going on. Internal Orthodox debates are not occurring for the same reasons as Neusner&#8217;s op-ed.. People are forever switching right and left. People often go back to the faith of their youth. Arguments need a fertile ground.- when Herman Wouk renounced his Orthodoxy for right wing Conservatisim- it did not make a splash because of the orthodox triumphalism of the time and becuase the Conservative movement was becoming liberal and had little use for a 1950&#8217;s right wing author.e are in an age of turning liberal that is reversing the course of the 80&#8217;s and 90&#8217;s.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/19/is-there-a-post-orthodox-judaism-that-corresponds-to-post-evangelical/#comment-189</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2009 05:51:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=293#comment-189</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/19/is-there-a-post-orthodox-judaism-that-corresponds-to-post-evangelical/#comment-178&quot;&gt;Jonathan Hirsch&lt;/a&gt;.

It is hard to get statistics of a live phenomena with no external signs.  We know that after the 1960&#039;s and 70&#039;s there were 45 % less Orthodox Jews.  Right now, it is hard to tell when someone is out of the community- some declare they are out at 22, others at 32 and others at 42. We will look back in 2025 and see the losses. We will also see how many of those who leave orthodoxy join mainline forms of liberal Judiasm and how many create some new limbo approach.

Unreliable Statistics on Young Evangelicals Are Deserting

• A recent TIME Magazine article points to research that found 61 percent of the adults now in their twenties participated in church activities as teens but not now.
• A study from UCLA found that only 29 percent of college students are still involved in church activities by their junior year.
• Josh McDowell estimates, &#039;over 69 percent of youth are leaving traditional church after high school.&#039;
• Mark Matlock finds, &#039;Depending on whose numbers you use, 58 percent - 84 percent of graduating youth from church youth groups are not returning.&#039;
• Glenn Schultz at LifeWay Christian Resources estimates that 75 percent of young people leave church in their late teens and aren&#039;t reconnecting later.
• Ron Luce in Battle Cry for a Generation estimates &#039;88 percent of kids raised in Christian homes do not continue to follow the Lord after they graduate from high school.&#039;
• Evangelical pollster George Barna says, &#039;Now only 33 percent of churched youth say that the church will play a part in their lives when they leave home. ]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/19/is-there-a-post-orthodox-judaism-that-corresponds-to-post-evangelical/#comment-178">Jonathan Hirsch</a>.</p>
<p>It is hard to get statistics of a live phenomena with no external signs.  We know that after the 1960&#8217;s and 70&#8217;s there were 45 % less Orthodox Jews.  Right now, it is hard to tell when someone is out of the community- some declare they are out at 22, others at 32 and others at 42. We will look back in 2025 and see the losses. We will also see how many of those who leave orthodoxy join mainline forms of liberal Judiasm and how many create some new limbo approach.</p>
<p>Unreliable Statistics on Young Evangelicals Are Deserting</p>
<p>• A recent TIME Magazine article points to research that found 61 percent of the adults now in their twenties participated in church activities as teens but not now.<br />
• A study from UCLA found that only 29 percent of college students are still involved in church activities by their junior year.<br />
• Josh McDowell estimates, &#8216;over 69 percent of youth are leaving traditional church after high school.&#8217;<br />
• Mark Matlock finds, &#8216;Depending on whose numbers you use, 58 percent &#8211; 84 percent of graduating youth from church youth groups are not returning.&#8217;<br />
• Glenn Schultz at LifeWay Christian Resources estimates that 75 percent of young people leave church in their late teens and aren&#8217;t reconnecting later.<br />
• Ron Luce in Battle Cry for a Generation estimates &#8217;88 percent of kids raised in Christian homes do not continue to follow the Lord after they graduate from high school.&#8217;<br />
• Evangelical pollster George Barna says, &#8216;Now only 33 percent of churched youth say that the church will play a part in their lives when they leave home. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: evanstonjew		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/19/is-there-a-post-orthodox-judaism-that-corresponds-to-post-evangelical/#comment-185</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[evanstonjew]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2009 01:46:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=293#comment-185</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Everyone seems to be using these arguments against the group to it&#039;s right. First against charedim by strict MO, then by the left of MO against the right. The Conservatives bang away at the  Orthodox in the name of historicism and liberalism. Now I see the eminent Rabbi Jacob Neusner has become Reform and is ranting at the Conservatives, for similar reasons. 
 http://forward.com/articles/119646/

It&#039;s a lot like dog bites man.

Why must going to the religious left always end in more and more  liberalism?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Everyone seems to be using these arguments against the group to it&#8217;s right. First against charedim by strict MO, then by the left of MO against the right. The Conservatives bang away at the  Orthodox in the name of historicism and liberalism. Now I see the eminent Rabbi Jacob Neusner has become Reform and is ranting at the Conservatives, for similar reasons.<br />
 <a href="http://forward.com/articles/119646/" rel="nofollow ugc">http://forward.com/articles/119646/</a></p>
<p>It&#8217;s a lot like dog bites man.</p>
<p>Why must going to the religious left always end in more and more  liberalism?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Jonathan Hirsch		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/19/is-there-a-post-orthodox-judaism-that-corresponds-to-post-evangelical/#comment-178</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jonathan Hirsch]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Nov 2009 02:12:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=293#comment-178</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Sounds familar ,can we get some real statistics ? those who leave are not comfortable with liberal options due to cultural reasons]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sounds familar ,can we get some real statistics ? those who leave are not comfortable with liberal options due to cultural reasons</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
