<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: A new blog with criticism of the Statement on Principles	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/27/a-new-blog-with-criticism-of-the-statement-on-principles/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/27/a-new-blog-with-criticism-of-the-statement-on-principles/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2010 12:18:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: cashia		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/27/a-new-blog-with-criticism-of-the-statement-on-principles/#comment-1434</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[cashia]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2010 12:18:20 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1750#comment-1434</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/27/a-new-blog-with-criticism-of-the-statement-on-principles/#comment-1418&quot;&gt;H Sragow&lt;/a&gt;.

H: 

&#062;&#062; To my reading, that’s exactly what the “Statement” was doing. Note its distinctions between what “Halacha” dictates (in a word, intolerance) and what “We” believes, and “the community” should do (accept, include). 

I am uncomfortable with this distinction (and this is what I continue to grapple with). I do not believe that halakha is inherently intolerant, nor do I believe that as a community we must automatically accept and include. I believe it is the responsibility of a halakhic community to live lives in accordance with that halakha, and I also believe that the halakha is dynamic and open to multiple, legitimate interpretations. 

Same point regarding your second comment. I believe there can be a moral &quot;right&quot; that goes beyond the halakha (ie something can be halakhically acceptable but morally more questionable) but there cannot be a moral &quot;right&quot; that goes AGAINST the halakha. 

At least, I do not believe that either of these can be the case unless we change our understanding of what halakha is and how it functions within Judaism, and within our societies.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/27/a-new-blog-with-criticism-of-the-statement-on-principles/#comment-1418">H Sragow</a>.</p>
<p>H: </p>
<p>&gt;&gt; To my reading, that’s exactly what the “Statement” was doing. Note its distinctions between what “Halacha” dictates (in a word, intolerance) and what “We” believes, and “the community” should do (accept, include). </p>
<p>I am uncomfortable with this distinction (and this is what I continue to grapple with). I do not believe that halakha is inherently intolerant, nor do I believe that as a community we must automatically accept and include. I believe it is the responsibility of a halakhic community to live lives in accordance with that halakha, and I also believe that the halakha is dynamic and open to multiple, legitimate interpretations. </p>
<p>Same point regarding your second comment. I believe there can be a moral &#8220;right&#8221; that goes beyond the halakha (ie something can be halakhically acceptable but morally more questionable) but there cannot be a moral &#8220;right&#8221; that goes AGAINST the halakha. </p>
<p>At least, I do not believe that either of these can be the case unless we change our understanding of what halakha is and how it functions within Judaism, and within our societies.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Len Moskowitz		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/27/a-new-blog-with-criticism-of-the-statement-on-principles/#comment-1430</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Len Moskowitz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2010 04:06:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1750#comment-1430</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[My wife reminded me that back in the 60&#039;s or 70&#039;s there was a poster that was popular in the women&#039;s movement.  The caption to the picture of a pregnant Pope was: &quot;If men could get pregnant,  abortion would be a sacrament.&quot;]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My wife reminded me that back in the 60&#8217;s or 70&#8217;s there was a poster that was popular in the women&#8217;s movement.  The caption to the picture of a pregnant Pope was: &#8220;If men could get pregnant,  abortion would be a sacrament.&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Kevin Rothman		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/27/a-new-blog-with-criticism-of-the-statement-on-principles/#comment-1425</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kevin Rothman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2010 10:46:38 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1750#comment-1425</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[  This is precisely why, in my opinion, you are seeing the laity taking an active role in determining what the law should be, that it should be &quot;right&quot;: because the rabbinate has shown itself unable to take the initiative.  If rabbinic leaders were to show meaningful leadership in this area it might be different.  On this note, I think R. Avi Weiss is an inspiring exception to this rule.  If others took his lead, at least in the overall direction of his thinking if not his specific rulings, american orthodoxy would be moving in a much better direction.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>  This is precisely why, in my opinion, you are seeing the laity taking an active role in determining what the law should be, that it should be &#8220;right&#8221;: because the rabbinate has shown itself unable to take the initiative.  If rabbinic leaders were to show meaningful leadership in this area it might be different.  On this note, I think R. Avi Weiss is an inspiring exception to this rule.  If others took his lead, at least in the overall direction of his thinking if not his specific rulings, american orthodoxy would be moving in a much better direction.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: H Sragow		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/27/a-new-blog-with-criticism-of-the-statement-on-principles/#comment-1423</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[H Sragow]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 29 Jul 2010 16:23:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1750#comment-1423</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Moshe -- I&#039;m sure you&#039;re right that many modern poskim discount mesira.  But until &quot;Stolen Innocence,&quot; halacha le-maaseh (at least as far as I saw) commonly required the ruling of a beit din before turning a Jew to the authorities.

For example, in late 1980s Brooklyn.  NY Post reported that the owner of a Jewish day-care center  was molesting the children entrusted to his care.  But the local rabbanim ruled that the parents cannot cooperate with the police, and must go to beit din first.   

The same pattern applied in the Lanner case itself, with a beit din ruling in 1988 that mesira is not warranted.

Overwhelming factual evidence was necessary in order to make psak change, particularly on a &quot;topic we can&#039;t discuss.&quot;    Looks to me like the signatories followed a similar path:  they recognized overwhelming factual evidence, and attempted to adjust accordingly.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Moshe &#8212; I&#8217;m sure you&#8217;re right that many modern poskim discount mesira.  But until &#8220;Stolen Innocence,&#8221; halacha le-maaseh (at least as far as I saw) commonly required the ruling of a beit din before turning a Jew to the authorities.</p>
<p>For example, in late 1980s Brooklyn.  NY Post reported that the owner of a Jewish day-care center  was molesting the children entrusted to his care.  But the local rabbanim ruled that the parents cannot cooperate with the police, and must go to beit din first.   </p>
<p>The same pattern applied in the Lanner case itself, with a beit din ruling in 1988 that mesira is not warranted.</p>
<p>Overwhelming factual evidence was necessary in order to make psak change, particularly on a &#8220;topic we can&#8217;t discuss.&#8221;    Looks to me like the signatories followed a similar path:  they recognized overwhelming factual evidence, and attempted to adjust accordingly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: moshe shoshan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/27/a-new-blog-with-criticism-of-the-statement-on-principles/#comment-1419</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[moshe shoshan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 29 Jul 2010 06:03:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1750#comment-1419</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I think your statement about mesirah is incorrect. There are numerous poskim, including in my understanding, the tzitz eliezer, who rule that mesira does not apply in democratic societies.   I dont think that mesirah was simply thrown by the wayside.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think your statement about mesirah is incorrect. There are numerous poskim, including in my understanding, the tzitz eliezer, who rule that mesira does not apply in democratic societies.   I dont think that mesirah was simply thrown by the wayside.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: H Sragow		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/27/a-new-blog-with-criticism-of-the-statement-on-principles/#comment-1418</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[H Sragow]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 29 Jul 2010 02:49:52 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1750#comment-1418</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Two comments.

Re: &quot;I just wonder if at any point the Orthodox community will explicitly grapple with the contradiction of halacha and our (independent?) moral instincts. &quot;

To my reading, that&#039;s exactly what the &quot;Statement&quot; was doing.   Note its distinctions between what &quot;Halacha&quot; dictates (in a word, intolerance) and what &quot;We&quot; believes, and &quot;the community&quot; should do (accept, include).  

Second comment:  I find the statement interesting for what it says about 21st century psak.     For example:  It uses non-rabbis to bolster its credibility on certain facts; and it advocates from what is &quot;right,&quot; quite apart from what the &quot;law&quot; is.    

We saw some of this pattern previously in the wake of Baruch Lanner.   Before &quot;Stolen Innocence,&quot; turning an Orthodox sexual abuser to the police was mesirah (handing a Jew to non-Jewish authorities) and forbidden.   But afterwards, mesirah was suddenly no longer a problem.  

Decisors at the time were able to cloak this innovation under pikuach nefesh, saying that lives were at stake.  The signatories of the &quot;Statement,&quot; however, apparently saw less need to resort to an halachic category to say what is &quot;right.&quot;]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Two comments.</p>
<p>Re: &#8220;I just wonder if at any point the Orthodox community will explicitly grapple with the contradiction of halacha and our (independent?) moral instincts. &#8221;</p>
<p>To my reading, that&#8217;s exactly what the &#8220;Statement&#8221; was doing.   Note its distinctions between what &#8220;Halacha&#8221; dictates (in a word, intolerance) and what &#8220;We&#8221; believes, and &#8220;the community&#8221; should do (accept, include).  </p>
<p>Second comment:  I find the statement interesting for what it says about 21st century psak.     For example:  It uses non-rabbis to bolster its credibility on certain facts; and it advocates from what is &#8220;right,&#8221; quite apart from what the &#8220;law&#8221; is.    </p>
<p>We saw some of this pattern previously in the wake of Baruch Lanner.   Before &#8220;Stolen Innocence,&#8221; turning an Orthodox sexual abuser to the police was mesirah (handing a Jew to non-Jewish authorities) and forbidden.   But afterwards, mesirah was suddenly no longer a problem.  </p>
<p>Decisors at the time were able to cloak this innovation under pikuach nefesh, saying that lives were at stake.  The signatories of the &#8220;Statement,&#8221; however, apparently saw less need to resort to an halachic category to say what is &#8220;right.&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/27/a-new-blog-with-criticism-of-the-statement-on-principles/#comment-1409</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Jul 2010 19:14:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1750#comment-1409</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/27/a-new-blog-with-criticism-of-the-statement-on-principles/#comment-1408&quot;&gt;Len Moskowitz&lt;/a&gt;.

Because they also start as an orthodoxy with strict observance, education, and living in an enclave.The rise of Centrism was due to many of the same cause and followed similar patterns.  Their younger set is moving and shifting around looking for changes and a form that fits their life.
So too in orthodoxy, the younger set is not looking to reform but are moving beyond their parents version. We hear greater talk about ethics, arts, lifestyle choices. Many of the complaints are similar.  Yet they want to remain in the tradition in the end. In some things we are closer to the Catholics. When I mean Evangelical I do not mean some stereotype of the deep South. I am thinking Rick Warren or Joel Hunter. You may want to see my original posts from half a year ago on post-orthodoxy and the emergent Church.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/27/a-new-blog-with-criticism-of-the-statement-on-principles/#comment-1408">Len Moskowitz</a>.</p>
<p>Because they also start as an orthodoxy with strict observance, education, and living in an enclave.The rise of Centrism was due to many of the same cause and followed similar patterns.  Their younger set is moving and shifting around looking for changes and a form that fits their life.<br />
So too in orthodoxy, the younger set is not looking to reform but are moving beyond their parents version. We hear greater talk about ethics, arts, lifestyle choices. Many of the complaints are similar.  Yet they want to remain in the tradition in the end. In some things we are closer to the Catholics. When I mean Evangelical I do not mean some stereotype of the deep South. I am thinking Rick Warren or Joel Hunter. You may want to see my original posts from half a year ago on post-orthodoxy and the emergent Church.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Len Moskowitz		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/07/27/a-new-blog-with-criticism-of-the-statement-on-principles/#comment-1408</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Len Moskowitz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Jul 2010 19:05:13 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1750#comment-1408</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Why do you think that the Evangelical experience is a useful reference for post-Orthodoxy?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Why do you think that the Evangelical experience is a useful reference for post-Orthodoxy?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
