<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Hitchens, Atheism, and Rav Kook	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/12/17/hitchens-atheism-and-rav-kook/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/12/17/hitchens-atheism-and-rav-kook/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2015 08:44:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: tillerofthesoil		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/12/17/hitchens-atheism-and-rav-kook/#comment-13231</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tillerofthesoil]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2015 08:44:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4437#comment-13231</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[“In every man there is an unknown spark that demands to unite with God. And sometimes it comes to life and awakens to know God, or to deny God (which is the same thing)” (Ba’al ha-Sullam, Rav Yehudah Ashlag, The Final Generation).]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>“In every man there is an unknown spark that demands to unite with God. And sometimes it comes to life and awakens to know God, or to deny God (which is the same thing)” (Ba’al ha-Sullam, Rav Yehudah Ashlag, The Final Generation).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: zjb		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/12/17/hitchens-atheism-and-rav-kook/#comment-3934</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[zjb]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2011 18:07:26 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4437#comment-3934</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I didn&#039;t think much of Hitchens&#039; new atheism until I read his article in  Vanity Fair on the King James translation of the Bible. It was as eloquent an argument for the importance of the Bible and the power of its language as I have ever read by any religionist after Buber and Rosenzweig or Robert Alter. No death bed conversion, the frame was thoroughly humanist, and I loved it. You can find it at: http://www.vanityfair.com/culture/features/2011/05/hitchens-201105]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I didn&#8217;t think much of Hitchens&#8217; new atheism until I read his article in  Vanity Fair on the King James translation of the Bible. It was as eloquent an argument for the importance of the Bible and the power of its language as I have ever read by any religionist after Buber and Rosenzweig or Robert Alter. No death bed conversion, the frame was thoroughly humanist, and I loved it. You can find it at: <a href="http://www.vanityfair.com/culture/features/2011/05/hitchens-201105" rel="nofollow ugc">http://www.vanityfair.com/culture/features/2011/05/hitchens-201105</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/12/17/hitchens-atheism-and-rav-kook/#comment-3908</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2011 20:30:29 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4437#comment-3908</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[You questions are difficult because they are  vague. Hitchens is a sideshow. He was a wonderful entertainer, sparkling polemicist, but his views changed radically over time, he lost most battles, and he ended in bed with the neo-Conservatives, promoting the Iraqi war and a WW4 in perpetuity against Islamofascism. His character was not  virtuous, in particular his intentional self abuse  in smoking and drinking, ad delo yadah every day of the year. Why then the admiration? I say because he  was a romantic figure, a Byronic- hero, and there are so few charismatic romantic figures available. Which brings me to my next point…what exactly is a vulgar believer and a vulgar atheist? For example, we can have scholastic religion, say Plantinga twists on epistemic justification, and Dennet style hard evolution on the other. Are these vulgar?  I would think not, but both do little to breathe any life into either religion or atheism. They lead to very technical questions in epistemology, evolution, probability, interesting to the specialist, kind of boring to everyone else. The vulgar thesis becomes more interesting if we are talking of romantic religion vs. romantic versions of Communism or  Conservativism. Then both sides are in a way vulgar, Gush colonial politics vs. world revolution,  chassidic anti modernism vs. Fascism/cowboy capitalism.
Once you have a goal it is much easier to find an atheism that purifies. Before we can talk of the reconstruction  of theology, we  need to make a very basic decision. Do we want a pragmatic Judaism, working for the spiritual and material welfare of Jews in realistic and practical ways, with the goal of not getting even but winning, or are we missing a new plausible version of romantic Judaism, now that socialism , Zionism &#038; American neo-liberalism have lost their attraction? Are we looking for some big messianic cause, are we in perpetual war against the world and its culture, or will we go for slow cumulative improvement at the margins? If you love a romantic religious sensibility, suburban self satisfied MO are problematic. If you are looking for spiritual and aesthetic improvement over time, MO like so many other Jews are on a learning curve. 
Plantiga/Dennet…  http://www.nytimes.com/2011/12/14/books/alvin-plantingas-new-book-on-god-and-science.html?_r=1&#038;scp=1&#038;sq=plantinga&#038;st=cse

Anti-Hitchens… http://leninology.blogspot.com/ (12/16/11) 
 http://www.lrb.co.uk/v32/n12/david-runciman/its-been-a-lot-of-fun]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>You questions are difficult because they are  vague. Hitchens is a sideshow. He was a wonderful entertainer, sparkling polemicist, but his views changed radically over time, he lost most battles, and he ended in bed with the neo-Conservatives, promoting the Iraqi war and a WW4 in perpetuity against Islamofascism. His character was not  virtuous, in particular his intentional self abuse  in smoking and drinking, ad delo yadah every day of the year. Why then the admiration? I say because he  was a romantic figure, a Byronic- hero, and there are so few charismatic romantic figures available. Which brings me to my next point…what exactly is a vulgar believer and a vulgar atheist? For example, we can have scholastic religion, say Plantinga twists on epistemic justification, and Dennet style hard evolution on the other. Are these vulgar?  I would think not, but both do little to breathe any life into either religion or atheism. They lead to very technical questions in epistemology, evolution, probability, interesting to the specialist, kind of boring to everyone else. The vulgar thesis becomes more interesting if we are talking of romantic religion vs. romantic versions of Communism or  Conservativism. Then both sides are in a way vulgar, Gush colonial politics vs. world revolution,  chassidic anti modernism vs. Fascism/cowboy capitalism.<br />
Once you have a goal it is much easier to find an atheism that purifies. Before we can talk of the reconstruction  of theology, we  need to make a very basic decision. Do we want a pragmatic Judaism, working for the spiritual and material welfare of Jews in realistic and practical ways, with the goal of not getting even but winning, or are we missing a new plausible version of romantic Judaism, now that socialism , Zionism &amp; American neo-liberalism have lost their attraction? Are we looking for some big messianic cause, are we in perpetual war against the world and its culture, or will we go for slow cumulative improvement at the margins? If you love a romantic religious sensibility, suburban self satisfied MO are problematic. If you are looking for spiritual and aesthetic improvement over time, MO like so many other Jews are on a learning curve.<br />
Plantiga/Dennet…  <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/12/14/books/alvin-plantingas-new-book-on-god-and-science.html?_r=1&#038;scp=1&#038;sq=plantinga&#038;st=cse" rel="nofollow ugc">http://www.nytimes.com/2011/12/14/books/alvin-plantingas-new-book-on-god-and-science.html?_r=1&#038;scp=1&#038;sq=plantinga&#038;st=cse</a></p>
<p>Anti-Hitchens… <a href="http://leninology.blogspot.com/" rel="nofollow ugc">http://leninology.blogspot.com/</a> (12/16/11)<br />
 <a href="http://www.lrb.co.uk/v32/n12/david-runciman/its-been-a-lot-of-fun" rel="nofollow ugc">http://www.lrb.co.uk/v32/n12/david-runciman/its-been-a-lot-of-fun</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Larry Yudelson		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/12/17/hitchens-atheism-and-rav-kook/#comment-3900</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Larry Yudelson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2011 18:26:14 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4437#comment-3900</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[What these apologetics evade is that the believers want to believe in religion in its most vulgar, and this includes those unfortunate souls given the unhappy task of defending against the atheists. In the century since Rav Kook, the Judaism of his followers reached depths of vulgarity and superstition and evil unimaginable in Rav Kook&#039;s time -- and it turns out that the study and worship of Rav Kook is no vaccine against this vulgarity. On the contrary.

For all that the believers whine that Dawkins et.al. haven&#039;t consulted the Guide before condemning religion, the believers spend little time refining their religion in the spirit of the Guide. We see, to take a local example, Rabbi Shmuley Boteach making a great show of debating Hitchens; but does he debate those in his community whose believe in the saving power of a dead rebbe?

The truth is that a refined religion would lack the certitudes of knowing that you have the one revealed handbook of the one true god, and that you are part of the elite who have been promised salvation in the next world and granted the privilege of voting for your leaders in this world. (And to be explicit, I&#039;m saying that Rav Kook&#039;s opposition to letting women vote is a forerunner of the idea of his followers that the West Bank could be colonized and its population treated as indigenous non-persons rather than as citizens of a democratic polis.)

In this critique of the religious who would have it both ways -- who would have the comforting certitude and community of their orthodoxies, while assuring themselves of their modernity and liberalism through affiliation with YCT, Edah, and Uri L&#039;Zedek -- it is not Hitchens but Sam Harris who offers the sternest rebuke. He wants believers to take responsibility for their own enlightened faith, but also for how they enable the faith of those less enlightened. He demands we ask ourselves: How refined our religion if we are sending our children to schools that teach that God broke through history to dictate to Moses the Torah, with its view that killing women and children is acceptable behavior in time of war?

One can refine away enough of this &quot;dross&quot; to leave sufficient religion to provoke an argument from Hitchens. I think Andrew Sullivan has burnt enough of his childhood Catholicism, through his friendship with Hitchens, his disgust with the Church&#039;s coverup for child molestation, and his own homosexuality, to have reached that point. But Sullivan&#039;s Catholicism is not that of a liberal Orthodox Jew; it is that of a Reconstructionist or Reform Jew.

And just to pick on VBM for a minute: 

&lt;i&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Hence heresy, “kefira,” is the only dark force capable of contributing to world perfection&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/i&gt;

What does this mean, dark force? Is Yetzer Hara a dark force? But can&#039;t it be used for good, as indicated by the well-known midrashim? Dawkins would no doubt point out there the utter inherent stupidity of religious language, which pretends to have knowledge (&quot;the only dark force&quot;) which it does not. A physicist can speak of four known (and perhaps one unknown) forces, and point back ultimately to physical phenomenon that demonstrate such forces. A rabbi can just make up things with vague allusions to ancient books and with no expectation of critique or peer review.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What these apologetics evade is that the believers want to believe in religion in its most vulgar, and this includes those unfortunate souls given the unhappy task of defending against the atheists. In the century since Rav Kook, the Judaism of his followers reached depths of vulgarity and superstition and evil unimaginable in Rav Kook&#8217;s time &#8212; and it turns out that the study and worship of Rav Kook is no vaccine against this vulgarity. On the contrary.</p>
<p>For all that the believers whine that Dawkins et.al. haven&#8217;t consulted the Guide before condemning religion, the believers spend little time refining their religion in the spirit of the Guide. We see, to take a local example, Rabbi Shmuley Boteach making a great show of debating Hitchens; but does he debate those in his community whose believe in the saving power of a dead rebbe?</p>
<p>The truth is that a refined religion would lack the certitudes of knowing that you have the one revealed handbook of the one true god, and that you are part of the elite who have been promised salvation in the next world and granted the privilege of voting for your leaders in this world. (And to be explicit, I&#8217;m saying that Rav Kook&#8217;s opposition to letting women vote is a forerunner of the idea of his followers that the West Bank could be colonized and its population treated as indigenous non-persons rather than as citizens of a democratic polis.)</p>
<p>In this critique of the religious who would have it both ways &#8212; who would have the comforting certitude and community of their orthodoxies, while assuring themselves of their modernity and liberalism through affiliation with YCT, Edah, and Uri L&#8217;Zedek &#8212; it is not Hitchens but Sam Harris who offers the sternest rebuke. He wants believers to take responsibility for their own enlightened faith, but also for how they enable the faith of those less enlightened. He demands we ask ourselves: How refined our religion if we are sending our children to schools that teach that God broke through history to dictate to Moses the Torah, with its view that killing women and children is acceptable behavior in time of war?</p>
<p>One can refine away enough of this &#8220;dross&#8221; to leave sufficient religion to provoke an argument from Hitchens. I think Andrew Sullivan has burnt enough of his childhood Catholicism, through his friendship with Hitchens, his disgust with the Church&#8217;s coverup for child molestation, and his own homosexuality, to have reached that point. But Sullivan&#8217;s Catholicism is not that of a liberal Orthodox Jew; it is that of a Reconstructionist or Reform Jew.</p>
<p>And just to pick on VBM for a minute: </p>
<p><i></p>
<blockquote><p>Hence heresy, “kefira,” is the only dark force capable of contributing to world perfection</p></blockquote>
<p></i></p>
<p>What does this mean, dark force? Is Yetzer Hara a dark force? But can&#8217;t it be used for good, as indicated by the well-known midrashim? Dawkins would no doubt point out there the utter inherent stupidity of religious language, which pretends to have knowledge (&#8220;the only dark force&#8221;) which it does not. A physicist can speak of four known (and perhaps one unknown) forces, and point back ultimately to physical phenomenon that demonstrate such forces. A rabbi can just make up things with vague allusions to ancient books and with no expectation of critique or peer review.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
