<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: We&#8217;re an American Blog?	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/18/we-are-an-american-blog/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/18/we-are-an-american-blog/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2011 18:10:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: (Professor Emeritus) Alan Jay Weisbard, Madison, WI		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/18/we-are-an-american-blog/#comment-3407</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[(Professor Emeritus) Alan Jay Weisbard, Madison, WI]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2011 18:10:30 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3898#comment-3407</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Just FYI--here is one non-Orthodox, long-time NHC havurahnik, plopped down in the American Middle West, who reads and enjoys your blog on a regular basis. I found your publication of (and/or links to) the Arthur Green /Daniel Landes exchange of particular interest and value. Keep them coming.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Just FYI&#8211;here is one non-Orthodox, long-time NHC havurahnik, plopped down in the American Middle West, who reads and enjoys your blog on a regular basis. I found your publication of (and/or links to) the Arthur Green /Daniel Landes exchange of particular interest and value. Keep them coming.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: tomerpersico		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/18/we-are-an-american-blog/#comment-3405</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tomerpersico]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 23 Jul 2011 17:51:26 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3898#comment-3405</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I moved from Kiryat-Atta to Jerusalem this week, and so unfortunately only now have I read this post. So, sorry for that, and thank you Prof&#039; Brill for your kind words.

I&#039;ll just say why I referred to your blog as &quot;US Judaism&quot; – it&#039;s simply that I find that most posts and talkback discussions here deal with the (evolving and changing) boarders and boundaries of Jewish American denominations and views. So it&#039;s not only the attitude, or the accent, so to speak, which is American, but the subjects you mostly deal with. At least that&#039;s my impression.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I moved from Kiryat-Atta to Jerusalem this week, and so unfortunately only now have I read this post. So, sorry for that, and thank you Prof&#8217; Brill for your kind words.</p>
<p>I&#8217;ll just say why I referred to your blog as &#8220;US Judaism&#8221; – it&#8217;s simply that I find that most posts and talkback discussions here deal with the (evolving and changing) boarders and boundaries of Jewish American denominations and views. So it&#8217;s not only the attitude, or the accent, so to speak, which is American, but the subjects you mostly deal with. At least that&#8217;s my impression.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: HS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/18/we-are-an-american-blog/#comment-3404</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[HS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2011 04:27:32 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3898#comment-3404</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Asking whether this blog is &quot;American&quot; is like asking whether we should classify it as &quot;Betamax&quot; or &quot;VHS.&quot;

Since the advent of mass media,  geography&#039;s importance in cultural identity and belief began to recede.   An entire country could listen to Ed Murrow and Walter Cronkite, and many people across wide geographic divides adopted the beliefs of their preferred moderate anchorman.  

Narrow-casting on cable TV allowed broadcasters to find a particular niche of identity, and serve them very strong opinions.   People could use cable TV to associate with a particular identity -- regardless of where they were -- and have their beliefs comfortably spit  back at them.  

Now social networking allows people to interact solely with people of increasingly specific and similar beliefs and preferences -- again, regardless of where they live.   

What makes us read and interact with this blog is our idiosyncratic preferences for a particular type of thinking about Jewish things.   Where we were raised and live now probably plays only a secondary role in building those preferences.

To illustrate, I would ask how many people in your kindergarten class are also participating in this blog (I don&#039;t believe any of mine are, but of course you never know with anonymous posters).]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Asking whether this blog is &#8220;American&#8221; is like asking whether we should classify it as &#8220;Betamax&#8221; or &#8220;VHS.&#8221;</p>
<p>Since the advent of mass media,  geography&#8217;s importance in cultural identity and belief began to recede.   An entire country could listen to Ed Murrow and Walter Cronkite, and many people across wide geographic divides adopted the beliefs of their preferred moderate anchorman.  </p>
<p>Narrow-casting on cable TV allowed broadcasters to find a particular niche of identity, and serve them very strong opinions.   People could use cable TV to associate with a particular identity &#8212; regardless of where they were &#8212; and have their beliefs comfortably spit  back at them.  </p>
<p>Now social networking allows people to interact solely with people of increasingly specific and similar beliefs and preferences &#8212; again, regardless of where they live.   </p>
<p>What makes us read and interact with this blog is our idiosyncratic preferences for a particular type of thinking about Jewish things.   Where we were raised and live now probably plays only a secondary role in building those preferences.</p>
<p>To illustrate, I would ask how many people in your kindergarten class are also participating in this blog (I don&#8217;t believe any of mine are, but of course you never know with anonymous posters).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/18/we-are-an-american-blog/#comment-3400</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2011 22:58:32 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3898#comment-3400</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[EJ-
I am definitely American but I don’t reflect the broad spectrum and variety of American Jewry. I have an American context but a narrow focus of a few neighborhoods in the US but that also includes South Jerusalem, I may be an American antipode to some of the Israeli and Anglo-Israeli trends, clearly American yet enmeshed in a group of people forming culture on both sides of the Atlantic.
For  many the gap year has created a second city for them to feel comfortable living in and returning on a regular basis. Not just the very wealthy or global few. And the very programs are the Israeli soil are an antipode to their symbolic and projected images of Israel. But they are not really Israeli, they are Anglo.
And in my neighborhood, people commute regularly between the countries. My upcoming posts will include the books people are bringing me this month from Israel.
Yet, I don’t really think the two ends are antipods. It is something much more complex. Maybe Shai will weigh in with his thoughts.
I am not sure why you fell into the false dichotomy rhetoric of Zionist or Satmar, but many elements of Judaism as practiced are not territorial. And this Anglo aliyah that is not unidirectional and not permanent is not classic Zionism. 
 Israel is affecting second day Yom Tov among many things. And American brought women’s learning to Israel. Yair Sheleg did a small pamphlet a decade ago about the Anglos in Israel- it was too meager and had the wrong focus. A longer study is definitely needed.

Actually, I think that many of us have multiple formulations of our identities. Interfaith &#038; Kabbalah are also not reducible to a simple US or Israel. ]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>EJ-<br />
I am definitely American but I don’t reflect the broad spectrum and variety of American Jewry. I have an American context but a narrow focus of a few neighborhoods in the US but that also includes South Jerusalem, I may be an American antipode to some of the Israeli and Anglo-Israeli trends, clearly American yet enmeshed in a group of people forming culture on both sides of the Atlantic.<br />
For  many the gap year has created a second city for them to feel comfortable living in and returning on a regular basis. Not just the very wealthy or global few. And the very programs are the Israeli soil are an antipode to their symbolic and projected images of Israel. But they are not really Israeli, they are Anglo.<br />
And in my neighborhood, people commute regularly between the countries. My upcoming posts will include the books people are bringing me this month from Israel.<br />
Yet, I don’t really think the two ends are antipods. It is something much more complex. Maybe Shai will weigh in with his thoughts.<br />
I am not sure why you fell into the false dichotomy rhetoric of Zionist or Satmar, but many elements of Judaism as practiced are not territorial. And this Anglo aliyah that is not unidirectional and not permanent is not classic Zionism.<br />
 Israel is affecting second day Yom Tov among many things. And American brought women’s learning to Israel. Yair Sheleg did a small pamphlet a decade ago about the Anglos in Israel- it was too meager and had the wrong focus. A longer study is definitely needed.</p>
<p>Actually, I think that many of us have multiple formulations of our identities. Interfaith &amp; Kabbalah are also not reducible to a simple US or Israel. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Talmud in the New World &#124; The Talmud Blog		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/18/we-are-an-american-blog/#comment-3399</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Talmud in the New World &#124; The Talmud Blog]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2011 22:34:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3898#comment-3399</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[[...] the other day, Alan Brill responded to Tomer Persico and his classification of Brill&#8217;s blog as &#8220;American,&#8221; by [...]]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] the other day, Alan Brill responded to Tomer Persico and his classification of Brill&#8217;s blog as &#8220;American,&#8221; by [&#8230;]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/18/we-are-an-american-blog/#comment-3398</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2011 16:44:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3898#comment-3398</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I would say you’re blog is American because you were born in America and spent most of your life there, however much you travel abroad. In addition you’re an American because as a citizen you subscribe I would hope to the idea of America, political liberalism, with equal rights and opportunities for minorities. You understand how a republic with a constitution separating church and state is so very important in a fair and decent society. Some Israelis believe in these  values, but many don’t at least with regard to the Palestinians and the rights of secular Jews to marry and divorce. I also assume you do not subscribe at the political level to Jewish or Israeli exceptionalism, whereby all other nations must protect minorities and allow religious freedom, but Jews have a right revealed in the Torah to act differently. 
Your appeal to globalization is for me also problematic. I think except for the very wealthy with multiple mansions, most people think of one place they are happy to call home. If you consult the literature on globalization it is supposed to entail deterritorialization, according to which a growing variety of social activities takes place irrespective of the geographical location of participants. Zionists have worked for over a century to establish a state in a particular place. They would be shocked to learn territory is no longer very important. I assume you are closer to Zionists than to Satmar, so this globalization is not exactly a cause for celebration. Similarly for the second main consequence of globalization, the speeding up of time. Judaism has not changed its liturgical year, we don’t celebrate Pesach twice a year, Shabbus has not been abolished,  everything goes on at the same pace as it did for our ancestors. And we are all grateful for this resistance to globalization. Even the neo-liberal goal of arbitraging  labor markets (outsourcing), whereby capitalists shift  production to low wage countries, has not affected life inside the world of Judaism. If it did, I have no doubt all our tefilin and sefer torahs  would be produced in China. Computer guys are threatened, but for the moment sofrim are safe. Many religious Jews spend their free time on Talmudic studies in depth. Life doesn’t get much slower than 30 blatt a year. The upshot is that Judaism spends much of its capital, both financial and human to resist globalization, and we rightfully take pride in pushing against the winds of change. What I am trying to say is that globalization might describe macro trends affecting the world’s economies. As a personal ideal it  is far from being an advance over what we had. There is much to be said for being a provincial and taking life slow. 
http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/globalization/]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I would say you’re blog is American because you were born in America and spent most of your life there, however much you travel abroad. In addition you’re an American because as a citizen you subscribe I would hope to the idea of America, political liberalism, with equal rights and opportunities for minorities. You understand how a republic with a constitution separating church and state is so very important in a fair and decent society. Some Israelis believe in these  values, but many don’t at least with regard to the Palestinians and the rights of secular Jews to marry and divorce. I also assume you do not subscribe at the political level to Jewish or Israeli exceptionalism, whereby all other nations must protect minorities and allow religious freedom, but Jews have a right revealed in the Torah to act differently.<br />
Your appeal to globalization is for me also problematic. I think except for the very wealthy with multiple mansions, most people think of one place they are happy to call home. If you consult the literature on globalization it is supposed to entail deterritorialization, according to which a growing variety of social activities takes place irrespective of the geographical location of participants. Zionists have worked for over a century to establish a state in a particular place. They would be shocked to learn territory is no longer very important. I assume you are closer to Zionists than to Satmar, so this globalization is not exactly a cause for celebration. Similarly for the second main consequence of globalization, the speeding up of time. Judaism has not changed its liturgical year, we don’t celebrate Pesach twice a year, Shabbus has not been abolished,  everything goes on at the same pace as it did for our ancestors. And we are all grateful for this resistance to globalization. Even the neo-liberal goal of arbitraging  labor markets (outsourcing), whereby capitalists shift  production to low wage countries, has not affected life inside the world of Judaism. If it did, I have no doubt all our tefilin and sefer torahs  would be produced in China. Computer guys are threatened, but for the moment sofrim are safe. Many religious Jews spend their free time on Talmudic studies in depth. Life doesn’t get much slower than 30 blatt a year. The upshot is that Judaism spends much of its capital, both financial and human to resist globalization, and we rightfully take pride in pushing against the winds of change. What I am trying to say is that globalization might describe macro trends affecting the world’s economies. As a personal ideal it  is far from being an advance over what we had. There is much to be said for being a provincial and taking life slow.<br />
<a href="http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/globalization/" rel="nofollow ugc">http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/globalization/</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: rabbichaplain		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/18/we-are-an-american-blog/#comment-3397</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[rabbichaplain]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2011 13:35:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3898#comment-3397</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I think that the mere fact a blog is broadcast in a global way precludes it from being labeled American or Israeli or whatever.  The issues on this blog traverse both societies and to me it boils down different aspects of the Jewish cultural experience.  Looking at the blog, while some does focus on Israeli culture and academia, much of the other material is American, such as the discussion about mormonism and about half shabbos.  Yet, both of those areas are merely locale based, as the Israeli academia is written for an American audience, hence its language, and its not as if the material you are reviewing tends to be Hebrew academic works.  I think labeling any blog is anathema to the general idea of the internet as a global community.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think that the mere fact a blog is broadcast in a global way precludes it from being labeled American or Israeli or whatever.  The issues on this blog traverse both societies and to me it boils down different aspects of the Jewish cultural experience.  Looking at the blog, while some does focus on Israeli culture and academia, much of the other material is American, such as the discussion about mormonism and about half shabbos.  Yet, both of those areas are merely locale based, as the Israeli academia is written for an American audience, hence its language, and its not as if the material you are reviewing tends to be Hebrew academic works.  I think labeling any blog is anathema to the general idea of the internet as a global community.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/18/we-are-an-american-blog/#comment-3394</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2011 23:00:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3898#comment-3394</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/18/we-are-an-american-blog/#comment-3393&quot;&gt;Shai Secunda&lt;/a&gt;.

Is your blog American or Israeli or Anglo? And it is not just that some of the US born come home for the summer, but one of your Israeli members is teaching at Drisha. 
What does it mean to be an oleh, if you would accept a tenure track position in the US?
How much of your readership is as mobile between countries as you are?
Most importantly, You have lived in Boston, Baltimore, Jerusalem, and NY. Is your time in J-M different than the others? Is living in Boston and NY different than J-M and NY? 
What is the intellectual relationship of your Irano-Talmud studied in the US from that of HU? Finally, if you are chosen to stay at HU, would it not be specifically because of what you are bringing from NY? ]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/18/we-are-an-american-blog/#comment-3393">Shai Secunda</a>.</p>
<p>Is your blog American or Israeli or Anglo? And it is not just that some of the US born come home for the summer, but one of your Israeli members is teaching at Drisha.<br />
What does it mean to be an oleh, if you would accept a tenure track position in the US?<br />
How much of your readership is as mobile between countries as you are?<br />
Most importantly, You have lived in Boston, Baltimore, Jerusalem, and NY. Is your time in J-M different than the others? Is living in Boston and NY different than J-M and NY?<br />
What is the intellectual relationship of your Irano-Talmud studied in the US from that of HU? Finally, if you are chosen to stay at HU, would it not be specifically because of what you are bringing from NY? </p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Shai Secunda		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/18/we-are-an-american-blog/#comment-3393</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shai Secunda]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2011 22:56:46 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3898#comment-3393</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This post deserves to be fleshed out!  I would love to hear more of your thoughts on globalization and the &quot;new&quot; anglo oleh!]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This post deserves to be fleshed out!  I would love to hear more of your thoughts on globalization and the &#8220;new&#8221; anglo oleh!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Moshe Shoshan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/18/we-are-an-american-blog/#comment-3391</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Moshe Shoshan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2011 14:57:40 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3898#comment-3391</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As one of your Anglo-Israeli readers, I definitively see this as an american blog. for all your familiarity with what is going on here in Israel, you still write from New Jersey and it comes across. Physical space still matters in this world.  Kids growing up in places like beit shemesh call themselves &quot;Anglos&quot; many feel very american till they actually spend time in america and realize how Israeli they are.  It is a mistake to think that we actually live in cyber space]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As one of your Anglo-Israeli readers, I definitively see this as an american blog. for all your familiarity with what is going on here in Israel, you still write from New Jersey and it comes across. Physical space still matters in this world.  Kids growing up in places like beit shemesh call themselves &#8220;Anglos&#8221; many feel very american till they actually spend time in america and realize how Israeli they are.  It is a mistake to think that we actually live in cyber space</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Charles Arian		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/07/18/we-are-an-american-blog/#comment-3390</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Charles Arian]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2011 14:40:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3898#comment-3390</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I think this is very much an American blog, but the question brings to mind a lot of other interesting questions about identity.

I presume I am not the only one of your American readers who made an unsuccessful attempt at aliyah. During the years that I lived in Israel, it always frustrated me that someone from virtually anywhere else in the world can make aliyah and is now seen by Israeli society as Israeli but an American oleh, no matter how long he or she lives in Israeli, is still seen as an American. I suspect part of that has to do with the fact that American olim made aliyah out of choice rather than necessity, retain their American citizenship, usually still have many relatives in &quot;the old country&quot; and go back and forth frequently.

My sense -- and it is very much impressionistic and I could be wrong -- is that most of the religiously-interesting and creative stuff happening in Israel has more influence on the American scene than on the Israeli scene. There are plenty of &quot;Shira Chadasha&quot;-type minyanim in the States but are there others in Israel? If so, are there many non-Anglo participants? Are there many non-Anglos who daven at Shira Chadasha?

There was a period in the late seventies and early eighties when David Hartman was pretty influential in general Israeli society. At the time I had quite a bit of contact with educators from places like Oranim and Seminar Ha-Kibbutzim and his name was mentioned frequently by non-Anglo Israeli educators. But I don&#039;t know how much influence he has today. I venture that the Hartman Institute is a lot more influential on American Jewry than it is in Israel.

There is certainly cross-fertilization and it goes both ways. A sabra friend of mine comes from a dati background. She did some graduate work in the US -- I was her Hillel rabbi -- and became interested in more egalitarian forms of Judaism. She and her husband recently had egalitarian davening in their home for their daughter&#039;s Bat Mitzvah rather than have it in the Orthodox Jerusalem synagogue where they are members. But I wonder to what extent all of these various American phenomena when practiced in Israel get beyond a certain highly-educated elite. My friend and her husband are not Anglo per-se but they are both highly-educated, affluent, fluent English speakers and received part of their university educations outside of Israel.

Many years ago I heard a provocative speech by Leon Wieseltier. Washington Hebrew Congregation, a large Classical Reform Temple, has an annual &quot;State of World Jewry&quot; or some such title lecture. Wieseltier said that for all its creativity American Jewry may ultimately prove to have made no lasting contribution to the ongoing Jewish project because all of our literary production is in English. We are the first large Diaspora not to produce our output in a Jewish language and indeed so no importance in Hebrew knowledge, by and large. How many American rabbis of whatever denomination can read an Israeli newspaper with ease? An Israeli novel? Give a talk or a drasha in Hebrew?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think this is very much an American blog, but the question brings to mind a lot of other interesting questions about identity.</p>
<p>I presume I am not the only one of your American readers who made an unsuccessful attempt at aliyah. During the years that I lived in Israel, it always frustrated me that someone from virtually anywhere else in the world can make aliyah and is now seen by Israeli society as Israeli but an American oleh, no matter how long he or she lives in Israeli, is still seen as an American. I suspect part of that has to do with the fact that American olim made aliyah out of choice rather than necessity, retain their American citizenship, usually still have many relatives in &#8220;the old country&#8221; and go back and forth frequently.</p>
<p>My sense &#8212; and it is very much impressionistic and I could be wrong &#8212; is that most of the religiously-interesting and creative stuff happening in Israel has more influence on the American scene than on the Israeli scene. There are plenty of &#8220;Shira Chadasha&#8221;-type minyanim in the States but are there others in Israel? If so, are there many non-Anglo participants? Are there many non-Anglos who daven at Shira Chadasha?</p>
<p>There was a period in the late seventies and early eighties when David Hartman was pretty influential in general Israeli society. At the time I had quite a bit of contact with educators from places like Oranim and Seminar Ha-Kibbutzim and his name was mentioned frequently by non-Anglo Israeli educators. But I don&#8217;t know how much influence he has today. I venture that the Hartman Institute is a lot more influential on American Jewry than it is in Israel.</p>
<p>There is certainly cross-fertilization and it goes both ways. A sabra friend of mine comes from a dati background. She did some graduate work in the US &#8212; I was her Hillel rabbi &#8212; and became interested in more egalitarian forms of Judaism. She and her husband recently had egalitarian davening in their home for their daughter&#8217;s Bat Mitzvah rather than have it in the Orthodox Jerusalem synagogue where they are members. But I wonder to what extent all of these various American phenomena when practiced in Israel get beyond a certain highly-educated elite. My friend and her husband are not Anglo per-se but they are both highly-educated, affluent, fluent English speakers and received part of their university educations outside of Israel.</p>
<p>Many years ago I heard a provocative speech by Leon Wieseltier. Washington Hebrew Congregation, a large Classical Reform Temple, has an annual &#8220;State of World Jewry&#8221; or some such title lecture. Wieseltier said that for all its creativity American Jewry may ultimately prove to have made no lasting contribution to the ongoing Jewish project because all of our literary production is in English. We are the first large Diaspora not to produce our output in a Jewish language and indeed so no importance in Hebrew knowledge, by and large. How many American rabbis of whatever denomination can read an Israeli newspaper with ease? An Israeli novel? Give a talk or a drasha in Hebrew?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
