<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>lawrence Kaplan &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/tag/lawrence-kaplan/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 May 2016 23:20:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='kavvanah.wordpress.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/c9f111237f93750b6b994fc5185d49c3?s=96&#038;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>lawrence Kaplan &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>Rav Soloveitchik on the Guide of the Perplexed-edited by Lawrence Kaplan</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2016/05/09/rav-soloveitchik-on-the-guide-of-the-perplexed-edited-by-lawrence-kaplan/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2016 04:08:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ethics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Guide of the Perplexed]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hermann Cohen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lawrence Kaplan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[maimonides]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pantheism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rabbi Soloveitchik]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rav soloveitchik]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=7421</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When Rabbi Soloveitchik arrived at Yeshiva University he gave classes for two decades on philosophic topics.  In these lectures, we see Soloveitchik as the graduate of the University of Berlin in philosophy and as the former student in the Berlin &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2016/05/09/rav-soloveitchik-on-the-guide-of-the-perplexed-edited-by-lawrence-kaplan/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When Rabbi Soloveitchik arrived at Yeshiva University he gave classes for two decades on philosophic topics.  In these lectures, we see Soloveitchik as the graduate of the University of Berlin in philosophy and as the former student in the Berlin Rabbinical seminary (for a year). Soloveitchik gave great weight to future rabbis having training in philosophy and having a master’s degree in Jewish Studies.</p>
<p>Did you ever want to know what Rabbi Soloveitchik&#8217;s early philosophy lectures were like? Did you ever wish to have been able to attend them? Here is your chance.</p>
<p>We now have a record of one of those early courses, edited thanks to the hard work of Lawrence Kaplan professor at Magill University, who was the official translator for <em>Halakhic Man.</em>  The new volumes is called  <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Maimonides-Between-Philosophy-Halakhah-Soloveitchik%C2%92s/dp/965524203X"><em>Maimonides – Between Philosophy and Halakhah: Rabbi Joseph B. Soloveitchik’s Lectures on the Guide of the Perplexed (Urim Publications).</em> </a>The work is based on  a complete set of notes, taken by Rabbi Gerald (Yaakov) Homnick. The original notes consisted of two five spiral notebooks of 375 pages and 224 pages.  For the philosophic reader of Soloveitchik, these are interesting and exciting lectures bringing many scattered ideas into one place. Kaplan provides a wonderful introductory essay setting out and explaining the ideas in the lectures.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="7423" data-permalink="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2016/05/09/rav-soloveitchik-on-the-guide-of-the-perplexed-edited-by-lawrence-kaplan/kaplan-cover/" data-orig-file="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2016/05/kaplan-cover.jpg" data-orig-size="186,270" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="kaplan cover" data-image-description="" data-medium-file="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2016/05/kaplan-cover.jpg?w=186" data-large-file="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2016/05/kaplan-cover.jpg?w=186" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-7423" src="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2016/05/kaplan-cover.jpg?w=500" alt="kaplan cover" srcset="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2016/05/kaplan-cover.jpg 186w, https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2016/05/kaplan-cover.jpg?w=103 103w" sizes="(max-width: 186px) 100vw, 186px"   /></p>
<p>In this volume we see Soloveitchik in his use of Isaac Husik, David Neumark  and Leo Roth to help him understand the texts of Jewish thought, and his reliance on the modern thought of Hume, Spinoza, and Bertrand Russell. We see him giving out an academic reading list to start and engage with university Jewish studies.</p>
<p>Soloveitchik was originally planning on writing his dissertation on Maimonides but that did not work out so instead he switched advisers to work on Hermann Cohen. But what did he plan to discuss in the original medieval dissertation? This work gives the reader a sense of what he would have written since Soloveitchik incubated his ideas for decades and remained for decades with the direction of his earliest thoughts. It seems to have been a modern reading and defense of Maimonides.</p>
<p>Hermann Cohen&#8217;s modern reading of Maimonides as ethical and Platonic was instrumental in the 20<sup>th</sup> century return to Maimonides and especially Soloveitchik’s understanding of Maimonides. This lectures in this volume show how Soloveitchik both used and differed with Cohen. However, the citations from Cohen in the original lectures were telegraphed, in that, Cohen was not available in English at the time and Soloveitchik was just giving the gist to audience that had not read him. This makes it harder for those who have not read Cohen recently.</p>
<p>Kaplan notes that Soloveitchik’s readings of Plato, Aristotle, Plotinus and Aquinas are “highly controversial” meaning that they are less confrontations with the texts of those thinkers and more the reception and rejection as found in early 20<sup>th</sup> century thinkers. His German Professors considered idealism as superseding the classics and Russell considered science and positivism as superseding the ancient. For these works, Maimonides was relegated to the medieval bin. Soloveitchik was going to save the great eagle.</p>
<p>In addition, the 19<sup>th</sup> century Jewish interpreters saw Maimonides as an abstract Aristotelian philosopher, and, if anything relevant, closer to Reform than Orthodoxy. The scholar George Y. Kohler showed that at the Berlin seminary they were quite ambivalent about Maimonides. In addition, the instructor in Jewish thought Isaiah Wohlgemuth at the seminary leaned in his teaching towards considering faith as absurdity- Tertullian meets Kierkegaard and Scheler.</p>
<p>So the point of these lectures, and probably the unwritten dissertation, was to show the continuous relevance of philosophy for the understanding of Torah and the relevance of Maimonides. The goal was also to show the importance of Torah study for Maimonides despite the explicit vision in the <em>Guide.</em> Much of this agenda was later set out and popularized by Soloveitchik’s students David Hartman and Isidore Twersky.</p>
<p>Soloveitchik sought to move the reading of Maimonides from the practical Aristotelian approach to a German idealistic higher ethic of imitating God.  According to Kaplan’s notes this reading is not really Maimonides’ own thought.</p>
<p>One of the bigger unexpected formulations of this volume is Soloveitchik’s presentation of a pantheistic view of God as the hesed (mercy or caritas) behind creation. As in many idealists where the world is fundamentally mental or immaterial, the world is in God -in some ways the real is the rational- but he sets this within a theistic scheme .</p>
<p>This pantheism led Soloveitchik to think that aspiring Torah scholars should attain a cosmic-intellectual experience and thereby identify with the world through their minds.</p>
<p>There lectures discuss the ascent from ecstatic prophet to the higher cosmic prophetic experience. For Soloveitchik, the goal of cosmic-intellectual prophecy is to surrender to God beyond words to an inexpressible point.</p>
<p>Soloveitchik distinguishes between two levels in the observance of halakhah. A lower approach where halakhah concerns obedience, duties and practical law; at this level ethics are instrumental. There is a second higher level of identifying with God and thereby with the cosmos. In the lower level there is obedience to a normative halakhah which is distinctly and qualitatively lower than having a cosmic intellectual experience where the divine is internalized as a prophetic experience in which one reaches the pinnacle of human existence.</p>
<p>Soloveitchik declares that halakhah is not about “how to” rather in its ideal state it is about merging into cosmos via cosmic experience to reach a higher truth into reality. (This ideal is quite unlike the way many today conceive of Soloveitchik).</p>
<p>Kaplan notes that these lectures present an innovative theory of fear, in which fear at that moment of cosmic consciousness generates a recoil thereby returning us to the halakhah and norms. After love and identity with God, one recoils in distance, submission and returns to the external norm.</p>
<p>For Soloveitchik concern for others and responsibility for fellows as hesed is the inclusion of the other in the cosmic vision. Just as God is inclusive of the world and knows the world because it is part of Him, the Talmud scholar knows about people through his universal understanding.</p>
<p>Kaplan points out how this is completely the opposite of Jewish thinkers such as Levinas where you actually confront the other and through the face of a real other person gains moral obligation.  (I am certain that Soloveitchik pantheistic-Idealist view of ethics will elicit some comments. )</p>
<p>Rav Soloveichik’s speaking style often consisted in sentence fragments and repetition of phrases, especially a repetition to return to where he left off, after a side interjection. Many times one did not know the relationship of the return to the interjection. Was it in agreement or disagreement? Unfortunately, I am not sure if this edition solved the problem in that there were many dangling sentences and lines that the reader would be unclear if it agreed or disagreed with the prior line. In addition, many of the lines in this book needed an explanatory footnote especially those concerning idealism and Hermann Cohen.  But despite these caveats, for the philosophic reader of Soloveitchik, we once again owe Kaplan gratitude f<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Maimonides-Between-Philosophy-Halakhah-Soloveitchik%C2%92s/dp/965524203X">or his fine work.</a> We should also thank him for this extensive interview analyzing many of the most important issues in the work.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="7431" data-permalink="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2016/05/09/rav-soloveitchik-on-the-guide-of-the-perplexed-edited-by-lawrence-kaplan/kaplan-2/" data-orig-file="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2016/05/kaplan-2.jpg" data-orig-size="216,233" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="kaplan 2" data-image-description="" data-medium-file="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2016/05/kaplan-2.jpg?w=216" data-large-file="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2016/05/kaplan-2.jpg?w=216" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-7431" src="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2016/05/kaplan-2.jpg?w=500" alt="kaplan 2" srcset="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2016/05/kaplan-2.jpg 216w, https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2016/05/kaplan-2.jpg?w=139 139w" sizes="(max-width: 216px) 100vw, 216px"   /></p>
<ol>
<li><strong>What is new in this work?</strong></li>
</ol>
<p>From the point of view of form, these lectures are certainly new, since until now we have never had an essay of Rav Soloveitchik [henceforth, “the Rav”], much less a book, devoted to an analysis of the <em>Guide</em>. But from the point of view of content, the matter is not so clear After all, the Rav discusses certain themes from the <em>Guide</em> at length in <em>Halakhic Man</em>, <em>Halakhic Mind</em>, and <em>U-Vikashtem mi-Sham</em> (<em>And from There You Shall Seek</em>). Also, another very important discussion of the <em>Guide</em> can be found in his Yiddish <em>Teshuvah Derashah</em> (Discourse on Repentance), “Yahid ve-Tzibbur” (“Individual and Community”) in his Yiddish volume of <em>Essays and Discourses</em>. The truth is that if combines what the Rav says in <em>U-Vikashtem mi-Sham</em> with what he says in “Yahid ve-Tzibbur,” you get much—not all—of the basic outline of the argument of these lectures. Still, there are a number of   new elements.</p>
<p>One point obvious, while, in another sense, new is that while the Rav in all his essays displays a great openness to scientific and philosophic thought, he never explicitly justifies such openness. In these lectures, however, the Rav finally justified his practices.  The Rav notes that Maimonides believes that non-Jews could also reach the high religious level of “serving the Lord continually.” In this connection he observes that Bahya often cites “pietists,” who turn out to be non-Jews, and similarly cites Arabic philosophers and Church Fathers. He goes on to cite Maimonides’ famous statement  “Accept the truth from whoever said it.” He also cites a passage from the <em>Laws of the Sanctification of the New Moon</em> to the same effect, and concludes “Maimonides is clear…we do not care who the author is.”</p>
<p>There are, however, three entirely new elements. First, in the lectures the Rav presents his basic argument as a response to the claim of medieval commentators on the <em>Guide</em> and, in the modern period, of Heinrich Graetz that Maimonides considers <em>Halakhah</em> (Jewish law), both its study and practice, as secondary to philosophy.</p>
<p>Second, though in <em>U-Vikashtem mi-Sham</em> the Rav maintains that according to Maimonides, “The existence of the world [is] not only caused by God, but [is] also rooted in Him,” he carefully avoids any use there of the word “pantheism.” In the lectures, by contrast, he does speak of Maimonides’ pantheism—to be sure, with certain important qualifications.  Third, the penultimate section of the book on <em>Yirat ha-Shem</em>, the fear of the Lord, is, to my knowledge, new, and, in important ways, it goes against what he states both in <em>Halakhic Man</em> and in <em>U-Vikashtem mi-Sham</em>.</p>
<p><strong>2) Could you elaborate on the claim that Maimonides considers <em>Halakhah</em> as secondary to philosophy? How does R. Soloveitchik counter this approach?</strong></p>
<p>This is an old objection to Maimonides. The claim is that Maimonides follows Aristotle in maintaining that knowledge is superior to morality, both moral virtue and moral action, and, furthermore, in arguing that only intellectual knowledge possesses intrinsic value, while morality possesses only instrumental worth, serving only as a steppingstone to attaining intellectual perfection. From this it would follow that <em>Halakhah</em>, dealing with action, is of lesser worth than science, and that <em>Talmud Torah</em>, that is, the study of <em>Halakhah</em>, is inferior to the study of the sciences.  The Rav—inaccurately by the way—quotes Graetz as stating that Maimonides in the <em>Guide</em> “sneered at halakhic scholarship.”</p>
<p>The Rav counters this objection by claiming that Maimonides distinguishes between two stages of ethics: pre-theoretical ethics, ethical action that precedes knowledge of the universe and God, and post-theoretical ethics, ethical action that follows upon knowledge of the universe and God. Pre-theoretical ethics is indeed inferior to theory and purely instrumental; however, post-theoretical ethics is ethics as the imitation of God’s divine attributes of action of <em>Hesed</em> (Loving Kindness), <em>Mishpat</em>, (Justice), and <em>Tzedakah</em> (Righteousness), the ethics referred to at the very end of the <em>Guide</em>, and this stage of ethics constitutes the individual’s highest perfection.</p>
<p><strong>3) It sounds as if here Soloveitchik is just following Hermann Cohen.</strong></p>
<p>The Rav, as he himself admits, takes the basic distinction between pre-theoretical ethics and post- theoretical ethics from Hermann Cohen, but his understanding of the imitation of the divine attributes of action involved in post-theoretical ethics differs from Cohen.</p>
<p>Cohen, following Kant’s thought, distinguishes sharply between practical and theoretical reason, ethics and the natural order, “is” and “ought.” For Cohen, God’s attributes of action do not belong to the realm of causality, but to that of purpose; they are not grounded in nature, but simply serve as models for human action.</p>
<p>What Cohen keeps apart, the Rav—and here he is, in my view and the view of others, for example, Avi Ravitzky and Dov Schwartz, more faithful to the historical Maimonides—brings together.  For the Rav, the main divine attribute of action is <em>Hesed</em>, God’s abundant lovingkindness, His “practicing beneficence toward one who has no right” to such beneficence. The prime example of <em>Hesed</em>, for Maimonides, is the creation of the world.  <em>This</em> act of creation is both an ethical act, whereby God freely wills the world into existence, and an ontological act, an overflow of divine being, whereby God brings the world into being by thinking it.  However, the Rav goes beyond what Maimonides states explicitly by maintaining that the deepest meaning of God’s <em>Hesed</em> is that he not only confers existence upon the world, but continuously sustains it <em>by including the existence of reality as whole in His order of existence</em>.</p>
<p><strong>4) Is this the basis of Soloveitchik’s claim that Maimonides is a pantheist?</strong></p>
<p>Yes. The Rav denies that Maimonides affirms substantive     pantheism, that is, in terms of substance there are two orders: a finite order, all reality other than God; and an infinite order, God Himself.</p>
<p>But he maintains that Maimonides was an ontological pantheist, inasmuch as God included the existence of reality as whole in His order of existence.  Actually—I did not make this point in my Introduction—I wonder whether the Rav might have done better to refer to Maimonides as a panentheist. Thus the Rav concludes that Maimonides agrees with the seventeenth century French Catholic philosopher, Malebranche that ontically the world exists <em>in</em> God, which is exactly what panentheism (All-in-God) means.</p>
<p><strong>5) Why do you think that Soloveitchik felt it was so important to make this claim of pantheism?</strong></p>
<p>I am not sure, but I believe it is may be motivated by his conception of what true human <em>Hesed</em> is. That is, formally, the Rav begins by articulating Maimonides’ conception of divine <em>Hesed</em>, and then maintains that human <em>Hesed</em> has to imitate and therefore resemble divine <em>Hesed</em>. But I wonder whether the Rav’s thought, in truth, proceeded in the opposite direction, that is, he began with a conception of what true human <em>Hesed</em> is, and then <em>projected</em> that conception back onto divine <em>Hesed</em>.</p>
<p>Anyway, the Rav’s argument is as follows. We can only grasp the divine <em>Hesed</em> and only imitate it through knowing the world in which that <em>Hesed</em> is manifest.  It is in this sense that the highest stage of ethics is post-theoretical, for it is based upon and follows from the knowledge of God attained through the knowledge of the cosmos. To spell this out, since God created and sustains the world through knowing it, when man knows the world, whether through philosophical knowledge or prophetic knowledge, he and God unite together, since they both have the same object—the world&#8211; as their object of thought.</p>
<p>More than that—and here the Rav’s interpretation of Maimonides follows that of Solomon Maimon, though, strangely enough, the Rav never cites Maimon in these lectures—in man’s every act of knowledge his finite intellect unites with the infinite divine intellect which constantly and uninterruptedly knows everything. Here, the Rav maintains, we find another type of pantheism in Maimonides, intellectual pantheism, the union of man’s finite intellect with God’s infinite intellect in the act of human knowledge.</p>
<p>But the real point, and, as I said, I think the motivation of all this, is that after this intellectual union with God, man first internalizes the all-embracing divine <em>Hesed</em>, and then imitates that <em>Hesed</em> in the sense that he not only helps and confers benefits upon all who are in need, but, rather, in God-like fashion, he invites them to share in, to participate in his own existence, including them in his own order of being.</p>
<p>Here I would contrast the Rav with Levinas. <em>Hesed</em>, for the Rav, is not extended to the other qua other, as Levinas would have it; but, to the contrary, it is extended to the other because he is <em>not</em> other, because I have made him part of myself, of my own existence. What is truly ethical is not acknowledging the otherness of individuals I interact with, but identifying with them.  And this, to repeat, constitutes the true imitation of God.</p>
<p>So I believe–this is yet another point I did not make in my introduction—that the Rav’s pantheistic or panentheistic reading of Maimonides’ view regarding God’s relationship to the world is motivated by what he perceives as its ethical payoff.</p>
<p><strong>6) Is Soloveitchik, then, claiming that for Maimonides there is no direct knowledge of God?</strong></p>
<p>Indeed, the Rav denies that for Maimonides there can be direct knowledge of God. In this way Maimonides differs, say, from Rav Kook, for whom the highest knowledge of God derives from the soul’s direct love of God as the highest good, a love not mediated through nature. As the Rav clearly says, for Maimonides the only way to know God is through knowledge of the world.</p>
<p>Three times in the lectures the Rav cites Maimonides’ statement in <em>Guide</em> 1:34 that “there is no way to apprehend [God] except through the things He has made.” Similarly, the Rav appears to understand Maimonides’ citing in <em>Guide</em> 3:51 the rabbinic statement that “Ben Zoma is still outside” to mean that Ben Zoma tried to attain direct knowledge of God without intellectually cognizing the universe.  To repeat, it can’t be done.</p>
<p><strong>7) What is the relationship for Maimonides, as Soloveitchik understands it, between philosophical and prophetic knowledge?</strong></p>
<p>For Soloveitchik, as stated earlier, when man knows the world, whether through philosophical knowledge or prophetic knowledge, he and God unite together.</p>
<p>As the Rav’s understands it, Maimonides’ view is that prophetic knowledge builds on philosophical knowledge, that is on the scientific knowledge of the cosmos. Or, as the Rav phrases it, first we have the pre-theoretical normative-halakhic experience, that is, the halakhic experience that precedes knowledge of the cosmos, then the cosmic-intellectual experience, and finally, building on and going beyond that cosmic-intellectual experience, the ecstatic–prophetic experience.</p>
<p>Sometimes the Rav emphasizes the difference between prophetic knowledge and philosophical knowledge, sometimes he blurs the distinction between the two. But there seem to be three features that characterize the ecstatic–prophetic experience as opposed to the cosmic-intellectual experience: intuition, vision, and self-surrender. The key point seems to be that while the cosmic-intellectual experience brings the individual into intellectual contact with God, the ecstatic–prophetic experience brings one into personal contact with God.</p>
<p>The way I understand this—the Rav never states this explicitly—is as follows. God created the world by an act of free will, and, as such, His relationship with the world is a voluntary one, and the connection between Himself and man is an ethical one. But God also created the world by an act of thought, in which case God’s relationship with man is primarily intellectual and ontological.</p>
<p>Ultimately these are two sides of the same coin, for, in Maimonides’ view, God’s will and wisdom are one. Still—again, this is my formulation of the Rav’s view—the philosopher who unites with God solely through the intellect focuses on God’s wisdom, on God as pure intellect, while the prophet who, in addition to uniting with God intellectually, also connects with Him via intuition, vision, and self- surrender, focuses on the personal God, whose creation of the world is a free ethical act.</p>
<p><strong>8) Does Soloveitchik deprecate philosophic thought, at least in comparison to prophetic knowledge? </strong></p>
<p>To an extent. But while the Rav refers to Maimonides’ alleged belief in “the insufficiency of the cosmic-intellectual experience,” nevertheless, in the Rav’s view, Maimonides is firm in affirming that this experience is a necessary stage in arriving at the ecstatic–prophetic experience.  The Rav could not be clearer that for Maimonides there is no bypassing the scientific knowledge of the cosmos.</p>
<p><strong> 9) </strong><strong>How would you answer someone who says that this book sets up each problem as goyish philosophy as opposed to Maimonides and that Maimonides is really a halakhic position? Ostensibly, this work rejects both Aristotle and Kant on most issues, leaving Maimonides as unique and as halakhic?</strong><br />
With reference to the Rav’s playing up Maimonides’ differences with Aristotle and (a-chronologically) with Kant, as I and other scholars have noted, one can broadly divide interpreters of Maimonides into two camps: the radicals who minimize the differences between Maimonides and the philosophers (particularly Aristotle), sometimes going so far as to deny that there are any differences; and the traditionalists, who emphasize these differences. The Rav clearly belongs in the traditionalist camp.</p>
<p>Still, though the Rav devotes an entire chapter to contrasting Aristotle and Maimonides, we must not forget that regarding the issue of the necessity for scientific knowledge of the cosmos, and regarding the conception of God as the unity of intellect, the subject of intellection, and the object of intellection the Rav forthrightly acknowledges that Maimonides follows in Aristotle’s wake.</p>
<p>I think that what the Rav objected to most in Aristotle, Plotinus, and<br />
Spinoza was that for them God’s relationship with the world and man is one of necessity. (I am not sure if the Rav is correct about Plotinus, but this is a long story.) They, thereby, negate the possibility of an ethical relationship between God and man, which, as stated above, is possible only if God’s creation of the world was a free and therefore an ethical act. Again we see the ethical motif coming to the fore.  Perhaps in this respect, the Rav reflects the influence of Kant.</p>
<p><strong>10) Is the ecstatic–prophetic experience the same thing for Soloveitchik as revelation? Does he have multiple conceptions of Maimonides’ view of revelation?</strong></p>
<p>Actually, the Rav contrasts the ecstatic-prophetic experience with prophecy and revelation proper, what the Rav refers to as “apocalyptic prophecy.” To cite the lectures: “The Prophetic-Ecstatic experience… is not the apocalyptic moment of prophecy he describes in the latter chapters of Book 2 of the <em>Guide</em>. That moment of prophecy, where God bestows upon man a prophetic revelation, is an act of grace on God’s part. The Prophetic-Ecstatic type of prophecy that Maimonides speaks about in <em>Guide</em> 3:51 can be obtained by all.</p>
<p>In sum, there are two types of prophecy:  The apocalyptic moment of prophecy is granted to the individual by God; the Prophetic-Ecstatic experience is a state of mind.”</p>
<p>Another indication that the ecstatic-prophetic experience is not to be identified with prophecy proper is that sometimes the Rav refers to the ecstatic-prophetic experience as the ecstatic-mystic experience.  This is part of the emphasis in all the Rav’s works not so much on theology, but on human experience, human states of consciousness. Nevertheless, I actually think there is some basis here for the Rav’s distinction in Maimonides’ texts, though it is not so clear and neat as he would have it.</p>
<p>In <em>U-Vikashtem mi-Sham</em>, when the Rav refers to the revelational experience he is referring to “apocalyptic prophecy,” which, for him, is a supernatural phenomenon.So <em>U-Vikashtem</em> and the lectures are operating on two different planes. Actually, I think that, contra the Rav, <em>all</em> prophecy, for Maimonides is natural, but, again, that is a long story. (For Kaplan&#8217;s understanding of revelation in Maimonides &#8211; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/07/25/maimonides-on-mosaic-revelation-prof-lawrence-j-kaplan/">see his prior post on Maimonides on Mosaic revelation</a>. )</p>
<p>Still, there may be an important difference between the lectures and <em>U-Vikashtem</em>. In the lectures, where the Rav speaks as an expositor of Maimonides, it is clear that no prophet, not even Moses, can bypass the cosmic-intellectual experience. In <em>U-Vikashtem</em>, where the Rav, though citing Maimonides, speaks in his own name, the revelational religious experience is discontinuous with what he refers to as the rational religious experience.</p>
<p><strong>11) How does this respond to the objection that even if Maimonides did not “sneer at halakhic scholarship,” nevertheless in his view the study of <em>Halakhah</em>, is inferior to the study of the sciences.</strong></p>
<p>The Rav, like a good “Brisker,” a practitioner and devotee of the analytic school of Talmud study, sharply distinguishes between the practical study of <em>Halakhah</em>, study in order to know how to perform the norm properly, and the conceptual and theoretical study of the <em>Halakhah</em>,<em> lomdus</em>. He grants that Maimonides deprecates the significance of the practical study of <em>Halakhah</em>, inasmuch as it belongs to the pre-theoretical, normative-halakhic, stage of religious experience, and, indeed, possesses only the instrumental value of enabling one to perform the commandments properly.</p>
<p>However, he argues that Maimonides would view <em>lomdus</em>, the theoretical study of the <em>Halakhah</em>, if carried out “in conjunction with the cosmic experience (science),” as providing a cosmic-ethical experience parallel to the cosmic-ethical experience attained in the study of the cosmos. Indeed, he claims that when Maimonides in <em>Guide</em> 3:52 states that the knowledge of the <em>de‘ot,</em> “the opinions the Torah teaches us” leads to the love of God,  he is referring not only to theoretical, metaphysical knowledge, but also to the theoretical understanding of the <em>Halakhah</em>.</p>
<p>This claim in my view lacks any textual basis in Maimonides. Still, perhaps the Rav might view his reading of Maimonides as a legitimate “updating” of Maimonides’ position.  Thus, as a number of scholars, including myself, have argued, Maimonides in the <em>Guide</em> appears to suggest, albeit not explicitly, that understanding the reasons for the commandments, that is, the divine wisdom inherent in the commandments, leads to the love of God. The Rav might argue that given that Maimonides’ view of nature was teleological, he viewed the wisdom inherent in the commandments in teleological terms, and thus focused in the <em>Guide</em> on <em>ta‘amei  ha-mitovot</em>, the purpose and aim of the commandments.</p>
<p>However, as the Rav often pointed out, modern science, as a result of the Galilean-Newtonian revolution, no longer views nature as teleological.   Rather the rationality found in nature is that of the abstract quantitative laws that parallel and thus serve to explain the particular, qualitative, natural phenomena. Following from this, the wisdom found in the commandments would not be their purpose, but the abstract legal principles that underlie the particular laws, i.e. <em>lomdus</em>!</p>
<p>But coming back to Maimonides himself, presumably, Maimonides, according to the Rav’s understanding, would not view the <em>lomdus</em> of Rav Hayyim Brisker, the Rav’s grandfather and the founder of the analytic school, as significant, since Rav Hayyim never studied science, and thus should be classified as one of the <em>talmudiyyim</em>, the unphilosophical jurists, to whom Maimonides refers in deprecating fashion in <em>Guide</em> 3:51, but he would approve of the Rav’s <em>lomdus</em>. This obviously is my own extrapolation.</p>
<p><strong>12) How is Soloveitchik’s discussion of the fear of the Lord, (</strong><strong>Yirat ha-Shem) original, and how does it goes against what he states elsewhere?</strong></p>
<p>The Rav’s take on the fear of God is, in my view, the most innovative part of the lectures. In <em>U-Vikashtem</em>, the Rav’s discussion of the love and fear of God follows, I would say, a <em>Mishneh Torah</em> model. That is, in the <em>Mishneh Torah</em>, his great code of Jewish Law, Maimonides discusses the love and fear of God, where fear follows love, in <em>Laws of the Foundations of the Torah</em> 2:2, and both are necessary. However, in <em>Laws of Repentance</em> 10:3 he only discusses the befitting love of God and does not mention fear. The Rav—questionably, I believe—understands this to mean that the love and fear of the <em>Laws of the Foundations of the Torah</em> 2:2 refer to a lower form of religious experience, <em>Hidammut</em>, imitation of God, but at the highest level of religious experience, <em>Devekut</em>, cleaving to God, there is only love and no fear, as Maimonides supposedly suggests in <em>Laws of Repentance</em> 10:3.</p>
<p>The Rav’s discussion of the love and fear of God in the lectures follows, I would say, a <em>Guide</em> model—not surprising, since these are lectures on the <em>Guide</em>—and differs from his discussion in <em>U-Vikashtem</em> in three ways. First, as I already noted, in the lectures, according to the Rav’s reading of the <em>Guide,</em> imitation of God does not precede but follows upon <em>Devekut</em> or union with God. Second, in the <em>Guide</em> Maimonides discusses love in <em>Guide</em> 3:51 and fear in 3:52, and in the conclusion of 3:52 he sums up his discussion by speaking first of love, then of fear. As the Rav, correctly I believe, understands it, fear here is the last word, and, unlike the alleged implication from <em>Laws of Repentance</em> 10:3, is indispensable.</p>
<p>The Rav notes that in <em>Guide</em> 3:52 Maimonides links fear with the “actions prescribed by the Law,” or, to use the Rav’s terminology, the <em>mitzvot ma‘asiyyot</em>, by which the Rav seems to have in mind rituals, such as—the example is his—<em>tzitizit</em> (ritual fringes). How is fear connected the “actions prescribed by the Law”? The Rav links Maimonides’ discussion of fear of God in <em>Guide</em> 3:52 with his discussion in the <em>Laws of the Foundations of the Torah</em> 2:2. There Maimonides states that while love of God is the drive to know God and unite with Him, in the fear of God the individual becomes aware of his lowliness and immediately “<em>nirta le-ahorav</em>,” recoils backward. Thus fear reopens the gap between God and man that love or union had closed up. In this way—and this is the Rav’s main point— fear fulfills a <em>halakhic function</em>. Via the love of God, via uniting with Him, the individual internalizes the Law. But the danger is that by internalizing the Law the binding force of the norm will fade away. Fear, by reinstating the distance between man and God, “rehabilitates the norm,” the performance of the law on the practical level. That is, only a heteronomous norm, only a norm imposed upon man from the outside retains its force and binding authority. And this, concludes the Rav, is the meaning of the link that Maimonides in the <em>Guide</em> 3:52 establishes between the fear of God and the “actions prescribed by the Law.”</p>
<p>Here we come to the third difference between the lectures and <em>U-Vikashtem mi-Sham</em>, and, I would add, <em>Halakhic Man</em>.  In the latter essays the highest religious level that halakhic man or the man of God reaches is precisely the love of God and consequently the autonomous internalization of the laws; but in the lectures internalization must be followed by externalization, autonomy by heteronomy. Of course, in the essays the Rav speaks in his own name; in the lectures as an expositor of Maimonides. Are we to conclude that the Rav’s exposition of Maimonides in these lectures is more “halakhic” and less “philosophic” than the Rav’s own philosophy?</p>
<p>I should add that while this reading of the link in <em>Guide</em> 3:52 between the fear of God and the “actions prescribed by the Law” is very ingenious and provocative, it is exceptionally hard to maintain that it is what Maimonides had in mind. The Rav’s attempt to understand Maimonides’ discussion of fear in <em>Guide</em> 3:52 in light of his discussion of fear in<em> Laws of the Foundations of the Torah</em> 2:2 fails, in my view, to convince.  For in <em>Guide</em> 3:52 Maimonides sees the fear of God as being connected <em>not</em> with distance from God, as he does in <em>Laws of the Foundations of the Torah</em> 2:2, but, to the contrary, with God’s constant presence, with, to use Moshe Halbertal’s phrase, the individual’s sense of constantly being scrutinized by God. How, in fact, then, Maimonides understands the link in <em>Guide</em> 3:52 between the fear of God and the “actions prescribed by the Law” remains to be established, but whatever it turns out to be, it is not what the Rav had in mind.</p>
<p><strong><em>13) You pointed to a number of places where you argued that is it difficult to uphold Soloveitchik’s interpretation as what Maimonides actually meant. Do you think this is true for Soloveitchik’s reading of the Guide more generally?</em></strong></p>
<p>While I think that the Rav’s understanding of the cosmic-intellectual experience in Maimonides, with its focus on the cognition of the cosmos and man uniting with God through the intellect is true to the spirit of Maimonides, I think the way he attempts to broaden and deepen this concept and argue that in the ecstatic-prophetic stage the total individual establishes personal contact with God is a modernizing reading that is much too existentialist for my tastes.</p>
<p>Negatively speaking, the presentation of Maimonides in the lectures differs from more recent interpretations of Maimonides by the almost complete absence in it of any concern for Maimonides’ political thought and, as well, with the almost complete lack of any concern for the hermeneutic aspect of the <em>Guide</em>, for the <em>Guide</em> as a reading of both Scripture and the rabbinic tradition.</p>
<p>This last point is ironic, for the lectures begin with a lengthy analysis of why Maimonides began the <em>Guide</em> with the verse “In the name of God, the Lord of the world” (Gen. 21:33).  In that connection, the Rav very presciently observes that Maimonides “in quoting a verse… casts off philosophic routine and jargon, and we can gain a more intimate glimpse of him. Maimonides’ citations of biblical verses and rabbinic <em>midrashim</em> throw new light on his thought.”  Prof. James Diamond couldn’t have said it better! But, alas, the Rav does not follow up on this insight.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2016/05/kaplan-cover.jpg" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kaplan cover</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2016/05/kaplan-2.jpg" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kaplan 2</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Professor Lawrence Kaplan and Yakir Englander on each other’s work</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/02/professor-lawrence-kaplan-and-yakir-englander-on-each-other%e2%80%99s-work/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/02/professor-lawrence-kaplan-and-yakir-englander-on-each-other%e2%80%99s-work/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 03 Oct 2010 00:02:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[chazon ish]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hazon ish]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lawrence Kaplan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[yakir englander]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2085</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A month ago, I posted a recent article by Yakir Englander of Hebrew University on the Hazon Ish. It received a highly emotive response by Prof. Lawrence Kaplan of McGill University. Before allowing Englander to respond, I asked Kaplan for &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/02/professor-lawrence-kaplan-and-yakir-englander-on-each-other%e2%80%99s-work/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A month ago,<a href="http:///kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/08/31/new-article-on-the-hazon-ish-by-yakir-englander/"> I posted a recent article by Yakir Englander</a> of Hebrew University on the Hazon Ish. It received a highly emotive response by Prof. Lawrence Kaplan of McGill University. Before allowing Englander to respond, I asked Kaplan for a more cognitive gesture. Below is Kaplan’s response to Englander and following that, if you scroll down, is Englander’s reply to Kaplan. If you wish to enter the fray, then please read both <a href='https://kavvanah.files.wordpress.com/2010/10/hazonish.pdf'>Lawrence Kaplan&#8217;s article (pdf) </a> and <a href="http://reshit.hartman.org.il/uploads/Articles/8_Reshit2-30082010_0959_36.pdf">Yakir Englander’s article(pdf),</a>  and <a href="http://reshit.hartman.org.il/Article_View_Heb.asp?Article_Id=27">an html version.</a> (Both responses were longer and more personal than I expected. In all of this, I do wonder what someone who teaches Hazon Ish as their personal view would make of this discussion).</p>
<p><strong></strong><strong>Prof. Lawrence Kaplan&#8217;s response.</strong></p>
<p><em>This post deals not so much with scholarly issues relating to differing interpretations of the world view of the Hazon Ish (=HI), but primarily with an issue of academic responsibility. </p>
<p>I believe that a comparison of my article with Englander’s—something I hope readers will undertake&#8211; will clearly show that Englander 1) misrepresents my thesis; and, more important, 2) that his own thesis, far from being a scholarly innovation, essentially follows along the lines of and develops the thesis presented in my article.  </p>
<p>With reference to my first point, the very title of my article, “The HI: Haredi Critic of Traditional Orthodoxy,” setting to the side the article’s contents for the moment, should alert the reader that Englander’s presentation of its thesis cannot stand. Since the title indicates that, in my view, the HI’s critique of Traditional Orthodoxy constitutes a major identifying feature of both his person and thought, how can it be maintained, as Englander does, that, to the contrary, I consider the HI’s criticisms to be “matters of differing emphases in the service of God, and not much more”?  </p>
<p>And turning now from the article’s title to the article itself, in its main section (pp.149-163) I set forth the thesis, specifically with reference to the HI’s critique of the mussar movement and the “Yeshivishe” method of study, that the “HI developed a rather subtle, oftentimes more implicit than explicit, but nevertheless powerful and far reaching critique of [Lithuanian] Orthodoxy” (p.150).  Again, in note 57 (p. 163), I refer to the HI’s “profound disagreement with the analytic method” and to his being in Emunah u-Bitahon “openly and forcefully critical about the mussar ideology.” “Differing emphases,” indeed! </p>
<p>With reference to my second and major point, I write with regard to the HI’s opposition to the mussar movement, “The HI was of the opinion that the fundamental mussar approach of working on oneself, of turning inward, in order to develop one’s spiritual personality … was fundamentally misguided. [He] was suspicious of the focus on, the concern for the self, even if that focusing, that concern, was for religious purposes” (p.159).  In order to explain the grounds of this suspicion, I pointed to the HI’s own psychology as opposed that of the mussar approach. </p>
<p>With regard to the HI’s opposition to the “Yeshivishe” method of study, I write “for the HI, the analytic approach allows too much room for self-expression, for play of the individual’s own intellectual powers, unconstrained by the discipline of the text….What the HI feels is called for in the area of traditional Jewish learning is not intellectual self-assertion, but intellectual submission, submission to the authority of the text” (pp. 155-156). I conclude my article’s main section thus: “In sum we are arguing that the HI’s critiques of both the analytic method of Talmudic scholarship and the mussar ideology stem from the same source….The proponents of both … in their praiseworthy efforts to bolster tradition and combat the attractions of modernity tacitly conceded too much to modernity by allowing too great a role for human self-assertion and human autonomy, even within a strictly traditional framework, and by not sufficiently insisting on the absolute submission of the individual to the authority of the tradition in the realm of both study and practice” (p.162).  </p>
<p>Developing this theme of submission even further, I devote the next section of my article to showing “how this ethos of submission is a fundamental and central element in the religious world–view of the HI” (p.164). </p>
<p>Alan Brill in his original post sums up Englander’s thesis thus: “Mussar and lomdut  are about the cultivation of the self. The anthropology of the HI is to bypass the self entirely.” If we add to this Englander’s point about the HI’s emphasis on the need for submission, we have a perfect summary of my article as well. </p>
<p>Even regarding minor points, I anticipate Englander. Thus Englander concludes his article by noting “Precisely on account of the central position of the HI in the Lithuanian community, it very interesting that his thought…has not been absorbed (nikletah) in a sweeping manner in that community” (p. 214). Compare that to my observation in my article’s conclusion that “despite the HI’s immense role in forming and shaping the ethos of the Haredi community, in a certain respect he was a failure. Certainly the full dimensions and implications of the HI’s critique of the traditional world of Lithuanian Mitnaggedism were never really absorbed, much less acted upon, by the Haredi community” (p.172).  (Also compare Englander, p. 195, n.46, with Kaplan, p. 162,  n. 57.)</p>
<p>All this is not to deny that there is much that is new, interesting, and important in Englander’s essay. While I discuss the HI’s psychology only briefly, focusing on the HI’s view that man’s fundamental evil trait is “allowing one’s natural life to flow along its natural course” (Emunah u-Bitahon 4:5) and that that evil trait can be overcome only through “the constant adhesion to the precise requirements of the law (dikduk ha-din),” Englander presents a fuller discussion of the HI’s view of man. He argues that for the HI man is comprised of body, imagination/ will, and intellect, and he analyzes at length the HI’s (very suspicious) attitude to each of these component parts. He has very interesting things to say about the analogy the HI draws between bodily and spiritual impurity (p.191). Particularly insightful is his observation that for the HI the common error shared by both the “yeshivishe” method of study and mussar ideology is the unwarranted confidence they both place in man’s intellect. Also worthy of note is Englander’s discussion of the HI’s view regarding the relationship between halakhah and interpersonal ethics, and his discussion in that connection of the famous example offered by the HI of the competing schoolteachers (pp. 197-198).  </p>
<p>Our articles also have somewhat different emphases. While I, perhaps somewhat speculatively, link, as indicated above, the contrast between the more positive attitude to the self taken by the “Yeshivishe” method of  study and the mussar  movement and the more negative attitude taken by the HI to their contrasting attitudes toward modernity, Englander limits himself to a more strictly internal analysis. Also, the HI’s attitude toward the self in my account, while quite pessimistic, is not quite as pessimistic as it is in Englander’s.</p>
<p>The path, then, that Englander should have taken is clear. He should have written something to the following effect. “My basic approach follows along the lines of the thesis presented in Lawrence Kaplan’s article, ‘The HI: Haredi Critic of Traditional Orthodoxy.’ I have, however, built and elaborated upon his approach, filled in lacuna, and in several places modified a number of his specific contentions.”  This is the way scholarship progresses: acknowledging its debt to past scholarship, and then both building upon and modifying that past scholarship in the service of greater insight and understanding.  This is not the path Englander chose.</em></p>
<p><strong></strong><strong>Here is the reply by Yakir Englander.</strong></p>
<p><em>I am grateful for the opportunity offered me by Alan Brill to clarify the differences between my approach to Hazon-Ish (=HI) and that of Professor Kaplan.</p>
<p>In order to make my position clear, let me first summarize Kaplan’s criticisms of my work as follows:</p>
<p>a.	My article, according to Kaplan, is based on the thesis he himself set forth in his own article. Instead of acknowledging my debt to Kaplan, he says, I digress into a discussion of the work of Dr. Brown;<br />
b.	Kaplan complains that I fail to present his thesis adequately, and thus I betray one of the principles of good scholarship;<br />
c.	Since my article is founded on Kaplan’s own position, it follows that my article has no new thesis to offer.</p>
<p>Regarding the first claim, I will point out that my article does not repeat Kaplan’s arguments, since in his article he occupies himself with a basic exposition of the actual sayings of HI. This exposition does not shed light on the general positions of HI, but stays too close to the descriptive level. It is true that my work enters into dialogue with the fascinating work of Dr. Benny Brown, who has made the first effort to set forth the thought of HI in a comprehensive fashion. I am in agreement with all aspects of Brown’s work, with only the one exception, to which my article is devoted.</p>
<p>Kaplan’s second claim is that I failed to adequately represent his position.  My response to this criticism is that in fact there is really nothing to represent. Kaplan is not presenting a new critical thesis, but rather simply repeating the words of HI himself. What Kaplan has done is provide an important service to English readers who may not have access to the actual Hebrew texts of HI; Kaplan thus offers a good preliminary introduction to the HI writings.</p>
<p>Now I address Kaplan’s third criticism. Anyone reading my article will in fact see that in this article an effort is made to present a comprehensive thesis concerning the thought of HI about the human person. As I argue, the central confrontation on the issue of Torah Study between HI and the Yeshivish Method of Study is not to be found in questions concerning the nature of study required, or what disposition the student should display, whether diligence and submission or some more traditional approach (cf. Kaplan 155- 156). There is nothing new here; all this has been stated already by HI himself.</p>
<p>The new element in my thesis is my assertion that the conflict between HI and the Yeshivish Method of Study is anchored in the concept of the human person, and of the human person’s essential task in this world. As I argue, HI asserts that the study methods required in the Yeshivish system do not come to terms with the desires and urges of the human individual. On the contrary, they perpetuate the submission of human being to the evil inclination. It is in contrast to this view that HI presents his own position. It follows, then, that even if HI, in his own system, demands of the student diligence and submission this does not show him to be more traditionalist than the Modern Yeshivish Method of Study. On the contrary, for HI diligence and submission will become means by which a human person may come to terms with the evil inclination. </p>
<p>Therefore, the view of HI is intimately interwoven with the drama of human existence; study of Torah is a central part of the human being’s process of becoming fully human. Clearly, on this point precisely, HI comes into conflict with the teachers of the Torat HaMusar Movement. For the goal of Torah Study is precisely not to reach a state of passivity and submission. On the contrary, any submission achieved is of the second order, not a goal in itself but the means to an end, which is the vanquishing of the evil inclination. </p>
<p>Kaplan fails to see the anthropological drama that HI highlights; instead, he chooses to analyze the sayings of HI using a static conceptual dichotomy of submission vs. creativity and tradition vs. modernity. Kaplan begins with a priori categories, into which he tries to fit whatever he finds in HI. I, on the other hand, like Brown, am endeavoring to listen to the words of HI himself, and to position those words in the appropriate conceptual network.<br />
My article is a reworking of a chapter in my doctoral dissertation (to be completed during the coming year) – a dissertation that examines the image of the human body in the Lithuanian Orthodox Jewish culture from the Holocaust to the present. In my opinion, the issue of the human body represents an axis of conflict in the entire Lithuanian tradition; only when one understands this tradition’s approach to the body can one fully grasp how this tradition in its various aspects takes shape. The first part of my dissertation deals with Lithuanian thought in general (contrasting the diametrically opposing stands of HI on one hand and Rabbi Avigdor Miller on the other). The second part considers the ideal image of the human body through the genre of hagiographic works on the tsadikim. The third part is devoted to the image of the female body, and the cultural and halakhic repercussions of this image.</p>
<p>To conclude: Professor Kaplan, acquainted as he is with Jewish Tradition and general philosophy, should be aware that controversy, disagreement and mutual clarification are all parts of the internal essence that motivates all knowledge. There can be no doubt that Professor Kaplan can claim a pioneering status in the effort to understand HI in a wider framework than that offered by halakhic sermonizing. This pioneering status, however, cannot be construed as ownership, nor does it indicate a boundary beyond which research may not go. Rather, Kaplan might have rejoiced to see research on the thought of HI not only continuing but deepening. Not all researchers need to agree on everything; texts remain open to interpretation. But on one thing we do need agreement: it is, on one hand, the right of every scholar to conduct research; on the other hand, it is never appropriate to gloss over differences and present another scholar’s research disingenuously. </p>
<p>Perhaps Professor Kaplan should keep in mind, that when he misrepresents his fellow scholar, he stands at risk of being himself besmirched. It was Hegel who pointed out that “only by night are all cows black.” Only in the darkest of nights could anyone fail to see the clear distinctions between the “thesis” of Kaplan and the new thesis that I myself offer.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/10/02/professor-lawrence-kaplan-and-yakir-englander-on-each-other%e2%80%99s-work/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Radicalism of Legal Positivism [in Halakhah]</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/15/the-radicalism-of-legal-positivism-in-halakhah/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/15/the-radicalism-of-legal-positivism-in-halakhah/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2010 18:00:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[halakhic theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[brian leiter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Emmanuel Rackman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lawrence Kaplan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[legal positivism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sittlichkeit]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=926</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Now that everyone is running from Legal positivism into all forms of situational thinking, Brian Leiter reminds us why legal positivism seemed so radical at the time. It undid all the Hegelian need for situational organic thinking, it undid social &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/15/the-radicalism-of-legal-positivism-in-halakhah/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Now that everyone is running from Legal positivism into all forms of situational thinking, Brian Leiter reminds us why legal positivism seemed so radical at the time. It undid all the Hegelian need for situational organic thinking, it undid social realism, and it undid moralism. The law is the law. The law has no external sources and there are no external implications.  Now, legal positivism seem stolid and unresponsive.  Along the way the anti-liberal Leiter gets in his critique of critical legal studies as not realizing that they were returning to Hegel. </p>
<p>Once upon a time Brisker inspired positivist approaches to halkahah seemed radical, now people are returning to values, [imagined] community, social realism. This article give some of the framework for the comments on the ideal versus real debate in halakhah and why the positivism once seemed attractive.</p>
<blockquote><p>The Radicalism of Legal Positivism<br />
Brian Leiter, University of Chicago Law School<br />
Guild Practitioner (forthcoming 2010) </p>
<p>Abstract:<br />
“Legal positivism” is often caricatured by its jurisprudential opponents, as well as by lawyers and legal scholars not immediately interested in jurisprudential inquiry. “Positivist” too often functions now as an “epithet” in legal discourse, equated (wrongly) with “formalism,” the view that judges must apply the law “as written,” regardless of the consequences. Lon Fuller, Ronald Dworkin, and the Critical Legal Studies writers have all contributed in different ways to the sense that &#8220;positivism&#8221; is either a political conservative or politically sterile position. This essay revisits the actual theory of law developed by positivist philosophers like Bentham, Hart, and Raz, emphasizing why it is, and was, understood by its proponents, to be a radical theory of law, one unfriendly to the status quo and anyone, judge or citizen, who thinks obedience to the law is paramount. To be clear, the leading theorists of legal positivism thought the theory gave the correct account of the nature of law as a social institution; they did not endorse it because of the political conclusions it entailed, and which they supported. Yet these theorists realized that the correct account of the nature of law had radical implications for conventional wisdom about law. We would do well to recapture their wisdom today.<br />
(The ful article has much more than the abstract)<br />
<a href="http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1568333">Full article is available here</a> </p></blockquote>
<p>On the same trajectory of legal positivism and sittlichkeit</p>
<p>I finally got around to reading  &#8211;<strong>Lawrence Kaplan, From Cooperation to Conflict: Rabbi Professor Emanuel Rackman, Rav Joseph B. Soloveitchik, and the Evolution of American Modern Orthodoxy</strong> <em>Modern Judaism </em>Volume 30, Number 1, February 2010. The article was good for clearing up the retrograding of the 1970’s tensions back onto the 1950’s when Rackman was indeed an official spokesman for Rav Soloveithchik. I thank the author for the generous shout out in the footnotes. </p>
<p>In that spirit, I must add to the article and move it more to legal theory. Rackman as a  lawyer and political science professor was influenced by Chief Justices Holmes, Brandeis, and Cordozo, by the emergent world of Mishpat Ivri and the rulings of the Warren court. Rav Soloveitchik thought about the rules of science and philosophy, Rabbi Rackman thought about a telos approach using legal categories. The emergent Conservative movement spoke historical approach to law of von Savigny, John Salmond, and economic judicial activism. It is worth considering that some of the YU “young poskim” with JD’s may have more philosophically in common with Rabbi Rackman that with Rabbi Soloveitchik.  </p>
<p>Why would Rackman switch to Judaism? Milton Konvitz was one of the three editors and was encouraging Jewish Legal thinking and Jewish Human rights thinking.  (And Konvitz was a fan of both Leo Jung and Jacob Agus)- see his <em>Nine American Jewish Thinkers.</em></p>
<p>The article by Brian Leiter will offer some terms for understanding the Rackman-Soloveitchik positions and return of sittlichkeit in our time.</p>
<p>Copyright © 2010 Alan Brill • All Rights Reserved</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/03/15/the-radicalism-of-legal-positivism-in-halakhah/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
