<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Chabad &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/tag/chabad/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Dec 2009 15:40:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='kavvanah.wordpress.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/c9f111237f93750b6b994fc5185d49c3?s=96&#038;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>Chabad &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>Chabad Menorahs in Public Spaces-Supreme Court Decision Twenty Years Ago</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/11/chabad-menorahs-in-public-spaces-supreme-court-decision-twenty-years-ago/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/11/chabad-menorahs-in-public-spaces-supreme-court-decision-twenty-years-ago/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 11 Dec 2009 15:15:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[popular religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chabad]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chanukah Menorah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[County of Allegheny v. American Civil Liberties Union]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme COurt]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=352</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It has been 20 years since the Supreme Court decision that allowed menorahs in public places. Chabad packaged itself as American civil religion with &#8220;no effort to proselytize&#8221;.  It is interesting to note how much of Chabad that we know &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/11/chabad-menorahs-in-public-spaces-supreme-court-decision-twenty-years-ago/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It has been 20 years since the Supreme Court decision that allowed menorahs in public places. Chabad packaged itself as American civil religion with &#8220;no effort to proselytize&#8221;.  It is interesting to note how much of Chabad that we know was created in the twilight last years of the Rebbe&#8217;s life. It is also interesting how much they expanded American concepts of religion.  <a href="http://lubavitch.com/news/article/2027834/Allegheny-vs-ACLU-Et-Al-Good-for-Chanukah.html">Chabad reports:</a></p>
<p>(lubavitch.com) When the U.S. Supreme Court ruled that placing Chabad-owned menorahs in public spaces did not violate the establishment clause, it set a slab of precedent for Chabad centers to rest their menorah requests upon.<br />
As the 21st  anniversary of the Allegheny vs. ACLU ruling nears, the experiences of Chabad representatives across the United States reveal just how useful or not the landmark decision has been in bringing Chanukah’s light, message of peace and religious liberty to the public square.  From Montana to Mumbai, from the Western Wall to the Great Wall of China, Chabad’s public menorah lightings number in the thousands.</p>
<p>Over the years, as calls from representatives lit up the switchboard at Lubavitch World Headquarters, Rabbi Krinsky’s office put them in touch with the well-known constitutional attorney Nathan Lewin of Washington, D.C. who has litigated many of the menorah cases. Lewin led Chabad’s case before the Supreme Court and created a packet of legal materials to help Chabad representatives present established precedents that consistently supported public menorah displays in a clear, concise manner. Attorney Charles Saul of Pittsburgh, PA saw Chabad’s landmark Allegheny vs. ACLU suit together with Mr. Lewin all the way through to the Supreme Court.</p>
<p>And <a href="http://www.law.cornell.edu/supct/html/historics/USSC_CR_0492_0573_ZS.html">here is the original Supreme Court decision</a></p>
<blockquote><p>JUSTICE BLACKMUN concluded in Part VI that the menorah display does not have the prohibited effect of endorsing religion, given its &#8220;particular physical setting.&#8221; Its combined display with a Christmas tree and a sign saluting liberty does not impermissibly endorse both the Christian and Jewish faiths, but simply recognizes that both Christmas and Chanukah are part of the same winter holiday season, which has attained a secular status in our society. The widely accepted view of the Christmas tree as the preeminent secular symbol of the Christmas season emphasizes this point. The tree, moreover, by virtue of its size and central position in the display, is clearly the predominant element, and the placement of the menorah beside it is readily understood as simply a recognition that Christmas is not the only traditional way of celebrating the season. The absence of a more secular alternative to the menorah negates the inference of endorsement.</p>
<p>JUSTICE O&#8217;CONNOR also concluded that the city&#8217;s display of a menorah, together with a Christmas tree and a sign saluting liberty, does not violate the Establishment Clause. The Christmas tree, whatever its origins, is widely viewed today as a secular symbol of the Christmas holiday. Although there may be certain secular aspects to Chanukah, it is primarily a religious holiday, and the menorah its central religious symbol and ritual object. By including the menorah with the tree, however, and with the sign saluting liberty, the city conveyed a message of pluralism and freedom of belief during the holiday season, which, in this particular physical setting, could not be interpreted by a reasonable <a name="pg_576"></a>observer as an endorsement of Judaism or Christianity or disapproval of alternative beliefs</p>
<p>In permitting the displays of the menorah and the creche, the city and county sought merely to &#8220;celebrate the season,&#8221; and to acknowledge the historical background and the religious as well as secular nature of the Chanukah and Christmas holidays.There is no suggestion here that the government&#8217;s power to coerce has been used to further Christianity or Judaism, or that the city or the county contributed money to further any one faith or intended to use the creche or the menorah to proselytize. Thus, the creche and menorah are purely passive symbols of religious holidays, and their use is permissible</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/12/11/chabad-menorahs-in-public-spaces-supreme-court-decision-twenty-years-ago/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sukkot Misc from the 9th and 20th centuries</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/05/sukkot-misc-from-the-9th-and-20th-centuries/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/05/sukkot-misc-from-the-9th-and-20th-centuries/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2009 03:49:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[holidays]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[liturgy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[popular religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chabad]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jonathan Sacks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[other nations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pesikta]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Shlomo Carlebach]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sukkah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sukkot]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ushpizin]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=120</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Sukkot is the holiday of the 6th to 9th centuries: Hoshanot are from this period, according to Goldschmidt. As is the custom of waving the lulav in 6 directions. First, Some random 6th -9th century ideas Guilt and treating the &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/05/sukkot-misc-from-the-9th-and-20th-centuries/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sukkot is the holiday of the 6<sup>th</sup> to 9<sup>th</sup> centuries: Hoshanot are from this period, according to Goldschmidt. As is the custom of waving the lulav in 6 directions.</p>
<p>First, Some random 6<sup>th</sup> -9<sup>th</sup> century ideas</p>
<p><strong>Guilt and treating the sukkah as exile, not as presense.</strong></p>
<blockquote><p>Said R&#8217; El&#8217;azar bar Maryom: Why do we make a sukkah after Yom Kippur? To teach you that on Rosh Hashanah The Holy One, Blessed Be He, sits in judgment on all mankind, and on Yom Kippur He signs the verdict. Perhaps Israel&#8217;s sentence is exile; therefore they make a sukkah and exile themselves from their homes to their sukkah Pesikta of Rav Kahana Parasha 2 addenda, Mandelbaum 457)</p></blockquote>
<p><strong> Don&#8217;t go to Great Adventure or other entertainment for chol hamoed.</strong></p>
<blockquote><p>The festivals make a difference between the nations and Israel: the nations eat and drink, and go to the circus and the theater, and anger the Lord by their words and deeds; Israel eats and drinks and goes to the houses of prayer to praise His name and to the houses of study  to learn His glory. Pesikta 340-1</p></blockquote>
<p><strong>Vicarious atonement for the nations</strong></p>
<blockquote><p>Just as this dove atones for sins, so does Israel atone for the nations, for all those seventy bulls which are sacrificed on the festival are on behalf of the seventy nations, so that the world not be bereft of them, as is written (Psalms 109) &#8220;<em>They answer my love with accusation but I am all prayer&#8221;</em> Midrash Shir Hashirim Rabba 1.<em> </em></p>
<p>&#8220;All seventy bulls that Israel used to sacrifice on the festival were for the seventy nations of the world, so that they not be removed from the world, as it is said: &#8216;They answer my love with accusation, but I am all prayer&#8217; (Ps. 109:4). That is, now they are protected by prayer instead of sacrifice.&#8221;<em> Pesikta de Rav Kahana</em> (par. 30)</p></blockquote>
<p><strong>And now 1000 years later, three very different fin de siècle 20<sup>th</sup> century ideas</strong></p>
<p>1] Chief Rabbi Dr Jonathan Sacks writing that the sukkah helps us identify with the poor of “Calcutta and Caracas.” <em>Dignity of Difference</em> 112</p>
<p>2 The sixth Lubavitcher Rebbe, Rabbi Yosef Yitzchak Schneersohn (1880-1950) spoke of seven &#8220;chassidic <em>ushpizin</em>&#8221; as well: the Baal Shem Tov, the Maggid (Rabbi DovBer of Mezeritch), and the first five rebbes of Chabad: Rabbi Schneur Zalman of Liadi, Rabbi DovBer of Lubavitch, Rabbi Menachem Mendel (the &#8220;Tzemach Tzeddek&#8221;), Rabbi Shmuel, and Rabbi Sholom DovBer.</p>
<p>Where I was for one or the meals the debate was between the method starting with the Besht or now should they start with the Alter Rebbe and end with the 7<sup>th</sup> Rebbe. This seems more widespread than I thought. Have the Biblical Ushpizin lost their resonance?</p>
<p>3] Old time R Shlomo Carlebach moving he six directions from cosmology or sefirot to personal experience of religion. <a href="http://www.mishpacha.org/sukkotlulav.shtml"> link</a></p>
<blockquote><p>First, face right. Right in Kabbalah signifies the attribute of <em>hesed</em>, kindness, mercy, overwhelming beneficence. Do you find it too hard to be generous? Or are you suffering from an excess of generosity, of kindness, of love? &#8221;</p>
<p>Then face left. Left in Kabbalah is <em>gevurah</em> – strength, strict judgment, limits. <em>Gevurah</em> is Isaac – bound for sacrifice on Mount  Moriah, unflinching, accepting of judgment. Take this opportunity to think of the limits, the judgments in your life. Are your circumstances too confining? Do you need more boundaries, or fewer? Do you need more strength? This is an opportunity to invite God to help you fix the limits in your life.</p>
<p>Next, face straight ahead: <em>tiferet, </em>or beauty. This is the balance, where the beneficence and the boundaries are in their proper proportions. It is Jacob, it is the middle course.</p>
<p>Then, look up. Can you connect with God? What’s the holiness you need in your life? How high can you rise this year?</p>
<p>Then, aim down. This is about groundedness, about your foundations. And it’s about your ability to find the buried treasures, under your feet; the truths buried in the dirt.</p>
<p>Finally, backwards. The essence of repentance is being able to go back and fix your past  by your coming to terms with it</p></blockquote>
<p>I find these three approaches to be quite different: the metonymic ethical, the binding to a saint, and the introspective.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/05/sukkot-misc-from-the-9th-and-20th-centuries/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Orthodox heilsgechichte</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/14/orthodox-heilsgechichte/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/14/orthodox-heilsgechichte/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Sep 2009 18:12:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chabad]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[heilsgechichte]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[historicism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rabbi Cherlow]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rabbi Elchanan Wasserman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rabbi Soloveitchik]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rabbi Zvi Yehudah Kook]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=28</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This weekend, I read a work on modern Jewish thought that considered the only Orthodox heilsgechichte as that of Rabbi Yoel Teitelbaum. The author, writing in 2006, could not name any other Orthodox theory of history. Actually, by definition most &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/14/orthodox-heilsgechichte/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This weekend, I read a work on modern Jewish thought that considered the only Orthodox heilsgechichte as that of Rabbi Yoel Teitelbaum. The author, writing in 2006, could not name any other Orthodox theory of history.</p>
<p>Actually, by definition most Orthodoxies must have a heilsgechichte to avoid secular causality and historicism. Therefore all of these authors will engage in the general outline of schoolbook history to produce a theology.Heilsgeschichte is German for &#8220;Salvation History.&#8221; The term is used for theological writing that is committed to two things: the affirmation of God&#8217;s suprahistorical activity in history and the need to critically reconstruct these events through the sources. In these approaches, the historical writings of Nahmanides, the Vilna Gaon, and Maharal are drafted into new contexts, to explain modern data.</p>
<p>About a decade ago a former colleague of mine asked about Orthodoxy and historicism and I gave a quick list of about eighteen  20<sup>th</sup> century orthodox theologies of history including:</p>
<p>Rabbi Isaac Breuer and Yeshaya Leibowitz who said that Judaism was ahistoric. This one is not popular anymore because it requires one to take refuge in philosophy. Now people need a theology of history. Especially since historical thinking was so important for modern thinking that it had to be subsumed, integrated and then overcome with a relgious theology against historicism.</p>
<p>As against secular history:Rabbi Elchanan Wasserman turned  Graetz on its head and making Torah study the causality for Graetz’s lachrymose history. Rav Shlomo Wolbe wrote a triumphalistic anti-Zionist vision of the end of modernity as shown by the baalei teshuvah. He includes quotes from several modern historians including Scholem.</p>
<p>As a messianic vision: Rabbi Zvi Yehudah Kook and the age of redemption and ingathering of the exiles. Rabbi Amital’s accounting for setbacks in the redemptive process. Rabbi Kasher (as probably author of Kol Hator), redemption through natural means.</p>
<p>On the Holocaust: Rabbi Teichtel’s blame of the Holocaust on the anti-Zionists. Rabbi Soloveitchik’s Kol Dodi Dofek, with its references to Secretary of State Dulles and recent American history.</p>
<p>Chabad: Rabbi Yosef Yitzhak’s messianism, and his version of Dubnow’s history of the common folk. He also has a history of the hidden saints. Rabbi M M Schneerson’s account of the fall of the Soviet Union and the post-historic messianic age.</p>
<p>Centrism:Treating Jewish history as history of the mesorah. (This one needs its own discussion because it accepts facts but without historicism.)</p>
<p>Even a figure as progressive as Rabbi Cherlow gave a paper at an academic conference on halakhah and ideology on the need for a theology of history. Cherlow wanted the academics to produce the chronology and raw facts, while rabbis will provide the meaning in history and evaluate the value of the data. Needless to say, it provoked reaction.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/09/14/orthodox-heilsgechichte/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>6</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
