<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Conversation with James Kugel- A Follow-up	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/02/11/conversation-with-james-kugel-a-follow-up/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/02/11/conversation-with-james-kugel-a-follow-up/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2015 14:11:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Eli		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/02/11/conversation-with-james-kugel-a-follow-up/#comment-13108</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eli]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2015 14:11:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5941#comment-13108</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I must admit that I am far less learned in philosophical matters than most (perhaps all?) of the previous posters here, but I am trying to make sense of Kugel and/or others who seem like they may be able to bring me to a better understanding of how to reconcile modern scholarship with classical Judaism.  What I can comment on that I am surprised that someone who is so good at explaining himself seems to express himself in such an opaque way on the subject of Torah Misinai, confusing minds greater than mine --- when people resort to categorizing his thoughts, rather than just debating their merits, that is a sign of lack of clarity.  I would have liked to hear his answer to questions such as &quot;Does G-d want you to (fill in the blank with several mitzvot d&#039;oraita lotaaseh and aseh --- leave out basar b&#039;chalav and the like, or take a minimalist approach and ask if He objects to people cooking a g&#039;di in it&#039;s mother&#039;s milk), and, if so, why?&quot; 
The why would be to differentiate an answer such as &quot;He wants us to follow the system as it evolved&quot; vs. &quot;We are not sure why but we know that he said/indicated so to our ancestors&quot;.

I am left not understanding whether Kugel&#039;s statement (stated in different forms and formats by him on several occasions) that being a Jew means following Halacha/Orthodoxy is due to sentimentality/culture/group cohesiveness or due to the simple imperitive to follow G-d&#039;s revealed will.

(I am aware that the post is by now old, but then again, isn&#039;t commentary on older texts what we are all about?)

It is interesting to think of the Chumash as one volume in a multi-volume set called &quot;Torah&quot;, but when Chazal refer to d&#039;oraita as opposed to d&#039;rabanan
Does Kugel posit that the categories of d’oraita and d’rabanan are merely legalistic categories to differentiate punishments and severity, or do the terms imply, as classically understood, a huge qualitative distinction, due to the fact that d’oraitas are what G-d actually said/dictated/indicated, whereas d’rabanan’s are products of human thought. Granted, the “hand-off” which Kugel refers to imbues d’rabanans with more significance than one would imagine based on mere contemplation of the distinction between the two categories, and this idea is found in Chazal.
]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I must admit that I am far less learned in philosophical matters than most (perhaps all?) of the previous posters here, but I am trying to make sense of Kugel and/or others who seem like they may be able to bring me to a better understanding of how to reconcile modern scholarship with classical Judaism.  What I can comment on that I am surprised that someone who is so good at explaining himself seems to express himself in such an opaque way on the subject of Torah Misinai, confusing minds greater than mine &#8212; when people resort to categorizing his thoughts, rather than just debating their merits, that is a sign of lack of clarity.  I would have liked to hear his answer to questions such as &#8220;Does G-d want you to (fill in the blank with several mitzvot d&#8217;oraita lotaaseh and aseh &#8212; leave out basar b&#8217;chalav and the like, or take a minimalist approach and ask if He objects to people cooking a g&#8217;di in it&#8217;s mother&#8217;s milk), and, if so, why?&#8221;<br />
The why would be to differentiate an answer such as &#8220;He wants us to follow the system as it evolved&#8221; vs. &#8220;We are not sure why but we know that he said/indicated so to our ancestors&#8221;.</p>
<p>I am left not understanding whether Kugel&#8217;s statement (stated in different forms and formats by him on several occasions) that being a Jew means following Halacha/Orthodoxy is due to sentimentality/culture/group cohesiveness or due to the simple imperitive to follow G-d&#8217;s revealed will.</p>
<p>(I am aware that the post is by now old, but then again, isn&#8217;t commentary on older texts what we are all about?)</p>
<p>It is interesting to think of the Chumash as one volume in a multi-volume set called &#8220;Torah&#8221;, but when Chazal refer to d&#8217;oraita as opposed to d&#8217;rabanan<br />
Does Kugel posit that the categories of d’oraita and d’rabanan are merely legalistic categories to differentiate punishments and severity, or do the terms imply, as classically understood, a huge qualitative distinction, due to the fact that d’oraitas are what G-d actually said/dictated/indicated, whereas d’rabanan’s are products of human thought. Granted, the “hand-off” which Kugel refers to imbues d’rabanans with more significance than one would imagine based on mere contemplation of the distinction between the two categories, and this idea is found in Chazal.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Joebug		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/02/11/conversation-with-james-kugel-a-follow-up/#comment-7629</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joebug]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2013 21:28:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5941#comment-7629</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Leibowitz or anatheism do seem a reasonable lens to interpret Kugel. Yet these perspectives have an internal consistency based on what is essentially a repudiation of the simple revelatory account of TMS which as previous posts indicate is how normative orthodoxy is usually understood. Yet Prof Kugel seems to want to have his cake and eat it, stretch TMS out of usual orthodox recognition, seemingly contradicting chazal&#039;s core theology on TMS as the previous post notes,  but still cling to chazal&#039;s view of a direct revelation with a mesorah that can demand obedience to mitzvot- unsurprisingly this leads to an internally inconsistent or even might I suggest incoherent position. Anatheism makes sense on its own terms, Kugel has yet to explain himself as clearly.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Leibowitz or anatheism do seem a reasonable lens to interpret Kugel. Yet these perspectives have an internal consistency based on what is essentially a repudiation of the simple revelatory account of TMS which as previous posts indicate is how normative orthodoxy is usually understood. Yet Prof Kugel seems to want to have his cake and eat it, stretch TMS out of usual orthodox recognition, seemingly contradicting chazal&#8217;s core theology on TMS as the previous post notes,  but still cling to chazal&#8217;s view of a direct revelation with a mesorah that can demand obedience to mitzvot- unsurprisingly this leads to an internally inconsistent or even might I suggest incoherent position. Anatheism makes sense on its own terms, Kugel has yet to explain himself as clearly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: David Z		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/02/11/conversation-with-james-kugel-a-follow-up/#comment-7611</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[David Z]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2013 03:44:33 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5941#comment-7611</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I&#039;ve really been trying to figure out what Kugel&#039;s beliefs are because he seems to have spent a lot of time formulating them and is talented write, yet they still seem so fuzzy.  I would have expected more: &quot;That&#039;s something we can&#039;t know.&quot;  Yet he also seems to want to embrace Orthodox Fundamentalism, if that&#039;s a term that makes sense.

After more thought on what he says about pashtanut and that being how he got into the field of biblical criticism, I think perhaps his approach is just like the pashtanim.  Why did rashba&quot;m spend so much time on p&#039;shat when it contradicts how khaza&quot;l and halakha read the p&#039;sukim?  Well whatever your answer is to that, is your answer to Kugel.  Except that p&#039;shat is so much more radical now.

But even that only takes you so far, because rashba&quot;m still assumed p&#039;shat would never lead you to believe that the tora was written by human hands (I&#039;m picking on rashba&quot;m here).  And then why would Kugel be forced to say that biblical criticism is incompatible with Orthodox Judaism when Orthodox Judaism has a place for it in pashtanut?  But Kugel hints to this when he says:

&quot;[M]odern scholars and traditional Judaism don’t even agree on what the “text” is: the former take it to be strictly the words on the page, the latter to include the whole Oral Torah (torah she-be’al peh). This is no minor disagreement: it represents two completely opposed notions of how to read the Bible.&quot;

You could say the same thing about pashtanim and khaza&quot;l (except you know that the pashtanim also revered khaza&quot;l and tora sheb&#039;al pe).

So I&#039;m still confused as to what Kugel believes, but I wonder if I&#039;m on the right tack.  Thoughts?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ve really been trying to figure out what Kugel&#8217;s beliefs are because he seems to have spent a lot of time formulating them and is talented write, yet they still seem so fuzzy.  I would have expected more: &#8220;That&#8217;s something we can&#8217;t know.&#8221;  Yet he also seems to want to embrace Orthodox Fundamentalism, if that&#8217;s a term that makes sense.</p>
<p>After more thought on what he says about pashtanut and that being how he got into the field of biblical criticism, I think perhaps his approach is just like the pashtanim.  Why did rashba&#8221;m spend so much time on p&#8217;shat when it contradicts how khaza&#8221;l and halakha read the p&#8217;sukim?  Well whatever your answer is to that, is your answer to Kugel.  Except that p&#8217;shat is so much more radical now.</p>
<p>But even that only takes you so far, because rashba&#8221;m still assumed p&#8217;shat would never lead you to believe that the tora was written by human hands (I&#8217;m picking on rashba&#8221;m here).  And then why would Kugel be forced to say that biblical criticism is incompatible with Orthodox Judaism when Orthodox Judaism has a place for it in pashtanut?  But Kugel hints to this when he says:</p>
<p>&#8220;[M]odern scholars and traditional Judaism don’t even agree on what the “text” is: the former take it to be strictly the words on the page, the latter to include the whole Oral Torah (torah she-be’al peh). This is no minor disagreement: it represents two completely opposed notions of how to read the Bible.&#8221;</p>
<p>You could say the same thing about pashtanim and khaza&#8221;l (except you know that the pashtanim also revered khaza&#8221;l and tora sheb&#8217;al pe).</p>
<p>So I&#8217;m still confused as to what Kugel believes, but I wonder if I&#8217;m on the right tack.  Thoughts?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/02/11/conversation-with-james-kugel-a-follow-up/#comment-7555</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2013 10:11:51 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5941#comment-7555</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/02/11/conversation-with-james-kugel-a-follow-up/#comment-7548&quot;&gt;Shaya&lt;/a&gt;.

I find it sad that someone thinks that understanding prophecy in scientific terms is &quot;completely alien to Jewish tradition.&quot; Saadya Gaon&#039;s theory of prophecy is precisely an attempt to see it as part of the natural fabric of creation. Rambam also gives what is essentially a naturalistic account of prophecy.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/02/11/conversation-with-james-kugel-a-follow-up/#comment-7548">Shaya</a>.</p>
<p>I find it sad that someone thinks that understanding prophecy in scientific terms is &#8220;completely alien to Jewish tradition.&#8221; Saadya Gaon&#8217;s theory of prophecy is precisely an attempt to see it as part of the natural fabric of creation. Rambam also gives what is essentially a naturalistic account of prophecy.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/02/11/conversation-with-james-kugel-a-follow-up/#comment-7551</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2013 23:43:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5941#comment-7551</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/02/11/conversation-with-james-kugel-a-follow-up/#comment-7549&quot;&gt;ruvie&lt;/a&gt;.

Tamar Ross in her paper referred to Kugel as in the camp of Leibowitz. she read him as following Leibowitz. Kugel responded strongly and viscerally stating that he is not in any way and that one should not preclude a historic revelation and the possibility that God talks. It was his amazing outburst that led me to discuss it with him after shabbos. To explain what he means, I am completely with Shaya, I can do it with Abulafia, or Ramchal or a modern metaphysical scheme. But then it is not Kugel anymore. Literature must give way to philosophy, Trivium and Quadrivium must give way to Philosophy and Theology.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/02/11/conversation-with-james-kugel-a-follow-up/#comment-7549">ruvie</a>.</p>
<p>Tamar Ross in her paper referred to Kugel as in the camp of Leibowitz. she read him as following Leibowitz. Kugel responded strongly and viscerally stating that he is not in any way and that one should not preclude a historic revelation and the possibility that God talks. It was his amazing outburst that led me to discuss it with him after shabbos. To explain what he means, I am completely with Shaya, I can do it with Abulafia, or Ramchal or a modern metaphysical scheme. But then it is not Kugel anymore. Literature must give way to philosophy, Trivium and Quadrivium must give way to Philosophy and Theology.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Lawrence Kaplan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/02/11/conversation-with-james-kugel-a-follow-up/#comment-7550</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lawrence Kaplan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2013 23:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5941#comment-7550</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Ruvie: I also thought of Leibowitz. See Gilad Bareli&#039;s essay.&quot;&quot;Emunah u-Mizvot,&quot; in Y. Leibowitz: Bein Shamranut le-Radicaliyyut,  ed A. Ravitzky, pp.275-276. &quot;On the one hand the religious Jew accepts the mitzvot as the mitzvot of God and accepts the yoke of the Torah as the word of God..On the other hand, he knows that these mitzvot and this word are human creations set down at a certain place and time. Is this not a contradiction?... No. The &quot;word of God&quot;  does not point to a fact; it points to a a specisl category of awareness on the part of the believer.   To see a certain matter as  the word of God is to maintain that it possesses a special  status in the consciousness  of the believer ... in terms of  his attitude  to the world and to humanity  and to fashioning his mode of life.:&quot;.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ruvie: I also thought of Leibowitz. See Gilad Bareli&#8217;s essay.&#8221;&#8221;Emunah u-Mizvot,&#8221; in Y. Leibowitz: Bein Shamranut le-Radicaliyyut,  ed A. Ravitzky, pp.275-276. &#8220;On the one hand the religious Jew accepts the mitzvot as the mitzvot of God and accepts the yoke of the Torah as the word of God..On the other hand, he knows that these mitzvot and this word are human creations set down at a certain place and time. Is this not a contradiction?&#8230; No. The &#8220;word of God&#8221;  does not point to a fact; it points to a a specisl category of awareness on the part of the believer.   To see a certain matter as  the word of God is to maintain that it possesses a special  status in the consciousness  of the believer &#8230; in terms of  his attitude  to the world and to humanity  and to fashioning his mode of life.:&#8221;.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ruvie		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/02/11/conversation-with-james-kugel-a-follow-up/#comment-7549</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ruvie]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2013 21:15:30 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5941#comment-7549</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Alan - is it possible for you to explain under the heading i think this is what he means? it may expand the conversation.
it would seem he believes in a &quot;hand off&quot; from God to man of something that later developed into torah - all inclusiveness of its parts and ongoing additions (kind of a ongoing revelation). the continuation of torah is what he calls &quot;lo bashamayim hee&quot; and may include parts of the penatuch. would you agree?
his answer reminds of the ongoing debate of what was given at sinai from ibn daud (Ravad I), rambam, students of ramban, chavot yair etc
I also wonder if he is better off with a leibowtizian definition of torah min hashamayim as a religious fact and not historical one in that the &quot;handoff&quot; can never be proven. thoughts?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Alan &#8211; is it possible for you to explain under the heading i think this is what he means? it may expand the conversation.<br />
it would seem he believes in a &#8220;hand off&#8221; from God to man of something that later developed into torah &#8211; all inclusiveness of its parts and ongoing additions (kind of a ongoing revelation). the continuation of torah is what he calls &#8220;lo bashamayim hee&#8221; and may include parts of the penatuch. would you agree?<br />
his answer reminds of the ongoing debate of what was given at sinai from ibn daud (Ravad I), rambam, students of ramban, chavot yair etc<br />
I also wonder if he is better off with a leibowtizian definition of torah min hashamayim as a religious fact and not historical one in that the &#8220;handoff&#8221; can never be proven. thoughts?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Shaya		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/02/11/conversation-with-james-kugel-a-follow-up/#comment-7548</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shaya]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2013 21:09:36 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5941#comment-7548</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Rabbi brill,
Why does kugel insist on trying to define revelation in pseudo scientific terms which are completely alien to Jewish tradition? Honestly, is he completely unaware of theologists like Ramchal or Rav Abulafia who dealt in these issues at length? Just today I read an article from tzvia rubin about  Ramchal and understanding graphic kabbalistic images.(in Daat 40).I find it ironic that a bible scholar who is familiar with near eastern myth is not versed in Zohar,the first book to agree with such interpretations.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rabbi brill,<br />
Why does kugel insist on trying to define revelation in pseudo scientific terms which are completely alien to Jewish tradition? Honestly, is he completely unaware of theologists like Ramchal or Rav Abulafia who dealt in these issues at length? Just today I read an article from tzvia rubin about  Ramchal and understanding graphic kabbalistic images.(in Daat 40).I find it ironic that a bible scholar who is familiar with near eastern myth is not versed in Zohar,the first book to agree with such interpretations.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/02/11/conversation-with-james-kugel-a-follow-up/#comment-7546</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2013 20:19:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5941#comment-7546</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Ruvie, 
 I agree there was dancing around in #4, for me less so in #5. I cannot answer for him. I do think I know what he means but I wont put words in his mouth. I also think it needs a little philosophic/theological rigor in someone else&#039;s hands. In medieval or Kantian terms, one can formulate an explanation. And I think Isaac is correct, we can use an anatheistic formulation.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ruvie,<br />
 I agree there was dancing around in #4, for me less so in #5. I cannot answer for him. I do think I know what he means but I wont put words in his mouth. I also think it needs a little philosophic/theological rigor in someone else&#8217;s hands. In medieval or Kantian terms, one can formulate an explanation. And I think Isaac is correct, we can use an anatheistic formulation.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Ruvie		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/02/11/conversation-with-james-kugel-a-follow-up/#comment-7545</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ruvie]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2013 19:48:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5941#comment-7545</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Alan - in question 4 he tap dances and doesn&#039;t answer what was given at Sinai. In question 5 he just ignores the question.

&quot;What was significant in the Sinai narrative was the fact that the Torah came from God; it is not, as others would have it, a “human reaction to the ineffable.” But equally important is the fact that it was given into human hands.&quot;
So what was given? Are you satisfied with these non answers? Why does he avoid it?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Alan &#8211; in question 4 he tap dances and doesn&#8217;t answer what was given at Sinai. In question 5 he just ignores the question.</p>
<p>&#8220;What was significant in the Sinai narrative was the fact that the Torah came from God; it is not, as others would have it, a “human reaction to the ineffable.” But equally important is the fact that it was given into human hands.&#8221;<br />
So what was given? Are you satisfied with these non answers? Why does he avoid it?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: zach		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/02/11/conversation-with-james-kugel-a-follow-up/#comment-7544</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[zach]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2013 18:45:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5941#comment-7544</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&lt;i&gt;What does Kugel really think went on at Mount Sinai? How much of the Torah as we have it—if anything!—was actually given to Moses?&lt;/i&gt;

I can&#039;t imagine that Professor Kugel&#039;s answer to this one will satisfy anyone. He seems to skirt around the issue, even to point of discussing an irrelevancy vis a vis the location of Mt Sinai. And although &quot;Torah&quot; can mean many things, I think to most people here the question relates to a written Torah produced by Moshe, but allowing for very minor changes over time (malei &#038; chaseir, dotted words possibly changed by Ezra as discussed by Halivni, the final pesukim, etc). Kugel does seem to imply that there may have been more significant changes, but on this point, at least, he sounds more like a diplomat than a scholar.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><i>What does Kugel really think went on at Mount Sinai? How much of the Torah as we have it—if anything!—was actually given to Moses?</i></p>
<p>I can&#8217;t imagine that Professor Kugel&#8217;s answer to this one will satisfy anyone. He seems to skirt around the issue, even to point of discussing an irrelevancy vis a vis the location of Mt Sinai. And although &#8220;Torah&#8221; can mean many things, I think to most people here the question relates to a written Torah produced by Moshe, but allowing for very minor changes over time (malei &amp; chaseir, dotted words possibly changed by Ezra as discussed by Halivni, the final pesukim, etc). Kugel does seem to imply that there may have been more significant changes, but on this point, at least, he sounds more like a diplomat than a scholar.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Isaac Shalev		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/02/11/conversation-with-james-kugel-a-follow-up/#comment-7539</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Isaac Shalev]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2013 15:04:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=5941#comment-7539</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I&#039;m reminded of Yair Lapid&#039;s speech at Kiryat Ono, where he describes the Zionist attempt to excise 2,000 years of Rabbinic Judaism and return to a Bilbical and landed conception of Judaism. It seems that Kugel is trying to similarly excise medieval parshanut from Judaism, and return to a Hazalian Judaism. 

So what is Kugel&#039;s actual approach to the content of revelation? He appears to be saying that revelation is, by its nature, vague and impossible to pin down in its precise specifics, but that nevertheless, a picture emerges which can rightfully be claimed as Revelation. This is a pretty novel claim, namely, that the text that we have is only a reflection of revelation as mediated by a process of transmission from Man to God that inevitably alters it - yet nevertheless, we may and must treat the product is Revelation. As much as Kugel places prophecy - the communication between God and Man - at the center of his Jewish theology, he problemitizes that communication by insisting that process itself significantly alters the content of the communication. By his mashal, God was transmitted an assortment of wavelengthys, but we ended up seeing &quot;Starry Night&quot;. Seems to me that this approach creates serious epistemological problems of the sort normally avoided by a theory of revelation. I&#039;d want to think more about it before tentatively claiming that there&#039;s strong similarities between Kugel&#039;s approach, taken to its logical conclusion, and anatheistic conceptions of the nature of revelation as an uncertain process that requires us to return over and over again to the moment of revelation to try and recall what was blindingly obvious in one moment, but gone the next.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m reminded of Yair Lapid&#8217;s speech at Kiryat Ono, where he describes the Zionist attempt to excise 2,000 years of Rabbinic Judaism and return to a Bilbical and landed conception of Judaism. It seems that Kugel is trying to similarly excise medieval parshanut from Judaism, and return to a Hazalian Judaism. </p>
<p>So what is Kugel&#8217;s actual approach to the content of revelation? He appears to be saying that revelation is, by its nature, vague and impossible to pin down in its precise specifics, but that nevertheless, a picture emerges which can rightfully be claimed as Revelation. This is a pretty novel claim, namely, that the text that we have is only a reflection of revelation as mediated by a process of transmission from Man to God that inevitably alters it &#8211; yet nevertheless, we may and must treat the product is Revelation. As much as Kugel places prophecy &#8211; the communication between God and Man &#8211; at the center of his Jewish theology, he problemitizes that communication by insisting that process itself significantly alters the content of the communication. By his mashal, God was transmitted an assortment of wavelengthys, but we ended up seeing &#8220;Starry Night&#8221;. Seems to me that this approach creates serious epistemological problems of the sort normally avoided by a theory of revelation. I&#8217;d want to think more about it before tentatively claiming that there&#8217;s strong similarities between Kugel&#8217;s approach, taken to its logical conclusion, and anatheistic conceptions of the nature of revelation as an uncertain process that requires us to return over and over again to the moment of revelation to try and recall what was blindingly obvious in one moment, but gone the next.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
