<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Joel Osteen will be in Israel- talks about Judaism	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/20/joel-osteen-will-be-in-israel-talks-about-judaism/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/20/joel-osteen-will-be-in-israel-talks-about-judaism/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2011 22:52:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/20/joel-osteen-will-be-in-israel-talks-about-judaism/#comment-2446</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2011 22:52:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2875#comment-2446</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/20/joel-osteen-will-be-in-israel-talks-about-judaism/#comment-2437&quot;&gt;tekhelet&lt;/a&gt;.

Perhaps Joel Osteen is simply following the ways of the synoptic gospels who also seemed to have different ideas about the real Jesus.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/20/joel-osteen-will-be-in-israel-talks-about-judaism/#comment-2437">tekhelet</a>.</p>
<p>Perhaps Joel Osteen is simply following the ways of the synoptic gospels who also seemed to have different ideas about the real Jesus.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: avrahambronstein		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/20/joel-osteen-will-be-in-israel-talks-about-judaism/#comment-2442</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[avrahambronstein]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2011 16:01:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2875#comment-2442</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[John Hagee is also a Word of Faith/Prosperity Gospel preacher, though with much more fire, brimstone, and millennialism, who has been remarkably successful in terms of Israel - see &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cufi.org&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Christians United For Israel&lt;/a&gt; and Christian Zionism as a movement.
I&#039;m interested to see if Osteen heads in that direction as well.  Hagee plays the political side of it (land-for-peace, Iran, terrorism, democracy), and there&#039;s probably a solid niche for Osteen to play the StartupNation side of it.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>John Hagee is also a Word of Faith/Prosperity Gospel preacher, though with much more fire, brimstone, and millennialism, who has been remarkably successful in terms of Israel &#8211; see <a href="http://www.cufi.org" rel="nofollow">Christians United For Israel</a> and Christian Zionism as a movement.<br />
I&#8217;m interested to see if Osteen heads in that direction as well.  Hagee plays the political side of it (land-for-peace, Iran, terrorism, democracy), and there&#8217;s probably a solid niche for Osteen to play the StartupNation side of it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: tekhelet		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/20/joel-osteen-will-be-in-israel-talks-about-judaism/#comment-2437</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tekhelet]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2011 06:59:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2875#comment-2437</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The &quot;Jesus&quot; that Mr. Joel Osteen teaches about, is not the Jesus/Yeshua from the bible. Let me inform you that false believers have come up with &quot;another Jesus&quot;. 

What Joel Osteen teaches is called the Word of Faith doctrines, and the roots of WOF are based on the teachings of people like Kenneth Hagin, just to name some. Known as Christian Mind Science cults.  

My advise is, not to follow this man&#039;s teachings. If you seriously want to know what is the true faith in Yeshua/Jesus, go to the bible. That is your best source. G-d blesses us but what the false teachers do is take it out of context, twists things around and suddenly the message becomes health, wealth and tons of blessings. If you read Scripture, you will see that the prophets were all  persecuted and suffered at the hands of the wicked. Isaiah, Jeremiah, Ezekiel etc. If you are a true follower of the Living G-d, you will go through tribulation and trials. He is our Provider and so we are looked after by Him, but chasing after wordly desires like the pagans do? No. But that is what the WOF teaches - it is called the prosperity gospel.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The &#8220;Jesus&#8221; that Mr. Joel Osteen teaches about, is not the Jesus/Yeshua from the bible. Let me inform you that false believers have come up with &#8220;another Jesus&#8221;. </p>
<p>What Joel Osteen teaches is called the Word of Faith doctrines, and the roots of WOF are based on the teachings of people like Kenneth Hagin, just to name some. Known as Christian Mind Science cults.  </p>
<p>My advise is, not to follow this man&#8217;s teachings. If you seriously want to know what is the true faith in Yeshua/Jesus, go to the bible. That is your best source. G-d blesses us but what the false teachers do is take it out of context, twists things around and suddenly the message becomes health, wealth and tons of blessings. If you read Scripture, you will see that the prophets were all  persecuted and suffered at the hands of the wicked. Isaiah, Jeremiah, Ezekiel etc. If you are a true follower of the Living G-d, you will go through tribulation and trials. He is our Provider and so we are looked after by Him, but chasing after wordly desires like the pagans do? No. But that is what the WOF teaches &#8211; it is called the prosperity gospel.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
