<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Interview with Menachem Kellner	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/02/14/interview-with-menachem-kellner/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/02/14/interview-with-menachem-kellner/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Mar 2012 09:33:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: walter benjamin		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/02/14/interview-with-menachem-kellner/#comment-4274</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[walter benjamin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Mar 2012 09:33:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4605#comment-4274</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I think the simple point here is that one is permitted to harbor whatever opinions he wishes to harbor but to publicly voice them and consider himself a Jew is a &#039;sensationalist&#039; act for bringing attention to himself.


edited by site owner]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think the simple point here is that one is permitted to harbor whatever opinions he wishes to harbor but to publicly voice them and consider himself a Jew is a &#8216;sensationalist&#8217; act for bringing attention to himself.</p>
<p>edited by site owner</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Beth Frank-Backman		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/02/14/interview-with-menachem-kellner/#comment-4181</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Beth Frank-Backman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 18 Feb 2012 20:07:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4605#comment-4181</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[--- Keeping mizvot as the basis of peoplehood to follow God’s command, and produce a stable and structured society. Mizvot without preconditions of belief or authority. ---

I&#039;m confused.   How does focusing on peoplehood and praxis, whilst moving away from dogma and dogmatism, solve the problems that divide the religious right and left of Judaism?  It seems to me that praxis is exactly what divides us, not theology.  Or more precisely, what divides us are differences in the  ways we reason about praxis and incorporate secular philosophy into our dialog with source texts .]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&#8212; Keeping mizvot as the basis of peoplehood to follow God’s command, and produce a stable and structured society. Mizvot without preconditions of belief or authority. &#8212;</p>
<p>I&#8217;m confused.   How does focusing on peoplehood and praxis, whilst moving away from dogma and dogmatism, solve the problems that divide the religious right and left of Judaism?  It seems to me that praxis is exactly what divides us, not theology.  Or more precisely, what divides us are differences in the  ways we reason about praxis and incorporate secular philosophy into our dialog with source texts .</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Shimshon Rubin		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/02/14/interview-with-menachem-kellner/#comment-4178</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shimshon Rubin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2012 10:41:26 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4605#comment-4178</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Shalom, 
Just to put things into perspective and to keep the record straight: Prof. Menachem Kellner has balanced his unsurpassed intellectual rigor and vast Jewish knowledge with something else too. Over the course of his life and career, Kellner has devoted a portion of his time and energy to making sure that Israel, Judaism and the Jews, remain focused upon, and associated with the highest standards of human ethical behavior in thought, word and deed. He has seen too much and knows too much to accept the narratives that portray Israel, Judaism or the Jewish people negatively and without sufficient understanding of the reality and context of the issues involved. And he knows too much to accept the trends within Judaism and Israel that portray thoughts, dogmas and deeds that deviate from the highest ethical standards of respect for human beings as fundamental to the core of Jewish tradition. One can find virtually (and perhaps literally) everything and anything within the corpus of Jewish thought and writing. Being able to quote something from a Jewish  source does not necessarily make it  &quot;Jewish.&quot; To understand the context and centrality of those texts and quotations, we need honest and unbiased scholars. Menachem Kellner is such a scholar. The fact that he is a mentsch is no less important.
Respectfully,
Simon Shimshon Rubin]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Shalom,<br />
Just to put things into perspective and to keep the record straight: Prof. Menachem Kellner has balanced his unsurpassed intellectual rigor and vast Jewish knowledge with something else too. Over the course of his life and career, Kellner has devoted a portion of his time and energy to making sure that Israel, Judaism and the Jews, remain focused upon, and associated with the highest standards of human ethical behavior in thought, word and deed. He has seen too much and knows too much to accept the narratives that portray Israel, Judaism or the Jewish people negatively and without sufficient understanding of the reality and context of the issues involved. And he knows too much to accept the trends within Judaism and Israel that portray thoughts, dogmas and deeds that deviate from the highest ethical standards of respect for human beings as fundamental to the core of Jewish tradition. One can find virtually (and perhaps literally) everything and anything within the corpus of Jewish thought and writing. Being able to quote something from a Jewish  source does not necessarily make it  &#8220;Jewish.&#8221; To understand the context and centrality of those texts and quotations, we need honest and unbiased scholars. Menachem Kellner is such a scholar. The fact that he is a mentsch is no less important.<br />
Respectfully,<br />
Simon Shimshon Rubin</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/02/14/interview-with-menachem-kellner/#comment-4175</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2012 20:08:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4605#comment-4175</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Someone asked me:Why did Kellner seem to have both harder and a greater questions than other interviews? Answer: I send everyone the same number of questions but some people answer fewer questions or they only go for the easier questions and ignore the hardball questions. Prof Kellner was open enough to answer more questions and harder ones. Same thing applies to the introductions, the more email banter between me and the interviewee before an interview gets posted the longer and more critical the introduction. The introductions are vetted by the interviewee and I remove what I am asked to remove.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Someone asked me:Why did Kellner seem to have both harder and a greater questions than other interviews? Answer: I send everyone the same number of questions but some people answer fewer questions or they only go for the easier questions and ignore the hardball questions. Prof Kellner was open enough to answer more questions and harder ones. Same thing applies to the introductions, the more email banter between me and the interviewee before an interview gets posted the longer and more critical the introduction. The introductions are vetted by the interviewee and I remove what I am asked to remove.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Brill		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/02/14/interview-with-menachem-kellner/#comment-4174</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2012 20:01:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4605#comment-4174</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[from Prof. Kellner:
thanks for your query about angels...I do not have much to add to what I wrote in the book; Rambam&#039;s strict monotheism outlaws angels as intermediaries, his attachment to what later came to be called Ockham&#039;s Razor outlaws their very existence, his opposition to all forms of astrological and magical thinking made them amanthema to him, etc. You can find more on the subject in the following:
Diamond, James. Converts, Heretics, and Lepers: Maimonides and the Outsider. Notre Dame: University of Notre Dame Press, 2007.
———. Maimonides and the Hermeneutics of Concealment: Deciphering Scripture and Midrash in the Guide of the Perplexed. Albany: SUNY Press, 2002.
Goodman, Lenn. &quot;Maimonidean Naturalism.&quot; In Neoplatonism and Jewish Thought, edited by Lenn Goodman, 157-94. Albany: SUNY Press, 1992.
Kasher, Hannah. &quot;The Dual Nature of the Biblical Angel in the Philosophy of Maimonides.&quot; In Philosophers and the Jewish Bible, edited by Charles Manekin and Robert Eisen, 41-60. College Park: University of Maryland Press, 2008.
Kreisel, Howard. Prophecy: The History of an Idea in Medieval Jewish Philosophy. Dordrecht: Kluwer, 2001.
Shapiro, Marc. The Limits of Orthodox Theology: Maimonides&#039; Thirteen Principles Reappraised. London: Littman Library of Jewish Civilization, 2004.

 as to your query concerning Rambam and modern science, I tried to address that in the attached. Several of these article are easily found in my book, SCIENCE IN THE BET MIDRASH: STUDIES IN MAIMONIDES]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>from Prof. Kellner:<br />
thanks for your query about angels&#8230;I do not have much to add to what I wrote in the book; Rambam&#8217;s strict monotheism outlaws angels as intermediaries, his attachment to what later came to be called Ockham&#8217;s Razor outlaws their very existence, his opposition to all forms of astrological and magical thinking made them amanthema to him, etc. You can find more on the subject in the following:<br />
Diamond, James. Converts, Heretics, and Lepers: Maimonides and the Outsider. Notre Dame: University of Notre Dame Press, 2007.<br />
———. Maimonides and the Hermeneutics of Concealment: Deciphering Scripture and Midrash in the Guide of the Perplexed. Albany: SUNY Press, 2002.<br />
Goodman, Lenn. &#8220;Maimonidean Naturalism.&#8221; In Neoplatonism and Jewish Thought, edited by Lenn Goodman, 157-94. Albany: SUNY Press, 1992.<br />
Kasher, Hannah. &#8220;The Dual Nature of the Biblical Angel in the Philosophy of Maimonides.&#8221; In Philosophers and the Jewish Bible, edited by Charles Manekin and Robert Eisen, 41-60. College Park: University of Maryland Press, 2008.<br />
Kreisel, Howard. Prophecy: The History of an Idea in Medieval Jewish Philosophy. Dordrecht: Kluwer, 2001.<br />
Shapiro, Marc. The Limits of Orthodox Theology: Maimonides&#8217; Thirteen Principles Reappraised. London: Littman Library of Jewish Civilization, 2004.</p>
<p> as to your query concerning Rambam and modern science, I tried to address that in the attached. Several of these article are easily found in my book, SCIENCE IN THE BET MIDRASH: STUDIES IN MAIMONIDES</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: L		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/02/14/interview-with-menachem-kellner/#comment-4172</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[L]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2012 04:35:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4605#comment-4172</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&quot;For Kellner, since an ordinary Jew who drives to shul can get an aliyah but a Reform Rabbi cannot makes it about dogma.&quot;

Does a woman count as an &quot;ordinary Jew&quot; as long as she&#039;s not a Reform Rabbi?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&#8220;For Kellner, since an ordinary Jew who drives to shul can get an aliyah but a Reform Rabbi cannot makes it about dogma.&#8221;</p>
<p>Does a woman count as an &#8220;ordinary Jew&#8221; as long as she&#8217;s not a Reform Rabbi?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: rabbifink		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/02/14/interview-with-menachem-kellner/#comment-4169</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[rabbifink]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2012 19:56:31 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4605#comment-4169</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Prof. Kellner,

I thoroughly enjoy your work, especially &quot;Maimonides Confrontation With Mysticism&quot;. Although the final chapter on angels felt a bit lacking. Would you mind commenting on how you understand Maimonides understanding of Angels. In particular I am curious what you think Rambam would say today when we have done away with Aristotelean physics. What would he write in Chapter 2 of the MT if he were writing it today? Is there definitive evidence that Maimonides rejected the Lurianic notion that each action we do creates angels in the netherworld? And what are we to make of the implicit encounters between angels and people made in Tanach? Any further illumination or elucidation on the subject would be much appreciated.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Prof. Kellner,</p>
<p>I thoroughly enjoy your work, especially &#8220;Maimonides Confrontation With Mysticism&#8221;. Although the final chapter on angels felt a bit lacking. Would you mind commenting on how you understand Maimonides understanding of Angels. In particular I am curious what you think Rambam would say today when we have done away with Aristotelean physics. What would he write in Chapter 2 of the MT if he were writing it today? Is there definitive evidence that Maimonides rejected the Lurianic notion that each action we do creates angels in the netherworld? And what are we to make of the implicit encounters between angels and people made in Tanach? Any further illumination or elucidation on the subject would be much appreciated.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alex		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/02/14/interview-with-menachem-kellner/#comment-4168</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alex]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2012 18:09:12 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4605#comment-4168</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&quot;Zionism is a political position and there’s nothing wrong with saying that perhaps the “Jewish problem” will not be solved (=has not been solved) by yet another nation state.&quot;

When opposing Zionism means supporting those who openly call for genocide (or denying Israel&#039;s right to use effective military means against them), there is quite a big problem indeed!

This immense problem is not one of ideology, politics, or dogma, but of basic morality. I.e. of the derekh eretz that comes before Torah. Kellner is absolutely right.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&#8220;Zionism is a political position and there’s nothing wrong with saying that perhaps the “Jewish problem” will not be solved (=has not been solved) by yet another nation state.&#8221;</p>
<p>When opposing Zionism means supporting those who openly call for genocide (or denying Israel&#8217;s right to use effective military means against them), there is quite a big problem indeed!</p>
<p>This immense problem is not one of ideology, politics, or dogma, but of basic morality. I.e. of the derekh eretz that comes before Torah. Kellner is absolutely right.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Joseph		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/02/14/interview-with-menachem-kellner/#comment-4167</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joseph]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2012 17:10:31 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4605#comment-4167</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[To take this in a different direction:
Prof. Kellner,

     Would you mind commenting on the evolution of your work? Meaning, you started out in Jewish ethics and proceeded to Maimonides&#039; mysticism and issues of dogma. Do you see a common thread linking your work? Is lack of dogma and rationalism, for instance, necessary for an ethical Judaism?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>To take this in a different direction:<br />
Prof. Kellner,</p>
<p>     Would you mind commenting on the evolution of your work? Meaning, you started out in Jewish ethics and proceeded to Maimonides&#8217; mysticism and issues of dogma. Do you see a common thread linking your work? Is lack of dogma and rationalism, for instance, necessary for an ethical Judaism?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: zbraiter		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/02/14/interview-with-menachem-kellner/#comment-4165</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[zbraiter]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2012 20:30:40 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4605#comment-4165</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[For the sake of throwing if just a little clarity re: Boyarin&#039;s position re: Zionism, let me requote from Alan&#039;s interview with Boyarin the following snippet: &quot;I don’t want to get into a political discussion here but, for me, as hinted below, Zionism does not seem like a traditional or historically orthodox solution to the problems of the Jews (although I will grant that it may have been necessary in some sense as well).&quot; 
In the spirit of Kellner&#039;s work, Boyarin&#039;s statement would seem not to reflect a &quot;dogmatic&quot; form of anti-Zionism.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For the sake of throwing if just a little clarity re: Boyarin&#8217;s position re: Zionism, let me requote from Alan&#8217;s interview with Boyarin the following snippet: &#8220;I don’t want to get into a political discussion here but, for me, as hinted below, Zionism does not seem like a traditional or historically orthodox solution to the problems of the Jews (although I will grant that it may have been necessary in some sense as well).&#8221;<br />
In the spirit of Kellner&#8217;s work, Boyarin&#8217;s statement would seem not to reflect a &#8220;dogmatic&#8221; form of anti-Zionism.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Amit		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2012/02/14/interview-with-menachem-kellner/#comment-4163</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Amit]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2012 14:15:57 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=4605#comment-4163</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I&#039;m appalled that the mere existence of anti-Zionists is a bane for Prof. Kellener, and that being an anti-Zionist disqualifies a person from having anything worthwhile to say about his academic field (in which, I might add, he is quite distinguished).
I&#039;m not surprised, though. As a member of the Shalem center, a right-wing think tank, Kellner is using the scare tactics of Im Tirzu to instigate a transatlantic witch-hunt against anti-Zionists everywhere.
Zionism is a political position and there&#039;s nothing wrong with saying that perhaps the &quot;Jewish problem&quot; will not be solved (=has not been solved) by yet another nation state. It&#039;s a valid position, a legal one, and one held by  members of Israel&#039;s governing coalition. I don&#039;t see why not let Prof. Boyarin voice his opinions on that and other matters. It&#039;s definitely no less respectable than being a fellow of the Shalem center.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m appalled that the mere existence of anti-Zionists is a bane for Prof. Kellener, and that being an anti-Zionist disqualifies a person from having anything worthwhile to say about his academic field (in which, I might add, he is quite distinguished).<br />
I&#8217;m not surprised, though. As a member of the Shalem center, a right-wing think tank, Kellner is using the scare tactics of Im Tirzu to instigate a transatlantic witch-hunt against anti-Zionists everywhere.<br />
Zionism is a political position and there&#8217;s nothing wrong with saying that perhaps the &#8220;Jewish problem&#8221; will not be solved (=has not been solved) by yet another nation state. It&#8217;s a valid position, a legal one, and one held by  members of Israel&#8217;s governing coalition. I don&#8217;t see why not let Prof. Boyarin voice his opinions on that and other matters. It&#8217;s definitely no less respectable than being a fellow of the Shalem center.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
