<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Tisha BeAv Evening	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/09/tisha-beav-evening/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/09/tisha-beav-evening/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2011 18:28:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Arie Folger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/09/tisha-beav-evening/#comment-3524</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arie Folger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2011 18:28:37 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3988#comment-3524</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Reading your description, and contrasting it with my experience, in Europe, where there is no sermon or explication on 9 Av, but where the service isn&#039;t any shorter, in fact, it is significantly longer, because all kinot are read out loud, sung in fact, in a mournful tune, by congregants who take turns, I wonder whether sometimes, less is not more. Do the speeches, sermons and explanation always add, or does the tune sometimes more than make up for it? I doubt the locals&#039; knowledge of kinot is very different from that of the people you saw. The Hebrew is difficult. But music, humming, mournful humming, transcends the language barrier, I believe. Thoughts?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Reading your description, and contrasting it with my experience, in Europe, where there is no sermon or explication on 9 Av, but where the service isn&#8217;t any shorter, in fact, it is significantly longer, because all kinot are read out loud, sung in fact, in a mournful tune, by congregants who take turns, I wonder whether sometimes, less is not more. Do the speeches, sermons and explanation always add, or does the tune sometimes more than make up for it? I doubt the locals&#8217; knowledge of kinot is very different from that of the people you saw. The Hebrew is difficult. But music, humming, mournful humming, transcends the language barrier, I believe. Thoughts?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: vernue		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/09/tisha-beav-evening/#comment-3512</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[vernue]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2011 10:42:54 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3988#comment-3512</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[ellie, if you see what we are mourning for on tba as a building, a government, a state, then you are right.  but why was it that the bavlim and the romans destroyed  just a building - what we are mourning is what we did to make it just a building - sinat hinam, immorality, and on and on.  we are (i am) mourning the spiritual condition of our people today that perpetuate that situation, and my part in contributing to that spiritual condition.  i am mourning the closeness that existed between us and hashem when we merited the bet hamikdash, as expressed in korbanot (sacrifices - closeness) that no longer exists.  i can see how  you might say, sacrifices - primitive (well, i can only see you saying that if you&#039;re a vegetarian).  But certainly a ritualized slaughter of animal, using that animal death as a way of internalizing what it means to be a human in a relationship with hashem - we might not understand how that works, but perhaps we should just say we don&#039;t understand rather than judge it.  Just as on pesah we should see ourselves as though we were taken from egypt, on tba we should also see ourselves as though it was we who were sent into exile.  one of the kinot says that, the repeating refrain - when i left egypt - when i left yerushalayim.  and if we really don&#039;t care that we are in exile (i don&#039;t mean just not living in israel), then, buddy, that really is something to mourn.
shabbat shalom.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ellie, if you see what we are mourning for on tba as a building, a government, a state, then you are right.  but why was it that the bavlim and the romans destroyed  just a building &#8211; what we are mourning is what we did to make it just a building &#8211; sinat hinam, immorality, and on and on.  we are (i am) mourning the spiritual condition of our people today that perpetuate that situation, and my part in contributing to that spiritual condition.  i am mourning the closeness that existed between us and hashem when we merited the bet hamikdash, as expressed in korbanot (sacrifices &#8211; closeness) that no longer exists.  i can see how  you might say, sacrifices &#8211; primitive (well, i can only see you saying that if you&#8217;re a vegetarian).  But certainly a ritualized slaughter of animal, using that animal death as a way of internalizing what it means to be a human in a relationship with hashem &#8211; we might not understand how that works, but perhaps we should just say we don&#8217;t understand rather than judge it.  Just as on pesah we should see ourselves as though we were taken from egypt, on tba we should also see ourselves as though it was we who were sent into exile.  one of the kinot says that, the repeating refrain &#8211; when i left egypt &#8211; when i left yerushalayim.  and if we really don&#8217;t care that we are in exile (i don&#8217;t mean just not living in israel), then, buddy, that really is something to mourn.<br />
shabbat shalom.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Larry Yudelson		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/09/tisha-beav-evening/#comment-3503</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Larry Yudelson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2011 19:31:54 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3988#comment-3503</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[For the first time, I miss the monarchy. Having a scion of David ruling Israel would give the protesters a target for their anger and a concrete proposal for action. I wonder how his response and fate would compare to that of Assad and Mubarak... or would King David II be wise like King Abdullah, and promise the people prosperity, relatively free speech, and an ecologically-conscious Star Trek theme park?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For the first time, I miss the monarchy. Having a scion of David ruling Israel would give the protesters a target for their anger and a concrete proposal for action. I wonder how his response and fate would compare to that of Assad and Mubarak&#8230; or would King David II be wise like King Abdullah, and promise the people prosperity, relatively free speech, and an ecologically-conscious Star Trek theme park?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Alan Mayer		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/09/tisha-beav-evening/#comment-3499</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Mayer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2011 16:47:42 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3988#comment-3499</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/09/tisha-beav-evening/#comment-3484&quot;&gt;Alan Brill&lt;/a&gt;.

Alan Brill!!  Yehudah sent this to me though I didn&#039;t realize it was you till now.  It brings our little corner of Morgenstern back together. 
Reading your piece it brought me back to my years in summer camp where  Tisha B&#039;av was one of the most compelling religious days of the year. I remember each bunk gathering together on their porch and then joining the 20 minute silent torch lit march down to the lake where we all sat on the ground with our flashlights and listened as Eicha was read aloud - watching it as it floated across the lake in stillness.  800 kids together in one space and for one night each summer nobody spoke, nobody joked, nobody broke the silence or the spell - miracle enough for a day in need of miracles.  The melody and that lake still haunt my memories with an intense feeling of sorrow and loss.  It transformed us all for those few hours from a group of your typical loud and noisy kids into something else - dare I suggest a congregation or even a community in mourning. It was one of the few memories where religion and spirituality coexisted so perfectly.

The sadnesss of it all is not just that the adults are unable or uninterested in creating that holy and solemn space together, but that their children - sitting in their play chairs -  will never know that wonderful bittersweet feeling of loss, and the promise of redemption.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/09/tisha-beav-evening/#comment-3484">Alan Brill</a>.</p>
<p>Alan Brill!!  Yehudah sent this to me though I didn&#8217;t realize it was you till now.  It brings our little corner of Morgenstern back together.<br />
Reading your piece it brought me back to my years in summer camp where  Tisha B&#8217;av was one of the most compelling religious days of the year. I remember each bunk gathering together on their porch and then joining the 20 minute silent torch lit march down to the lake where we all sat on the ground with our flashlights and listened as Eicha was read aloud &#8211; watching it as it floated across the lake in stillness.  800 kids together in one space and for one night each summer nobody spoke, nobody joked, nobody broke the silence or the spell &#8211; miracle enough for a day in need of miracles.  The melody and that lake still haunt my memories with an intense feeling of sorrow and loss.  It transformed us all for those few hours from a group of your typical loud and noisy kids into something else &#8211; dare I suggest a congregation or even a community in mourning. It was one of the few memories where religion and spirituality coexisted so perfectly.</p>
<p>The sadnesss of it all is not just that the adults are unable or uninterested in creating that holy and solemn space together, but that their children &#8211; sitting in their play chairs &#8211;  will never know that wonderful bittersweet feeling of loss, and the promise of redemption.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ellie		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/09/tisha-beav-evening/#comment-3498</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ellie]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2011 16:01:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3988#comment-3498</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A day that is meant to mourn destruction of a temple that people don&#039;t really want back. Perhaps it&#039;s true about keeping Judaism relevant on a larger scale, perhaps it&#039;s more true in the states than in Israel, more true for the MO than the yeshevish. I don&#039;t know. But I do know that it&#039;s a problem-- mourning this temple. Does anyone really want it back, the way it was? Can we really blame people for not feeling the tragedy of the missing building? The missing monarchy? The missing theocracy? Tisha Bav seems more complicated in Israel than here, even- since the struggle is real to figure out what works and what does not. 
Of course there are real tragedies to mourn- the holocaust, the inquisition, crusades, etc. But the main tragedies of the day are lost to me. And I think they are lost to most people.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A day that is meant to mourn destruction of a temple that people don&#8217;t really want back. Perhaps it&#8217;s true about keeping Judaism relevant on a larger scale, perhaps it&#8217;s more true in the states than in Israel, more true for the MO than the yeshevish. I don&#8217;t know. But I do know that it&#8217;s a problem&#8211; mourning this temple. Does anyone really want it back, the way it was? Can we really blame people for not feeling the tragedy of the missing building? The missing monarchy? The missing theocracy? Tisha Bav seems more complicated in Israel than here, even- since the struggle is real to figure out what works and what does not.<br />
Of course there are real tragedies to mourn- the holocaust, the inquisition, crusades, etc. But the main tragedies of the day are lost to me. And I think they are lost to most people.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: vernue		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/09/tisha-beav-evening/#comment-3496</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[vernue]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2011 09:35:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3988#comment-3496</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[My erev tisha b&#039;av,

we gathered in a almond grove at the bottom of the tel which once was the home of the mishkan, men and women sitting separate, some children playing with flashlights, but most sitting with their family or friends.  After ma&#039;ariv, five men took turns, each reading a perek from eicha.  Some who read were weeping - I&#039;m not one who much cares for weeping during the tfila because it always seems forced - but these men, even after they read, were weeping.  After eicha, kinot.  No one left, no iphones, no extraneous talking.  Afterwards, a rav who we all love and respect stood and spoke some words - I guess one would say of tochacha, but really words that were meant to show directions which we way have missed, to examine our ways.  We walked back to our cars in the darkness, together.

my intent is not to deride.  I know how difficult it is in the States to be focused on the spiritual.  But I feel like the elders of Yisrael who came to the elders of Reuven Gad and hetzi shevet Menashe after they built the mizbeah at glilot hayarden (yehoshua 22?) - if the land in which you have settled is impure, then come here and we shall make a nahala for you in eretz yisrael.  

we should all merit the consciousness to build the mikdash within, so that we may merit to build the mikdash in Yerushalayim]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My erev tisha b&#8217;av,</p>
<p>we gathered in a almond grove at the bottom of the tel which once was the home of the mishkan, men and women sitting separate, some children playing with flashlights, but most sitting with their family or friends.  After ma&#8217;ariv, five men took turns, each reading a perek from eicha.  Some who read were weeping &#8211; I&#8217;m not one who much cares for weeping during the tfila because it always seems forced &#8211; but these men, even after they read, were weeping.  After eicha, kinot.  No one left, no iphones, no extraneous talking.  Afterwards, a rav who we all love and respect stood and spoke some words &#8211; I guess one would say of tochacha, but really words that were meant to show directions which we way have missed, to examine our ways.  We walked back to our cars in the darkness, together.</p>
<p>my intent is not to deride.  I know how difficult it is in the States to be focused on the spiritual.  But I feel like the elders of Yisrael who came to the elders of Reuven Gad and hetzi shevet Menashe after they built the mizbeah at glilot hayarden (yehoshua 22?) &#8211; if the land in which you have settled is impure, then come here and we shall make a nahala for you in eretz yisrael.  </p>
<p>we should all merit the consciousness to build the mikdash within, so that we may merit to build the mikdash in Yerushalayim</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Jonathan		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/09/tisha-beav-evening/#comment-3494</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jonathan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2011 23:35:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3988#comment-3494</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I guess the question is: you described  what you saw, now we should explore why they acted that way.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I guess the question is: you described  what you saw, now we should explore why they acted that way.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Mark		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/09/tisha-beav-evening/#comment-3493</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mark]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2011 17:56:30 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3988#comment-3493</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Some people are into it and some people aren&#039;t. That&#039;s life.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Some people are into it and some people aren&#8217;t. That&#8217;s life.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/09/tisha-beav-evening/#comment-3492</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2011 17:25:13 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3988#comment-3492</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[We couldbe melameed zechus on people as follows . Monday was a horrendous day in the market. The feeling everywhere is that the world financial system is unraveling, and there will be no place to run. Everything goes down, people run to Treasuries and then suddenly there will be hyper-inflation. When the market is down ten percent, most portfolios are down more, because in order to get a return unzerer yiden pile into stocks with high volatility, and then depending on what they feel forced to earn, add leverage. A typical guy could have seen 20% of his weath disappear in a few days. Who wouldn&#039;t be upset? And who has the strength not to think of today&#039;s tzurus on Tisha Beav. If the rabbi proposal of kinot for 1492 is appropriate, the current situation where entire countries, (Greece, Italy,  maybe France) are going bankrupt deserves at least a sigh.

We should all be proud of how these anxieties are playing out in Israel where 300,000 demoinstrators came out in protest of neo-liberalism. In England, they are rioting, and in America these anxieties have led to the tea party in Israel they dream of social justice. I find it interesting that no blogger or Orthodox paper has though the demonstrations in Israel of any great signi8cance.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We couldbe melameed zechus on people as follows . Monday was a horrendous day in the market. The feeling everywhere is that the world financial system is unraveling, and there will be no place to run. Everything goes down, people run to Treasuries and then suddenly there will be hyper-inflation. When the market is down ten percent, most portfolios are down more, because in order to get a return unzerer yiden pile into stocks with high volatility, and then depending on what they feel forced to earn, add leverage. A typical guy could have seen 20% of his weath disappear in a few days. Who wouldn&#8217;t be upset? And who has the strength not to think of today&#8217;s tzurus on Tisha Beav. If the rabbi proposal of kinot for 1492 is appropriate, the current situation where entire countries, (Greece, Italy,  maybe France) are going bankrupt deserves at least a sigh.</p>
<p>We should all be proud of how these anxieties are playing out in Israel where 300,000 demoinstrators came out in protest of neo-liberalism. In England, they are rioting, and in America these anxieties have led to the tea party in Israel they dream of social justice. I find it interesting that no blogger or Orthodox paper has though the demonstrations in Israel of any great signi8cance.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ysh		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/09/tisha-beav-evening/#comment-3491</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ysh]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2011 17:16:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3988#comment-3491</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/09/tisha-beav-evening/#comment-3487&quot;&gt;Alan Brill&lt;/a&gt;.

This is not a new issue.  Can&#039;t the same be said of any davening?  For example, does anyone in a large MO shul really feel the aimah and yirah of RH and YK they felt at yeshiva in Israel (or that their [great-]grandparents felt in the shtetl?   The only difference is the presence of the i-phone in public since it wasn&#039;t Shabbat or YT.  Your disappointment shouldn&#039;t be a result of Kinot on 9 Av.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/09/tisha-beav-evening/#comment-3487">Alan Brill</a>.</p>
<p>This is not a new issue.  Can&#8217;t the same be said of any davening?  For example, does anyone in a large MO shul really feel the aimah and yirah of RH and YK they felt at yeshiva in Israel (or that their [great-]grandparents felt in the shtetl?   The only difference is the presence of the i-phone in public since it wasn&#8217;t Shabbat or YT.  Your disappointment shouldn&#8217;t be a result of Kinot on 9 Av.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: tesyaa		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/09/tisha-beav-evening/#comment-3490</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tesyaa]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2011 16:26:48 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3988#comment-3490</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/09/tisha-beav-evening/#comment-3489&quot;&gt;Cheryl&lt;/a&gt;.

&lt;i&gt;I think in my innocence I expect more from people. &lt;/i&gt;

In some ways I&#039;ve become cynical, because I used to expect more from people too.  However, I found I  didn&#039;t benefit from expecting more from other people.  

You can look for more elsewhere, as in a more right-wing community, but you may be disappointed there as well (in all likelihood).  

It&#039;s really better imho not to look at other people, or if you do, look for the good, not what&#039;s disappointing.  You will always find something disappointing.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/09/tisha-beav-evening/#comment-3489">Cheryl</a>.</p>
<p><i>I think in my innocence I expect more from people. </i></p>
<p>In some ways I&#8217;ve become cynical, because I used to expect more from people too.  However, I found I  didn&#8217;t benefit from expecting more from other people.  </p>
<p>You can look for more elsewhere, as in a more right-wing community, but you may be disappointed there as well (in all likelihood).  </p>
<p>It&#8217;s really better imho not to look at other people, or if you do, look for the good, not what&#8217;s disappointing.  You will always find something disappointing.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Cheryl		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/09/tisha-beav-evening/#comment-3489</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cheryl]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2011 16:18:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3988#comment-3489</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Jesse,
I&#039;m not misunderstanding or exploiting the post. I think in my innocence I expect more from people. There are certain basic things we are taught that are and are not done in every situation. No leather shoes during shiva and on Tisha B&#039;Av, done. No jewelry on both as well. I felt disappointed by the report.

Tesyaa,
It is nice people showed up but how much credit do you really get? You don&#039;t get passed to the next grade in school for just showing up and besides, what else are you going to do Tisha B&#039;av night? go to the movies?

I just felt very sad and empty by the post.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Jesse,<br />
I&#8217;m not misunderstanding or exploiting the post. I think in my innocence I expect more from people. There are certain basic things we are taught that are and are not done in every situation. No leather shoes during shiva and on Tisha B&#8217;Av, done. No jewelry on both as well. I felt disappointed by the report.</p>
<p>Tesyaa,<br />
It is nice people showed up but how much credit do you really get? You don&#8217;t get passed to the next grade in school for just showing up and besides, what else are you going to do Tisha B&#8217;av night? go to the movies?</p>
<p>I just felt very sad and empty by the post.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Saul		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/08/09/tisha-beav-evening/#comment-3488</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Saul]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2011 15:41:50 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3988#comment-3488</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Hopefully, with over 500 in attendance you were just in the wrong section of the shul.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hopefully, with over 500 in attendance you were just in the wrong section of the shul.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
