<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Ramhal as expressing 18th century Enlightenment values	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/25/ramhal-as-expressing-18th-century-enlightenment-values/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/25/ramhal-as-expressing-18th-century-enlightenment-values/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2011 22:02:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: billyphillips7		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/25/ramhal-as-expressing-18th-century-enlightenment-values/#comment-2545</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[billyphillips7]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2011 22:02:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2906#comment-2545</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I am the lecturer who presented material on Valle. And yes, Valle says there were &quot;repugnant lies&quot; made up about the teachings of Jesus and that he came to bring the true Torah to the gentile world. That was his role. Valle refers to Zechariah ans the verse describing the Jewish man who the gentile nations hang onto by the shirt tails (tzit tzit).

 The Arizal says something profoundly similar: that the reason for the continued exile is that the gentile nations cannot extract themselves out of the klippah. Only the soul of Torah, the essence, the Zohar, the wisdom and energy of Kabbalah has that power and that is why the Israelites are sent out into the world. And if they fail, then there will be persecutions against them. Valle&#039;s criticism of Christianity is nuanced, subtle and profound, as he explains how the Israelites were forced to endure exile among the idol worshipping nations as a result of the sin of the Golden Calf and destruction of the temples. Christianity, when taken literally, appears to be idol-worshipping. But through the lens of Kabbalah, it is Torah. This was God&#039;s way of providing a lifeline, an umbilical cord back to the Torah for the pagans and Israelites who assimilated into this world, while they endured exile. 

Valle says we must correct the lies about Jesus&#039; teachings and the connection to Torah in order to bring about the redemption. He says Christians have it wrong and the Jews have it wrong. Only Kabbalah can explain the conflict and reveal the underlying unity.

--billy phillips]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I am the lecturer who presented material on Valle. And yes, Valle says there were &#8220;repugnant lies&#8221; made up about the teachings of Jesus and that he came to bring the true Torah to the gentile world. That was his role. Valle refers to Zechariah ans the verse describing the Jewish man who the gentile nations hang onto by the shirt tails (tzit tzit).</p>
<p> The Arizal says something profoundly similar: that the reason for the continued exile is that the gentile nations cannot extract themselves out of the klippah. Only the soul of Torah, the essence, the Zohar, the wisdom and energy of Kabbalah has that power and that is why the Israelites are sent out into the world. And if they fail, then there will be persecutions against them. Valle&#8217;s criticism of Christianity is nuanced, subtle and profound, as he explains how the Israelites were forced to endure exile among the idol worshipping nations as a result of the sin of the Golden Calf and destruction of the temples. Christianity, when taken literally, appears to be idol-worshipping. But through the lens of Kabbalah, it is Torah. This was God&#8217;s way of providing a lifeline, an umbilical cord back to the Torah for the pagans and Israelites who assimilated into this world, while they endured exile. </p>
<p>Valle says we must correct the lies about Jesus&#8217; teachings and the connection to Torah in order to bring about the redemption. He says Christians have it wrong and the Jews have it wrong. Only Kabbalah can explain the conflict and reveal the underlying unity.</p>
<p>&#8211;billy phillips</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: avraham rosenblum		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/01/25/ramhal-as-expressing-18th-century-enlightenment-values/#comment-2471</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[avraham rosenblum]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 Jan 2011 15:57:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2906#comment-2471</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I am bothered by the fact that there does not seem to be much interface between the enlightenment thinkers  and the kabalah.This bothers me because i feel that the arizal had great insight not just into the higher spiritual worlds but also into the human soul. I admit the application of the ari to the soul seem to be more of an emphasis of rebbi nachman but still i feel it is inherent in the ari.
Yet Ari nor the gra nor rebbi nachman deal with the important issues of the enlightenment.
First of all a lot of the force behind the enlightenment was Hobbes  and the insight that the type of virtue of priest and princes was abject failure .
The enlightenment was an attempt to create a new type of virtue--the industrious man who is selfish in an enlightened way (IE bourgeois).
This paints a very shallow picture of a human being. So while i can see the importance of the dept of the kabala i am disappointed at the lack of dealing with the fact that medieval virtue was a failure.

(edited by site owner)

So Again why i see kabalah as the was out of this horrible mess we are in--i am bothered that there does not seem to be any interface between it and modern issues. Kabala&#039;s values seem to be a straightforward reversion to the middle ages.  That might be better than anything else out there but it still does not answer the problem that medieval values are medieval. 
Or put better our problem is we don&#039;t have a thinker of the stature of the rambam.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I am bothered by the fact that there does not seem to be much interface between the enlightenment thinkers  and the kabalah.This bothers me because i feel that the arizal had great insight not just into the higher spiritual worlds but also into the human soul. I admit the application of the ari to the soul seem to be more of an emphasis of rebbi nachman but still i feel it is inherent in the ari.<br />
Yet Ari nor the gra nor rebbi nachman deal with the important issues of the enlightenment.<br />
First of all a lot of the force behind the enlightenment was Hobbes  and the insight that the type of virtue of priest and princes was abject failure .<br />
The enlightenment was an attempt to create a new type of virtue&#8211;the industrious man who is selfish in an enlightened way (IE bourgeois).<br />
This paints a very shallow picture of a human being. So while i can see the importance of the dept of the kabala i am disappointed at the lack of dealing with the fact that medieval virtue was a failure.</p>
<p>(edited by site owner)</p>
<p>So Again why i see kabalah as the was out of this horrible mess we are in&#8211;i am bothered that there does not seem to be any interface between it and modern issues. Kabala&#8217;s values seem to be a straightforward reversion to the middle ages.  That might be better than anything else out there but it still does not answer the problem that medieval values are medieval.<br />
Or put better our problem is we don&#8217;t have a thinker of the stature of the rambam.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
