<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Rav Aviner- Democracy as the Will of the Jewish People	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/12/28/rav-aviner-democracy-as-the-will-of-the-people-what-would-ej-say/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/12/28/rav-aviner-democracy-as-the-will-of-the-people-what-would-ej-say/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Dec 2010 02:15:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/12/28/rav-aviner-democracy-as-the-will-of-the-people-what-would-ej-say/#comment-2297</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 30 Dec 2010 02:15:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2683#comment-2297</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I have a problem with the general schema of Rabbl Folger&#039;s comments. He is in favor of  Israel being governed along liberal democratic principles. His argument is that there are special conditions that must be changed before it is reasonable to expect a movement towards democracy. Thus not much can be expected of Rabbi Aviner unless all actors, right and left, slowly inch towards a different way of thinking, which in turn is unlikely because of the Israeli system of coalition politics. And again he doubts if the Israeli  inability to see the other as having a valid point  can truly change as long as the surrounding nations don’t.
It would seem the day when Israel will be ready for democracy similar to the standards in other Western countries is lo hawya vlo nivra...there will never be such a day, which may indeed turn out to be be correct. But then, and this is my first point, it is not an exception, a special situation, it&#039;s how it is period. We know that if you allow for a liberal use of exceptions, there is hardly an authoritarian or even fascist government that cannot be justified. In America according to Bush and now Obama ever since 9/11 we are at war with al-Qaeda. Because of this exceptional situation where we are threatened domestically, certain civil liberties must be suspended, even if this war lasts forever. The trick is always the same...we want the good stuff but alas not now because we are living in a special situation. Cameron in the UK wants to help the lower middle class and poor, but he must institute draconian cuts because it&#039;s a crisis. Paulson gave a trillion dollars to the bankers who caused the problem, again because it was a crisis. Israel between the Holocaust and the many  wars and enemies has never had a day which wasn&#039;t an exception, when they weren&#039;t in crisis. Perpetual traumatization.

I don&#039;t quite know how to counter this Carl Schmidt type rhetoric, nor does the left in general. Where ever you look the social democratic left is in disarray. What I was trying to say in my initial comment on Rawls is that changing the language, by just repeating the ideas of what makes a society right and just  as if it is possible now, yes crisis or no crisis, is I hope, an effective method of bringing change.

Tell me again Rabbi Aviner why can&#039;t there be a tradeoff between a Jewish state and a just state? Why must they be lexically ordered? Why should a state created by secular Zionists be goverened by the visions of the Rabbi Kooks. Are dead rabbis sovereign? And so on ....
To say that justice is the first vitue of a society, not efficiency, or pleasing the clergy means not to accept anti-decency rhetoric as the way things are; it means being political and pushing back.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have a problem with the general schema of Rabbl Folger&#8217;s comments. He is in favor of  Israel being governed along liberal democratic principles. His argument is that there are special conditions that must be changed before it is reasonable to expect a movement towards democracy. Thus not much can be expected of Rabbi Aviner unless all actors, right and left, slowly inch towards a different way of thinking, which in turn is unlikely because of the Israeli system of coalition politics. And again he doubts if the Israeli  inability to see the other as having a valid point  can truly change as long as the surrounding nations don’t.<br />
It would seem the day when Israel will be ready for democracy similar to the standards in other Western countries is lo hawya vlo nivra&#8230;there will never be such a day, which may indeed turn out to be be correct. But then, and this is my first point, it is not an exception, a special situation, it&#8217;s how it is period. We know that if you allow for a liberal use of exceptions, there is hardly an authoritarian or even fascist government that cannot be justified. In America according to Bush and now Obama ever since 9/11 we are at war with al-Qaeda. Because of this exceptional situation where we are threatened domestically, certain civil liberties must be suspended, even if this war lasts forever. The trick is always the same&#8230;we want the good stuff but alas not now because we are living in a special situation. Cameron in the UK wants to help the lower middle class and poor, but he must institute draconian cuts because it&#8217;s a crisis. Paulson gave a trillion dollars to the bankers who caused the problem, again because it was a crisis. Israel between the Holocaust and the many  wars and enemies has never had a day which wasn&#8217;t an exception, when they weren&#8217;t in crisis. Perpetual traumatization.</p>
<p>I don&#8217;t quite know how to counter this Carl Schmidt type rhetoric, nor does the left in general. Where ever you look the social democratic left is in disarray. What I was trying to say in my initial comment on Rawls is that changing the language, by just repeating the ideas of what makes a society right and just  as if it is possible now, yes crisis or no crisis, is I hope, an effective method of bringing change.</p>
<p>Tell me again Rabbi Aviner why can&#8217;t there be a tradeoff between a Jewish state and a just state? Why must they be lexically ordered? Why should a state created by secular Zionists be goverened by the visions of the Rabbi Kooks. Are dead rabbis sovereign? And so on &#8230;.<br />
To say that justice is the first vitue of a society, not efficiency, or pleasing the clergy means not to accept anti-decency rhetoric as the way things are; it means being political and pushing back.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Arie Folger		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/12/28/rav-aviner-democracy-as-the-will-of-the-people-what-would-ej-say/#comment-2282</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Arie Folger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2010 11:16:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2683#comment-2282</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I think it is difficult if not impossible to evaluate the actions and statements of one actor, even an ideological, thoughtful actor, in a vacuum. Israeli democracy has a particular form that does not function according to the unwritten rules of France, Belgium, Switzerland or the US. Every political system, political culture and political tradition leaves its long term impact, a kind of signature, on the actions of its constituent leaders. Thus, the kind of debates and forms of expressions are quite different in the various democratic parliaments.

While it may be all the more fascinating for visitors to watch a session of those respective parliaments in action, it does make it harder to compare the statements of the political actors.

Concretely, the American political system encourages politicians to work on behalf of the entire population of their districts, not just their voters, because there is a real chance they will convince voters in their districts to support the incumbent the next time around. The representative is also the sole boss over his district at his level of government, or share the dias with a limited number of other actors. In a proportional democracy, the competition is national, and there is a lot of work going on to advance within the hierarchy of one&#039;s own party, to be closer to the top of the list.

All the above is exacerbated by the Israeli political culture, where politicians constantly lobby for their own national constituency, and jostle for prestige within the party. It is this aspect of Israeli political culture, more than anything else, that hurts the notions of equality. One cannot get R&#039; Aviner or the signatories to the ban on renting to Arabs, to truly change, unless all actors, right and left, slowly inch towards a different way of thinking. Because of coalition politics, parties also seem to see their time in the coalition as a time to achieve a maximum number of things they care about at the expense of all others, because that&#039;s how everybody acts.

I am not sure what is the way out of that quagmire, which, in my mind, is a far greater threat of internal cohesion in Israel, but I do know that everybody there is guilty of it. I vividly recall a prime minister expressing himself regarding demonstrations by the opposition, in a way that would not only never fly in Europe, but be actually inconceivable.

The present failures of Israeli politics aren&#039;t only about a measure of racism in a beleaguered country, but the almost inability to see the other as having a valid point, be that other Arab or Jew. And that fault is even worse in the Palestinian Arab public. Which in turn, leads me to ask whether it is even possible to truly change the Israeli political culture as long as the surrounding nations don&#039;t.

Does Rawls only apply to ideals in law and politics, or also in effecting change so that a society can come closer to implementing his ideas?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think it is difficult if not impossible to evaluate the actions and statements of one actor, even an ideological, thoughtful actor, in a vacuum. Israeli democracy has a particular form that does not function according to the unwritten rules of France, Belgium, Switzerland or the US. Every political system, political culture and political tradition leaves its long term impact, a kind of signature, on the actions of its constituent leaders. Thus, the kind of debates and forms of expressions are quite different in the various democratic parliaments.</p>
<p>While it may be all the more fascinating for visitors to watch a session of those respective parliaments in action, it does make it harder to compare the statements of the political actors.</p>
<p>Concretely, the American political system encourages politicians to work on behalf of the entire population of their districts, not just their voters, because there is a real chance they will convince voters in their districts to support the incumbent the next time around. The representative is also the sole boss over his district at his level of government, or share the dias with a limited number of other actors. In a proportional democracy, the competition is national, and there is a lot of work going on to advance within the hierarchy of one&#8217;s own party, to be closer to the top of the list.</p>
<p>All the above is exacerbated by the Israeli political culture, where politicians constantly lobby for their own national constituency, and jostle for prestige within the party. It is this aspect of Israeli political culture, more than anything else, that hurts the notions of equality. One cannot get R&#8217; Aviner or the signatories to the ban on renting to Arabs, to truly change, unless all actors, right and left, slowly inch towards a different way of thinking. Because of coalition politics, parties also seem to see their time in the coalition as a time to achieve a maximum number of things they care about at the expense of all others, because that&#8217;s how everybody acts.</p>
<p>I am not sure what is the way out of that quagmire, which, in my mind, is a far greater threat of internal cohesion in Israel, but I do know that everybody there is guilty of it. I vividly recall a prime minister expressing himself regarding demonstrations by the opposition, in a way that would not only never fly in Europe, but be actually inconceivable.</p>
<p>The present failures of Israeli politics aren&#8217;t only about a measure of racism in a beleaguered country, but the almost inability to see the other as having a valid point, be that other Arab or Jew. And that fault is even worse in the Palestinian Arab public. Which in turn, leads me to ask whether it is even possible to truly change the Israeli political culture as long as the surrounding nations don&#8217;t.</p>
<p>Does Rawls only apply to ideals in law and politics, or also in effecting change so that a society can come closer to implementing his ideas?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/12/28/rav-aviner-democracy-as-the-will-of-the-people-what-would-ej-say/#comment-2279</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Dec 2010 19:11:24 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2683#comment-2279</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[To be fair, it is not just Israel that struggles with the question of what Democracy means. Does it necessitate liberalism or can it function without it? Can nationalism sometimes trump liberalism and can liberalism trump the free exercise of anti-liberal religious or ethnic practices?

Americans like to think that the Constitution somehow insures that there is a simple answer to these questions, but in truth it is the rapid assimilation of minorities that has gone the farthest to avoid major conflicts. A country like Israel, which is truly riven by religious, ideological and ethnic differences was never going to be an easy democracy to hold together. And is more likely to fall victim to the small mindedness of special-interest party parliamentary maneuvering. 

R. Aviner&#039;s problem (rather, my problem with him)  is not his definition of democracy per se, it is his identification of the will of the Jews as a trans-historic will that is inherent in every Jew, religious or secular, yearning toward religious-national redemption, hence the quote from Herzl. If that is the will that a Jewish democracy must instantiate then all questions are already closed. Democracy just becomes the shape that that the spirit of the Jews inhabits at this political moment, not an inherently valuable institution by which the public will is shaped, refined and expressed via deliberative processes.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>To be fair, it is not just Israel that struggles with the question of what Democracy means. Does it necessitate liberalism or can it function without it? Can nationalism sometimes trump liberalism and can liberalism trump the free exercise of anti-liberal religious or ethnic practices?</p>
<p>Americans like to think that the Constitution somehow insures that there is a simple answer to these questions, but in truth it is the rapid assimilation of minorities that has gone the farthest to avoid major conflicts. A country like Israel, which is truly riven by religious, ideological and ethnic differences was never going to be an easy democracy to hold together. And is more likely to fall victim to the small mindedness of special-interest party parliamentary maneuvering. </p>
<p>R. Aviner&#8217;s problem (rather, my problem with him)  is not his definition of democracy per se, it is his identification of the will of the Jews as a trans-historic will that is inherent in every Jew, religious or secular, yearning toward religious-national redemption, hence the quote from Herzl. If that is the will that a Jewish democracy must instantiate then all questions are already closed. Democracy just becomes the shape that that the spirit of the Jews inhabits at this political moment, not an inherently valuable institution by which the public will is shaped, refined and expressed via deliberative processes.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/12/28/rav-aviner-democracy-as-the-will-of-the-people-what-would-ej-say/#comment-2278</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Dec 2010 19:02:29 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2683#comment-2278</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I think the particular example you chose is not the best way to discuss how Israeli democracy can be established in a broader, fairer way. If you read the discussions in the press, paranoia is operating on both sides. The left sees these measures as code for an eventual ethnic cleansing where the Israeli Arabs will be forced to leave. It also feels these loyalty oaths  are asking the Israeli Arabs to accept as just all the inequalities they feel attached to the idea of a Jewish state. 
It seems to me unequal opportunity is a clearer, less symbolic issue, where there are concrete facts that would be relevant. Have the Israeli Arabs been allowed to build new communities within Israel? Are they give the same subsidies as Jewish Israelis?  Do they have roughly equal opportunities in education and employment? If not, why not? Each sub-issue  should be looked at separately in the hope that fair and equal treatment would in time increase the loyalty of this community. 
There are also symbolic issues that go a long way in  creating loyal citizens. I remember the fears we all had here in Chicago after the riots in 1967(?), when the blacks  burnt down so much of the West Side, driving all Jewish business out of the area. Chicago today remains a segregated city, inequalities in America have grown wider decade by decade. The blacks may have had some relative improvement, but now are much less significant a force given the new huge  Latino community. What has changed are the attitudes of whites, and their willingness to accept symbolic change, a black police chief, a black Mayor, a mea culpa of the Kerner report, Oprah and more Oprah. The change in the white attitudes has kept relations between black and whites on an even keel. The blacks are no longer demonized, they know this, and life has improved for both groups. 
Is this mutual respect and acknowledgement part of a liberal Rawlsian vision? I believe so. Is this a cover up for cosmetic changes in what is really a master slave relationship? I’ll leave this last question to the left Hegelians. 
PS...While I appreciate the honor,  I feel uncomfortable seeing my handle as part of the heading of your posts...&quot;EJ and Rawls, What would EJ say?&quot; I post my opinions, but I am just a blogger, a single person, and apparently a blogger who at times is subject to serious philosophical confusions. I am here to talk in learning, no different than  the many  other commentators who are interested in deepening their understanding by the back and forth of discussions.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think the particular example you chose is not the best way to discuss how Israeli democracy can be established in a broader, fairer way. If you read the discussions in the press, paranoia is operating on both sides. The left sees these measures as code for an eventual ethnic cleansing where the Israeli Arabs will be forced to leave. It also feels these loyalty oaths  are asking the Israeli Arabs to accept as just all the inequalities they feel attached to the idea of a Jewish state.<br />
It seems to me unequal opportunity is a clearer, less symbolic issue, where there are concrete facts that would be relevant. Have the Israeli Arabs been allowed to build new communities within Israel? Are they give the same subsidies as Jewish Israelis?  Do they have roughly equal opportunities in education and employment? If not, why not? Each sub-issue  should be looked at separately in the hope that fair and equal treatment would in time increase the loyalty of this community.<br />
There are also symbolic issues that go a long way in  creating loyal citizens. I remember the fears we all had here in Chicago after the riots in 1967(?), when the blacks  burnt down so much of the West Side, driving all Jewish business out of the area. Chicago today remains a segregated city, inequalities in America have grown wider decade by decade. The blacks may have had some relative improvement, but now are much less significant a force given the new huge  Latino community. What has changed are the attitudes of whites, and their willingness to accept symbolic change, a black police chief, a black Mayor, a mea culpa of the Kerner report, Oprah and more Oprah. The change in the white attitudes has kept relations between black and whites on an even keel. The blacks are no longer demonized, they know this, and life has improved for both groups.<br />
Is this mutual respect and acknowledgement part of a liberal Rawlsian vision? I believe so. Is this a cover up for cosmetic changes in what is really a master slave relationship? I’ll leave this last question to the left Hegelians.<br />
PS&#8230;While I appreciate the honor,  I feel uncomfortable seeing my handle as part of the heading of your posts&#8230;&#8221;EJ and Rawls, What would EJ say?&#8221; I post my opinions, but I am just a blogger, a single person, and apparently a blogger who at times is subject to serious philosophical confusions. I am here to talk in learning, no different than  the many  other commentators who are interested in deepening their understanding by the back and forth of discussions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
