<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Jonathan Sacks &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/tag/jonathan-sacks/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Sep 2010 13:20:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='kavvanah.wordpress.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/c9f111237f93750b6b994fc5185d49c3?s=96&#038;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>Jonathan Sacks &#8211; The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="The Book of Doctrines and Opinions:" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>Rabbi Jonathan Sacks- Introductory Speaker for Pope Benedict.</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/09/20/rabbi-jonathan-sacks-introductory-speaker-for-pope-benedict/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/09/20/rabbi-jonathan-sacks-introductory-speaker-for-pope-benedict/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Sep 2010 23:23:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Benedict]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[chief rabbi sacks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[christianity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jewish-christian relations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jonathan Sacks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lord rabbi sacks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pope Benedict]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rabbi sacks chapel speech]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rabbi sacks pope britain]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[reconcilliation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sacks dialouge]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sacks pope britain]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=2015</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Last Friday, the eve of Yom Kippur, Lord Rabbi Jonathan Sacks gave the introductory speech before Pope Benedict addressed and interfaith gathering in the chapel at St Marys University College in Twickenham. Rabbi Sacks seems to have invested a great &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/09/20/rabbi-jonathan-sacks-introductory-speaker-for-pope-benedict/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Last Friday, the eve of Yom Kippur, Lord Rabbi Jonathan Sacks gave the introductory speech before Pope Benedict addressed and interfaith gathering in the chapel at St Marys University College in Twickenham. </p>
<p>Rabbi Sacks seems to have invested a great deal of time and import to the visit. He first prepared his own Jewish community in a message conveying the importance of the event, he then issued a message to the British newspapers, and finally he gave a third message before the religious leaders assembled in the chapel waiting to hear Pope Benedict’s message. In total three messages about the Pope’s visit before Yom Kippur.</p>
<p><em><a href="http://www.chiefrabbi.org/ReadArtical.aspx?id=1675">Atonement and Forgiveness</a></em> was his message for the Jewish community. In this talk, he starts with the persecutions of Judaism by Christianity, but he segues into the Jewish need to recognize the Christian change in attitude and their sincere reconciliation. Catholic and Jews are now friends. The chief rabbis applies the message of Yom Kippur of atonement and forgiveness to the Catholic Church and seeks a healing of the relationship of the two faiths.</p>
<blockquote><p><a href="http://www.chiefrabbi.org/ReadArtical.aspx?id=1675">Selections from &#8220;Atonement and Forgiveness, still have the power to transform relationships&#8221; </a><br />
 The story might have continued were it not for the darkest night of all, the Holocaust. In the wake of that event, a very great Pope indeed, Pope John XXIII, who had helped save many lives in the war years, began to reflect on the history of Christian attitudes toward the Jews, and came to the conclusion that those attitudes must change.  </p>
<p>In 1962 he convened the Second Vatican Council, setting in motion what became three years later, though he did not live to see it, the declaration Nostra Aetate, “In Our Age.” It redefined the relationship between the Catholic Church and other faiths, especially Judaism and Islam. It was one of the greatest acts of reconciliation in religious history, and today Catholics and Jews meet not as enemies or strangers but as friends.  </p>
<p>And by one of those coincidences that seem providential, the night of that meeting, this Friday, will be the beginning of the holiest day of the Jewish year, the Day of Atonement, our festival of forgiveness. How moving it will be, this year, to bear witness to how those two ancient ideas, atonement and forgiveness, still have the power to transform relationships and heal the wounds of time. </p></blockquote>
<p>Rabbi Sack spoke in the chapel as the representative of all non-Catholic faiths. He praises the Vatican for its important Nosta Aetate and its instrumental role in creating an ecumenical environment. Sacks considers the secularization of the Seventeenth Century as due to the inability of religions to live peacefully together. It is interesting to note that Sacks does not quote Torah, rather John Henry Cardinal Newman, and Pope Benedict’s own <em>Caritas in Veritate</em>. In seeming appreciation nd agreement with the Pope, he quotes: &#8220;the development of peoples depends . . . on a recognition that the human race is  a single family, working together in true communion, not simply a group of  subjects who happen to live side by side.&#8221; </p>
<p>Sacks gives his own theology when he states: “We celebrate both our commonalities and differences, because if we had  nothing in common we could not communicate, and if we had everything in common, we would have nothing to say. “ We all have commonalities in faith and we have difference neither side should  be ignored. There is one monotheistic God, but we should give dignity to our differences as enriching the world. </p>
<p>Some of the commonalities of Judaism with Christianity and other religions is that: “We believe in marriage  as a commitment, parenthood as a responsibility, and the poetry of everyday life when it is etched, in homes and schools, with the charisma of holiness and grace.” He continues, “In our communities we value people…for what they are, every one of them a fragment of the Divine presence. We hold life holy. And each of us is lifted by the knowledge that we are part of something greater than all of us, that created  us in forgiveness and love, and asks us to create in forgiveness and love. His further expansion of the ideas of faith itself as important and that we can relate to one another at a universal level of the God in the soul, which encourages engaging the other. “we recognize in one another the presence of faith itself, that habit of the  heart that listens to the music beneath the noise, and knows that God is the point at which soul touches soul and is enlarged by the presence of otherness.” </p>
<p>Sack as a firm believer in having an Establishment Church assumes that “one of our commonalities is that we surely all believe that faith has a major role in strengthening civil society.” </p>
<p>Finally, Sacks concludes with the need to show honor to the Pope who has lead all of us “with wisdom and generosity of spirit, and may all<br />
our efforts combine to become a blessing to humanity and to God.”</p>
<blockquote><p><a href="http://www.chiefrabbi.org/ReadArtical.aspx?id=1678">The entire Opening address at Interfaith gathering for Papal Visit </a></p>
<p>We welcome you, leader of a great faith, to this gathering of many faiths, in a land where once battles were fought in the name of faith,<br />
and where now we share friendship across faiths. </p>
<p>That is a climate change worth celebrating. And we recognize the immense  role the Vatican played and continues to play in bringing it about. It was Nostra Aetate, 45 years ago, that brought about the single greatest transformation in interfaith relations in recent history, and we recognize your visit here today as a new chapter in that story, and a vital one. </p>
<p>The secularization of Europe that began in the seventeenth century  did not happen because people lost faith in God. Newton and Descartes, heroes of the Enlightenment, believed in God very much indeed. What led to  secularization was that people lost faith in the ability of people of faith to live peaceably together. And we must never go down that road again. We remember the fine words of John Henry Cardinal Newman, &#8220;We should ever conduct ourselves towards our enemy as if he were one day to be our friend,&#8221;  as well as your own words, in Caritas in Veritate, that &#8220;the development of peoples depends . . . on a recognition that the human race is  a single family, working together in true communion, not simply a group of  subjects who happen to live side by side.&#8221; </p>
<p>We celebrate both our commonalities and differences, because if we had nothing in common we could not communicate, and if we had everything in common, we would have nothing to say. You have spoken of the  Catholic Church as a creative minority. And perhaps that is what we should all aspire to be, creative minorities, inspiring one another, and bringing our different gifts to the common good. </p>
<p>Britain has been so enriched by its minorities, by every group represented here today and the intricate harmonies of our several voices. And one of our commonalities is that we surely all believe that faith has a major role in  strengthening civil society. </p>
<p>In the face of a deeply individualistic culture, we offer community. Against consumerism, we talk about the things that have value but not a price. Against cynicism we dare to admire and respect. In the face of fragmenting families, we believe in consecrating relationships. We believe in marriage as a commitment, parenthood as a responsibility, and the poetry of everyday life when it is etched, in homes and schools, with the charisma of holiness and grace. </p>
<p>In our communities we value people not for what they earn or what they buy or how they vote but for what they are, every one of them a fragment of the<br />
Divine presence. We hold life holy. And each of us is lifted by the knowledge that we are part of something greater than all of us, that created us in forgiveness and love, and asks us to create in forgiveness and love. Each of us in our own way is a guardian of values that are in danger of being lost, in our short-attention-span, hyperactive, information-saturated,  wisdom-starved age. And though our faiths are profoundly different, yet we recognize in one another the presence of faith itself, that habit of the  heart that listens to the music beneath the noise, and knows that God is the point at which soul touches soul and is enlarged by the presence of  otherness. </p>
<p>You have honoured us with your presence, and we honour you. May you continue to lead with wisdom and generosity of spirit, and may all our efforts combine to become a blessing to humanity and to God. </p></blockquote>
<p>The third piece that Sacks wrote was an op-ed message to the Pope about how the loss of faith in Europe has led to its loss of vitality and decent into a decadence without family, with poverty, suicide, and depression. Sack’s answer is to return to the 19th century values of Newman. A subtext is that the Pope can accomplish more as an intellectual and public religious figure, kinda like Sacks himself, than as the monarch over the Church. </p>
<p>selections from <a href="http://www.chiefrabbi.org/ReadArtical.aspx?id=1674">General message to the Pope</a></p>
<blockquote><p>Times Op Ed &#8211; The Pope will find more glory without power </p>
<p>The current Pope is more than the leader of the largest religious community in the world. He is also a significant public intellectual with a strong sense of history</p>
<p>.According to Save the Children, 3.9 million children are today living in poverty, 1.7 million of them in severe, persistent poverty.  4000 children call Childline every day.  100,000 children run away from home every year. 20 per cent of deaths among young people aged from 15 to 24 are suicides.  In 2009, 29.4 million antidepressants were dispensed, up 334 per cent from 1985. During the same period, Samaritans answered 4.6 million calls from people in distress. An estimated one million elderly people do not see a friend or neighbour during an average week. </p>
<p>These are the kinds of social problem that cannot be solved by government spending. They are the result of the breakdown of families and communities and the loss of trust and social capital. In the broadest sense, they have to do with culture and the lack of a shared moral code. Having lost much of its Christian heritage, Britain does not seem to have found a satisfying substitute.   </p>
<p>Yet in the nineteenth century it became re-moralized in a process in which John Henry Newman, the man Pope Benedict XVI has come to beatify, played a significant part. It was a joint effort of churches, temperance movements, Sunday schools, charities and friendly societies. It was, admittedly, an imperialistic age, but it also saw the abolition of slavery, the birth of universal education, and campaigns against inhuman working conditions and cruel punishments. It showed that national decline is not inevitable. A culture can be renewed Britain </p></blockquote>
<p>The Pope himself was equally enamored with Rabbi Sacks who was specially invited to give the address. He wished Jews “a happy and holy celebration of Yom Kippur.” And resonated with Sacks’ universalism. “I would like to begin my remarks by expressing the Catholic Church’s appreciation for the important witness that all of you bear as spiritual men and women living at a time when religious convictions are not always understood or appreciated.”</p>
<p>Pope Benedict paraphrased one of Rabbi Sacks ideas in his own speech. Sacks talks about working side by side in  making the world better as well as face to face in dialogue. “As followers of different religious traditions working together for the good of the community at large, we attach great importance to this “side by side” dimension of our cooperation, which complements the “face to face” aspect of our continuing dialogue.” Then Pope Benedict translated the two aspects into the Church’s official PCID four aspects.</p>
<blockquote><p>Ever since the Second Vatican Council, the Catholic Church has placed special emphasis on the importance of dialogue and cooperation with the followers of other religions. In order to be fruitful, this requires reciprocity on the part of all partners in dialogue and the followers of other religions…Once such a respect and openness has been established, peoples of all religions will work together effectively for peace and mutual understanding, and so give a convincing witness before the world. </p>
<p>This kind of dialogue needs to take place on a number of different levels, and should not be limited to formal discussions The dialogue of life [a form of &#8220;side by side&#8221; dialogue] involves simply living alongside one another and learning from one another in such a way as to grow in mutual knowledge and respect. The dialogue of action [another form of &#8220;side by side&#8221; dialogue] brings us together in concrete forms of collaboration, as we apply our religious insights to the task of promoting integral human development, working for peace, justice and the stewardship of creation. Such a dialogue may include exploring together how to defend human life at every stage and how to ensure the non-exclusion of the religious dimension of individuals and communities in the life of society. Then at the level of formal conversations [&#8220;face to face&#8221; dialogue], there is a need not only for theological exchange, but also sharing our spiritual riches [formally known as a &#8220;dialogue of religious experience&#8221; ], speaking of our experience of prayer and contemplation, and expressing to one another the joy of our encounter with divine love.</p>
<p>My dear friends, as I conclude my remarks, let me assure you that the Catholic Church follows the path of engagement and dialogue out of a genuine sense of respect for you and your beliefs</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/09/20/rabbi-jonathan-sacks-introductory-speaker-for-pope-benedict/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>7</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Haggadot 2010</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/29/haggadot-2010/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/29/haggadot-2010/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 29 Apr 2010 19:48:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[holidays]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[artscroll]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gra]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[haggadah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jonathan Sacks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Passover haggadah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tabory]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=1201</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I never got around to posting this after Passover, so Pesah Sheni reminded me to get this posted ASAP. All of these are impressions from their use at the table, not in depth studies. JPS Tabory- he is an expert &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/29/haggadot-2010/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I never got around to posting this after Passover, so Pesah Sheni reminded me to get this posted ASAP. All of these are impressions from their use at the table, not in depth studies. </p>
<p>JPS Tabory- he is an expert on the topic and I like his scholarly articles on the Pasover  seder but was disappointed with the haggadah. I blame it more on the editor.  There are points where the comment on the bottom states “Popular theories are not true”  without giving his own opinion. For a popular haggadah just to state that others are false is not good editing.  The introduction was more trendy in scholarship than I expected, cutting edge debates around Israel Yuval’s work and whether  Christianity is the source of the Haggadah and not visa versa. I would have liked more of the basics from his scholarship. And of course he discusses “Pour out they love upon the gentiles.”</p>
<p>This year, I listened to Jonathan Sacks through someone else reading from its comments.  Sacks quotes Primo Levi on the same page as the Hartman’s Haggadah, we have noted in the past his reliance on Hartman’s but the Primo Levi is also quoted in the classic Schoken haggadah by Nachum Glatzer. Sacks was consistently in favor of community at the expense of faithless spirituality and individualism. He even manages to twist a Kotzker statement about letting God into one heart into the need to affirm the future of the community. I was most piqued by his statements about the need for the hope of Jewish history and peoplehood- and the message of the haggadah is not the details of Temple law. Having been acculturated into Brisker appreciation for Temple law- this was unexpected. His language of peoplehood and continuity sounded like a 1950’s Conservative haggadah, I pulled one or two off the shelf, finding the sentiment, but I could not find Sacks exact language</p>
<p>The Carlebach Haggadah was more Holocaust oriented than I remembered. </p>
<p>The  MM Kasher Haggadah where everything is explained as messianic and golly gee whiz we can have a return to the Temple does not seem as innocuous anymore.</p>
<p>Marge Piercy’s mix of Jewish renewal, poetry, and foodie recipes is a nice gift for right person.</p>
<p>The Artscroll Vilna Gaon Haggadah remain a gem for conveying the traditional Lithuanian understanding of the Haggadah. &#8220;Zekher Yetziat mitzrayim as a chance for unending Talmud Torah.&#8221; The Haggadah was not actually written by the Gra. When the Gra died in 1797 – he left behind 10 official books- 8 of them in Kabbalah. There were some early fragments of the Gra on the Haggdah published in 1813 but  in the 1850’s there was a full commentary created. Most people knew the Gra only through this accessible entry point of the haggadh. When ordinary rabbis quoted the Gra this was the volume that they could understand. The volume had an effect on the nusach of the haggadah both on Russian printings and on the American Hebrew Publishing company. I could pick issues with the translation but is nice to have some real Torah transalted.</p>
<p>But I wonder why they don’t translate the Nesivos Haggadah?  The Haggadah Maaseh Nissim of  Rabbi Yaakov Lorberbaum called by his legal commentary Netivot was the major shaper of Eastern European drush on the Haggadah. All these people claiming to wait the view of the mesorah of eastern Europe are not referring to anything spoken at the seder in Europe if they don’t have the Maasah Nissim. </p>
<p>On the other hand, Artscroll did waste their time putting a pile of haggadahs from various contemporary gedolim that are gibberish. I don’t blame the rabbanim and I wont list which ones. But they are quite a few that were sent out as fundraisers by various yeshivas that have vorts that the reader cannot tell if the gadol is telling over the Gra? Differing with the Gra? Offering his own approach to the Gra? Collections of random butchered quotes of Aharonim that only a high pitched tenth grader proving he is stark could love. They should have done the Nesivos instead.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2010/04/29/haggadot-2010/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>8</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lord Jonathan Sacks on the Siddur</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/29/lord-jonathan-sacks-on-the-siddur/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/29/lord-jonathan-sacks-on-the-siddur/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2009 05:44:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[liturgy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[popular religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rabbis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[and dignity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[creation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[faith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Franz Rosenzweig]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hope]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jonathan Sacks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jonathan Sacks Siddur]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[justice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lord sacks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[orthodox universalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[prayer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[redemption]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[revelation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[universalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[witness]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=316</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[1] When I think of certain prayer books commentaries, I sometimes think of them with a few words. Hirsch – moral aspiration, Birnbaum &#8211; historical anti-Semitism Artscroll – Hashem centered,   Rebbe – attachment to God For Sacks, the words are &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/29/lord-jonathan-sacks-on-the-siddur/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>1] When I think of certain prayer books commentaries, I sometimes think of them with a few words. Hirsch – moral aspiration, Birnbaum &#8211; historical anti-Semitism Artscroll – Hashem centered,   Rebbe – attachment to God</p>
<p><strong>For Sacks, the words are hope, faith, and dignity.</strong></p>
<p>Full disclosure – I received a copy from the publisher after <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/08/lord-jonathan-sacks-on-the-concept-of-witness/">my last post on the idea of witness in his thought</a>. In short, my reaction is that his books are generally well crafted and delivered publicly, but here we have short comments not fully explained or justified.</p>
<p>2]  Collective Prayer</p>
<p>His message throughout the siddur is collective faith, we join with others. Prayer concerns the past and future of the community, the people Israel. The prayer is adoration and praise for God – our highest aspirations for the Jewish people. He favors Yehudah Halevi– prayer shows a God of history and human events. We learn from prayer the need to maintain faith, hope, dignity, and pride.</p>
<p>What is prayer? Prayer changes us – it is self-fulfillment He opens the book with a definition that prayer is conversation with God and never actually uses that definition in the book. From his commentary, prayer is listening and shaping oneself from the liturgy. Symbols need meditations therefore many do the yehi ratzon (cf. Hirsch).</p>
<p>His commentary is not very spiritual, emotional, or experiential, despite his use of these words. For example, he states the repetition of the amidah is the peak of religious experience because it contains the kedushah which was based on prophetic and mystic visions. Liturgy is not experience or experiential. Nor will one find much solace or human struggle in the prayer book.</p>
<p>Like the commentaries on Book of Common Prayer – he offers Biblical teachings applied in everyday life. The book is not very Rabbinic.</p>
<p>The commentary on the weekday shaharit is on the history of the liturgy and on the Shabbat shaharit is more theological.</p>
<p>3] Justice</p>
<p>His vision is that prayer will teach us personal and social responsibilitie. There is a cosmic moral standard of justice  God’s eternal values for the affairs of humankind-are justice to the oppressed, food to the hungry, freedom to captives, and hope to those at the margins of society.” Korban (sacrifice) is the pledging of ourselves to do his will. Peace the ultimate hope of monotheism. [Wow – this is nice universalism and good ethical monotheism- will it mold Orthodoxy?]</p>
<p>He writes: We believe that “The world is the product of single will , not the blind clash of conflicting elements”.[what of divine mandated clashes and exclusivism?]</p>
<p>He writes &#8220;Havdalah means making distinctions&#8221;, &#8220;to make order out of chaos, God wants us to be creative.&#8221; That is great homiletic but will it encourage the production of what the wider world calls creativity?</p>
<p>4] Revelation</p>
<p>Sacks writes that in contrast to the universal demands on Jews, Revelation is particular – it is our covenant of love with God – a relationship.Torah is our written constitution, collective memory, and record of covenant- not just sacred literature The message, however, of revelation is the universal justice, compassion, inalienable rights for the downtrodden.[This is the point were I find this commentary as selected quotes from his books on global ethics. Nothing is substantiated or justified here but they are justified in the books.In addition, the books come from speeches delivered in public to answer a need. These comments have no criteria for their inclusion.]</p>
<p>5] Christian locutions</p>
<p>a) Sacks writes that Resurrection is hope “ Jews kept hope alive, hope kept the Jewish people alive.”We have a divine promise and hope defeats tragedy</p>
<p>This is one of my pet peeve – tikvah and spes are not the same even if both translated as hope.</p>
<p>The former word tikvah is restoration –</p>
<p>[There is a debate of Radak and Ramban is if has the same meaning as kav – to make a line.]</p>
<p>Nahmanides says that just as a blueprint has lines drawn so too our tikvah for the national redemption is already drawn. Christian meaning of spes is of unseen things, the future, as part of the supernatural virtues of faith hope, and charity. For Christians hope is a virtue, for Jews, God (or Torah) has kept up Jewish hope for the redemption. One hopes in God, one does not hope as a virtue.</p>
<p>Sacks uses the word in several places in the Christian sense  and even has locutions like faith, hope, and dignity – cf the Christian faith, hope and charity</p>
<p>The use of the word hope in this sense is also used often in Shakespeare</p>
<p>b) On page 146 – he writes we are your witnesses, the bearers of your name. (Jews don&#8217;t use it like this)- <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/08/lord-jonathan-sacks-on-the-concept-of-witness/">see my prior post</a></p>
<p>c) He uses the phrase “free air of hope” – page 152 coined by the Irish theologian <em>George Tyrrell</em> (1861 – 1909).</p>
<p>6] He views religious language as metaphor</p>
<p>In many places he has a variant of the following: God is unknowable and belong words – the goal is to get behind words.</p>
<p>7] As a book</p>
<p>Well…A large number of quotes are quite cryptic – he likes good phrases better than good comments. Many times one cannot make out what it means. The full ideas in other books are here reduced to bon mots. Comments sometimes say “it may be” “may reflect” – so the effect is a more of a homily than a commentary.</p>
<p>Sometimes he cites his sources – in one case there are three cited names in a single  passage&#8212;and then there are many pages without a single citation. Yet, in his other works he cites the author of the interpretation. It seems arbitrary.</p>
<p>8] Sources and comparisons</p>
<p>a) On the topic of liturgy and spontaneity, he surprisingly does not use the usually rabbinic passages on keva and kavvanah but discusses the topic through passages the in Bible. Source seems to be an unnamed book on the Bible or early Rabbinics.</p>
<p>b) He cites historical material from a much much earlier decade with any new insight- he does not references to Yakovson (Jacobson), Abrahams, Elbogen or other works that he relies on.</p>
<p>c) Conspicuous in its absence is the Lubavitcher Rebbe since Sacks relied heavily on the Rebbe in earlier works and adapted a volume of the Rebbe on parashah. But Sacks makes prayer thankfulness and adoration – and does not follow the Rebbe that prayer is connection to God.</p>
<p>d) Sacks noticeably quotes Rav Soloveitchik in his introduction, as if to claim continuity or authenticity, but does not follow his approach to prayer in the commentary.For Soloveitchik, Prayer is the personal existential cry in which there is personal redemption through the tefilot and more importantly, the Torah give us words that raise us above our natural inarticulate grunts of animals.</p>
<p>e) Isaiah Berlin on negative freedom and positive freedom – is unattributed here, and presented as Hazal. In addition, he states that Jews as eternal from Tolstoy (in an earlier work he credited the citation to Hertz quoting Tolstoy) This quote of Tolstoy is also in Isaiah Berlin.But quoting that Jews are eternal from Tolstoy&#8212;and not from Krokhmal, Kook, Rosenzweig or Reines—reduced it to a bon mot.</p>
<p>f) In Alenu, he explains “leTaken Olam bemalkhut Shadai” as Lurianic tikkun – is it from Elliott Dorff in My People’s Prayer Book?</p>
<p>9] The sections in the introduction on study, mysticism, and history was less than adequate and quite vague. The section on mysticism could be from more than half a century ago. It has a tone of “Mysticism devalues world”</p>
<p>He takes Kabbalat Shabbat from Elbogen recognized by Elbogen&#8217;s its mistaken reliance on Solomon Schechter.  And one is not inspired to confidence when he writes that the source of Ushpezin is a nebulous “Jewish mystical tradition.”</p>
<p>10]  Now what of his frequent citation of Franz Rosenzweig on creation, revelation, redemption? I don&#8217;t get this one.</p>
<p>This triad is originally from Hermann Cohen where the triad is a divine meaning to creation in the natural order, the revelation of ethics in the human mind, and human work to make the world a better place. (One finds this Cohen triad occasionally in Rav Soloveitchik;s homilies.)</p>
<p>For Rosenzweig, it is God presence as meaning that negates nihilism, revelation is human love for God, and the liturgical fulfillment of eternity. Prayer along with poetry and love are means to let us be existentially human. For Gershom Scholem, it is a creation of emanation and tzimtzum, revelation of creativity and antinomianism, and redemption through apocalyptic change.</p>
<p>But for Sacks, it is God in nature, God revealed in Torah and prayer, and our redemption in history and life. Where is this mild version from and why bother linking it to Rosenzweig? I have not checked yet, but Netiv Binah by Jacobson and Taamei Hamizvot by Heinneman both combine Hirsch and Rosenzweig into a milder form.</p>
<p>Yet the way Sacks frames the triad it can just as well be Albo’s God, Revelation, and Reward or Cordovero’s God, Torah and Israel. There is a triad in Rabbinic thought and liturgy and in the Rabbinic reading of the Bible which has been formulated different ways in different eras. (see Max Kadushin’s Organic Thinking on this thinking in triads) I am not sure why Sacks attributed his reading to Rosenzweig when Albo or Cordovero would have better served his needs.</p>
<p>But then I found on the web a position similar to Sacks&#8212;“Rabbi Shlomo Wolbe explained that mans&#8217; relationship with G-d is three-dimensional; we know Him through His creation, His revelation at Sinai, and His promise of redemption.” Did both Sacks and Wolbe take it from Jacobson or Heinneman? Or another secondary source produced by German Jewry? Hmm..</p>
<p><strong>In short, I like the Orthodox universalism, but will stick to reading his longer works,</strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/29/lord-jonathan-sacks-on-the-siddur/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>5</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lord Jonathan Sacks on the concept of Witness-Updated</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/08/lord-jonathan-sacks-on-the-concept-of-witness/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/08/lord-jonathan-sacks-on-the-concept-of-witness/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 08 Nov 2009 23:47:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[jewish thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[liturgy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rabbis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[dignity of difference]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Emil Fackenheim]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Isaiah 53]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jonathan Sacks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jonathan Sacks Siddur]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[witness]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=230</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Lord Jonathan Sacks has a style that addresses his Anglican listeners and at the same time addresses his Jewish audience. Jews generally speak of Torah, avodah, gemilat hasadim; or God, Revelation and olam haba;  or God, Torah, and Israel; and &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/08/lord-jonathan-sacks-on-the-concept-of-witness/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Lord Jonathan Sacks has a style that addresses his Anglican listeners and at the same time addresses his Jewish audience.</p>
<p>Jews generally speak of Torah, avodah, gemilat hasadim; or God, Revelation and olam haba;  or God, Torah, and Israel; and now creation-revelation-redemption. All sets point back to Torah.</p>
<p>Christians use the words witness, mission, covenant, proclamation- all about good news to be brought to the world.   “witness.” in their reading of Israel’s covenant history: means the proclamation and exchange of views held with conviction.</p>
<p>Jonathan Sacks has discussed “witness” as a theological concept in almost all of his books.</p>
<p>In his 1992 <em>Crisis and Covenant, </em>he writes,  “An early rabbinic commentary put the point audaciously: &#8216; &#8220;You are My <em>witnesses</em>, says the Lord, and I am God&#8221; (Isaiah 43:12)” (28) In this work he uses the word the way Emil Fackenhim does, we as witnesses to the destruction of our people in the holocaust and now we give witness by the survival of the Jewish people. Our news to the world is the survival of the Jewish people.</p>
<p>In 1997, he writes “Somehow the Jewish people would be the people in whose daily lives the will of G-d, and in whose collective history the presence of G-d would be particularly evident.  You could look at Jews and see G-d.  In that magnificent phrase in Isaiah: “you are my witnesses, Isaiah 43:10, says G-d and so it happened.” Jews are witnesses to God’s existence.”  This is a Jewish version of the Christian doctrine of the witness; Jews point to God and the original revelation to humanity.</p>
<p>But Jews usually assume the verse talks to Jews about their own redemption   As examples, Rashi explains the witness as Abraham and Jacob testifying to their promise for Israel’s redemption and Radak explains that the prophet testifies that just as Sanherib was destroyed so too all of Israel’s enemies will vanish and Israel will be redeemed. Or the use of it for the haftarah of Bereshit is that just as God created the world he is true to his promise to redeem Israel.</p>
<p>A decade later in his <em>Dignity of Difference</em>, Sacks writes “ But from here on he will focus on one family, and eventually one people, to be his <em>witnesses</em> and bearers of his covenant.”(52) The argument is that undifferentiated pluralism leads to totalitarianism, but God chose a single people, the Jews, to teach the world that each people is unique and that there is a pluralism of diversity of different peoples. But the locution is more Christian, Jews are to witness and bear the covenant of Gods’ designs.</p>
<p>None of the Jewish commentators ad loc interpret it in that direction</p>
<p>In his <em>Heal a Fractured World</em><strong>, </strong>he writes that we witness to God<strong> “</strong>not by seeking to convert those of another faith, but simply by reaching out to embrace the image of God in another human being, by seeing the <strong>image of God in another human being (47) </strong>We have Levinas adapted as an answer to the Christians who seek to convert those of another faith.</p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p>Finally, in his recent<strong> </strong>siddur<strong> “</strong>The Jewish people &#8230; have &#8230; been singled out for the most exalted mission ever entrusted to mankind: to be witnesses, in ourselves, to something beyond ourselves: to be God&#8217;s &#8220;signal of transcendence&#8221; in a world in which his presence is often hidden (Siddur p. xxiv).</p>
<p>Jews have Mission to mankind for the presence of God. Hmm… I did a quick online check of the 19 letters to see if Hirsch used it that way, and from my quick check of 19 Letters- Rabbi Hirsch limits witness- Edut to contexts of duty and service of mankind toward God. God is know through the natural order, duty is the Jewish message. I need to check other works of Hirsch and Hertz. But here in Sack&#8217;s prayer book the very knowledge of God is the Jewish mission. Is this more Anglican or Jewish?</p>
<p>Update</p>
<p>I checked the commentary of Dr Mendel Hirsch on the Haftarot (called by most people as the commentary of the father) on the relevant verses in Isaiah. Dr. Hirsch comments that only man has will to act on a higher calling of righteousness. Only through zedek will people realize the nature of reality consisting of freedom from  material slavery in order to live in happiness and freedom. We are a light to the nations when there will be righteousness in the governments. The concept of witness is that the proof of every historical fact rests , on people who were there, on tradition The Jewish people have witnessesed the rise and fall of the nations around them. You were all at the going out from Egypt, which proves a world of providential care. You are witness to your revelation becuase you saw God&#8217;s hand in history.</p>
<p>Hmm..Hirsch does not seem like Sacks. I will check the essays if I get a chance.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/11/08/lord-jonathan-sacks-on-the-concept-of-witness/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>6</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sukkot Misc from the 9th and 20th centuries</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/05/sukkot-misc-from-the-9th-and-20th-centuries/</link>
					<comments>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/05/sukkot-misc-from-the-9th-and-20th-centuries/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alan Brill]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2009 03:49:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[holidays]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[liturgy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[popular religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chabad]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jonathan Sacks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[other nations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pesikta]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Shlomo Carlebach]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sukkah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sukkot]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ushpizin]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=120</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Sukkot is the holiday of the 6th to 9th centuries: Hoshanot are from this period, according to Goldschmidt. As is the custom of waving the lulav in 6 directions. First, Some random 6th -9th century ideas Guilt and treating the &#8230; <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/05/sukkot-misc-from-the-9th-and-20th-centuries/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sukkot is the holiday of the 6<sup>th</sup> to 9<sup>th</sup> centuries: Hoshanot are from this period, according to Goldschmidt. As is the custom of waving the lulav in 6 directions.</p>
<p>First, Some random 6<sup>th</sup> -9<sup>th</sup> century ideas</p>
<p><strong>Guilt and treating the sukkah as exile, not as presense.</strong></p>
<blockquote><p>Said R&#8217; El&#8217;azar bar Maryom: Why do we make a sukkah after Yom Kippur? To teach you that on Rosh Hashanah The Holy One, Blessed Be He, sits in judgment on all mankind, and on Yom Kippur He signs the verdict. Perhaps Israel&#8217;s sentence is exile; therefore they make a sukkah and exile themselves from their homes to their sukkah Pesikta of Rav Kahana Parasha 2 addenda, Mandelbaum 457)</p></blockquote>
<p><strong> Don&#8217;t go to Great Adventure or other entertainment for chol hamoed.</strong></p>
<blockquote><p>The festivals make a difference between the nations and Israel: the nations eat and drink, and go to the circus and the theater, and anger the Lord by their words and deeds; Israel eats and drinks and goes to the houses of prayer to praise His name and to the houses of study  to learn His glory. Pesikta 340-1</p></blockquote>
<p><strong>Vicarious atonement for the nations</strong></p>
<blockquote><p>Just as this dove atones for sins, so does Israel atone for the nations, for all those seventy bulls which are sacrificed on the festival are on behalf of the seventy nations, so that the world not be bereft of them, as is written (Psalms 109) &#8220;<em>They answer my love with accusation but I am all prayer&#8221;</em> Midrash Shir Hashirim Rabba 1.<em> </em></p>
<p>&#8220;All seventy bulls that Israel used to sacrifice on the festival were for the seventy nations of the world, so that they not be removed from the world, as it is said: &#8216;They answer my love with accusation, but I am all prayer&#8217; (Ps. 109:4). That is, now they are protected by prayer instead of sacrifice.&#8221;<em> Pesikta de Rav Kahana</em> (par. 30)</p></blockquote>
<p><strong>And now 1000 years later, three very different fin de siècle 20<sup>th</sup> century ideas</strong></p>
<p>1] Chief Rabbi Dr Jonathan Sacks writing that the sukkah helps us identify with the poor of “Calcutta and Caracas.” <em>Dignity of Difference</em> 112</p>
<p>2 The sixth Lubavitcher Rebbe, Rabbi Yosef Yitzchak Schneersohn (1880-1950) spoke of seven &#8220;chassidic <em>ushpizin</em>&#8221; as well: the Baal Shem Tov, the Maggid (Rabbi DovBer of Mezeritch), and the first five rebbes of Chabad: Rabbi Schneur Zalman of Liadi, Rabbi DovBer of Lubavitch, Rabbi Menachem Mendel (the &#8220;Tzemach Tzeddek&#8221;), Rabbi Shmuel, and Rabbi Sholom DovBer.</p>
<p>Where I was for one or the meals the debate was between the method starting with the Besht or now should they start with the Alter Rebbe and end with the 7<sup>th</sup> Rebbe. This seems more widespread than I thought. Have the Biblical Ushpizin lost their resonance?</p>
<p>3] Old time R Shlomo Carlebach moving he six directions from cosmology or sefirot to personal experience of religion. <a href="http://www.mishpacha.org/sukkotlulav.shtml"> link</a></p>
<blockquote><p>First, face right. Right in Kabbalah signifies the attribute of <em>hesed</em>, kindness, mercy, overwhelming beneficence. Do you find it too hard to be generous? Or are you suffering from an excess of generosity, of kindness, of love? &#8221;</p>
<p>Then face left. Left in Kabbalah is <em>gevurah</em> – strength, strict judgment, limits. <em>Gevurah</em> is Isaac – bound for sacrifice on Mount  Moriah, unflinching, accepting of judgment. Take this opportunity to think of the limits, the judgments in your life. Are your circumstances too confining? Do you need more boundaries, or fewer? Do you need more strength? This is an opportunity to invite God to help you fix the limits in your life.</p>
<p>Next, face straight ahead: <em>tiferet, </em>or beauty. This is the balance, where the beneficence and the boundaries are in their proper proportions. It is Jacob, it is the middle course.</p>
<p>Then, look up. Can you connect with God? What’s the holiness you need in your life? How high can you rise this year?</p>
<p>Then, aim down. This is about groundedness, about your foundations. And it’s about your ability to find the buried treasures, under your feet; the truths buried in the dirt.</p>
<p>Finally, backwards. The essence of repentance is being able to go back and fix your past  by your coming to terms with it</p></blockquote>
<p>I find these three approaches to be quite different: the metonymic ethical, the binding to a saint, and the introspective.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2009/10/05/sukkot-misc-from-the-9th-and-20th-centuries/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://0.gravatar.com/avatar/3c03ae2a4d660bbae7c017f271adb19c?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=R" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kavvanah</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
