<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Yoga as a Torah Shiur	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/08/06/yoga-as-a-torah-shiur/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/08/06/yoga-as-a-torah-shiur/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2013 04:24:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Ira Rohde		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/08/06/yoga-as-a-torah-shiur/#comment-8149</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ira Rohde]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2013 04:24:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6146#comment-8149</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I have been in gym and yoga-studio classes where they dedicate the practice, or the teacher asks the students to dedicate the practice, especially to a loved one, so it seems to be a common thing in non-Jewish yoga classes these days, and I do recall specifically a dedication in memory of the deceased. Maybe the instructors got this from some of the many yoga teachers of Jewish origin, who knows? 

I generally agree that yoga&#039;s background in a polytheistic way of thinking shouldn&#039;t be passed over lightly, even if I feel that asana/hatha yoga itself, or even some of the other &quot;branches&quot; of yoga, may not be so problematic. Yoga Journal had an article about how the late 19th and early 20th century originators of modern hatha yoga were studying Swedish and perhaps other European physical-culture publications, and adapted &quot;asanas&quot; from them. 
Who knows if modern hatha &quot;yoga&quot; derives more Patanjali&#039;s sutras or from the tantra tradition, or from the remnants of martial arts stamped out by the British, but Patanjali does seem to come out of samkhya and hence is more monistically philosophical rather than &quot;religious.&quot; Patanjali is also very self/soul/psychologically oriented. Anyway, &quot;Down dog&quot; certainly doesn&#039;t sound like a name a Hindu would invent (K. Pattabhi Jois tried to insist on naming the pose after Mt. Meru instead). 

I can understand why Jewish yoga students would prefer to practice in environments free of Ganesh statues, statues which have little to do with yoga per se, but are just part of the &quot;baggage&quot; a practicing traditional Hindu sage brings along, and often passes on to his students. It is good, I think, overall, to encourage Jews to explore these things in a sophisticated way, in some depth, among Jews, and synagogues lend themselves as good places to do so, but that isn&#039;t always possible for all of us. And all too often, things are taught very superficially (disappointingly so at JCCs) and swathed in pop culture, although there are really good, deep teachers out there. 

But most Jews I find are quite aware of the alienness and Hindu background of yoga, unlike modern psychology (which has had interesting connections with Western and Eastern pagan and Christian religion all the way through), which claims to be &quot;scientific&quot; and universal. Most yogis and those New Agers influenced by them are &quot;up front&quot; with the background of what they practice (even Shlomo Carlebach admitted his indebtedness to yoga), unlike the psychologists, social workers, and those influenced by them whose hiding of their &quot;baggage&quot; I find to be far more insidious.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have been in gym and yoga-studio classes where they dedicate the practice, or the teacher asks the students to dedicate the practice, especially to a loved one, so it seems to be a common thing in non-Jewish yoga classes these days, and I do recall specifically a dedication in memory of the deceased. Maybe the instructors got this from some of the many yoga teachers of Jewish origin, who knows? </p>
<p>I generally agree that yoga&#8217;s background in a polytheistic way of thinking shouldn&#8217;t be passed over lightly, even if I feel that asana/hatha yoga itself, or even some of the other &#8220;branches&#8221; of yoga, may not be so problematic. Yoga Journal had an article about how the late 19th and early 20th century originators of modern hatha yoga were studying Swedish and perhaps other European physical-culture publications, and adapted &#8220;asanas&#8221; from them.<br />
Who knows if modern hatha &#8220;yoga&#8221; derives more Patanjali&#8217;s sutras or from the tantra tradition, or from the remnants of martial arts stamped out by the British, but Patanjali does seem to come out of samkhya and hence is more monistically philosophical rather than &#8220;religious.&#8221; Patanjali is also very self/soul/psychologically oriented. Anyway, &#8220;Down dog&#8221; certainly doesn&#8217;t sound like a name a Hindu would invent (K. Pattabhi Jois tried to insist on naming the pose after Mt. Meru instead). </p>
<p>I can understand why Jewish yoga students would prefer to practice in environments free of Ganesh statues, statues which have little to do with yoga per se, but are just part of the &#8220;baggage&#8221; a practicing traditional Hindu sage brings along, and often passes on to his students. It is good, I think, overall, to encourage Jews to explore these things in a sophisticated way, in some depth, among Jews, and synagogues lend themselves as good places to do so, but that isn&#8217;t always possible for all of us. And all too often, things are taught very superficially (disappointingly so at JCCs) and swathed in pop culture, although there are really good, deep teachers out there. </p>
<p>But most Jews I find are quite aware of the alienness and Hindu background of yoga, unlike modern psychology (which has had interesting connections with Western and Eastern pagan and Christian religion all the way through), which claims to be &#8220;scientific&#8221; and universal. Most yogis and those New Agers influenced by them are &#8220;up front&#8221; with the background of what they practice (even Shlomo Carlebach admitted his indebtedness to yoga), unlike the psychologists, social workers, and those influenced by them whose hiding of their &#8220;baggage&#8221; I find to be far more insidious.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: תומר פרסיקו		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/08/06/yoga-as-a-torah-shiur/#comment-8126</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[תומר פרסיקו]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2013 04:52:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6146#comment-8126</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Very interesting. It needs to be asked whether the Yoga class dedicated to the rising of the soul is considered by its practitioners as exercise devoid of spiritual meaning. I would guess otherwise. 
I wrote a bit about Yoga&#039;s adoption in the west in Ma&#039;ariv a few months ago, translated into English here: http://tomerpersicoenglish.wordpress.com/2013/04/25/spirituality-athletics-yoga-pizza/
	
&lt;blockquote&gt;At the end of February this year a woman named Ronnie Abramson went to a yoga class. Amidst the positions and stretching exercises she was dismayed to realize that the instructor was telling her about the month of Adar, the Book of Esther, the feast of Purim and the Almighty. Abramson, who sought only a standard yoga class, felt that she was not getting what she paid for, and was in fact suffering a minor assault of religious coercion. She wrote a short account of the experience for ‘Haaretz’ in which she asks that secular folks be allowed to practice yoga without being forced to listen to religious sermons.&lt;/blockquote&gt;


]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Very interesting. It needs to be asked whether the Yoga class dedicated to the rising of the soul is considered by its practitioners as exercise devoid of spiritual meaning. I would guess otherwise.<br />
I wrote a bit about Yoga&#8217;s adoption in the west in Ma&#8217;ariv a few months ago, translated into English here: <a href="http://tomerpersicoenglish.wordpress.com/2013/04/25/spirituality-athletics-yoga-pizza/" rel="nofollow ugc">http://tomerpersicoenglish.wordpress.com/2013/04/25/spirituality-athletics-yoga-pizza/</a></p>
<blockquote><p>At the end of February this year a woman named Ronnie Abramson went to a yoga class. Amidst the positions and stretching exercises she was dismayed to realize that the instructor was telling her about the month of Adar, the Book of Esther, the feast of Purim and the Almighty. Abramson, who sought only a standard yoga class, felt that she was not getting what she paid for, and was in fact suffering a minor assault of religious coercion. She wrote a short account of the experience for ‘Haaretz’ in which she asks that secular folks be allowed to practice yoga without being forced to listen to religious sermons.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: HS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/08/06/yoga-as-a-torah-shiur/#comment-8118</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[HS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2013 14:39:15 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6146#comment-8118</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I have seen at least one Orthodox synagogue offer T&#039;ai Chi Chu&#039;an before shabbat prayers.  It is consciously scheduled as preparation for the mainstream synagogue service.  It&#039;s a step beyond the Toradojo classes that commonly use space in Greater NYC synagogue buildings (although the t&#039;ai chi chu&#039;an leaders often come from that organization).]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have seen at least one Orthodox synagogue offer T&#8217;ai Chi Chu&#8217;an before shabbat prayers.  It is consciously scheduled as preparation for the mainstream synagogue service.  It&#8217;s a step beyond the Toradojo classes that commonly use space in Greater NYC synagogue buildings (although the t&#8217;ai chi chu&#8217;an leaders often come from that organization).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
