<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Rishikesh: Israelis, Chabad, and Theology	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/30/rishikesh-israelis-chabad-and-theology/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/30/rishikesh-israelis-chabad-and-theology/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2014 10:00:46 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Jon		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/30/rishikesh-israelis-chabad-and-theology/#comment-12746</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jon]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2014 10:00:46 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6413#comment-12746</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I remember when I was reading about Yoga and Buddhism that I thought that Judaism was like the early stages of Yoga or Buddhism. First negative prohibitions, second affirmative requirements and further on different paths and practices to prepare the individual for mysticism. Judaism seems to stop short with the first two.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I remember when I was reading about Yoga and Buddhism that I thought that Judaism was like the early stages of Yoga or Buddhism. First negative prohibitions, second affirmative requirements and further on different paths and practices to prepare the individual for mysticism. Judaism seems to stop short with the first two.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: alon goshen-gottstein		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/30/rishikesh-israelis-chabad-and-theology/#comment-9697</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[alon goshen-gottstein]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2014 16:59:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6413#comment-9697</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[3 comments. one trivial - there is a hindu minority in Malaysia. Swami Sivananda of Rishikesh started his career as a doctor in Malaysia. More significantly - I am concerned about an overidealization of ashrams and concommitant downplaying of spiritual benefits of studying at yeshivat tomchei temimim, or any other yeshiva. You can spend many years in Ashram and learn next to nothing and you can find some very good jewish education. the thought about 3 months in each resorts to a stereotype that may not be true to reality. Even more important - I think this is a highly idealized view of ashram also in terms of its actual practices. the imagined model of what ashram looks like, as the basis for the imagined yeshivashram, corresponds to only one out of a many ashrams that I visited. the rest are as ritualistic, practical etc. Certainly this is true for the various ashrams in rishikesh, within spitting distance of where chabad house is located. they do the ritual. maybe yoga courses for westerners have a different configuration, but ashrams are complex things and do not correspond to this highly idealized description.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>3 comments. one trivial &#8211; there is a hindu minority in Malaysia. Swami Sivananda of Rishikesh started his career as a doctor in Malaysia. More significantly &#8211; I am concerned about an overidealization of ashrams and concommitant downplaying of spiritual benefits of studying at yeshivat tomchei temimim, or any other yeshiva. You can spend many years in Ashram and learn next to nothing and you can find some very good jewish education. the thought about 3 months in each resorts to a stereotype that may not be true to reality. Even more important &#8211; I think this is a highly idealized view of ashram also in terms of its actual practices. the imagined model of what ashram looks like, as the basis for the imagined yeshivashram, corresponds to only one out of a many ashrams that I visited. the rest are as ritualistic, practical etc. Certainly this is true for the various ashrams in rishikesh, within spitting distance of where chabad house is located. they do the ritual. maybe yoga courses for westerners have a different configuration, but ashrams are complex things and do not correspond to this highly idealized description.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Pinchos Chalk		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/30/rishikesh-israelis-chabad-and-theology/#comment-9266</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pinchos Chalk]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2013 04:59:36 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6413#comment-9266</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Maybe I could promote my cousins sefer &#039;Ayin el ha&#039;ayin - An eye to the infinite&#039; (Rubin) for the kosher ashram (I do not get commission).

Entering a beis avodah zarah for the purpose of kiruv would seem to be mutar as entering is not abizreihu so not yehareg ve&#039;al yaavor and would be nidcheh by the various asin and lavin of doing kiruv in this scenario (lo saamod al dam re&#039;echah etc.)

I think the Arizal spent 7 years meditating in a hut by the Nile before he went to Tzephas so maybe some kisvei ha&#039;Ari could serve as part of the foundation course for the Ashram. The Alter of Novahrodock also spent a few years in hisbodedus after his first wife died but I am not sure if Madregas ha&#039;Adam would go down with chumas.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Maybe I could promote my cousins sefer &#8216;Ayin el ha&#8217;ayin &#8211; An eye to the infinite&#8217; (Rubin) for the kosher ashram (I do not get commission).</p>
<p>Entering a beis avodah zarah for the purpose of kiruv would seem to be mutar as entering is not abizreihu so not yehareg ve&#8217;al yaavor and would be nidcheh by the various asin and lavin of doing kiruv in this scenario (lo saamod al dam re&#8217;echah etc.)</p>
<p>I think the Arizal spent 7 years meditating in a hut by the Nile before he went to Tzephas so maybe some kisvei ha&#8217;Ari could serve as part of the foundation course for the Ashram. The Alter of Novahrodock also spent a few years in hisbodedus after his first wife died but I am not sure if Madregas ha&#8217;Adam would go down with chumas.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Len Moskowitz		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/30/rishikesh-israelis-chabad-and-theology/#comment-9263</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Len Moskowitz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2013 05:26:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6413#comment-9263</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/30/rishikesh-israelis-chabad-and-theology/#comment-9253&quot;&gt;walter benjamin&lt;/a&gt;.

The state of k&#039;dusha resulting from doing a mitzva is temporary and can be removed by sin or wrong/coarse action. See the first few paragraphs in the Neffesh Ha-chayyim, Sha-ar 4, chapter 29 on the subject of &quot;kee mitzva nair, v&#039;torah ore&quot;. That applies to your first case of nah-val bir&#039;shoot ha-torah.

And the effect of roteness when performing mitzvote - which might or might not be the context of mitzvaht ah-na-sheem m&#039;loo-ma-da - is not simply understood. See what the Neffesh Ha-chayyim says about the effects of mitzvote done without any intention, near the end of Gate 1, chapter 22. Also, see what he has to say in regards to the mitzva of talmood torah sheh-lo lishma (involvement with Torah not for its own sake) in the P&#039;rakim, chapters 2 and 3, and in Sha-ar 4, chapter 18. He also mentions there the effect of doing things by rote.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/30/rishikesh-israelis-chabad-and-theology/#comment-9253">walter benjamin</a>.</p>
<p>The state of k&#8217;dusha resulting from doing a mitzva is temporary and can be removed by sin or wrong/coarse action. See the first few paragraphs in the Neffesh Ha-chayyim, Sha-ar 4, chapter 29 on the subject of &#8220;kee mitzva nair, v&#8217;torah ore&#8221;. That applies to your first case of nah-val bir&#8217;shoot ha-torah.</p>
<p>And the effect of roteness when performing mitzvote &#8211; which might or might not be the context of mitzvaht ah-na-sheem m&#8217;loo-ma-da &#8211; is not simply understood. See what the Neffesh Ha-chayyim says about the effects of mitzvote done without any intention, near the end of Gate 1, chapter 22. Also, see what he has to say in regards to the mitzva of talmood torah sheh-lo lishma (involvement with Torah not for its own sake) in the P&#8217;rakim, chapters 2 and 3, and in Sha-ar 4, chapter 18. He also mentions there the effect of doing things by rote.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Howie Katz		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/30/rishikesh-israelis-chabad-and-theology/#comment-9262</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Howie Katz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2013 01:14:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6413#comment-9262</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Interesting website/post. A few comments:

1) The idea of a Jewish ashram is an intriguing one. However, I don&#039;t know that an institution of this type should specialize only in Jnana Yoga/Vedanta/Non-dualism. An equally pressing need, in my opinion, is for institutions that emphasize bhakti marga. Many Jews are devotionally oriented and there are few if any places for them within traditional Judaism. In my extended family, for example, there is a young man  who is not a &quot;learner&quot; and is devotionally inclined. Almost by default, he wound up in Breslov Chassidus which, while positive in some respects, is deeply problematic in others.A Jewish sadhana that stressed kavannah in davvening, cultivating simcha-shel-mitzvah, and other devotional practices
might fill a huge gap.

2) I agree with your point that Mitzvot and Yoga have different spiritual goals.Yes, Judaism is not about either nirvikalpa samadhi or moksha(and I have yet to meet any Jivanmuktas on Avenue J in Brooklyn).  However, I do not see why you then propose &quot;demoting&quot; yoga to asanas-only. Why not practice BOTH the Torah of Mitzvot and Raja/Ashtanga Yoga and Vedanta, especially if they fulfill different needs?(Assuming of course that Raja Yoga and Vedanta are OK Jewishly, which you seem to agree with).

3) Yes, American yoga is cluttered with eclectic and trendy dilletantism, with yoga studios throwing together statues of the Buddha  alongside those of Hanuman, Shiva etc(which, btw, many Hindus find offensive) - mostly because these are &quot;cool&quot;. However, as virtually every Yoga Master alive today (and not only Hatha Yoga Masters)would say, the Hindu &quot;flavor&quot; is not needed. This should not be an impediment to exploring the deeper aspects of yoga.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Interesting website/post. A few comments:</p>
<p>1) The idea of a Jewish ashram is an intriguing one. However, I don&#8217;t know that an institution of this type should specialize only in Jnana Yoga/Vedanta/Non-dualism. An equally pressing need, in my opinion, is for institutions that emphasize bhakti marga. Many Jews are devotionally oriented and there are few if any places for them within traditional Judaism. In my extended family, for example, there is a young man  who is not a &#8220;learner&#8221; and is devotionally inclined. Almost by default, he wound up in Breslov Chassidus which, while positive in some respects, is deeply problematic in others.A Jewish sadhana that stressed kavannah in davvening, cultivating simcha-shel-mitzvah, and other devotional practices<br />
might fill a huge gap.</p>
<p>2) I agree with your point that Mitzvot and Yoga have different spiritual goals.Yes, Judaism is not about either nirvikalpa samadhi or moksha(and I have yet to meet any Jivanmuktas on Avenue J in Brooklyn).  However, I do not see why you then propose &#8220;demoting&#8221; yoga to asanas-only. Why not practice BOTH the Torah of Mitzvot and Raja/Ashtanga Yoga and Vedanta, especially if they fulfill different needs?(Assuming of course that Raja Yoga and Vedanta are OK Jewishly, which you seem to agree with).</p>
<p>3) Yes, American yoga is cluttered with eclectic and trendy dilletantism, with yoga studios throwing together statues of the Buddha  alongside those of Hanuman, Shiva etc(which, btw, many Hindus find offensive) &#8211; mostly because these are &#8220;cool&#8221;. However, as virtually every Yoga Master alive today (and not only Hatha Yoga Masters)would say, the Hindu &#8220;flavor&#8221; is not needed. This should not be an impediment to exploring the deeper aspects of yoga.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Ira Rohde		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/30/rishikesh-israelis-chabad-and-theology/#comment-9256</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ira Rohde]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2013 03:27:13 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6413#comment-9256</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Jewish Ashram sounds good, or almost any attempt to bring classical discipline and disciplines into Jewish life. Without minimal levels of striving for basic self-discipline (and here I don&#039;t mean the forced discipline of Tzahal, a discipline which their constant intoxication in India right after discharge threatens to make a mockery of, although as father of a ninenteen-year-old guy I do believe that we have to give these dudes some rope to cut loose and decompress), most aspects of Judaism are impoverished. Are you speaking strictly of setting up one in India, or are you talking American Catskills or Boulder, or Israeli mountains or deserts or elsewhere? How would &quot;Jewish ashram&quot; differ and avoid pitfalls of previous attempts, both Orthodox and liberal? There were the attempts of R. Zalman and his followers, Pnai Ohr, Eylat Chen, there was even the earlier days of Morristown Yeshiva, which I recall with some fondness.  Sounds like the head of the Lubavitch outpost in Rishikesh is educated and deserves support, although the situation seems to make such a mockery of what Jews ought to stand for. Should ashrams be preferred over retreat centers or urban groups? Since Buddhism is much less theistic and hence less polytheistic, aren&#039;t Buddhist monastaries much less problematic? And then there are the problems of lacking clear, developed, agreed-upon Jewish paths (which Advaita and Samkhya and Yoga provide for Hinduism), all of which leads to reliance upon the charismatic leadership and the pitfals of that. And how should staff manage the worldly existence of such a thing, and the students&#039; and staff&#039;s own grhastha (baal ha-bayit) worldly obligations? Perhaps us older guys need take our obligations more seriously to become zeqenim and to move on to the Vanaprastha stage. After all, it was always Socrates and the older sophists with the young men in the Academy, Zeqenim with the young disciples in the Beit Midrash, and elder gurus with the young men in the Ashram. But even partial &quot;retirement&quot; and its potential for our own growth as well as to give back to society seems like an ever more remote possibility for most of us....]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Jewish Ashram sounds good, or almost any attempt to bring classical discipline and disciplines into Jewish life. Without minimal levels of striving for basic self-discipline (and here I don&#8217;t mean the forced discipline of Tzahal, a discipline which their constant intoxication in India right after discharge threatens to make a mockery of, although as father of a ninenteen-year-old guy I do believe that we have to give these dudes some rope to cut loose and decompress), most aspects of Judaism are impoverished. Are you speaking strictly of setting up one in India, or are you talking American Catskills or Boulder, or Israeli mountains or deserts or elsewhere? How would &#8220;Jewish ashram&#8221; differ and avoid pitfalls of previous attempts, both Orthodox and liberal? There were the attempts of R. Zalman and his followers, Pnai Ohr, Eylat Chen, there was even the earlier days of Morristown Yeshiva, which I recall with some fondness.  Sounds like the head of the Lubavitch outpost in Rishikesh is educated and deserves support, although the situation seems to make such a mockery of what Jews ought to stand for. Should ashrams be preferred over retreat centers or urban groups? Since Buddhism is much less theistic and hence less polytheistic, aren&#8217;t Buddhist monastaries much less problematic? And then there are the problems of lacking clear, developed, agreed-upon Jewish paths (which Advaita and Samkhya and Yoga provide for Hinduism), all of which leads to reliance upon the charismatic leadership and the pitfals of that. And how should staff manage the worldly existence of such a thing, and the students&#8217; and staff&#8217;s own grhastha (baal ha-bayit) worldly obligations? Perhaps us older guys need take our obligations more seriously to become zeqenim and to move on to the Vanaprastha stage. After all, it was always Socrates and the older sophists with the young men in the Academy, Zeqenim with the young disciples in the Beit Midrash, and elder gurus with the young men in the Ashram. But even partial &#8220;retirement&#8221; and its potential for our own growth as well as to give back to society seems like an ever more remote possibility for most of us&#8230;.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: walter benjamin		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/30/rishikesh-israelis-chabad-and-theology/#comment-9253</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[walter benjamin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2013 06:23:50 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6413#comment-9253</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Again all these references are &#039;potential&#039; situations&#039; not that one automatically achieves &#039;holiness&#039; by doing מצות.
We also have at least two examples of the performance of מצות and obviously קדושה is not attained:
נוכל ברשות התורה 
אנשי מלומדה
In both the cases above and the examples given in diff place it is obvious that even though they are performing the מצות כהלכתן there is no קדושה  involved.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Again all these references are &#8216;potential&#8217; situations&#8217; not that one automatically achieves &#8216;holiness&#8217; by doing מצות.<br />
We also have at least two examples of the performance of מצות and obviously קדושה is not attained:<br />
נוכל ברשות התורה<br />
אנשי מלומדה<br />
In both the cases above and the examples given in diff place it is obvious that even though they are performing the מצות כהלכתן there is no קדושה  involved.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Len Moskowitz		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/30/rishikesh-israelis-chabad-and-theology/#comment-9249</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Len Moskowitz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2013 01:04:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6413#comment-9249</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Walter Benjamin wrote:

&#062; How do you know this so clearly? קדושה is not a given for just observing the מצות.

It&#039;s stated in the third paragraph of the Sh&#039;ma (B&#039;midbar 15:40): l&#039;ma-ahn tiz-k&#039;roo va-ah-see-tem et kol mitz-vo-tai, v&#039;heh-yee-tem k&#039;doe-shim l&#039;ei-lo-hei-khem... .

We say it in the bra-kha that accompanies mitzvote: ahsher kidsha-noo b&#039;mitzvotav.

In the Shabbat Sha-kha-reet ah-mee-da we say: v&#039;keedahshtanoo b&#039;mitzvoteh-kha.

The whole parsha of K&#039;doshim (Va-yikra 19:2), which starts with the prescription &quot;k&#039;doe-sheem ti-hee-yoo&quot;, is nothing but mitzvote. It ends (20:26) similarly.

And more recently, in the Neffesh Ha-chayyim  (Sha-ar 1, chapters 4 through 6), Rav Chaim Volozhiner states clearly over and over again that the performance of the mitzvote brings the state of k&#039;doosha.

&#062; Last but not least gentiles are not commanded by the Torah and thus you cannot deny them spirituality or some kind of קדושה on the grounds of them not being Jewish.

No one is denying non-Jews spirituality. Alan was talking about a Yeshiva Ashram for Jews, not for non-Jews. I was only addressing Jews.

But since you bring up the subject...

We know that non-Jews can merit the world to come. One example is Rebbi Chanaya ben Tradyon&#039;s executioner (TB Avoda Zara 18a).

And non-Jews also seem to have a baseline level of K&#039;doosha, as they are permitted to bring an offering to the Mikdash and to approach up to the Kheil (or Soreg), but no further. Jews can lose that baseline level of k&#039;doosha via certain types of tum&#039;ah (e.g., a m&#039;tzo-ra).]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Walter Benjamin wrote:</p>
<p>&gt; How do you know this so clearly? קדושה is not a given for just observing the מצות.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s stated in the third paragraph of the Sh&#8217;ma (B&#8217;midbar 15:40): l&#8217;ma-ahn tiz-k&#8217;roo va-ah-see-tem et kol mitz-vo-tai, v&#8217;heh-yee-tem k&#8217;doe-shim l&#8217;ei-lo-hei-khem&#8230; .</p>
<p>We say it in the bra-kha that accompanies mitzvote: ahsher kidsha-noo b&#8217;mitzvotav.</p>
<p>In the Shabbat Sha-kha-reet ah-mee-da we say: v&#8217;keedahshtanoo b&#8217;mitzvoteh-kha.</p>
<p>The whole parsha of K&#8217;doshim (Va-yikra 19:2), which starts with the prescription &#8220;k&#8217;doe-sheem ti-hee-yoo&#8221;, is nothing but mitzvote. It ends (20:26) similarly.</p>
<p>And more recently, in the Neffesh Ha-chayyim  (Sha-ar 1, chapters 4 through 6), Rav Chaim Volozhiner states clearly over and over again that the performance of the mitzvote brings the state of k&#8217;doosha.</p>
<p>&gt; Last but not least gentiles are not commanded by the Torah and thus you cannot deny them spirituality or some kind of קדושה on the grounds of them not being Jewish.</p>
<p>No one is denying non-Jews spirituality. Alan was talking about a Yeshiva Ashram for Jews, not for non-Jews. I was only addressing Jews.</p>
<p>But since you bring up the subject&#8230;</p>
<p>We know that non-Jews can merit the world to come. One example is Rebbi Chanaya ben Tradyon&#8217;s executioner (TB Avoda Zara 18a).</p>
<p>And non-Jews also seem to have a baseline level of K&#8217;doosha, as they are permitted to bring an offering to the Mikdash and to approach up to the Kheil (or Soreg), but no further. Jews can lose that baseline level of k&#8217;doosha via certain types of tum&#8217;ah (e.g., a m&#8217;tzo-ra).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: walter benjamin		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/30/rishikesh-israelis-chabad-and-theology/#comment-9244</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[walter benjamin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2013 17:13:42 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6413#comment-9244</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&quot;All the spirituality in the world won’t make up for not following the Torah’s commandments. Spirituality can enhance the result of following the Torah’s commandments but it can’t replace them.&quot;
How do you know this so clearly? קדושה is not a given for just observing the מצות.
As far as &quot;In Judaism, it’s what you do, not what you think or perceive.&quot; that is a very nebulous statement e.g. the qabbalists of בית אל who left their houses after הבדלה  and only returned for שבת קידוש.
So they spent their time &#039;perceiving&#039;  either in talmud or qabbalah the entire week- a 6 day &#039;ashram&#039;.
As far as perceiving goes their is no מצוה to believe in god but there is one to know him.
IMO the essence of the מורה נבוכים  is based on this: firstly in the initial chapter dealing with צלם which would be pure intellect where the perceiver and perceived are one e.g. what the Persian metaphysicians call &#039;ilm al huduri, &#039;knowledge by presence&#039; or &#039;non-representational knowledge&#039; i.e. the absence of images.
The Rambam then goes on in the 2nd chapter to extrapolate explaining that אלהים{which is not sanctified here and therefore חול} is &#039;judges&#039; like Onkelos translates and not &#039;gods&#039; as most seem to assume. 
So before &#039;eating from the tree..&#039; Adam&#039;s perception was of אמת ושקר whereas after the &#039;repast&#039; his &#039;perception&#039; was &#039;downgraded&#039; to מפורמסות i.e. &#039;relative&#039; meanings which change, let us say, according to situation, time, place etc.
So it seems that the way you understand &#039;perceiving&#039; seems somewhat pedestrian.
Last but not least gentiles are not commanded by the Torah and thus you cannot deny them spirituality or some kind of  קדושה on the grounds of them not being Jewish.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&#8220;All the spirituality in the world won’t make up for not following the Torah’s commandments. Spirituality can enhance the result of following the Torah’s commandments but it can’t replace them.&#8221;<br />
How do you know this so clearly? קדושה is not a given for just observing the מצות.<br />
As far as &#8220;In Judaism, it’s what you do, not what you think or perceive.&#8221; that is a very nebulous statement e.g. the qabbalists of בית אל who left their houses after הבדלה  and only returned for שבת קידוש.<br />
So they spent their time &#8216;perceiving&#8217;  either in talmud or qabbalah the entire week- a 6 day &#8216;ashram&#8217;.<br />
As far as perceiving goes their is no מצוה to believe in god but there is one to know him.<br />
IMO the essence of the מורה נבוכים  is based on this: firstly in the initial chapter dealing with צלם which would be pure intellect where the perceiver and perceived are one e.g. what the Persian metaphysicians call &#8216;ilm al huduri, &#8216;knowledge by presence&#8217; or &#8216;non-representational knowledge&#8217; i.e. the absence of images.<br />
The Rambam then goes on in the 2nd chapter to extrapolate explaining that אלהים{which is not sanctified here and therefore חול} is &#8216;judges&#8217; like Onkelos translates and not &#8216;gods&#8217; as most seem to assume.<br />
So before &#8216;eating from the tree..&#8217; Adam&#8217;s perception was of אמת ושקר whereas after the &#8216;repast&#8217; his &#8216;perception&#8217; was &#8216;downgraded&#8217; to מפורמסות i.e. &#8216;relative&#8217; meanings which change, let us say, according to situation, time, place etc.<br />
So it seems that the way you understand &#8216;perceiving&#8217; seems somewhat pedestrian.<br />
Last but not least gentiles are not commanded by the Torah and thus you cannot deny them spirituality or some kind of  קדושה on the grounds of them not being Jewish.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Len Moskowitz		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/30/rishikesh-israelis-chabad-and-theology/#comment-9236</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Len Moskowitz]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2013 13:28:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6413#comment-9236</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Alan writes:

&#062; Which reopens up the question that people used to ask: Should Judaism have opened up an ashram? ... Meaning that the Yeshiva Ashram would only teach and practice the Raja Yogic and Vedanta, and Advaitan parts of Judaism. It would leave all the karma yoga of practice, halakhah, and the study of the laws for the advanced students.

It seems to me that this suggestion misses the nature of Judaism.

In Hinduism and Buddhism, perception is (or leads to) salvation. In Judaism, it&#039;s what you do, not what you think or perceive.

In Judaism, if you somehow arrive at perceiving the one-ness of God in everything but don&#039;t keep Shabbat, you&#039;re on the wrong path. If you sit in meditation and contemplation all day long but don&#039;t say the Sh&#039;ma at the right time, you haven&#039;t accomplished much. If you sing and dance and feel spiritually connected to God, but eat non-kosher, you&#039;re doing wrong.

All the spirituality in the world won&#039;t make up for not following the Torah&#039;s commandments. Spirituality can enhance the result of following the Torah&#039;s commandments but it can&#039;t replace them.

First basic k&#039;dusha, then rukhneeyoot. No?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Alan writes:</p>
<p>&gt; Which reopens up the question that people used to ask: Should Judaism have opened up an ashram? &#8230; Meaning that the Yeshiva Ashram would only teach and practice the Raja Yogic and Vedanta, and Advaitan parts of Judaism. It would leave all the karma yoga of practice, halakhah, and the study of the laws for the advanced students.</p>
<p>It seems to me that this suggestion misses the nature of Judaism.</p>
<p>In Hinduism and Buddhism, perception is (or leads to) salvation. In Judaism, it&#8217;s what you do, not what you think or perceive.</p>
<p>In Judaism, if you somehow arrive at perceiving the one-ness of God in everything but don&#8217;t keep Shabbat, you&#8217;re on the wrong path. If you sit in meditation and contemplation all day long but don&#8217;t say the Sh&#8217;ma at the right time, you haven&#8217;t accomplished much. If you sing and dance and feel spiritually connected to God, but eat non-kosher, you&#8217;re doing wrong.</p>
<p>All the spirituality in the world won&#8217;t make up for not following the Torah&#8217;s commandments. Spirituality can enhance the result of following the Torah&#8217;s commandments but it can&#8217;t replace them.</p>
<p>First basic k&#8217;dusha, then rukhneeyoot. No?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: moti		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2013/11/30/rishikesh-israelis-chabad-and-theology/#comment-9218</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[moti]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2013 00:58:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=6413#comment-9218</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Just as a side note, another book to mention- the Hovot HaLevavot: your description of a potential of path within Judaism, focused inwardly and leaving aside detailed concentration on Halakhahic study, matches his message, and in his introduction he argues the point explicitly.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Just as a side note, another book to mention- the Hovot HaLevavot: your description of a potential of path within Judaism, focused inwardly and leaving aside detailed concentration on Halakhahic study, matches his message, and in his introduction he argues the point explicitly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
