<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Modern Orthodox words in my mouth	</title>
	<atom:link href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/05/modern-orthodox-words-in-my-mouth/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/05/modern-orthodox-words-in-my-mouth/</link>
	<description>notes on Jewish theology and spirituality</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2012 14:35:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Who is Responsible for the Term Modern Orthodoxy &#171; Menachem Mendel		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/05/modern-orthodox-words-in-my-mouth/#comment-4026</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Who is Responsible for the Term Modern Orthodoxy &#171; Menachem Mendel]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2012 14:35:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3393#comment-4026</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[[...] that they were interesting none the less. For some discussion of the origins of the term, see this post by Alan [...]]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] that they were interesting none the less. For some discussion of the origins of the term, see this post by Alan [&#8230;]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Larry Yudelson		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/05/modern-orthodox-words-in-my-mouth/#comment-2923</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Larry Yudelson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2011 13:37:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3393#comment-2923</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/05/modern-orthodox-words-in-my-mouth/#comment-2920&quot;&gt;AS&lt;/a&gt;.

I think the need for labels in Orthodoxies is that Orthodoxy is ultimately a negative definition: Not Reform, not liberal, not Conservative. At the same time, it is about a claimed Authenticity -- which needs to label others as inauthentic.

The result is that any tiny variation needs to claim its own Authenticity and become, to those who believe in it, in effect its own identification.

This has only hastened as the old markers -- Shabbat, kashrut, mikveh, even tzitzit -- have been reclaimed by Jews who don&#039;t see themselves as constrained by Orthodoxy. The result is the creation again of a space for non-observant Orthodox Jews, who give fealty to the markers but not the mitzvot.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/05/modern-orthodox-words-in-my-mouth/#comment-2920">AS</a>.</p>
<p>I think the need for labels in Orthodoxies is that Orthodoxy is ultimately a negative definition: Not Reform, not liberal, not Conservative. At the same time, it is about a claimed Authenticity &#8212; which needs to label others as inauthentic.</p>
<p>The result is that any tiny variation needs to claim its own Authenticity and become, to those who believe in it, in effect its own identification.</p>
<p>This has only hastened as the old markers &#8212; Shabbat, kashrut, mikveh, even tzitzit &#8212; have been reclaimed by Jews who don&#8217;t see themselves as constrained by Orthodoxy. The result is the creation again of a space for non-observant Orthodox Jews, who give fealty to the markers but not the mitzvot.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: What Lola Wants		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/05/modern-orthodox-words-in-my-mouth/#comment-2922</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[What Lola Wants]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2011 12:43:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3393#comment-2922</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Mr. Clark,
If you are going to speak about something such as the &quot;Yale 5&quot;. Do it from their mouths and actually speak with more than one of the participants. They each had a different reason and agenda for doing what they did. While you are at it, speak to the MO and CO students who were at Yale at the same time who were totally against what these &quot;5&quot;  were doing - publically and privately. Let&#039;s be accurate.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Mr. Clark,<br />
If you are going to speak about something such as the &#8220;Yale 5&#8221;. Do it from their mouths and actually speak with more than one of the participants. They each had a different reason and agenda for doing what they did. While you are at it, speak to the MO and CO students who were at Yale at the same time who were totally against what these &#8220;5&#8221;  were doing &#8211; publically and privately. Let&#8217;s be accurate.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/05/modern-orthodox-words-in-my-mouth/#comment-2920</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2011 21:42:12 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3393#comment-2920</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/05/modern-orthodox-words-in-my-mouth/#comment-2918&quot;&gt;ej&lt;/a&gt;.

Perhaps this reflects that in modernity, religion becomes &quot;deeply personal.&quot; Affiliation is optional so, so affiliating with a group that matches your religious worldview is itself a matter of personal expression.

But more to the point, I think that you underplay the extent to which identity and identification plays important roles in modern secular society - and the extent to which feelings of alienation are pervasive throughout society. If people generally don&#039;t seem to spend all that much time worrying about who they are, it is because identity has been comodified and pre-packaged. Take a look at contemporary advertising - to a large extent it sells identities.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/05/modern-orthodox-words-in-my-mouth/#comment-2918">ej</a>.</p>
<p>Perhaps this reflects that in modernity, religion becomes &#8220;deeply personal.&#8221; Affiliation is optional so, so affiliating with a group that matches your religious worldview is itself a matter of personal expression.</p>
<p>But more to the point, I think that you underplay the extent to which identity and identification plays important roles in modern secular society &#8211; and the extent to which feelings of alienation are pervasive throughout society. If people generally don&#8217;t seem to spend all that much time worrying about who they are, it is because identity has been comodified and pre-packaged. Take a look at contemporary advertising &#8211; to a large extent it sells identities.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Eli D. Clark		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/05/modern-orthodox-words-in-my-mouth/#comment-2919</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eli D. Clark]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2011 21:10:15 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3393#comment-2919</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/05/modern-orthodox-words-in-my-mouth/#comment-2917&quot;&gt;AS&lt;/a&gt;.

I obviously was not clear. Most dictionaries list multiple definitions of words in an order that reflects frequency of usage. All I was trying to say -- and evidently I was not successful -- was that the meaning of &quot;Modern Orthodox&quot; that Alan finds most interesting is a meaning that is less frequently used than the others.  I am to blame for making this point obliquely and perhaps opaquely. But I was not expressing a view whether one can speak of a sociological group or a religious ideology in terms of definitions as opposed to descriptions.   
Are the sociologists of American Orthodoxy sloppier on average than their colleagues? It&#039;s an interesting question, but I do not have sufficient data to answer it.
Finally, it is my sense that sociological training does not foster the kind of long and hard thinking you prescribe.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/05/modern-orthodox-words-in-my-mouth/#comment-2917">AS</a>.</p>
<p>I obviously was not clear. Most dictionaries list multiple definitions of words in an order that reflects frequency of usage. All I was trying to say &#8212; and evidently I was not successful &#8212; was that the meaning of &#8220;Modern Orthodox&#8221; that Alan finds most interesting is a meaning that is less frequently used than the others.  I am to blame for making this point obliquely and perhaps opaquely. But I was not expressing a view whether one can speak of a sociological group or a religious ideology in terms of definitions as opposed to descriptions.<br />
Are the sociologists of American Orthodoxy sloppier on average than their colleagues? It&#8217;s an interesting question, but I do not have sufficient data to answer it.<br />
Finally, it is my sense that sociological training does not foster the kind of long and hard thinking you prescribe.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: ej		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/05/modern-orthodox-words-in-my-mouth/#comment-2918</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ej]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2011 20:54:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3393#comment-2918</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I may be wrong on this, but my impression is that these defining terms are important for those close to a border that they think important. Thus some bloggers go out of their way to distinguish between Left Charedi and Right Wing MO, as if the discontinuity when we go from one label to the other, reveals deep and important information. But consider the self identification of those Jews, maybe 3-5 million, who  think of themselves as secular. They are Jews and secular, end of the description. Further self identification is now in terms of virtues,( &quot;I am kind and caring&quot;) activities and interests. People begin to stand out in the secular world when they stop talking of identity, and begin to exhibit, not list,  distinctive sensibilities and personalities. Think of authors, movie stars, charismatic types, people who stand out. No one would differentiate between say Saul Bellow and Philip Roth by describing some detailed feature of their behavior, e.g. Roth  eats meat , but Bellow  doesn&#039;t. 

I think this identity craze, this need to find the exact right box is overdone. We&#039;d be far better off if  we classified Jews by Myer Briggs indicators...&quot;The Chazon Ish, why would you expect otherwise, he&#039;s after all a INTJ.&quot; And in the first person case, we would all be better off if we worried less about whether we do or do not believe chazal never made a scientific mistake, and more about  our sensibilities...how do we experience the world and why. If any of this is right we can understand a common refrain in Orthodoxy . I find people always saying &quot;I just don&#039;t fit in,I must be an odd bird. I need to start my own minyan where I can find someone to talk to.&quot; Orthodoxy has now been spliced and diced every which way, the boxes are a constant subject of converrsation, and yet so many can&#039;t find an appropriate crowd(box).]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I may be wrong on this, but my impression is that these defining terms are important for those close to a border that they think important. Thus some bloggers go out of their way to distinguish between Left Charedi and Right Wing MO, as if the discontinuity when we go from one label to the other, reveals deep and important information. But consider the self identification of those Jews, maybe 3-5 million, who  think of themselves as secular. They are Jews and secular, end of the description. Further self identification is now in terms of virtues,( &#8220;I am kind and caring&#8221;) activities and interests. People begin to stand out in the secular world when they stop talking of identity, and begin to exhibit, not list,  distinctive sensibilities and personalities. Think of authors, movie stars, charismatic types, people who stand out. No one would differentiate between say Saul Bellow and Philip Roth by describing some detailed feature of their behavior, e.g. Roth  eats meat , but Bellow  doesn&#8217;t. </p>
<p>I think this identity craze, this need to find the exact right box is overdone. We&#8217;d be far better off if  we classified Jews by Myer Briggs indicators&#8230;&#8221;The Chazon Ish, why would you expect otherwise, he&#8217;s after all a INTJ.&#8221; And in the first person case, we would all be better off if we worried less about whether we do or do not believe chazal never made a scientific mistake, and more about  our sensibilities&#8230;how do we experience the world and why. If any of this is right we can understand a common refrain in Orthodoxy . I find people always saying &#8220;I just don&#8217;t fit in,I must be an odd bird. I need to start my own minyan where I can find someone to talk to.&#8221; Orthodoxy has now been spliced and diced every which way, the boxes are a constant subject of converrsation, and yet so many can&#8217;t find an appropriate crowd(box).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: AS		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/05/modern-orthodox-words-in-my-mouth/#comment-2917</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AS]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2011 17:52:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3393#comment-2917</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/05/modern-orthodox-words-in-my-mouth/#comment-2915&quot;&gt;Eli D. Clark&lt;/a&gt;.

&quot;the meaning of modern Orthodox that most interests you is an important one, but , I hope you will agree, not the first definition that would appear in a dictionary entry&quot;

You are missing the point: that is not a &quot;definition&quot; per se, it is a description of what is happening. Indeed, aiming for a definition puts one in the conceptual mode of asking what are the necessary and sufficient conditions to apply the term to a certain group or person or for a person or group to claim membership in the class. That itself is ultimately prescriptive.

That you made the mistake is understandable because many sociologists of American orthodoxy make this mistake and rather foolishly adopt the same terms that people self-apply and then use them as categories that are supposed to reflect sociological realities. These descriptions then take on normative weight. Most of these sociologists are downright sloppy and should not be writing about the communities to which they belong without thinking long and hard about what exactly they are doing and what exactly they are supposedly studying.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/05/modern-orthodox-words-in-my-mouth/#comment-2915">Eli D. Clark</a>.</p>
<p>&#8220;the meaning of modern Orthodox that most interests you is an important one, but , I hope you will agree, not the first definition that would appear in a dictionary entry&#8221;</p>
<p>You are missing the point: that is not a &#8220;definition&#8221; per se, it is a description of what is happening. Indeed, aiming for a definition puts one in the conceptual mode of asking what are the necessary and sufficient conditions to apply the term to a certain group or person or for a person or group to claim membership in the class. That itself is ultimately prescriptive.</p>
<p>That you made the mistake is understandable because many sociologists of American orthodoxy make this mistake and rather foolishly adopt the same terms that people self-apply and then use them as categories that are supposed to reflect sociological realities. These descriptions then take on normative weight. Most of these sociologists are downright sloppy and should not be writing about the communities to which they belong without thinking long and hard about what exactly they are doing and what exactly they are supposedly studying.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: S.		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/05/modern-orthodox-words-in-my-mouth/#comment-2916</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[S.]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2011 15:20:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3393#comment-2916</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&#062;The third meaning which is the one that I am most interested in- is that many groups since the late 18th century have mediated both modern and Orthodox. 

Is it your opinion that the Italians and Western Sephardim weren&#039;t doing this even in the 17th century?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&gt;The third meaning which is the one that I am most interested in- is that many groups since the late 18th century have mediated both modern and Orthodox. </p>
<p>Is it your opinion that the Italians and Western Sephardim weren&#8217;t doing this even in the 17th century?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Eli D. Clark		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/05/modern-orthodox-words-in-my-mouth/#comment-2915</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eli D. Clark]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2011 15:06:22 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3393#comment-2915</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[First, sorry for keeping you up. Second, sorry for the erroneous citation; I should not have mentioned you at all in a piece of armchair sociology. (It was not my idea, but I take full responsibility.) Third, thank you for the clarification and summary.  Fourth, even if I had understood your approach in all its nuance, which I did not, I was subject to space constraints that would not have allowed me to do it justice. Fifth, though you eschew the terminology of a &quot;move to the right,&quot; this is a popular term to describe a panoply of changes in the  Orthodox community, of which the development and spread of Centrist Orthodox ideology is one. So I apologize for implying that you engage in spectrum-speak. And please forgive those of us who do. Sixth, I respect your statement that that you do not come to this as a sociologist, but in the same post you write that you are &quot;trying to create a thick description of the workings of Centrism.&quot; To my untutored ear, that sounds like sociology, so please forgive my confusion. Seventh: I think Conservative Judaism retained the language of &quot;movement&quot; well past mid-century. Eighth, the meaning of modern Orthodox that most interests you is an important one, but , I hope you will agree, not the first definition that would appear in a dictionary entry.  Ninth, it seems that when you wear your sociologist hat, you detect parallels between, say, Evangelicals and Centrist Orthodoxy, but when you wear your student of contemporary religion hat, you tease out ever-increasing numbers of ideologies that casual observers lump together.  Tenth: Re CO skepticism of MO values, I will translate into your terminology: Centrist Orthodoxy as an ideology takes a more skeptical, if not critical, stance of certain values associated with contemporary liberal values than Modern Orthodox ideology.  Take the Yale 5, who wanted a Yale education (or at least a Yale diploma) but did not want to live in the undergraduate dormitories.  Eleventh: I don&#039;t lump all haredim together either, except in the occasional blog post about other groups or ideologies.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>First, sorry for keeping you up. Second, sorry for the erroneous citation; I should not have mentioned you at all in a piece of armchair sociology. (It was not my idea, but I take full responsibility.) Third, thank you for the clarification and summary.  Fourth, even if I had understood your approach in all its nuance, which I did not, I was subject to space constraints that would not have allowed me to do it justice. Fifth, though you eschew the terminology of a &#8220;move to the right,&#8221; this is a popular term to describe a panoply of changes in the  Orthodox community, of which the development and spread of Centrist Orthodox ideology is one. So I apologize for implying that you engage in spectrum-speak. And please forgive those of us who do. Sixth, I respect your statement that that you do not come to this as a sociologist, but in the same post you write that you are &#8220;trying to create a thick description of the workings of Centrism.&#8221; To my untutored ear, that sounds like sociology, so please forgive my confusion. Seventh: I think Conservative Judaism retained the language of &#8220;movement&#8221; well past mid-century. Eighth, the meaning of modern Orthodox that most interests you is an important one, but , I hope you will agree, not the first definition that would appear in a dictionary entry.  Ninth, it seems that when you wear your sociologist hat, you detect parallels between, say, Evangelicals and Centrist Orthodoxy, but when you wear your student of contemporary religion hat, you tease out ever-increasing numbers of ideologies that casual observers lump together.  Tenth: Re CO skepticism of MO values, I will translate into your terminology: Centrist Orthodoxy as an ideology takes a more skeptical, if not critical, stance of certain values associated with contemporary liberal values than Modern Orthodox ideology.  Take the Yale 5, who wanted a Yale education (or at least a Yale diploma) but did not want to live in the undergraduate dormitories.  Eleventh: I don&#8217;t lump all haredim together either, except in the occasional blog post about other groups or ideologies.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Dr. Natan Ophir		</title>
		<link>https://kavvanah.wordpress.com/2011/04/05/modern-orthodox-words-in-my-mouth/#comment-2913</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dr. Natan Ophir]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2011 05:02:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://kavvanah.wordpress.com/?p=3393#comment-2913</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[How about PMO - Post Modern Orthodox? Where does that fit in the discussion? Or doesn&#039;t it yet fit in?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>How about PMO &#8211; Post Modern Orthodox? Where does that fit in the discussion? Or doesn&#8217;t it yet fit in?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
